·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 1. 𐑤𐑵𐑥𐑦𐑙𐑟.

𐑒𐑷𐑤 𐑥𐑰 ·𐑦𐑖𐑥𐑱𐑩𐑤. 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑘𐑽𐑟 𐑩𐑜𐑴—𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑥𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑣𐑬 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑲𐑕𐑤𐑦—𐑣𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑹 𐑯𐑴 𐑥𐑳𐑯𐑦 𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑲 𐑐𐑻𐑕, 𐑯 𐑯𐑳𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑐𐑼𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑼 𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑥𐑰 𐑪𐑯 𐑖𐑹, 𐑲 𐑔𐑷𐑑 𐑲 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑕𐑱𐑤 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑩 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑯 𐑕𐑰 𐑞 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼𐑦 𐑐𐑸𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛. 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑩 𐑢𐑱 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑝 𐑛𐑮𐑲𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑪𐑓 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑤𐑰𐑯 𐑯 𐑮𐑧𐑜𐑿𐑤𐑱𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑕𐑻𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯. 𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑲 𐑓𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑥𐑲𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑜𐑮𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑜𐑮𐑦𐑥 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑞 𐑥𐑬𐑔; 𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑩 𐑛𐑨𐑥𐑐, 𐑛𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑤𐑦 𐑯𐑴𐑝𐑧𐑥𐑚𐑼 𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑲 𐑕𐑴𐑤; 𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑲 𐑓𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑥𐑲𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑪𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑺𐑦𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑷𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑒𐑪𐑓𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑺𐑣𐑬𐑟𐑩𐑟, 𐑯 𐑚𐑮𐑦𐑙𐑦𐑙 𐑳𐑐 𐑞 𐑮𐑽 𐑝 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑓𐑿𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑲 𐑥𐑰𐑑; 𐑯 𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑥𐑲 𐑣𐑲𐑐𐑴𐑟 𐑜𐑧𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩𐑯 𐑳𐑐𐑼 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑝 𐑥𐑰, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑢𐑲𐑼𐑟 𐑩 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑪𐑙 𐑥𐑪𐑮𐑩𐑤 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑐𐑩𐑤 𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑝𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑥𐑰 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑚𐑼𐑩𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑰𐑑, 𐑯 𐑥𐑦𐑔𐑪𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑦 𐑯𐑪𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑐𐑰𐑐𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑑𐑕 𐑪𐑓—𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑲 𐑩𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑣𐑲 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑑 𐑜𐑧𐑑 𐑑 𐑕𐑰 𐑨𐑟 𐑕𐑵𐑯 𐑨𐑟 𐑲 𐑒𐑨𐑯. 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑲 𐑕𐑳𐑚𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑑𐑿𐑑 𐑓 𐑐𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑯 𐑚𐑷𐑤. 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑓𐑦𐑤𐑩𐑕𐑪𐑓𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑓𐑤𐑳𐑮𐑦𐑖 ·𐑒𐑱𐑑𐑴 𐑔𐑮𐑴𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑹𐑛; 𐑲 𐑒𐑢𐑲𐑩𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑑 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐. 𐑞𐑺 𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑳𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑼𐑐𐑮𐑲𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕. 𐑦𐑓 𐑞𐑱 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑯𐑿 𐑦𐑑, 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑛𐑦𐑜𐑮𐑰, 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑹 𐑳𐑞𐑼, 𐑗𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑖 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑯𐑽𐑤𐑦 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑓𐑰𐑤𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑑𐑩𐑢𐑹𐑛𐑟 𐑞 𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑥𐑰.

𐑞𐑺 𐑯𐑬 𐑦𐑟 𐑘𐑹 𐑦𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑤𐑼 𐑕𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑥𐑨𐑯𐑣𐑨𐑑𐑴𐑟, 𐑚𐑧𐑤𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑢𐑹𐑝𐑟 𐑨𐑟 ·𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑾𐑯 𐑲𐑤𐑟 𐑚𐑲 𐑒𐑪𐑮𐑩𐑤 𐑮𐑰𐑓𐑕—𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑻𐑕 𐑕𐑼𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑻 𐑕𐑻𐑓. 𐑮𐑲𐑑 𐑯 𐑤𐑧𐑓𐑑, 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑰𐑑𐑕 𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑿 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼𐑢𐑼𐑛. 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑰𐑥 𐑛𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑬𐑯 𐑦𐑟 𐑞 𐑚𐑨𐑑𐑼𐑦, 𐑢𐑺 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑯𐑴𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑥𐑴𐑤 𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑪𐑖𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑢𐑱𐑝𐑟, 𐑯 𐑒𐑵𐑤𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑚𐑮𐑰𐑟𐑩𐑟, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑩 𐑓𐑿 𐑬𐑼𐑟 𐑐𐑮𐑰𐑝𐑾𐑕 𐑢𐑻 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑕𐑲𐑑 𐑝 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛. 𐑤𐑫𐑒 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑬𐑛𐑟 𐑝 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼-𐑜𐑱𐑟𐑼𐑟 𐑞𐑺.

𐑕𐑻𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑨𐑥𐑚𐑿𐑤𐑱𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑝 𐑩 𐑛𐑮𐑰𐑥𐑦 ·𐑕𐑨𐑚𐑩𐑔 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼𐑯𐑵𐑯. 𐑜𐑴 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 ·𐑒𐑹𐑤𐑽𐑟 ·𐑣𐑫𐑒 𐑑 ·𐑒𐑴𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑟 ·𐑕𐑤𐑦𐑐, 𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞𐑧𐑯𐑕, 𐑚𐑲 ·𐑢𐑲𐑑𐑣𐑷𐑤, 𐑯𐑹𐑔𐑢𐑼𐑛. 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑛𐑵 𐑿 𐑕𐑰?—𐑐𐑴𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑕𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑷𐑤 𐑼𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑞 𐑑𐑬𐑯, 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑔𐑬𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑔𐑬𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑝 𐑥𐑹𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑓𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑮𐑧𐑝𐑼𐑦𐑟. 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑤𐑰𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑲𐑤𐑟; 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑕𐑰𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑐𐑽-𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑟; 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑞 𐑚𐑫𐑤𐑢𐑼𐑒𐑕 𐑝 𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑕 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 ·𐑗𐑲𐑯𐑩; 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑣𐑲 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑓𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑮𐑦𐑜𐑦𐑙, 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑓 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑜𐑧𐑑 𐑩 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑚𐑧𐑑𐑼 𐑕𐑰𐑢𐑼𐑛 𐑐𐑰𐑐. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑸 𐑷𐑤 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟𐑥𐑧𐑯; 𐑝 𐑢𐑰𐑒 𐑛𐑱𐑟 𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑳𐑐 𐑦𐑯 𐑤𐑭𐑔 𐑯 𐑐𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑼—𐑑𐑲𐑛 𐑑 𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑟, 𐑯𐑱𐑤𐑛 𐑑 𐑚𐑧𐑯𐑗𐑩𐑟, 𐑒𐑤𐑦𐑯𐑗𐑑 𐑑 𐑛𐑧𐑕𐑒𐑕. 𐑣𐑬 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑦𐑟 𐑞𐑦𐑕? 𐑸 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑯 𐑓𐑰𐑤𐑛𐑟 𐑜𐑪𐑯? 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑛𐑵 𐑞𐑱 𐑣𐑽?

𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑤𐑫𐑒! 𐑣𐑽 𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑥𐑹 𐑒𐑮𐑬𐑛𐑟, 𐑐𐑱𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑓 𐑞 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼, 𐑯 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑓 𐑩 𐑛𐑲𐑝. 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡! 𐑯𐑳𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑰𐑥𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑤𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛; 𐑤𐑶𐑑𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑞 𐑖𐑱𐑛𐑦 𐑤𐑰 𐑝 𐑘𐑪𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑢𐑺𐑣𐑬𐑟𐑩𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑩𐑓𐑲𐑕. 𐑯𐑴. 𐑞𐑱 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑜𐑧𐑑 𐑡𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑯𐑲 𐑞 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼 𐑨𐑟 𐑞𐑱 𐑐𐑪𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑 𐑓𐑷𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯. 𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑞𐑱 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛—𐑥𐑲𐑤𐑟 𐑝 𐑞𐑧𐑥—𐑤𐑰𐑜𐑟. 𐑦𐑯𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑟 𐑷𐑤, 𐑞𐑱 𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑤𐑱𐑯𐑟 𐑯 𐑨𐑤𐑦𐑟, 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑰𐑑𐑕 𐑯 𐑨𐑝𐑩𐑯𐑿𐑟—𐑯𐑹𐑔, 𐑰𐑕𐑑, 𐑕𐑬𐑔, 𐑯 𐑢𐑧𐑕𐑑. 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑣𐑽 𐑞𐑱 𐑷𐑤 𐑿𐑯𐑲𐑑. 𐑑𐑧𐑤 𐑥𐑰, 𐑛𐑳𐑟 𐑞 𐑥𐑨𐑜𐑯𐑧𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑝𐑻𐑗𐑵 𐑝 𐑞 𐑯𐑰𐑛𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑝 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑕 𐑩𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑒𐑑 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑞𐑦𐑞𐑼?

𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑕 𐑥𐑹. 𐑕𐑱 𐑿 𐑸 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑒𐑳𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑦; 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑣𐑲 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑝 𐑤𐑱𐑒𐑕. 𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑐𐑭𐑔 𐑿 𐑐𐑤𐑰𐑟, 𐑯 𐑑𐑧𐑯 𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑦𐑑 𐑒𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑟 𐑿 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑛𐑱𐑤, 𐑯 𐑤𐑰𐑝𐑟 𐑿 𐑞𐑺 𐑚𐑲 𐑩 𐑐𐑵𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑰𐑥. 𐑞𐑺 𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑨𐑡𐑦𐑒 𐑦𐑯 𐑦𐑑. 𐑤𐑧𐑑 𐑞 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑨𐑚𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑑-𐑥𐑲𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑝 𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑚𐑰 𐑐𐑤𐑳𐑯𐑡𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑛𐑰𐑐𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑮𐑧𐑝𐑼𐑦𐑟—𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑤𐑧𐑜𐑟, 𐑕𐑧𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑰𐑑 𐑩-𐑜𐑴𐑦𐑙, 𐑯 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑦𐑯𐑓𐑨𐑤𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑤𐑰𐑛 𐑿 𐑑 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼, 𐑦𐑓 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼 𐑞𐑺 𐑚𐑰 𐑦𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑮𐑰𐑡𐑩𐑯. 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑿 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑚𐑰 𐑩𐑔𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 ·𐑩𐑥𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑛𐑧𐑟𐑼𐑑, 𐑑𐑮𐑲 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑, 𐑦𐑓 𐑘𐑹 𐑒𐑨𐑮𐑩𐑝𐑨𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑩𐑯 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑕𐑩𐑐𐑤𐑲𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑥𐑧𐑑𐑩𐑓𐑦𐑟𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑓𐑧𐑕𐑼. 𐑘𐑧𐑕, 𐑨𐑟 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑯𐑴𐑟, 𐑥𐑧𐑛𐑦𐑑𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑯 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼 𐑸 𐑢𐑧𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑓 𐑧𐑝𐑼.

𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑣𐑽 𐑦𐑟 𐑩𐑯 𐑸𐑑𐑦𐑕𐑑. 𐑣𐑰 𐑛𐑦𐑟𐑲𐑼𐑟 𐑑 𐑐𐑱𐑯𐑑 𐑿 𐑞 𐑛𐑮𐑰𐑥𐑾𐑕𐑑, 𐑖𐑱𐑛𐑾𐑕𐑑, 𐑒𐑢𐑲𐑩𐑑𐑩𐑕𐑑, 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑗𐑭𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑦𐑑 𐑝 𐑮𐑴𐑥𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑕𐑒𐑱𐑐 𐑦𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑝𐑨𐑤𐑦 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑨𐑒𐑴. 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑞 𐑗𐑰𐑓 𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑶𐑟? 𐑞𐑺 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑑𐑮𐑰𐑟, 𐑰𐑗 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑣𐑪𐑤𐑴 𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑙𐑒, 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑓 𐑩 𐑣𐑻𐑥𐑦𐑑 𐑯 𐑩 𐑒𐑮𐑵𐑕𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑒𐑕 𐑢𐑻 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑦𐑯; 𐑯 𐑣𐑽 𐑕𐑤𐑰𐑐𐑕 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑧𐑛𐑴, 𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑕𐑤𐑰𐑐 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑨𐑑𐑩𐑤; 𐑯 𐑳𐑐 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑘𐑪𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑒𐑪𐑑𐑦𐑡 𐑜𐑴𐑟 𐑩 𐑕𐑤𐑰𐑐𐑦 𐑕𐑥𐑴𐑒. 𐑛𐑰𐑐 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑢𐑫𐑛𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑢𐑲𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑩 𐑥𐑱𐑟𐑦 𐑢𐑱, 𐑮𐑰𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑴𐑝𐑼𐑤𐑨𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑟 𐑝 𐑥𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑚𐑱𐑞𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑣𐑦𐑤-𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑚𐑤𐑵. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞𐑴 𐑞 𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑗𐑼 𐑤𐑲𐑟 𐑞𐑳𐑕 𐑑𐑮𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑑, 𐑯 𐑞𐑴 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑐𐑲𐑯-𐑑𐑮𐑰 𐑖𐑱𐑒𐑕 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑕𐑲𐑟 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑤𐑰𐑝𐑟 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑖𐑧𐑐𐑼𐑛𐑟 𐑣𐑧𐑛, 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑢𐑻 𐑝𐑱𐑯, 𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑧𐑕 𐑞 𐑖𐑧𐑐𐑼𐑛𐑟 𐑲 𐑢𐑻 𐑓𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑑 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑥𐑨𐑡𐑦𐑒 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑰𐑥 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑣𐑦𐑥. 𐑜𐑴 𐑝𐑦𐑟𐑦𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑮𐑺𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑡𐑵𐑯, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑓 𐑕𐑒𐑹𐑟 𐑪𐑯 𐑕𐑒𐑹𐑟 𐑝 𐑥𐑲𐑤𐑟 𐑿 𐑢𐑱𐑛 𐑯𐑰-𐑛𐑰𐑐 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 ·𐑑𐑲𐑜𐑼-𐑤𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑟—𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑞 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑗𐑸𐑥 𐑢𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑙?—𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼—𐑞𐑺 𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑩 𐑛𐑮𐑪𐑐 𐑝 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼 𐑞𐑺! 𐑢𐑻 ·𐑯𐑲𐑨𐑜𐑼𐑩 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑩 𐑒𐑨𐑑𐑼𐑨𐑒𐑑 𐑝 𐑕𐑨𐑯𐑛, 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑿 𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑝𐑩𐑤 𐑘𐑹 𐑔𐑬𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑥𐑲𐑤𐑟 𐑑 𐑕𐑰 𐑦𐑑? 𐑢𐑲 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑞 𐑐𐑫𐑼 𐑐𐑴𐑩𐑑 𐑝 ·𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑩𐑕𐑰, 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑰𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑑𐑵 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑓𐑫𐑤𐑟 𐑝 𐑕𐑦𐑤𐑝𐑼, 𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑚𐑼𐑱𐑑 𐑢𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑩 𐑒𐑴𐑑, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑨𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑯𐑰𐑛𐑩𐑛, 𐑹 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑳𐑯𐑦 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑐𐑦𐑛𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑾𐑯 𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑐 𐑑 ·𐑮𐑪𐑒𐑩𐑢𐑱 ·𐑚𐑰𐑗? 𐑢𐑲 𐑦𐑟 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑮𐑴𐑚𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑔𐑦 𐑚𐑶 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑮𐑴𐑚𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑔𐑦 𐑕𐑴𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑹 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑒𐑮𐑱𐑟𐑦 𐑑 𐑜𐑴 𐑑 𐑕𐑰? 𐑢𐑲 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑘𐑹 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑝𐑶𐑦𐑡 𐑨𐑟 𐑩 𐑐𐑨𐑕𐑦𐑯𐑡𐑼, 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑿 𐑘𐑹𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑓𐑰𐑤 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩 𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑝𐑲𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑑𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑿 𐑯 𐑘𐑹 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑢𐑻 𐑯𐑬 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑕𐑲𐑑 𐑝 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛? 𐑢𐑲 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑞 𐑴𐑤𐑛 ·𐑐𐑻𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑞 𐑕𐑰 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑦? 𐑢𐑲 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑞 ·𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑒𐑕 𐑜𐑦𐑝 𐑦𐑑 𐑩 𐑕𐑧𐑐𐑼𐑩𐑑 𐑛𐑱𐑦𐑑𐑦, 𐑯 𐑴𐑯 𐑚𐑮𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑝 ·𐑡𐑴𐑝? 𐑖𐑫𐑼𐑤𐑦 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑 𐑥𐑰𐑯𐑦𐑙. 𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑛𐑰𐑐𐑼 𐑞 𐑥𐑰𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑹𐑦 𐑝 ·𐑯𐑸𐑕𐑦𐑕𐑩𐑕, 𐑣𐑵 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑪𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑜𐑮𐑭𐑕𐑐 𐑞 𐑑𐑹𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑙, 𐑥𐑲𐑤𐑛 𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑡 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑷 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑯, 𐑐𐑤𐑳𐑯𐑡𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑦𐑑 𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑛𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑡, 𐑢𐑰 𐑬𐑼𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑝𐑟 𐑕𐑰 𐑦𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑮𐑦𐑝𐑼𐑟 𐑯 𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟. 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑞 𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑡 𐑝 𐑞 𐑳𐑯𐑜𐑮𐑭𐑕𐑐𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑓𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑥 𐑝 𐑤𐑲𐑓; 𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑦𐑟 𐑞 𐑒𐑰 𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑷𐑤.

𐑯𐑬, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑲 𐑕𐑱 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑲 𐑨𐑥 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑣𐑨𐑚𐑦𐑑 𐑝 𐑜𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑕𐑰 𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑲 𐑚𐑦𐑜𐑦𐑯 𐑑 𐑜𐑮𐑴 𐑣𐑱𐑟𐑦 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑞 𐑲𐑟, 𐑯 𐑚𐑦𐑜𐑦𐑯 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑥𐑲 𐑤𐑳𐑙𐑟, 𐑲 𐑛𐑵 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑥𐑰𐑯 𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑓𐑻𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑲 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑜𐑴 𐑑 𐑕𐑰 𐑨𐑟 𐑩 𐑐𐑨𐑕𐑦𐑯𐑡𐑼. 𐑓 𐑑 𐑜𐑴 𐑨𐑟 𐑩 𐑐𐑨𐑕𐑦𐑯𐑡𐑼 𐑿 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑯𐑰𐑛𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑩 𐑐𐑻𐑕, 𐑯 𐑩 𐑐𐑻𐑕 𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑩 𐑮𐑨𐑜 𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑧𐑕 𐑿 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑦𐑑. 𐑚𐑦𐑕𐑲𐑛𐑟, 𐑐𐑨𐑕𐑦𐑯𐑡𐑼𐑟 𐑜𐑧𐑑 𐑕𐑰-𐑕𐑦𐑒—𐑜𐑮𐑴 𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑮𐑩𐑤𐑕𐑩𐑥—𐑛𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑕𐑤𐑰𐑐 𐑝 𐑯𐑲𐑑𐑕—𐑛𐑵 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑡𐑶 𐑞𐑧𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑝𐑟 𐑥𐑳𐑗, 𐑨𐑟 𐑩 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑔𐑦𐑙;—𐑯𐑴, 𐑲 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑜𐑴 𐑨𐑟 𐑩 𐑐𐑨𐑕𐑦𐑯𐑡𐑼; 𐑯𐑹, 𐑞𐑴 𐑲 𐑨𐑥 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑩 𐑕𐑷𐑤𐑑, 𐑛𐑵 𐑲 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑜𐑴 𐑑 𐑕𐑰 𐑨𐑟 𐑩 ·𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑛𐑹, 𐑹 𐑩 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯, 𐑹 𐑩 ·𐑒𐑫𐑒. 𐑲 𐑩𐑚𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑯 𐑞 𐑜𐑤𐑹𐑦 𐑯 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑪𐑓𐑦𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑑 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑣𐑵 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑞𐑧𐑥. 𐑓 𐑥𐑲 𐑐𐑸𐑑, 𐑲 𐑩𐑚𐑪𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑱𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑪𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑑𐑶𐑤𐑟, 𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑩𐑤𐑟, 𐑯 𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑚𐑿𐑤𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑒𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑢𐑪𐑑𐑕𐑴𐑧𐑝𐑼. 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑨𐑟 𐑲 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑛𐑵 𐑑 𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑒𐑺 𐑝 𐑥𐑲𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓, 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑 𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑒𐑺 𐑝 𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑕, 𐑚𐑸𐑒𐑕, 𐑚𐑮𐑦𐑜𐑟, 𐑕𐑒𐑵𐑯𐑼𐑟, 𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑑. 𐑯 𐑨𐑟 𐑓 𐑜𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑨𐑟 𐑒𐑫𐑒,—𐑞𐑴 𐑲 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑓𐑧𐑕 𐑞𐑺 𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑼𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑜𐑤𐑹𐑦 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑, 𐑩 𐑒𐑫𐑒 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑕𐑹𐑑 𐑝 𐑪𐑓𐑦𐑕𐑼 𐑪𐑯 𐑖𐑦𐑐-𐑚𐑹𐑛—𐑘𐑧𐑑, 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑣𐑬, 𐑲 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑓𐑨𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑛 𐑚𐑮𐑶𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑬𐑤𐑟;—𐑞𐑴 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑕 𐑚𐑮𐑶𐑤𐑛, 𐑡𐑵𐑛𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑳𐑑𐑼𐑛, 𐑯 𐑡𐑳𐑡𐑥𐑱𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑷𐑤𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑯 𐑐𐑧𐑐𐑼𐑛, 𐑞𐑺 𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑴 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑣𐑵 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑒 𐑥𐑹 𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑓𐑩𐑤𐑦, 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑑 𐑕𐑱 𐑮𐑧𐑝𐑼𐑧𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑤𐑦, 𐑝 𐑩 𐑚𐑮𐑶𐑤𐑛 𐑓𐑬𐑤 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑲 𐑢𐑦𐑤. 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑲𐑛𐑪𐑤𐑩𐑑𐑮𐑩𐑕 𐑛𐑴𐑑𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑴𐑤𐑛 ·𐑦𐑡𐑦𐑐𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑚𐑮𐑶𐑤𐑛 𐑲𐑚𐑦𐑕 𐑯 𐑮𐑴𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑮𐑦𐑝𐑼 𐑣𐑹𐑕, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑿 𐑕𐑰 𐑞 𐑥𐑳𐑥𐑦𐑟 𐑝 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑒𐑮𐑰𐑗𐑼𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑣𐑿𐑡 𐑚𐑱𐑒-𐑣𐑬𐑟𐑩𐑟 𐑞 𐑐𐑦𐑮𐑩𐑥𐑦𐑛𐑟.

𐑯𐑴, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑲 𐑜𐑴 𐑑 𐑕𐑰, 𐑲 𐑜𐑴 𐑨𐑟 𐑩 𐑕𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑼, 𐑮𐑲𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑞 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑, 𐑐𐑤𐑳𐑥 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑓𐑴𐑒𐑕𐑩𐑤, 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑓𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑑 𐑞 𐑮𐑶𐑩𐑤 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑-𐑣𐑧𐑛. 𐑑𐑮𐑵, 𐑞𐑱 𐑮𐑭𐑞𐑼 𐑹𐑛𐑼 𐑥𐑰 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑥, 𐑯 𐑥𐑱𐑒 𐑥𐑰 𐑡𐑳𐑥𐑐 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑕𐑐𐑸 𐑑 𐑕𐑐𐑸, 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑜𐑮𐑭𐑕𐑣𐑪𐑐𐑼 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑥𐑱 𐑥𐑧𐑛𐑴. 𐑯 𐑨𐑑 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑, 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑕𐑹𐑑 𐑝 𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑟 𐑳𐑯𐑐𐑤𐑧𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑳𐑓. 𐑦𐑑 𐑑𐑳𐑗𐑩𐑟 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑟 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑕 𐑝 𐑪𐑯𐑼, 𐑐𐑼𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑼𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑓 𐑿 𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑝 𐑩𐑯 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑚𐑤𐑦𐑖𐑑 𐑓𐑨𐑥𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛, 𐑞 ·𐑝𐑨𐑯 ·𐑮𐑧𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑤𐑺𐑟, 𐑹 ·𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑪𐑤𐑓𐑕, 𐑹 ·𐑙𐑸𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑘𐑵𐑑𐑕. 𐑯 𐑥𐑹 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑷𐑤, 𐑦𐑓 𐑡𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑰𐑝𐑾𐑕 𐑑 𐑐𐑫𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑘𐑹 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑑𐑸-𐑐𐑪𐑑, 𐑿 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑤𐑹𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑩 𐑒𐑳𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑦 𐑕𐑒𐑵𐑤𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑼, 𐑥𐑱𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑑𐑷𐑤𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑶𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑷 𐑝 𐑿. 𐑞 𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑟𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑟 𐑩 𐑒𐑰𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯, 𐑲 𐑩𐑖𐑫𐑼 𐑿, 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑩 𐑕𐑒𐑵𐑤𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑼 𐑑 𐑩 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑼, 𐑯 𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑢𐑲𐑼𐑟 𐑩 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑪𐑙 𐑛𐑩𐑒𐑪𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 ·𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑩𐑒𐑩 𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑑𐑴𐑦𐑒𐑕 𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑱𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑿 𐑑 𐑜𐑮𐑦𐑯 𐑯 𐑚𐑺 𐑦𐑑. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑺𐑟 𐑪𐑓 𐑦𐑯 𐑑𐑲𐑥.

𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑝 𐑦𐑑, 𐑦𐑓 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑣𐑳𐑙𐑒𐑕 𐑝 𐑩 𐑕𐑰-𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 𐑹𐑛𐑼𐑟 𐑥𐑰 𐑑 𐑜𐑧𐑑 𐑩 𐑚𐑮𐑵𐑥 𐑯 𐑕𐑢𐑰𐑐 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑒𐑕? 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑛𐑳𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑜𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑩𐑥𐑬𐑯𐑑 𐑑, 𐑢𐑱𐑛, 𐑲 𐑥𐑰𐑯, 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑒𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑯𐑿 ·𐑑𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑? 𐑛𐑵 𐑿 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒 𐑞 𐑸𐑒𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑩𐑤 ·𐑜𐑭𐑚𐑮𐑦𐑧𐑤 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑕 𐑧𐑯𐑦𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑤𐑧𐑕 𐑝 𐑥𐑰, 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑪𐑟 𐑲 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑥𐑐𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑯 𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑓𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑴𐑚𐑱 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑣𐑳𐑙𐑒𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑐𐑼𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑼 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕? 𐑣𐑵 𐑱𐑯𐑑 𐑩 𐑕𐑤𐑱𐑝? 𐑑𐑧𐑤 𐑥𐑰 𐑞𐑨𐑑. 𐑢𐑧𐑤, 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑣𐑬𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑞 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑕𐑰-𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑟 𐑥𐑱 𐑹𐑛𐑼 𐑥𐑰 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑—𐑣𐑬𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑞𐑱 𐑥𐑱 𐑔𐑳𐑥𐑐 𐑯 𐑐𐑳𐑯𐑗 𐑥𐑰 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑, 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑨𐑑𐑦𐑕𐑓𐑨𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑯𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑷𐑤 𐑮𐑲𐑑; 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦 𐑧𐑤𐑕 𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑢𐑱 𐑹 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑕𐑻𐑝𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑢𐑱—𐑲𐑞𐑼 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑓𐑦𐑟𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑹 𐑥𐑧𐑑𐑩𐑓𐑦𐑟𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑐𐑶𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑝𐑿, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑟; 𐑯 𐑕𐑴 𐑞 𐑿𐑯𐑦𐑝𐑻𐑕𐑩𐑤 𐑔𐑳𐑥𐑐 𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛, 𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑮𐑳𐑚 𐑰𐑗 𐑳𐑞𐑼𐑟 𐑖𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑼-𐑚𐑤𐑱𐑛𐑟, 𐑯 𐑚𐑰 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑑.

𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯, 𐑲 𐑷𐑤𐑢𐑱𐑟 𐑜𐑴 𐑑 𐑕𐑰 𐑨𐑟 𐑩 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑼, 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑪𐑟 𐑞𐑱 𐑥𐑱𐑒 𐑩 𐑐𐑶𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑐𐑱𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑰 𐑓 𐑥𐑲 𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑚𐑩𐑤, 𐑢𐑺𐑨𐑟 𐑞𐑱 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑐𐑱 𐑐𐑨𐑕𐑦𐑯𐑡𐑼𐑟 𐑩 𐑕𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑩𐑤 𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑲 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑣𐑻𐑛 𐑝. 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑺𐑦, 𐑐𐑨𐑕𐑦𐑯𐑡𐑼𐑟 𐑞𐑧𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑝𐑟 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑐𐑱. 𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑦𐑟 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑛𐑦𐑓𐑼𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑢𐑰𐑯 𐑐𐑱𐑦𐑙 𐑯 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑐𐑱𐑛. 𐑞 𐑨𐑒𐑑 𐑝 𐑐𐑱𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑼𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑕 𐑞 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑳𐑯𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑓𐑼𐑑𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑯𐑓𐑤𐑦𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑑𐑵 𐑹𐑗𐑼𐑛 𐑔𐑰𐑝𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑱𐑤𐑛 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑳𐑕. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑐𐑱𐑛,—𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑺 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑦𐑑? 𐑞 𐑻𐑚𐑱𐑯 𐑨𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑩 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑰𐑝𐑟 𐑥𐑳𐑯𐑦 𐑦𐑟 𐑮𐑾𐑤𐑦 𐑥𐑸𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑩𐑕, 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑰 𐑕𐑴 𐑻𐑯𐑩𐑕𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑰𐑝 𐑥𐑳𐑯𐑦 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑞 𐑮𐑵𐑑 𐑝 𐑷𐑤 𐑻𐑔𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑤𐑟, 𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑪𐑯 𐑯𐑴 𐑩𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑩 𐑥𐑳𐑯𐑦𐑛 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑼 𐑣𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑯. 𐑭! 𐑣𐑬 𐑗𐑽𐑓𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑢𐑰 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑲𐑯 𐑬𐑼𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑝𐑟 𐑑 𐑐𐑼𐑛𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯!

𐑓𐑲𐑯𐑩𐑤𐑦, 𐑲 𐑷𐑤𐑢𐑱𐑟 𐑜𐑴 𐑑 𐑕𐑰 𐑨𐑟 𐑩 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑼, 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑪𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑕𐑩𐑥 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑼𐑕𐑲𐑟 𐑯 𐑐𐑘𐑫𐑼 𐑺 𐑝 𐑞 𐑓𐑹-𐑒𐑭𐑕𐑩𐑤 𐑛𐑧𐑒. 𐑓 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛, 𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑸 𐑓𐑸 𐑥𐑹 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑩𐑕𐑑𐑻𐑯 (𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑟, 𐑦𐑓 𐑿 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑤𐑱𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑲𐑔𐑨𐑜𐑼𐑾𐑯 𐑥𐑨𐑒𐑕𐑦𐑥), 𐑕𐑴 𐑓 𐑞 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑐𐑸𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑛𐑹 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑒𐑢𐑹𐑑𐑼-𐑛𐑧𐑒 𐑜𐑧𐑑𐑕 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑨𐑑𐑥𐑩𐑕𐑓𐑽 𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑧𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑼𐑟 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑴𐑒𐑕𐑩𐑤. 𐑣𐑰 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑕 𐑣𐑰 𐑚𐑮𐑰𐑞𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑴. 𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑢𐑱 𐑛𐑵 𐑞 𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑤𐑑𐑦 𐑤𐑰𐑛 𐑞𐑺 𐑤𐑰𐑛𐑼𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑟, 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑤𐑰𐑛𐑼𐑟 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑩𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑 𐑦𐑑. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑺𐑓𐑹 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑣𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑰𐑑𐑩𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑥𐑧𐑤𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑰 𐑨𐑟 𐑩 𐑥𐑻𐑗𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑼, 𐑲 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑯𐑬 𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑥𐑲 𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑑 𐑜𐑴 𐑪𐑯 𐑩 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑝𐑶𐑦𐑡; 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑦𐑟𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑐𐑩𐑤𐑰𐑕 𐑪𐑓𐑦𐑕𐑼 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑓𐑱𐑑𐑕, 𐑣𐑵 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑕𐑼𐑝𐑱𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑝 𐑥𐑰, 𐑯 𐑕𐑰𐑒𐑮𐑩𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑪𐑜𐑟 𐑥𐑰, 𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑓𐑤𐑵𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑥𐑰 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑳𐑯𐑩𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑱—𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑚𐑧𐑑𐑼 𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑼 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑧𐑤𐑕. 𐑯, 𐑛𐑬𐑑𐑤𐑩𐑕, 𐑥𐑲 𐑜𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑪𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑝𐑶𐑦𐑡, 𐑓𐑹𐑥𐑛 𐑐𐑸𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑐𐑮𐑴𐑜𐑮𐑨𐑥 𐑝 ·𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑝𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑛𐑮𐑷𐑯 𐑳𐑐 𐑩 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑩𐑜𐑴. 𐑦𐑑 𐑒𐑱𐑥 𐑦𐑯 𐑨𐑟 𐑩 𐑕𐑹𐑑 𐑝 𐑚𐑮𐑰𐑓 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑤𐑵𐑛 𐑯 𐑕𐑴𐑤𐑴 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑢𐑰𐑯 𐑥𐑹 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑝 𐑐𐑼𐑓𐑹𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟. 𐑲 𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑦𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑐𐑸𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑚𐑦𐑤 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑮𐑳𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑞𐑦𐑕:

“𐑜𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑛 ·𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛 ·𐑦𐑤𐑧𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑓 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑟𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑿𐑯𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑛 ·𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑑𐑕. “·𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙 ·𐑝𐑶𐑦𐑡 𐑚𐑲 𐑢𐑳𐑯 ·𐑦𐑖𐑥𐑱𐑩𐑤. “·𐑚𐑤𐑳𐑛𐑦 ·𐑚𐑨𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑯 ·𐑨𐑓𐑜𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯.”

𐑞𐑴 𐑲 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑑𐑧𐑤 𐑢𐑲 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑦𐑜𐑟𐑨𐑒𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑡 𐑥𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑡𐑼𐑟, 𐑞 ·𐑓𐑱𐑑𐑕, 𐑐𐑫𐑑 𐑥𐑰 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑓 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑖𐑨𐑚𐑦 𐑐𐑸𐑑 𐑝 𐑩 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑝𐑶𐑦𐑡, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑳𐑞𐑼𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑕𐑧𐑑 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑓 𐑥𐑨𐑜𐑯𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑐𐑸𐑑𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑲 𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑡𐑩𐑛𐑦𐑟, 𐑯 𐑖𐑹𐑑 𐑯 𐑰𐑟𐑦 𐑐𐑸𐑑𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑰𐑤 𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑛𐑦𐑟, 𐑯 𐑡𐑪𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑸𐑑𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑓𐑸𐑕𐑩𐑟—𐑞𐑴 𐑲 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑑𐑧𐑤 𐑢𐑲 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑦𐑜𐑟𐑨𐑒𐑑𐑤𐑦; 𐑘𐑧𐑑, 𐑯𐑬 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑲 𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑷𐑤 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑕𐑻𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟, 𐑲 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒 𐑲 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑕𐑰 𐑩 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑯 𐑥𐑴𐑑𐑦𐑝𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑒𐑳𐑯𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑑 𐑥𐑰 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑝𐑺𐑾𐑕 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑜𐑲𐑟𐑩𐑟, 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑿𐑕𐑑 𐑥𐑰 𐑑 𐑕𐑧𐑑 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑐𐑼𐑓𐑹𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑐𐑸𐑑 𐑲 𐑛𐑦𐑛, 𐑚𐑦𐑕𐑲𐑛𐑟 𐑒𐑩𐑡𐑴𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑰 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑵𐑠𐑩𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩 𐑗𐑶𐑕 𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑳𐑤𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑥𐑲 𐑴𐑯 𐑳𐑯𐑚𐑲𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑰𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑯 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑱𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑡𐑳𐑡𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑.

𐑗𐑰𐑓 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑥𐑴𐑑𐑦𐑝𐑟 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞 𐑴𐑝𐑼𐑢𐑧𐑤𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑲𐑛𐑾 𐑝 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓. 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩 𐑐𐑹𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑕 𐑯 𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑽𐑾𐑕 𐑥𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑼 𐑮𐑬𐑟𐑛 𐑷𐑤 𐑥𐑲 𐑒𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑦𐑪𐑕𐑦𐑑𐑦. 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑲𐑤𐑛 𐑯 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑟 𐑢𐑺 𐑣𐑰 𐑮𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑚𐑳𐑤𐑒; 𐑞 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑝𐑼𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤, 𐑯𐑱𐑥𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑐𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑤𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤; 𐑞𐑰𐑟, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑩𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑸𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑝 𐑩 𐑔𐑬𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑛 ·𐑐𐑨𐑑𐑩𐑜𐑴𐑯𐑾𐑯 𐑕𐑲𐑑𐑕 𐑯 𐑕𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑟, 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑐𐑑 𐑑 𐑕𐑢𐑱 𐑥𐑰 𐑑 𐑥𐑲 𐑢𐑦𐑖. 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑥𐑧𐑯, 𐑐𐑼𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑕, 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑿𐑕𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑓 𐑥𐑰, 𐑲 𐑨𐑥 𐑑𐑹𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩𐑯 𐑧𐑝𐑼𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑗 𐑓 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑴𐑑. 𐑲 𐑤𐑳𐑝 𐑑 𐑕𐑱𐑤 𐑓𐑼𐑚𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑯 𐑕𐑰𐑟, 𐑯 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑪𐑯 𐑚𐑸𐑚𐑼𐑩𐑕 𐑒𐑴𐑕𐑑𐑕. 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑦𐑜𐑯𐑹𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑜𐑫𐑛, 𐑲 𐑨𐑥 𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑒 𐑑 𐑐𐑼𐑕𐑰𐑝 𐑩 𐑣𐑪𐑮𐑼, 𐑯 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑚𐑰 𐑕𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑦𐑑—𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑞𐑱 𐑤𐑧𐑑 𐑥𐑰—𐑕𐑦𐑯𐑕 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑧𐑤 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑪𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑑𐑻𐑥𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑥𐑱𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑤𐑪𐑡𐑩𐑟 𐑦𐑯.

𐑚𐑲 𐑮𐑰𐑟𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑟, 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑝𐑶𐑦𐑡 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑢𐑧𐑤𐑒𐑩𐑥; 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑓𐑤𐑳𐑛-𐑜𐑱𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼-𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛 𐑕𐑢𐑳𐑙 𐑴𐑐𐑩𐑯, 𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑲𐑤𐑛 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑰𐑑𐑕 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑢𐑱𐑛 𐑥𐑰 𐑑 𐑥𐑲 𐑐𐑻𐑐𐑩𐑕, 𐑑𐑵 𐑯 𐑑𐑵 𐑞𐑺 𐑓𐑤𐑴𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑥𐑲 𐑦𐑯𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑴𐑤, 𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑕𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑯, 𐑥𐑦𐑛 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑝 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑷𐑤, 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑜𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑣𐑫𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑓𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑥, 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑕𐑯𐑴 𐑣𐑦𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑺.

·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 2. 𐑞 ·𐑒𐑸𐑐𐑩𐑑-·𐑚𐑨𐑜.

𐑲 𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑓𐑑 𐑩 𐑖𐑻𐑑 𐑹 𐑑𐑵 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑥𐑲 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑒𐑸𐑐𐑩𐑑-𐑚𐑨𐑜, 𐑑𐑳𐑒𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑥𐑲 𐑸𐑥, 𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑓 ·𐑒𐑱𐑐 ·𐑣𐑹𐑯 𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑩𐑕𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑒. 𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑕𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑝 𐑴𐑤𐑛 ·𐑥𐑨𐑯𐑣𐑨𐑑𐑴, 𐑲 𐑛𐑵𐑤𐑦 𐑼𐑲𐑝𐑛 𐑦𐑯 ·𐑯𐑿 ·𐑚𐑧𐑛𐑓𐑼𐑛. 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩 𐑕𐑨𐑑𐑼𐑛𐑱 𐑯𐑲𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑧𐑥𐑚𐑼. 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑲 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑩𐑐𐑶𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑤𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑐𐑨𐑒𐑩𐑑 𐑓 ·𐑯𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑷𐑤𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑦 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑛, 𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑯𐑴 𐑢𐑱 𐑝 𐑮𐑰𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑪𐑓𐑼, 𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑞 𐑓𐑪𐑤𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑱.

𐑨𐑟 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑘𐑳𐑙 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑑𐑕 𐑓 𐑞 𐑐𐑱𐑯𐑟 𐑯 𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑩𐑤𐑑𐑦𐑟 𐑝 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑑𐑪𐑐 𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑕𐑱𐑥 ·𐑯𐑿 ·𐑚𐑧𐑛𐑓𐑼𐑛, 𐑞𐑧𐑯𐑕 𐑑 𐑦𐑥𐑚𐑸𐑒 𐑪𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑝𐑶𐑦𐑡, 𐑦𐑑 𐑥𐑱 𐑨𐑟 𐑢𐑧𐑤 𐑚𐑰 𐑮𐑦𐑤𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑲, 𐑓 𐑢𐑳𐑯, 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑯𐑴 𐑲𐑛𐑾 𐑝 𐑕𐑴 𐑛𐑵𐑦𐑙. 𐑓 𐑥𐑲 𐑥𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑳𐑐 𐑑 𐑕𐑱𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑯𐑴 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑩 ·𐑯𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑑 𐑒𐑮𐑭𐑓𐑑, 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑪𐑟 𐑞𐑺 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩 𐑓𐑲𐑯, 𐑚𐑶𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑩𐑕 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑓𐑱𐑥𐑩𐑕 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑩𐑥𐑱𐑟𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑤𐑰𐑟𐑛 𐑥𐑰. 𐑚𐑦𐑕𐑲𐑛𐑟 𐑞𐑴 ·𐑯𐑿 ·𐑚𐑧𐑛𐑓𐑼𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑝 𐑤𐑱𐑑 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑜𐑮𐑨𐑡𐑵𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑪𐑐𐑩𐑤𐑲𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑚𐑦𐑟𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙, 𐑯 𐑞𐑴 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑥𐑨𐑑𐑼 𐑐𐑫𐑼 𐑴𐑤𐑛 ·𐑯𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑬 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑚𐑦𐑣𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑣𐑻, 𐑘𐑧𐑑 ·𐑯𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑣𐑻 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑼𐑦𐑡𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑤—𐑞 ·𐑑𐑲𐑼 𐑝 𐑞𐑦𐑕 ·𐑒𐑸𐑔𐑦𐑡;—𐑞 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕 𐑢𐑺 𐑞 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑛𐑧𐑛 ·𐑩𐑥𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛. 𐑢𐑺 𐑧𐑤𐑕 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 ·𐑯𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑨𐑚𐑼𐑦𐑡𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑥𐑧𐑯, 𐑞 ·𐑮𐑧𐑛-·𐑥𐑧𐑯, 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑨𐑤𐑦 𐑬𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑵𐑟 𐑑 𐑜𐑦𐑝 𐑗𐑱𐑕 𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑤𐑩𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑔𐑩𐑯? 𐑯 𐑢𐑺 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 ·𐑯𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑑, 𐑑𐑵, 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑩𐑛𐑝𐑧𐑯𐑗𐑼𐑩𐑕 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑤𐑵𐑐 𐑐𐑫𐑑 𐑓𐑹𐑔, 𐑐𐑸𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑤𐑱𐑛𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑹𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑒𐑪𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑕𐑑𐑴𐑯𐑟—𐑕𐑴 𐑜𐑴𐑟 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑹𐑦—𐑑 𐑔𐑮𐑴 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟, 𐑦𐑯 𐑹𐑛𐑼 𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑳𐑝𐑼 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑞𐑱 𐑢𐑻 𐑯𐑲 𐑦𐑯𐑳𐑓 𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑒 𐑩 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑑?

𐑯𐑬 𐑣𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑯𐑲𐑑, 𐑩 𐑛𐑱, 𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑩𐑯𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑯𐑲𐑑 𐑓𐑪𐑤𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑥𐑰 𐑦𐑯 ·𐑯𐑿 ·𐑚𐑧𐑛𐑓𐑼𐑛, 𐑺 𐑲 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑦𐑥𐑚𐑸𐑒 𐑓 𐑥𐑲 𐑛𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑛 𐑐𐑹𐑑, 𐑦𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑱𐑥 𐑩 𐑥𐑨𐑑𐑼 𐑝 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑻𐑯𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑢𐑺 𐑲 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑑 𐑰𐑑 𐑯 𐑕𐑤𐑰𐑐 𐑥𐑰𐑯𐑢𐑲𐑤. 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑛𐑿𐑚𐑾𐑕-𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑦𐑙, 𐑯𐑱, 𐑩 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑛𐑸𐑒 𐑯 𐑛𐑦𐑟𐑥𐑩𐑤 𐑯𐑲𐑑, 𐑚𐑲𐑑𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑯 𐑗𐑽𐑤𐑩𐑕. 𐑲 𐑯𐑿 𐑯𐑴 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕. 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑕 𐑜𐑮𐑨𐑐𐑯𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑕𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑥𐑲 𐑐𐑪𐑒𐑩𐑑, 𐑯 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑮𐑷𐑑 𐑳𐑐 𐑩 𐑓𐑿 𐑐𐑰𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑝 𐑕𐑦𐑤𐑝𐑼,—𐑕𐑴, 𐑢𐑺𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑿 𐑜𐑴, ·𐑦𐑖𐑥𐑱𐑩𐑤, 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑲 𐑑 𐑥𐑲𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓, 𐑨𐑟 𐑲 𐑕𐑑𐑫𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑥𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑩 𐑛𐑮𐑽𐑦 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑰𐑑 𐑖𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑲 𐑚𐑨𐑜, 𐑯 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑺𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑜𐑤𐑵𐑥 𐑑𐑩𐑢𐑹𐑛𐑟 𐑞 𐑯𐑹𐑔 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑛𐑸𐑒𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑑𐑩𐑢𐑹𐑛𐑟 𐑞 𐑕𐑬𐑔—𐑢𐑺𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑦𐑯 𐑘𐑹 𐑢𐑦𐑟𐑛𐑩𐑥 𐑿 𐑥𐑱 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑒𐑤𐑵𐑛 𐑑 𐑤𐑪𐑡 𐑓 𐑞 𐑯𐑲𐑑, 𐑥𐑲 𐑛𐑽 ·𐑦𐑖𐑥𐑱𐑩𐑤, 𐑚𐑰 𐑖𐑫𐑼 𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑢𐑲𐑼 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑲𐑕, 𐑯 𐑛𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑑𐑵 𐑐𐑼𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑼.

𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑷𐑤𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑐𐑕 𐑲 𐑐𐑱𐑕𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑰𐑑𐑕, 𐑯 𐑐𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑲𐑯 𐑝 “𐑞 ·𐑒𐑮𐑪𐑕𐑑 ·𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑟”—𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑑 𐑑𐑵 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑝 𐑯 𐑡𐑪𐑤𐑦 𐑞𐑺. 𐑓𐑻𐑞𐑼 𐑪𐑯, 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑚𐑮𐑲𐑑 𐑮𐑧𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑴𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 “𐑕𐑹𐑛-·𐑓𐑦𐑖 ·𐑦𐑯,” 𐑞𐑺 𐑒𐑱𐑥 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑓𐑻𐑝𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑮𐑱𐑟, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑥𐑧𐑤𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑞 𐑐𐑨𐑒𐑑 𐑕𐑯𐑴 𐑯 𐑲𐑕 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑞 𐑣𐑬𐑕, 𐑓 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦𐑢𐑺 𐑧𐑤𐑕 𐑞 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑡𐑰𐑤𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑕𐑑 𐑤𐑱 𐑑𐑧𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑗𐑩𐑟 𐑔𐑦𐑒 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑣𐑸𐑛, 𐑨𐑕𐑓𐑨𐑤𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑐𐑱𐑝𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑,—𐑮𐑭𐑞𐑼 𐑢𐑽𐑦 𐑓 𐑥𐑰, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑲 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑒 𐑥𐑲 𐑓𐑫𐑑 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑞 𐑓𐑤𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑦 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑡𐑧𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟, 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑪𐑟 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑣𐑸𐑛, 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑹𐑕𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑕𐑻𐑝𐑦𐑕 𐑞 𐑕𐑴𐑤𐑟 𐑝 𐑥𐑲 𐑚𐑵𐑑𐑕 𐑢𐑻 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑥𐑦𐑟𐑼𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑐𐑤𐑲𐑑. 𐑑𐑵 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑝 𐑯 𐑡𐑪𐑤𐑦, 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯 𐑔𐑷𐑑 𐑲, 𐑐𐑷𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑥𐑴𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑗 𐑞 𐑚𐑮𐑷𐑛 𐑜𐑤𐑺 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑰𐑑, 𐑯 𐑣𐑽 𐑞 𐑕𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑑𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑜𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑦𐑯. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑜𐑴 𐑪𐑯, ·𐑦𐑖𐑥𐑱𐑩𐑤, 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑲 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑; 𐑛𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑿 𐑣𐑽? 𐑜𐑧𐑑 𐑩𐑢𐑱 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑞 𐑛𐑹; 𐑘𐑹 𐑐𐑨𐑗𐑑 𐑚𐑵𐑑𐑕 𐑸 𐑕𐑑𐑪𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑢𐑱. 𐑕𐑴 𐑪𐑯 𐑲 𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑑. 𐑲 𐑯𐑬 𐑚𐑲 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑑 𐑓𐑪𐑤𐑴𐑛 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑰𐑑𐑕 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑑𐑫𐑒 𐑥𐑰 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼𐑢𐑼𐑛, 𐑓 𐑞𐑺, 𐑛𐑬𐑑𐑤𐑩𐑕, 𐑢𐑻 𐑞 𐑗𐑰𐑐𐑩𐑕𐑑, 𐑦𐑓 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑞 𐑗𐑽𐑾𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑟.

𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑛𐑮𐑽𐑦 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑰𐑑𐑕! 𐑚𐑤𐑪𐑒𐑕 𐑝 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑒𐑯𐑩𐑕, 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑣𐑬𐑟𐑩𐑟, 𐑪𐑯 𐑲𐑞𐑼 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛, 𐑯 𐑣𐑽 𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑩 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑤, 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑤 𐑥𐑵𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑑𐑵𐑥. 𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑬𐑼 𐑝 𐑞 𐑯𐑲𐑑, 𐑝 𐑞 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑛𐑱 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑰𐑒, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑒𐑢𐑹𐑑𐑼 𐑝 𐑞 𐑑𐑬𐑯 𐑐𐑮𐑵𐑝𐑛 𐑷𐑤 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑟𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑛. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑲 𐑒𐑱𐑥 𐑑 𐑩 𐑕𐑥𐑴𐑒𐑦 𐑤𐑲𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑴𐑕𐑰𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑩 𐑤𐑴, 𐑢𐑲𐑛 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑛𐑦𐑙, 𐑞 𐑛𐑹 𐑝 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑕𐑑𐑫𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑲𐑑𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑴𐑐𐑩𐑯. 𐑦𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑩 𐑒𐑺𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑤𐑫𐑒, 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑓 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑻 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑓 𐑞 𐑿𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑐𐑳𐑚𐑤𐑦𐑒; 𐑕𐑴, 𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑦𐑙, 𐑞 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑲 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑥𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑩𐑯 𐑨𐑖-𐑚𐑪𐑒𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑐𐑹𐑗. 𐑣𐑭! 𐑔𐑷𐑑 𐑲, 𐑣𐑭, 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑓𐑤𐑲𐑦𐑙 𐑐𐑸𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑗𐑴𐑒𐑑 𐑥𐑰, 𐑸 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑨𐑖𐑩𐑟 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑶𐑛 𐑕𐑦𐑑𐑦, ·𐑜𐑩𐑥𐑹𐑩? 𐑚𐑳𐑑 “𐑞 ·𐑒𐑮𐑪𐑕𐑑 ·𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑟,” 𐑯 “𐑞 ·𐑕𐑹𐑛-·𐑓𐑦𐑖?”—𐑞𐑦𐑕, 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑯𐑰𐑛𐑟 𐑚𐑰 𐑞 𐑕𐑲𐑯 𐑝 “𐑞 ·𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑐.” 𐑣𐑬𐑧𐑝𐑼, 𐑲 𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑑 𐑥𐑲𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑳𐑐 𐑯 𐑣𐑽𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑤𐑬𐑛 𐑝𐑶𐑕 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑦𐑯, 𐑐𐑫𐑖𐑑 𐑪𐑯 𐑯 𐑴𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑩 𐑕𐑧𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑛, 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑽𐑽 𐑛𐑹.

𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 ·𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑒 ·𐑐𐑸𐑤𐑩𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑕𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 ·𐑑𐑪𐑐𐑣𐑧𐑑. 𐑩 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑒 𐑓𐑱𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑛 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑮𐑴𐑟 𐑑 𐑐𐑽; 𐑯 𐑚𐑦𐑘𐑪𐑯𐑛, 𐑩 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑒 ·𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑩𐑤 𐑝 ·𐑛𐑵𐑥 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑚𐑰𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑚𐑫𐑒 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑐𐑫𐑤𐑐𐑦𐑑. 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩 𐑯𐑰𐑜𐑮𐑴 𐑗𐑻𐑗; 𐑯 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑰𐑗𐑼'𐑟 𐑑𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑞 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑒𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑛𐑸𐑒𐑯𐑩𐑕, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑰𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑯 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑯 𐑑𐑰𐑔-𐑯𐑨𐑖𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑺. 𐑣𐑭, ·𐑦𐑖𐑥𐑱𐑩𐑤, 𐑥𐑳𐑑𐑼𐑛 𐑲, 𐑚𐑨𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑬𐑑, ·𐑮𐑧𐑗𐑩𐑛 𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑑𐑱𐑯𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑲𐑯 𐑝 '𐑞 ·𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑐!'

𐑥𐑵𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑪𐑯, 𐑲 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑒𐑱𐑥 𐑑 𐑩 𐑛𐑦𐑥 𐑕𐑹𐑑 𐑝 𐑤𐑲𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑓𐑸 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑛𐑪𐑒𐑕, 𐑯 𐑣𐑻𐑛 𐑩 𐑓𐑼𐑤𐑹𐑯 𐑒𐑮𐑰𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑺; 𐑯 𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑳𐑐, 𐑕𐑷 𐑩 𐑕𐑢𐑦𐑙𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑲𐑯 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑞 𐑛𐑹 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑐𐑱𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑦𐑑, 𐑓𐑱𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑧𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑑𐑷𐑤 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑡𐑧𐑑 𐑝 𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑦 𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑱, 𐑯 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑢𐑻𐑛𐑟 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑯𐑰𐑔—“𐑞 ·𐑕𐑐𐑬𐑑𐑼 ·𐑦𐑯:—𐑐𐑰𐑑𐑼 ·𐑒𐑪𐑓𐑦𐑯.”

𐑒𐑪𐑓𐑦𐑯?—𐑕𐑐𐑬𐑑𐑼?—𐑮𐑭𐑞𐑼 𐑪𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑐𐑼𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑼 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑧𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯, 𐑔𐑷𐑑 𐑲. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑩 𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑯𐑱𐑥 𐑦𐑯 ·𐑯𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑑, 𐑞𐑱 𐑕𐑱, 𐑯 𐑲 𐑕𐑩𐑐𐑴𐑟 𐑞𐑦𐑕 ·𐑐𐑰𐑑𐑼 𐑣𐑽 𐑦𐑟 𐑩𐑯 𐑧𐑥𐑦𐑜𐑮𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞𐑺. 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑤𐑲𐑑 𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑑 𐑕𐑴 𐑛𐑦𐑥, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕, 𐑓 𐑞 𐑑𐑲𐑥, 𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑑 𐑒𐑢𐑲𐑩𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑳𐑓, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑨𐑐𐑦𐑛𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑫𐑛𐑩𐑯 𐑣𐑬𐑕 𐑦𐑑𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑓 𐑦𐑑 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑒𐑸𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑣𐑽 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑮𐑵𐑦𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑚𐑻𐑯𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑑, 𐑯 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑕𐑢𐑦𐑙𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑲𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑩 𐑐𐑪𐑝𐑼𐑑𐑦-𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑕𐑹𐑑 𐑝 𐑒𐑮𐑰𐑒 𐑑 𐑦𐑑, 𐑲 𐑔𐑷𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑽 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑕𐑐𐑪𐑑 𐑓 𐑗𐑰𐑐 𐑤𐑪𐑡𐑦𐑙𐑟, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑝 𐑐𐑰 𐑒𐑪𐑓𐑦.

𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩 𐑒𐑢𐑽 𐑕𐑹𐑑 𐑝 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕—𐑩 𐑜𐑱𐑚𐑩𐑤-𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑣𐑬𐑕, 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑐𐑷𐑤𐑟𐑦𐑛 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑻, 𐑯 𐑤𐑰𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑕𐑨𐑛𐑤𐑦. 𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑫𐑛 𐑪𐑯 𐑩 𐑖𐑸𐑐 𐑚𐑤𐑰𐑒 𐑒𐑹𐑯𐑼, 𐑢𐑺 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑑𐑧𐑥𐑐𐑧𐑕𐑗𐑵𐑩𐑕 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛 ·𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑴𐑒𐑤𐑲𐑛𐑩𐑯 𐑒𐑧𐑐𐑑 𐑳𐑐 𐑩 𐑢𐑻𐑕 𐑣𐑬𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑦𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑐𐑫𐑼 ·𐑐𐑷𐑤'𐑟 𐑑𐑪𐑕𐑑 𐑒𐑮𐑭𐑓𐑑. ·𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑴𐑒𐑤𐑲𐑛𐑩𐑯, 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼𐑞𐑩𐑤𐑧𐑕, 𐑦𐑟 𐑩 𐑥𐑲𐑑𐑦 𐑐𐑤𐑧𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑟𐑧𐑓𐑼 𐑑 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑦𐑯-𐑛𐑹𐑟, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑰𐑑 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑣𐑪𐑚 𐑒𐑢𐑲𐑩𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑑𐑴𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑓 𐑚𐑧𐑛. “𐑦𐑯 𐑡𐑳𐑡𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑑𐑧𐑥𐑐𐑧𐑕𐑗𐑵𐑩𐑕 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛 𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑛 ·𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑴𐑒𐑤𐑲𐑛𐑩𐑯,” 𐑕𐑧𐑟 𐑩𐑯 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑮𐑲𐑑𐑼—𐑝 𐑣𐑵𐑟 𐑢𐑻𐑒𐑕 𐑲 𐑐𐑩𐑟𐑧𐑕 𐑞 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑪𐑐𐑦 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑑—“𐑦𐑑 𐑥𐑱𐑒𐑩𐑔 𐑩 𐑥𐑸𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑛𐑦𐑓𐑼𐑩𐑯𐑕, 𐑢𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑞𐑬 𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑬𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑩 𐑜𐑤𐑭𐑕 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑴 𐑢𐑺 𐑞 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑷𐑤 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑬𐑑𐑕𐑲𐑛, 𐑹 𐑢𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑞𐑬 𐑩𐑚𐑟𐑻𐑝𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑨𐑖𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑴, 𐑢𐑺 𐑞 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑪𐑯 𐑚𐑴𐑔 𐑕𐑲𐑛𐑟, 𐑯 𐑝 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑞 𐑢𐑲𐑑 ·𐑛𐑧𐑔 𐑦𐑟 𐑞 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑜𐑤𐑱𐑟𐑽.” 𐑑𐑮𐑵 𐑦𐑯𐑳𐑓, 𐑔𐑷𐑑 𐑲, 𐑨𐑟 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑐𐑨𐑕𐑦𐑡 𐑩𐑒𐑻𐑛 𐑑 𐑥𐑲 𐑥𐑲𐑯𐑛—𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑒-𐑤𐑧𐑑𐑼, 𐑞𐑬 𐑮𐑰𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑢𐑧𐑤. 𐑘𐑧𐑕, 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑲𐑟 𐑸 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑴𐑟, 𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦 𐑝 𐑥𐑲𐑯 𐑦𐑟 𐑞 𐑣𐑬𐑕. 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑩 𐑐𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑞𐑱 𐑛𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑪𐑐 𐑳𐑐 𐑞 𐑗𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑕 𐑯 𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑟 𐑞𐑴, 𐑯 𐑔𐑮𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑤𐑦𐑯𐑑 𐑣𐑽 𐑯 𐑞𐑺. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑑'𐑕 𐑑𐑵 𐑤𐑱𐑑 𐑑 𐑥𐑱𐑒 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑮𐑵𐑝𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑯𐑬. 𐑞 𐑿𐑯𐑦𐑝𐑻𐑕 𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑖𐑑; 𐑞 𐑒𐑴𐑐𐑕𐑑𐑴𐑯 𐑦𐑟 𐑪𐑯, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑗𐑦𐑐𐑕 𐑢𐑻 𐑒𐑸𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑪𐑓 𐑩 𐑥𐑦𐑤𐑾𐑯 𐑘𐑽𐑟 𐑩𐑜𐑴. 𐑐𐑫𐑼 ·𐑤𐑨𐑟𐑼𐑩𐑕 𐑞𐑺, 𐑗𐑨𐑑𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑑𐑰𐑔 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑞 𐑒𐑻𐑚𐑕𐑑𐑴𐑯 𐑓 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑦𐑤𐑴, 𐑯 𐑖𐑱𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑪𐑓 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑑𐑨𐑑𐑼𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑖𐑦𐑝𐑼𐑦𐑙𐑟, 𐑣𐑰 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑐𐑤𐑳𐑜 𐑳𐑐 𐑚𐑴𐑔 𐑽𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑮𐑨𐑜𐑟, 𐑯 𐑐𐑫𐑑 𐑩 𐑒𐑹𐑯-𐑒𐑪𐑚 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑬𐑔, 𐑯 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑒𐑰𐑐 𐑬𐑑 𐑞 𐑑𐑧𐑥𐑐𐑧𐑕𐑗𐑵𐑩𐑕 ·𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑴𐑒𐑤𐑲𐑛𐑩𐑯. ·𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑴𐑒𐑤𐑲𐑛𐑩𐑯! 𐑕𐑧𐑟 𐑴𐑤𐑛 ·𐑛𐑲𐑝𐑟, 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑮𐑧𐑛 𐑕𐑦𐑤𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑮𐑨𐑐𐑼—(𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑩 𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑼 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼𐑢𐑼𐑛𐑟) 𐑐𐑵, 𐑐𐑵! 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑩 𐑓𐑲𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑕𐑑𐑦 𐑯𐑲𐑑; 𐑣𐑬 ·𐑹𐑲𐑩𐑯 𐑜𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑼𐑟; 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑯𐑹𐑞𐑼𐑯 𐑤𐑲𐑑𐑕! 𐑤𐑧𐑑 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑑𐑷𐑒 𐑝 𐑞𐑺 ·𐑹𐑦𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑼 𐑒𐑤𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑝 𐑧𐑝𐑼𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑻𐑝𐑩𐑑𐑼𐑦𐑟; 𐑜𐑦𐑝 𐑥𐑰 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑡 𐑝 𐑥𐑱𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑲 𐑴𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑼 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑥𐑲 𐑴𐑯 𐑒𐑴𐑤𐑟.

𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑕 ·𐑤𐑨𐑟𐑼𐑩𐑕? 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑹𐑥 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑤𐑵 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑚𐑲 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑳𐑐 𐑑 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑯𐑹𐑞𐑼𐑯 𐑤𐑲𐑑𐑕? 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 ·𐑤𐑨𐑟𐑼𐑩𐑕 𐑮𐑭𐑞𐑼 𐑚𐑰 𐑦𐑯 ·𐑕𐑵𐑥𐑭𐑑𐑮𐑩 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑣𐑽? 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑣𐑰 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑓𐑸 𐑮𐑭𐑞𐑼 𐑤𐑱 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑤𐑧𐑙𐑔𐑢𐑲𐑟 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑞 𐑤𐑲𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑦𐑒𐑢𐑱𐑑𐑼; 𐑘𐑱, 𐑘𐑰 𐑜𐑪𐑛𐑟! 𐑜𐑴 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑑 𐑞 𐑓𐑲𐑼𐑦 𐑐𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑑𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓, 𐑦𐑯 𐑹𐑛𐑼 𐑑 𐑒𐑰𐑐 𐑬𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑕𐑑?

𐑯𐑬, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 ·𐑤𐑨𐑟𐑼𐑩𐑕 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑤𐑲 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑞𐑺 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑒𐑻𐑚𐑕𐑑𐑴𐑯 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑞 𐑛𐑹 𐑝 ·𐑛𐑲𐑝𐑟, 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑹 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑩𐑯 𐑲𐑕𐑚𐑻𐑜 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑚𐑰 𐑥𐑫𐑼𐑛 𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑥𐑩𐑤𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑟. 𐑘𐑧𐑑 ·𐑛𐑲𐑝𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓, 𐑣𐑰 𐑑𐑵 𐑤𐑦𐑝𐑟 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 ·𐑑𐑕𐑸 𐑦𐑯 𐑩𐑯 𐑲𐑕 𐑐𐑨𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑝 𐑓𐑮𐑴𐑟𐑩𐑯 𐑕𐑲𐑟, 𐑯 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑟𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑩 𐑑𐑧𐑥𐑐𐑼𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑕𐑩𐑕𐑲𐑩𐑑𐑦, 𐑣𐑰 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑮𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑕 𐑞 𐑑𐑧𐑐𐑦𐑛 𐑑𐑽𐑟 𐑝 𐑹𐑓𐑩𐑯𐑟.

𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑯𐑴 𐑥𐑹 𐑝 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑚𐑤𐑳𐑚𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑯𐑬, 𐑢𐑰 𐑸 𐑜𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑩-𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙, 𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑤𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑦 𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑑 𐑒𐑳𐑥. 𐑤𐑧𐑑 𐑳𐑕 𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑱𐑐 𐑞 𐑲𐑕 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑬𐑼 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑓𐑰𐑑, 𐑯 𐑕𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑹𐑑 𐑝 𐑩 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕 𐑞𐑦𐑕 “𐑕𐑐𐑬𐑑𐑼” 𐑥𐑱 𐑚𐑰.

·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 3. 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑐𐑬𐑑𐑼-·𐑦𐑯.

𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑜𐑱𐑚𐑩𐑤-𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 ·𐑕𐑐𐑬𐑑𐑼-·𐑦𐑯, 𐑿 𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑘𐑹𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑢𐑲𐑛, 𐑤𐑴, 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑜𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑦 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑴𐑤𐑛-𐑓𐑨𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑢𐑱𐑯𐑕𐑒𐑪𐑑𐑕, 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑲𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑚𐑫𐑤𐑢𐑼𐑒𐑕 𐑝 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑛𐑧𐑥𐑛 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑒𐑮𐑭𐑓𐑑. 𐑪𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑣𐑳𐑙 𐑩 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑤𐑸𐑡 𐑶𐑤𐑐𐑱𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑴 𐑔𐑳𐑮𐑴𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑦𐑕𐑥𐑴𐑒𐑑, 𐑯 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑢𐑱 𐑛𐑦𐑓𐑱𐑕𐑑, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑳𐑯𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑩𐑤 𐑒𐑮𐑪𐑕𐑤𐑲𐑑𐑕 𐑚𐑲 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑿 𐑝𐑿𐑛 𐑦𐑑, 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑲 𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑡𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑛𐑦 𐑯 𐑩 𐑕𐑽𐑰𐑟 𐑝 𐑕𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑥𐑨𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑝𐑦𐑟𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑑 𐑦𐑑, 𐑯 𐑒𐑺𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑢𐑲𐑼𐑦 𐑝 𐑞 𐑯𐑱𐑚𐑼𐑟, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑿 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑢𐑱 𐑼𐑲𐑝 𐑨𐑑 𐑩𐑯 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑐𐑻𐑐𐑩𐑕. 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑳𐑯𐑩𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑥𐑨𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑝 𐑖𐑱𐑛𐑟 𐑯 𐑖𐑨𐑛𐑴𐑟, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑿 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑔𐑷𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑨𐑥𐑚𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑕 𐑘𐑳𐑙 𐑸𐑑𐑦𐑕𐑑, 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑯𐑿 ·𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑜𐑟, 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑧𐑝𐑼𐑛 𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑱𐑑 𐑒𐑱𐑪𐑕 𐑚𐑦𐑢𐑦𐑗𐑑. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑛𐑦𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑯 𐑻𐑯𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯, 𐑯 𐑪𐑓𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑰𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑐𐑪𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑦𐑙𐑟, 𐑯 𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑲 𐑔𐑮𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑴𐑐𐑩𐑯 𐑞 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑴 𐑑𐑩𐑢𐑹𐑛𐑟 𐑞 𐑚𐑨𐑒 𐑝 𐑞 𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑦, 𐑿 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑑 𐑞 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑒𐑤𐑵𐑠𐑩𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩𐑯 𐑲𐑛𐑾, 𐑣𐑬𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑢𐑲𐑤𐑛, 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑷𐑤𐑑𐑩𐑜𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑳𐑯𐑢𐑪𐑮𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛.

𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑐𐑳𐑟𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑯 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑿 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩 𐑤𐑪𐑙, 𐑤𐑦𐑥𐑚𐑼, 𐑐𐑹𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑕, 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑒 𐑥𐑨𐑕 𐑝 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑪𐑝𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑼 𐑝 𐑞 𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑗𐑼 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑚𐑤𐑵, 𐑛𐑦𐑥, 𐑐𐑻𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑼 𐑤𐑲𐑯𐑟 𐑓𐑤𐑴𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑯𐑱𐑥𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑘𐑰𐑕𐑑. 𐑩 𐑚𐑪𐑜𐑦, 𐑕𐑪𐑜𐑦, 𐑕𐑒𐑦𐑗𐑦 𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑗𐑼 𐑑𐑮𐑵𐑤𐑦, 𐑦𐑯𐑳𐑓 𐑑 𐑛𐑮𐑲𐑝 𐑩 𐑯𐑻𐑝𐑩𐑕 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑛. 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞𐑺 𐑩 𐑕𐑹𐑑 𐑝 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑧𐑓𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑑, 𐑣𐑭𐑓-𐑩𐑑𐑱𐑯𐑛, 𐑳𐑯𐑦𐑥𐑨𐑡𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑓𐑺𐑤𐑦 𐑓𐑮𐑴𐑟 𐑿 𐑑 𐑦𐑑, 𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑿 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑪𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑺𐑦𐑤𐑦 𐑑𐑫𐑒 𐑩𐑯 𐑴𐑔 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑘𐑹𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑑 𐑓𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑬𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑸𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑐𐑱𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑. 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑯 𐑩𐑯𐑪𐑯 𐑩 𐑚𐑮𐑲𐑑, 𐑚𐑳𐑑, 𐑩𐑤𐑨𐑕, 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑧𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑝 𐑲𐑛𐑾 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑛𐑸𐑑 𐑿 𐑔𐑮𐑵.—𐑦𐑑'𐑕 𐑞 ·𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑒 ·𐑕𐑰 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑥𐑦𐑛𐑯𐑲𐑑 𐑜𐑱𐑤.—𐑦𐑑'𐑕 𐑞 𐑳𐑯𐑯𐑨𐑗𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑚𐑨𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑓𐑹 𐑐𐑮𐑲𐑥𐑩𐑤 𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕.—𐑦𐑑'𐑕 𐑩 𐑚𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑣𐑰𐑔.—𐑦𐑑'𐑕 𐑩 ·𐑣𐑲𐑐𐑼𐑚𐑹𐑾𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼 𐑕𐑰𐑯.—𐑦𐑑'𐑕 𐑞 𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑒𐑦𐑙-𐑳𐑐 𐑝 𐑞 𐑲𐑕𐑚𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑰𐑥 𐑝 ·𐑑𐑲𐑥. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑓𐑨𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑟 𐑘𐑰𐑤𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑐𐑹𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑕 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑗𐑼'𐑟 𐑥𐑦𐑛𐑕𐑑. 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑕 𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑬𐑑, 𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑢𐑻 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑯. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑪𐑐; 𐑛𐑳𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑚𐑺 𐑩 𐑓𐑱𐑯𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑧𐑥𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑑 𐑩 𐑡𐑲𐑜𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑓𐑦𐑖? 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑤𐑩𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑔𐑩𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓?

𐑦𐑯 𐑓𐑨𐑒𐑑, 𐑞 𐑸𐑑𐑦𐑕𐑑'𐑕 𐑛𐑦𐑟𐑲𐑯 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑞𐑦𐑕: 𐑩 𐑓𐑲𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑔𐑽𐑦 𐑝 𐑥𐑲 𐑴𐑯, 𐑐𐑸𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑱𐑕𐑑 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑨𐑜𐑮𐑦𐑜𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑩𐑐𐑦𐑯𐑘𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑱𐑡𐑛 𐑐𐑻𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑵𐑥 𐑲 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑝𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑚𐑡𐑧𐑒𐑑. 𐑞 𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑗𐑼 𐑮𐑧𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑩 ·𐑒𐑱𐑐-·𐑣𐑹𐑯𐑼 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑣𐑳𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑱𐑯; 𐑞 𐑣𐑭𐑓-𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑛 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑢𐑧𐑤𐑑𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑺 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑥𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑕 𐑩𐑤𐑴𐑯 𐑝𐑦𐑟𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤; 𐑯 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑜𐑟𐑨𐑕𐑐𐑼𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑐𐑻𐑐𐑩𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑙 𐑒𐑤𐑰𐑯 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑭𐑓𐑑, 𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑹𐑥𐑩𐑕 𐑨𐑒𐑑 𐑝 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑-𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑟.

𐑞 𐑪𐑐𐑩𐑟𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑷𐑤 𐑝 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑦 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑣𐑳𐑙 𐑷𐑤 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑣𐑰𐑞𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑖 𐑼𐑱 𐑝 𐑥𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑩𐑕 𐑒𐑤𐑳𐑚𐑟 𐑯 𐑕𐑐𐑽𐑟. 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑢𐑻 𐑔𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑧𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑜𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑑𐑰𐑔 𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑧𐑥𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑲𐑝𐑼𐑦 𐑕𐑷𐑟; 𐑳𐑞𐑼𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑑𐑳𐑓𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑯𐑪𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑣𐑿𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑣𐑺; 𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤-𐑖𐑱𐑐𐑑, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑝𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑢𐑰𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑞 𐑕𐑧𐑜𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑯𐑿-𐑥𐑴𐑯 𐑜𐑮𐑭𐑕 𐑚𐑲 𐑩 𐑤𐑪𐑙-𐑸𐑥𐑛 𐑥𐑴𐑼. 𐑿 𐑖𐑳𐑛𐑼𐑛 𐑨𐑟 𐑿 𐑜𐑱𐑟𐑛, 𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑛 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑥𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑩𐑕 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑯 𐑕𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑡 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑜𐑪𐑯 𐑩 𐑛𐑧𐑔-𐑣𐑸𐑝𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩 𐑣𐑨𐑒𐑦𐑙, 𐑣𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑓𐑲𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑦𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑. 𐑥𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑮𐑳𐑕𐑑𐑦 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑯 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑟 𐑷𐑤 𐑚𐑮𐑴𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑯 𐑛𐑦𐑓𐑹𐑥𐑛. 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑢𐑻 𐑕𐑑𐑹𐑦𐑛 𐑢𐑧𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑟. 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑕 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑕, 𐑯𐑬 𐑢𐑲𐑤𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑧𐑤𐑚𐑴𐑛, 𐑓𐑦𐑓𐑑𐑦 𐑘𐑽𐑟 𐑩𐑜𐑴 𐑛𐑦𐑛 ·𐑯𐑱𐑔𐑩𐑯 ·𐑕𐑢𐑱𐑯 𐑒𐑦𐑤 𐑓𐑦𐑓𐑑𐑰𐑯 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑢𐑰𐑯 𐑩 𐑕𐑳𐑯𐑮𐑲𐑟 𐑯 𐑩 𐑕𐑳𐑯𐑕𐑧𐑑. 𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯—𐑕𐑴 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑒𐑹𐑒𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑵 𐑯𐑬—𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑓𐑤𐑳𐑙 𐑦𐑯 ·𐑡𐑭𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑕𐑰𐑟, 𐑯 𐑮𐑳𐑯 𐑩𐑢𐑱 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑚𐑲 𐑩 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑘𐑽𐑟 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼𐑢𐑼𐑛𐑟 𐑕𐑤𐑱𐑯 𐑪𐑓 𐑞 ·𐑒𐑱𐑐 𐑝 ·𐑚𐑤𐑭𐑙𐑒𐑴. 𐑞 𐑼𐑦𐑡𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑲𐑼𐑯 𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑛 𐑯𐑲 𐑞 𐑑𐑱𐑤, 𐑯, 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑯𐑰𐑛𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑪𐑡𐑼𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦 𐑝 𐑩 𐑥𐑨𐑯, 𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑓𐑫𐑤 𐑓𐑹𐑑𐑦 𐑓𐑰𐑑, 𐑯 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑥𐑚𐑧𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑣𐑳𐑥𐑐.

𐑒𐑮𐑪𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑛𐑳𐑕𐑒𐑦 𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑦, 𐑯 𐑪𐑯 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑘𐑪𐑯 𐑤𐑴-𐑸𐑗𐑑 𐑢𐑱—𐑒𐑳𐑑 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑩 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑩𐑤 𐑗𐑦𐑥𐑯𐑦 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑓𐑲𐑼𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑷𐑤 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛—𐑿 𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑼 𐑞 𐑐𐑳𐑚𐑤𐑦𐑒 𐑮𐑵𐑥. 𐑩 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑛𐑳𐑕𐑒𐑽 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕 𐑦𐑟 𐑞𐑦𐑕, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑤𐑴 𐑐𐑪𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑩𐑕 𐑚𐑰𐑥𐑟 𐑩𐑚𐑳𐑝, 𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑮𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑐𐑤𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑕 𐑚𐑦𐑯𐑰𐑔, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑿 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑓𐑨𐑯𐑕𐑦 𐑿 𐑑𐑮𐑪𐑛 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑒𐑮𐑭𐑓𐑑'𐑕 𐑒𐑪𐑒𐑐𐑦𐑑𐑕, 𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑝 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩 𐑣𐑬𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑯𐑲𐑑, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑒𐑹𐑯𐑼-𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑼𐑛 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑸𐑒 𐑮𐑪𐑒𐑑 𐑕𐑴 𐑓𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑾𐑕𐑤𐑦. 𐑪𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑕𐑑𐑫𐑛 𐑩 𐑤𐑪𐑙, 𐑤𐑴, 𐑖𐑧𐑤𐑓-𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑑𐑱𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑒𐑳𐑝𐑼𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑨𐑒𐑑 𐑜𐑤𐑭𐑕 𐑒𐑱𐑕𐑩𐑟, 𐑓𐑦𐑤𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑛𐑳𐑕𐑑𐑦 𐑮𐑺𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑟 𐑜𐑨𐑞𐑼𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑲𐑛 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛'𐑟 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑴𐑑𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑯𐑫𐑒𐑕. 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑡𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑓𐑻𐑞𐑼 𐑨𐑙𐑜𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑞 𐑮𐑵𐑥 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑩 𐑛𐑸𐑒-𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑛𐑧𐑯—𐑞 𐑚𐑸—𐑩 𐑮𐑵𐑛 𐑩𐑑𐑧𐑥𐑐𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑩 𐑮𐑲𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑤'𐑟 𐑣𐑧𐑛. 𐑚𐑰 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑬 𐑦𐑑 𐑥𐑱, 𐑞𐑺 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑞 𐑝𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑸𐑗𐑑 𐑚𐑴𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤'𐑟 𐑡𐑷, 𐑕𐑴 𐑢𐑲𐑛, 𐑩 𐑒𐑴𐑗 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑛𐑮𐑲𐑝 𐑚𐑦𐑯𐑰𐑔 𐑦𐑑. 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑦𐑯 𐑸 𐑖𐑨𐑚𐑦 𐑖𐑧𐑤𐑝𐑟, 𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑛 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑟, 𐑚𐑪𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑟, 𐑓𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑒𐑕; 𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑡𐑷𐑟 𐑝 𐑕𐑢𐑦𐑓𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯, 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩𐑯𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑒𐑻𐑕𐑑 ·𐑡𐑴𐑯𐑩 (𐑚𐑲 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑯𐑱𐑥 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑰𐑛 𐑞𐑱 𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥), 𐑚𐑳𐑕𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑩 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑼𐑛 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑥𐑨𐑯, 𐑣𐑵, 𐑓 𐑞𐑺 𐑥𐑳𐑯𐑦, 𐑛𐑽𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑟 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑼𐑟 𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑽𐑾𐑥𐑟 𐑯 𐑛𐑧𐑔.

𐑩𐑚𐑪𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑸 𐑞 𐑑𐑳𐑥𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑼𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑣𐑰 𐑐𐑹𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑶𐑟𐑩𐑯. 𐑞𐑴 𐑑𐑮𐑵 𐑕𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑—𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑦𐑯, 𐑞 𐑝𐑦𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑯 𐑜𐑪𐑜𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑜𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑰𐑑𐑓𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑑𐑱𐑐𐑼𐑛 𐑛𐑬𐑯𐑢𐑼𐑛𐑟 𐑑 𐑩 𐑗𐑰𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑪𐑑𐑩𐑥. 𐑐𐑨𐑮𐑩𐑤𐑧𐑤 𐑥𐑼𐑦𐑛𐑾𐑯𐑟 𐑮𐑵𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑜𐑤𐑭𐑕, 𐑕𐑼𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑓𐑫𐑑𐑐𐑨𐑛𐑟' 𐑜𐑪𐑚𐑤𐑩𐑑𐑕. 𐑓𐑦𐑤 𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑥𐑸𐑒, 𐑯 𐑘𐑹 𐑗𐑸𐑡 𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑩 𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑦; 𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑩 𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑥𐑹; 𐑯 𐑕𐑴 𐑪𐑯 𐑑 𐑞 𐑓𐑫𐑤 𐑜𐑤𐑭𐑕—𐑞 ·𐑒𐑱𐑐 ·𐑣𐑹𐑯 𐑥𐑧𐑠𐑼, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑿 𐑥𐑱 𐑜𐑳𐑤𐑐 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑓 𐑩 𐑖𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑙.

𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕 𐑲 𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑩 𐑯𐑳𐑥𐑚𐑼 𐑝 𐑘𐑳𐑙 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑜𐑨𐑞𐑼𐑛 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑩 𐑑𐑱𐑚𐑩𐑤, 𐑦𐑜𐑟𐑨𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑲 𐑩 𐑛𐑦𐑥 𐑤𐑲𐑑 𐑛𐑲𐑝𐑼𐑟 𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑟𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑼. 𐑲 𐑕𐑷𐑑 𐑞 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑤𐑹𐑛, 𐑯 𐑑𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑲 𐑛𐑦𐑟𐑲𐑼𐑛 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑩𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑛𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑮𐑵𐑥, 𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑰𐑝𐑛 𐑓 𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑼 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑬𐑕 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑓𐑫𐑤—𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑩 𐑚𐑧𐑛 𐑳𐑯𐑪𐑒𐑿𐑐𐑲𐑛. “𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑩𐑝𐑭𐑕𐑑,” 𐑣𐑰 𐑨𐑛𐑩𐑛, 𐑑𐑨𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑛, “𐑿 𐑣𐑱𐑯𐑑 𐑯𐑴 𐑩𐑚𐑡𐑧𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑑 𐑖𐑺𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑽'𐑟 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑩𐑑, 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑘𐑰? 𐑲 𐑕'𐑐𐑴𐑕 𐑿 𐑸 𐑜𐑴𐑦𐑯' 𐑩-𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑯', 𐑕𐑴 𐑿'𐑛 𐑚𐑧𐑑𐑼 𐑜𐑧𐑑 𐑿𐑟𐑛 𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑹𐑑 𐑝 𐑔𐑦𐑙.”

𐑲 𐑑𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑲 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑤𐑲𐑒𐑑 𐑑 𐑕𐑤𐑰𐑐 𐑑𐑵 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑚𐑧𐑛; 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑓 𐑲 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑛𐑵 𐑕𐑴, 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑛𐑦𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑵 𐑞 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑽 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑚𐑰, 𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑓 𐑣𐑰 (𐑞 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑤𐑹𐑛) 𐑮𐑾𐑤𐑦 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑯𐑴 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕 𐑓 𐑥𐑰, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑽 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑲𐑛𐑩𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑩𐑚𐑡𐑧𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤, 𐑢𐑲 𐑮𐑭𐑞𐑼 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑓𐑻𐑞𐑼 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑩 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡 𐑑𐑬𐑯 𐑪𐑯 𐑕𐑴 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑼 𐑩 𐑯𐑲𐑑, 𐑲 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑐𐑫𐑑 𐑳𐑐 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑣𐑭𐑓 𐑝 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑛𐑰𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑥𐑨𐑯'𐑟 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑩𐑑.

“𐑲 𐑔𐑷𐑑 𐑕𐑴. 𐑷𐑤 𐑮𐑲𐑑; 𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑩 𐑕𐑰𐑑. 𐑕𐑳𐑐𐑼?—𐑿 𐑢𐑪𐑯𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑐𐑼? 𐑕𐑳𐑐𐑼'𐑤 𐑚𐑰 𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑦 𐑛𐑦𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑤𐑦.”

𐑲 𐑕𐑨𐑑 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑪𐑯 𐑩𐑯 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑢𐑫𐑛𐑩𐑯 𐑕𐑧𐑑𐑩𐑤, 𐑒𐑸𐑝𐑛 𐑷𐑤 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑚𐑧𐑯𐑗 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑚𐑨𐑑𐑼𐑦. 𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑩 𐑮𐑵𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑱𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑑𐑸 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑓𐑻𐑞𐑼 𐑩𐑛𐑹𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑡𐑨𐑒-𐑯𐑲𐑓, 𐑕𐑑𐑵𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑯 𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑡𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑢𐑻𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑢𐑱 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑱𐑕 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑢𐑰𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑤𐑧𐑜𐑟. 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑨𐑑 𐑩 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑓𐑫𐑤 𐑕𐑱𐑤, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑛𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑥𐑱𐑒 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑢𐑱, 𐑲 𐑔𐑷𐑑.

𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑓𐑹 𐑹 𐑓𐑲𐑝 𐑝 𐑳𐑕 𐑢𐑻 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑑 𐑬𐑼 𐑥𐑰𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑩𐑯 𐑩𐑡𐑶𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑮𐑵𐑥. 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑒𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑨𐑟 ·𐑲𐑕𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛—𐑯𐑴 𐑓𐑲𐑼 𐑨𐑑 𐑷𐑤—𐑞 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑤𐑹𐑛 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑫𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑩𐑓𐑹𐑛 𐑦𐑑. 𐑯𐑳𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑑𐑵 𐑛𐑦𐑟𐑥𐑩𐑤 𐑑𐑨𐑤𐑴 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑤𐑟, 𐑰𐑗 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑢𐑲𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑖𐑰𐑑. 𐑢𐑰 𐑢𐑻 𐑓𐑱𐑯 𐑑 𐑚𐑳𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑳𐑐 𐑬𐑼 𐑥𐑳𐑙𐑒𐑦 𐑡𐑨𐑒𐑩𐑑𐑕, 𐑯 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑑 𐑬𐑼 𐑤𐑦𐑐𐑕 𐑒𐑳𐑐𐑕 𐑝 𐑕𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑑𐑰 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑬𐑼 𐑣𐑭𐑓 𐑓𐑮𐑴𐑟𐑩𐑯 𐑓𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑼𐑟. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞 𐑓𐑺 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑤 𐑒𐑲𐑯𐑛—𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑥𐑰𐑑 𐑯 𐑐𐑩𐑑𐑱𐑑𐑴𐑟, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑛𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑦𐑙𐑟; 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑣𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑯𐑟! 𐑛𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑓 𐑕𐑳𐑐𐑼! 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑘𐑳𐑙 𐑓𐑧𐑤𐑴 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑯 𐑚𐑪𐑒𐑕 𐑒𐑴𐑑, 𐑩𐑛𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑑 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑛𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑛𐑲𐑼𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑥𐑨𐑯𐑼.

“𐑥𐑲 𐑚𐑶,” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑞 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑤𐑹𐑛, “𐑿'𐑤 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑞 𐑯𐑲𐑑𐑥𐑺 𐑑 𐑩 𐑛𐑧𐑛 𐑕𐑸𐑑𐑱𐑯𐑑𐑦.”

“𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑤𐑹𐑛,” 𐑲 𐑢𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑼𐑛, “𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑱𐑯𐑑 𐑞 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑽 𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑑?”

“𐑴, 𐑯𐑴,” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑣𐑰, 𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑕𐑹𐑑 𐑝 𐑛𐑲𐑩𐑚𐑪𐑤𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑦 𐑓𐑳𐑯𐑦, “𐑞 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑽 𐑦𐑟 𐑩 𐑛𐑸𐑒 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑧𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑗𐑨𐑐. 𐑣𐑰 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑰𐑑𐑕 𐑛𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑦𐑙𐑟, 𐑣𐑰 𐑛𐑴𐑯𐑑—𐑣𐑰 𐑰𐑑𐑕 𐑯𐑳𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑕, 𐑯 𐑣𐑰 𐑤𐑲𐑒𐑕 '𐑩𐑥 𐑮𐑺.”

“𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑤 𐑣𐑰 𐑛𐑳𐑟,” 𐑕𐑧𐑟 𐑲. “𐑢𐑺 𐑦𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑽? 𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑽?”

“𐑣𐑰'𐑤 𐑚𐑰 𐑣𐑽 𐑩𐑓𐑹 𐑤𐑪𐑙,” 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞 𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑼.

𐑲 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑐 𐑦𐑑, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑲 𐑚𐑦𐑜𐑨𐑯 𐑑 𐑓𐑰𐑤 𐑕𐑩𐑕𐑐𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑞𐑦𐑕 “𐑛𐑸𐑒 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑧𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑛” 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑽. 𐑨𐑑 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑮𐑱𐑑, 𐑲 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑳𐑐 𐑥𐑲 𐑥𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑓 𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑴 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑛 𐑬𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑰 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑕𐑤𐑰𐑐 𐑑𐑩𐑜𐑧𐑞𐑼, 𐑣𐑰 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑮𐑧𐑕 𐑯 𐑜𐑧𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑚𐑧𐑛 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑲 𐑛𐑦𐑛.

𐑕𐑳𐑐𐑼 𐑴𐑝𐑼, 𐑞 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑦 𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑚𐑨𐑒 𐑑 𐑞 𐑚𐑸-𐑮𐑵𐑥, 𐑢𐑧𐑯, 𐑯𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑧𐑤𐑕 𐑑 𐑛𐑵 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑥𐑲𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓, 𐑲 𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑪𐑤𐑝𐑛 𐑑 𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑞 𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑰𐑝𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑨𐑟 𐑩 𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑼 𐑪𐑯.

𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑩 𐑮𐑲𐑩𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑯𐑶𐑟 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑣𐑻𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑. 𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑳𐑐, 𐑞 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑤𐑹𐑛 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛, “𐑞𐑨𐑑'𐑕 𐑞 ·𐑜𐑮𐑨𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑕'𐑩𐑟 𐑒𐑮𐑵. 𐑲 𐑕𐑰𐑛 𐑣𐑻 𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑹𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑪𐑓𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑥𐑹𐑯𐑦𐑙; 𐑩 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑘𐑽𐑟' 𐑝𐑶𐑦𐑡, 𐑯 𐑩 𐑓𐑫𐑤 𐑖𐑦𐑐. 𐑣𐑼𐑭, 𐑚𐑶𐑟; 𐑯𐑬 𐑢𐑰'𐑤 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑞 𐑤𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑯𐑿𐑟 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 ·𐑝𐑰𐑡𐑰𐑟.”

𐑩 𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑥𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑕𐑰 𐑚𐑵𐑑𐑕 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑣𐑻𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑦; 𐑞 𐑛𐑹 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑓𐑤𐑳𐑙 𐑴𐑐𐑩𐑯, 𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑮𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑩 𐑢𐑲𐑤𐑛 𐑕𐑧𐑑 𐑝 𐑥𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑯𐑼𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑳𐑓. 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑧𐑤𐑩𐑐𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑖𐑨𐑜𐑦 𐑢𐑪𐑗 𐑒𐑴𐑑𐑕, 𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞𐑺 𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑟 𐑥𐑳𐑓𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑫𐑤𐑩𐑯 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑓𐑼𐑑𐑼𐑟, 𐑷𐑤 𐑚𐑧𐑛𐑸𐑯𐑛 𐑯 𐑮𐑨𐑜𐑛, 𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑚𐑽𐑛𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑓 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑲𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑟, 𐑞𐑱 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑮𐑳𐑐𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑚𐑺𐑟 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 ·𐑤𐑨𐑚𐑮𐑩𐑛𐑹. 𐑞𐑱 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑡𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞𐑺 𐑚𐑴𐑑, 𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑬𐑕 𐑞𐑱 𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑛. 𐑯𐑴 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼, 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑱 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑩 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑒 𐑓 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤'𐑟 𐑥𐑬𐑔—𐑞 𐑚𐑸—𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑞 𐑮𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑴𐑤𐑛 ·𐑡𐑴𐑯𐑩, 𐑞𐑺 𐑩𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑦𐑱𐑑𐑦𐑙, 𐑕𐑵𐑯 𐑐𐑹𐑛 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑬𐑑 𐑚𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑼𐑟 𐑷𐑤 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛. 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑯𐑛 𐑝 𐑩 𐑚𐑨𐑛 𐑒𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑧𐑛, 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑗 ·𐑡𐑴𐑯𐑩 𐑥𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑩 𐑐𐑦𐑗-𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑐𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑡𐑦𐑯 𐑯 𐑥𐑩𐑤𐑨𐑕𐑩𐑟, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑢𐑹 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩 𐑕𐑪𐑝𐑮𐑩𐑯 𐑒𐑘𐑫𐑼 𐑓 𐑷𐑤 𐑒𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑟 𐑯 𐑒𐑩𐑑𐑸𐑟 𐑢𐑪𐑑𐑕𐑴𐑧𐑝𐑼, 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑥𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑝 𐑣𐑬 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙, 𐑹 𐑢𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑒𐑷𐑑 𐑪𐑓 𐑞 𐑒𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑝 ·𐑤𐑨𐑚𐑮𐑩𐑛𐑹, 𐑹 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑝 𐑩𐑯 𐑲𐑕-𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛.

𐑞 𐑤𐑦𐑒𐑼 𐑕𐑵𐑯 𐑥𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞𐑺 𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑟, 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑳𐑟 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑨𐑮𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑑𐑴𐑐𐑼𐑟 𐑯𐑿𐑤𐑦 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑕𐑰, 𐑯 𐑞𐑱 𐑚𐑦𐑜𐑨𐑯 𐑒𐑱𐑐𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑩𐑚𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑧𐑐𐑼𐑩𐑕𐑤𐑦.

𐑲 𐑩𐑚𐑟𐑻𐑝𐑛, 𐑣𐑬𐑧𐑝𐑼, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑛 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑩𐑤𐑵𐑓, 𐑯 𐑞𐑴 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑛𐑦𐑟𐑲𐑼𐑩𐑕 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑑 𐑕𐑐𐑶𐑤 𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑤𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑥𐑱𐑑𐑕 𐑚𐑲 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑴𐑯 𐑕𐑴𐑚𐑼 𐑓𐑱𐑕, 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑣𐑴𐑤 𐑣𐑰 𐑮𐑦𐑓𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑥𐑱𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑨𐑟 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑯𐑶𐑟 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑑. 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑩𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑥𐑰 𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑕; 𐑯 𐑕𐑦𐑯𐑕 𐑞 𐑕𐑰-𐑜𐑪𐑛𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑹𐑛𐑱𐑯𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑕𐑵𐑯 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑥𐑲 𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑥𐑱𐑑 (𐑞𐑴 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑩 𐑕𐑤𐑰𐑐𐑦𐑙-𐑐𐑸𐑑𐑯𐑼 𐑢𐑳𐑯, 𐑕𐑴 𐑓𐑸 𐑨𐑟 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑑𐑦𐑝 𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑻𐑯𐑛), 𐑲 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑣𐑽 𐑝𐑧𐑯𐑗𐑼 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑩 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑥. 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑑𐑫𐑛 𐑓𐑫𐑤 𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑕 𐑓𐑰𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑲𐑑, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑯𐑴𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑖𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑼𐑟, 𐑯 𐑩 𐑗𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑒𐑪𐑓𐑼-𐑛𐑨𐑥. 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑛𐑩𐑥 𐑕𐑰𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑚𐑮𐑷𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑥𐑨𐑯. 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑱𐑕 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑛𐑰𐑐𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑮𐑬𐑯 𐑯 𐑚𐑻𐑯𐑑, 𐑥𐑱𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑑𐑰𐑔 𐑛𐑨𐑟𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑭𐑕𐑑; 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑛𐑰𐑐 𐑖𐑨𐑛𐑴𐑟 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑲𐑟 𐑓𐑤𐑴𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑮𐑧𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑥 𐑑 𐑜𐑦𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑡𐑶. 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑝𐑶𐑕 𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑕 𐑩𐑯𐑬𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩 ·𐑕𐑳𐑞𐑼𐑯𐑼, 𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑲𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑗𐑼, 𐑲 𐑔𐑷𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑑𐑷𐑤 𐑥𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑽𐑟 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 ·𐑨𐑤𐑦𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑾𐑯 ·𐑮𐑦𐑡 𐑦𐑯 ·𐑝𐑼𐑡𐑦𐑯𐑾. 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑞 𐑮𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑮𐑦 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑨𐑯𐑘𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑥𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑑 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑣𐑲𐑑, 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑕𐑤𐑦𐑐𐑑 𐑩𐑢𐑱 𐑳𐑯𐑩𐑚𐑟𐑻𐑝𐑛, 𐑯 𐑲 𐑕𐑷 𐑯𐑴 𐑥𐑹 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑣𐑰 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑱𐑥 𐑥𐑲 𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑮𐑱𐑛 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑰. 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑓𐑿 𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑕, 𐑣𐑬𐑧𐑝𐑼, 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑥𐑱𐑑𐑕, 𐑯 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙, 𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑟, 𐑓 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑮𐑰𐑟𐑩𐑯 𐑩 𐑣𐑿𐑡 𐑓𐑱𐑝𐑼𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞𐑧𐑥, 𐑞𐑱 𐑮𐑱𐑟𐑛 𐑩 𐑒𐑮𐑲 𐑝 “𐑚𐑳𐑤𐑒𐑦𐑙𐑑𐑩𐑯! 𐑚𐑳𐑤𐑒𐑦𐑙𐑑𐑩𐑯! 𐑢𐑺'𐑟 ·𐑚𐑳𐑤𐑒𐑦𐑙𐑑𐑩𐑯?” 𐑯 𐑛𐑸𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑣𐑬𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑐𐑼𐑕𐑿𐑑 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑥.

𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑬 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑯𐑲𐑯 𐑴'𐑒𐑤𐑪𐑒, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑮𐑵𐑥 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑵𐑐𐑼𐑯𐑨𐑗𐑼𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑢𐑲𐑩𐑑 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑹𐑡𐑦𐑟, 𐑲 𐑚𐑦𐑜𐑨𐑯 𐑑 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑜𐑮𐑨𐑗𐑩𐑤𐑱𐑑 𐑥𐑲𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑩 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑐𐑤𐑨𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑩𐑒𐑻𐑛 𐑑 𐑥𐑰 𐑡𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑰𐑝𐑾𐑕 𐑑 𐑞 𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑧𐑯.

𐑯𐑴 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑓𐑻𐑟 𐑑 𐑕𐑤𐑰𐑐 𐑑𐑵 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑚𐑧𐑛. 𐑦𐑯 𐑓𐑨𐑒𐑑, 𐑿 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑩 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑛𐑰𐑤 𐑮𐑭𐑞𐑼 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑤𐑰𐑐 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑘𐑹 𐑴𐑯 𐑚𐑮𐑳𐑞𐑼. 𐑲 𐑛𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑯𐑴 𐑣𐑬 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑐𐑰𐑐𐑩𐑤 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑐𐑮𐑲𐑝𐑩𐑑 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑞𐑱 𐑸 𐑕𐑤𐑰𐑐𐑦𐑙. 𐑯 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑦𐑑 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑟 𐑑 𐑕𐑤𐑰𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩𐑯 𐑳𐑯𐑯𐑴𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑼, 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡 𐑦𐑯, 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡 𐑑𐑬𐑯, 𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑼 𐑩 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑽, 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑘𐑹 𐑩𐑚𐑡𐑧𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑧𐑓𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑥𐑳𐑤𐑑𐑦𐑐𐑤𐑲. 𐑯𐑹 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞𐑺 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑻𐑔𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑰𐑟𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑲 𐑲 𐑨𐑟 𐑩 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑼 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑕𐑤𐑰𐑐 𐑑𐑵 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑚𐑧𐑛, 𐑥𐑹 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑧𐑯𐑦𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦 𐑧𐑤𐑕; 𐑓 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑼𐑟 𐑯𐑴 𐑥𐑹 𐑕𐑤𐑰𐑐 𐑑𐑵 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑚𐑧𐑛 𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑰, 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑚𐑨𐑗𐑩𐑤𐑼 ·𐑒𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑛𐑵 𐑩𐑖𐑹. 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑖𐑫𐑼 𐑞𐑱 𐑷𐑤 𐑕𐑤𐑰𐑐 𐑑𐑩𐑜𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑩𐑐𐑸𐑑𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑿 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑘𐑹 𐑴𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑥𐑩𐑒, 𐑯 𐑒𐑳𐑝𐑼 𐑘𐑹𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑘𐑹 𐑴𐑯 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑩𐑑, 𐑯 𐑕𐑤𐑰𐑐 𐑦𐑯 𐑘𐑹 𐑴𐑯 𐑕𐑒𐑦𐑯.

𐑞 𐑥𐑹 𐑲 𐑐𐑪𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑛 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑽, 𐑞 𐑥𐑹 𐑲 𐑩𐑚𐑪𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑞 𐑔𐑷𐑑 𐑝 𐑕𐑤𐑰𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑥. 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑓𐑺 𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑿𐑥 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑽, 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑤𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑯 𐑹 𐑢𐑫𐑤𐑩𐑯, 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑒𐑱𐑕 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑚𐑰, 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑝 𐑞 𐑑𐑲𐑛𐑾𐑕𐑑, 𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑯𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑓𐑲𐑯𐑩𐑕𐑑. 𐑲 𐑚𐑦𐑜𐑨𐑯 𐑑 𐑑𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑷𐑤 𐑴𐑝𐑼. 𐑚𐑦𐑕𐑲𐑛𐑟, 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑜𐑧𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑤𐑱𐑑, 𐑯 𐑥𐑲 𐑛𐑰𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑽 𐑷𐑑 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑣𐑴𐑥 𐑯 𐑜𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑧𐑛𐑢𐑼𐑛𐑟. 𐑕𐑩𐑐𐑴𐑟 𐑯𐑬, 𐑣𐑰 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑑𐑳𐑥𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑥𐑰 𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑦𐑛𐑯𐑲𐑑—𐑣𐑬 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑲 𐑑𐑧𐑤 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑝𐑲𐑤 𐑣𐑴𐑤 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑦𐑙?

“𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑤𐑹𐑛! 𐑲'𐑝 𐑗𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑛 𐑥𐑲 𐑥𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑽.—𐑲 𐑖𐑭𐑯𐑑 𐑕𐑤𐑰𐑐 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑥. 𐑲'𐑤 𐑑𐑮𐑲 𐑞 𐑚𐑧𐑯𐑗 𐑣𐑽.”

“𐑡𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑿 𐑐𐑤𐑰𐑟; 𐑲'𐑥 𐑕𐑪𐑮𐑦 𐑲 𐑒𐑭𐑯𐑑 𐑕𐑐𐑺 𐑘𐑰 𐑩 𐑑𐑱𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑒𐑤𐑪𐑔 𐑓 𐑩 𐑥𐑨𐑑𐑮𐑩𐑕, 𐑯 𐑦𐑑'𐑕 𐑩 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑜𐑦 𐑮𐑳𐑓 𐑚𐑹𐑛 𐑣𐑽”—𐑓𐑰𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑞 𐑯𐑪𐑑𐑕 𐑯 𐑯𐑪𐑗𐑩𐑟. “𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑑 𐑩 𐑚𐑦𐑑, ·𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑟𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑼; 𐑲'𐑝 𐑜𐑪𐑑 𐑩 𐑒𐑸𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑼'𐑟 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑸—𐑢𐑱𐑑, 𐑲 𐑕𐑱, 𐑯 𐑲'𐑤 𐑥𐑱𐑒 𐑘𐑰 𐑕𐑯𐑳𐑜 𐑦𐑯𐑳𐑓.” 𐑕𐑴 𐑕𐑱𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑰 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑒𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑛 𐑞 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑯; 𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑕𐑦𐑤𐑒 𐑣𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑼𐑗𐑦𐑓 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑛𐑳𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑚𐑧𐑯𐑗, 𐑝𐑦𐑜𐑼𐑩𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑧𐑑 𐑑 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑢𐑱 𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑲 𐑚𐑧𐑛, 𐑞 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑜𐑮𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩𐑯 𐑱𐑐. 𐑞 𐑖𐑱𐑝𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑓𐑤𐑵 𐑮𐑲𐑑 𐑯 𐑤𐑧𐑓𐑑; 𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑞 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑯-𐑲𐑼𐑯 𐑒𐑱𐑥 𐑚𐑳𐑥𐑐 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑯𐑪𐑑. 𐑞 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑤𐑹𐑛 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑽 𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑑, 𐑯 𐑲 𐑑𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑓 𐑣𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑯'𐑟 𐑕𐑱𐑒 𐑑 𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑑—𐑞 𐑚𐑧𐑛 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑪𐑓𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑳𐑓 𐑑 𐑕𐑵𐑑 𐑥𐑰, 𐑯 𐑲 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑯𐑴 𐑣𐑬 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑥𐑱𐑒 𐑲𐑛𐑼 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑝 𐑩 𐑐𐑲𐑯 𐑐𐑤𐑨𐑙𐑒. 𐑕𐑴 𐑜𐑨𐑞𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑳𐑐 𐑞 𐑖𐑱𐑝𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩𐑯𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑜𐑮𐑦𐑯, 𐑯 𐑔𐑮𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑴𐑝 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑥𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑞 𐑮𐑵𐑥, 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑦𐑟𐑯𐑩𐑕, 𐑯 𐑤𐑧𐑓𐑑 𐑥𐑰 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑚𐑮𐑬𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑛𐑦.

𐑲 𐑯𐑬 𐑑𐑫𐑒 𐑞 𐑥𐑧𐑠𐑼 𐑝 𐑞 𐑚𐑧𐑯𐑗, 𐑯 𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩 𐑓𐑫𐑑 𐑑𐑵 𐑖𐑹𐑑; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑚𐑰 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑗𐑺. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩 𐑓𐑫𐑑 𐑑𐑵 𐑯𐑼𐑴, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑚𐑧𐑯𐑗 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑮𐑵𐑥 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑓𐑹 𐑦𐑯𐑗𐑩𐑟 𐑣𐑲𐑼 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑞 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑯𐑛 𐑢𐑳𐑯—𐑕𐑴 𐑞𐑺 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑴 𐑘𐑴𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑧𐑥. 𐑲 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕𐑑 𐑞 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑧𐑯𐑗 𐑤𐑧𐑙𐑔𐑢𐑲𐑟 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑞 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑤𐑽 𐑕𐑐𐑱𐑕 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑞 𐑢𐑷𐑤, 𐑤𐑰𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑝𐑩𐑤 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑢𐑰𐑯, 𐑓 𐑥𐑲 𐑚𐑨𐑒 𐑑 𐑕𐑧𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑦𐑯. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑲 𐑕𐑵𐑯 𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑒𐑱𐑥 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩 𐑛𐑮𐑭𐑓𐑑 𐑝 𐑒𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑺 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑥𐑰 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑞 𐑕𐑦𐑤 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑴, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑐𐑤𐑨𐑯 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑛𐑵 𐑨𐑑 𐑷𐑤, 𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑨𐑟 𐑩𐑯𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑒𐑳𐑮𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑑𐑦 𐑛𐑹 𐑥𐑧𐑑 𐑞 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑴, 𐑯 𐑚𐑴𐑔 𐑑𐑩𐑜𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑓𐑹𐑥𐑛 𐑩 𐑕𐑽𐑰𐑟 𐑝 𐑕𐑥𐑷𐑤 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑦𐑥𐑰𐑛𐑾𐑑 𐑝𐑦𐑕𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑪𐑑 𐑢𐑺 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑔𐑷𐑑 𐑑 𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑞 𐑯𐑲𐑑.

𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑤 𐑓𐑧𐑗 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑽, 𐑔𐑷𐑑 𐑲, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑪𐑐, 𐑒𐑫𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑲 𐑕𐑑𐑰𐑤 𐑩 𐑥𐑸𐑗 𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥—𐑚𐑴𐑤𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑛𐑹 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑲𐑛, 𐑯 𐑡𐑳𐑥𐑐 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑧𐑛, 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑢𐑱𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑒𐑦𐑙𐑟? 𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑯𐑴 𐑚𐑨𐑛 𐑲𐑛𐑾; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑕𐑧𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑔𐑷𐑑𐑕 𐑲 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑑. 𐑓 𐑣𐑵 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑑𐑧𐑤 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑞 𐑯𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑 𐑥𐑹𐑯𐑦𐑙, 𐑕𐑴 𐑕𐑵𐑯 𐑨𐑟 𐑲 𐑐𐑪𐑐𐑑 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑮𐑵𐑥, 𐑞 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑽 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑦, 𐑷𐑤 𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑦 𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑒 𐑥𐑰 𐑛𐑬𐑯!

𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤, 𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑥𐑰 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯, 𐑯 𐑕𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑯𐑴 𐑐𐑪𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑗𐑭𐑯𐑕 𐑝 𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑕𐑳𐑓𐑼𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑯𐑲𐑑 𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑧𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑐𐑻𐑕𐑩𐑯'𐑟 𐑚𐑧𐑛, 𐑲 𐑚𐑦𐑜𐑨𐑯 𐑑 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑷𐑤 𐑲 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑗𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑖𐑦𐑙 𐑳𐑯𐑢𐑪𐑮𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑡𐑩𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑳𐑯𐑯𐑴𐑯 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑽. 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑕 𐑲, 𐑲'𐑤 𐑢𐑱𐑑 𐑩𐑢𐑲𐑤; 𐑣𐑰 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑛𐑮𐑪𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑤𐑪𐑙. 𐑲'𐑤 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑩 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑤𐑫𐑒 𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑯 𐑐𐑼𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑕 𐑢𐑰 𐑥𐑱 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑡𐑪𐑤𐑦 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑚𐑧𐑛𐑓𐑧𐑤𐑴𐑟 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑷𐑤—𐑞𐑺'𐑟 𐑯𐑴 𐑑𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑙.

𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞𐑴 𐑞 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑚𐑹𐑛𐑼𐑟 𐑒𐑧𐑐𐑑 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑚𐑲 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑟, 𐑑𐑵𐑟, 𐑯 𐑔𐑮𐑰𐑟, 𐑯 𐑜𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑚𐑧𐑛, 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑯𐑴 𐑕𐑲𐑯 𐑝 𐑥𐑲 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑽.

“𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑤𐑹𐑛!” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑲, “𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑹𐑑 𐑝 𐑩 𐑗𐑨𐑐 𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑰—𐑛𐑳𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑷𐑤𐑢𐑱𐑟 𐑒𐑰𐑐 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑤𐑱𐑑 𐑬𐑼𐑟?” 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑬 𐑣𐑸𐑛 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑑𐑢𐑧𐑤𐑝 𐑴'𐑒𐑤𐑪𐑒.

𐑞 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑤𐑹𐑛 𐑗𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑤𐑰𐑯 𐑗𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑤, 𐑯 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑥𐑲𐑑𐑦𐑤𐑦 𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑦𐑘𐑪𐑯𐑛 𐑥𐑲 𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑣𐑧𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑯. “𐑯𐑴,” 𐑣𐑰 𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑼𐑛, “𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑣𐑰'𐑟 𐑩𐑯 𐑻𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑻𐑛—𐑺𐑤𐑦 𐑑 𐑚𐑧𐑛 𐑯 𐑺𐑤𐑦 𐑑 𐑮𐑲𐑟—𐑘𐑧𐑕, 𐑣𐑰'𐑟 𐑞 𐑚𐑻𐑛 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑒𐑨𐑗𐑩𐑟 𐑞 𐑢𐑻𐑥. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑑-𐑯𐑲𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑬𐑑 𐑩 𐑐𐑧𐑛𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙, 𐑿 𐑕𐑰, 𐑯 𐑲 𐑛𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑕𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑪𐑯 ·𐑱𐑻𐑔 𐑒𐑰𐑐𐑕 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑕𐑴 𐑤𐑱𐑑, 𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑧𐑕, 𐑥𐑱 𐑚𐑰, 𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑭𐑯𐑑 𐑕𐑧𐑤 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑧𐑛.”

“𐑒𐑭𐑯𐑑 𐑕𐑧𐑤 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑧𐑛?—𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑹𐑑 𐑝 𐑩 𐑚𐑨𐑥𐑚𐑵𐑟𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑑𐑹𐑦 𐑦𐑟 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑿 𐑸 𐑑𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑰?” 𐑜𐑧𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑩 𐑑𐑬𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑮𐑱𐑡. “𐑛𐑵 𐑿 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑑 𐑕𐑱, 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑤𐑹𐑛, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑽 𐑦𐑟 𐑨𐑒𐑗𐑵𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑯𐑜𐑱𐑡𐑛 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑚𐑤𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑨𐑑𐑼𐑛𐑱 𐑯𐑲𐑑, 𐑹 𐑮𐑭𐑞𐑼 𐑕𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑱 𐑥𐑹𐑯𐑦𐑙, 𐑦𐑯 𐑐𐑧𐑛𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑼𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑑𐑬𐑯?”

“𐑞𐑨𐑑'𐑕 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑲𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑑,” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑞 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑤𐑹𐑛, “𐑯 𐑲 𐑑𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑫𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑕𐑧𐑤 𐑦𐑑 𐑣𐑽, 𐑞 𐑥𐑸𐑒𐑩𐑑'𐑕 𐑴𐑝𐑼𐑕𐑑𐑪𐑒𐑑.”

“𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑢𐑪𐑑?” 𐑖𐑬𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑲.

“𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑟 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑖𐑫𐑼; 𐑱𐑯𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑑𐑵 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛?”

“𐑲 𐑑𐑧𐑤 𐑿 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟, 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑤𐑹𐑛,” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑲 𐑒𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑒𐑭𐑥𐑤𐑦, “𐑿'𐑛 𐑚𐑧𐑑𐑼 𐑕𐑑𐑪𐑐 𐑕𐑐𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑘𐑸𐑯 𐑑 𐑥𐑰—𐑲'𐑥 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑯.”

“𐑥𐑱 𐑚𐑰 𐑯𐑪𐑑,” 𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑬𐑑 𐑩 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑑𐑵𐑔𐑐𐑦𐑒, “𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑲 𐑮𐑱𐑔𐑼 𐑜𐑧𐑕 𐑿'𐑤 𐑚𐑰 𐑛𐑳𐑯 𐑚𐑮𐑬𐑯 𐑦𐑓 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑺 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑽 𐑣𐑽𐑟 𐑿 𐑩 𐑕𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑦𐑯' 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑧𐑛.”

“𐑲'𐑤 𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑒 𐑦𐑑 𐑓 𐑣𐑦𐑥,” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑲, 𐑯𐑬 𐑓𐑤𐑲𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑩 𐑐𐑭𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯 𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑳𐑯𐑩𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑓𐑼𐑭𐑜𐑴 𐑝 𐑞 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑤𐑹𐑛'𐑟.

“𐑦𐑑'𐑕 𐑚𐑮𐑴𐑒 𐑩'𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑦,” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑣𐑰.

“𐑚𐑮𐑴𐑒,” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑲—“𐑚𐑮𐑴𐑒, 𐑛𐑵 𐑿 𐑥𐑰𐑯?”

“𐑕𐑸𐑑𐑱𐑯, 𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑'𐑕 𐑞 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑮𐑰𐑟𐑩𐑯 𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑭𐑯𐑑 𐑕𐑧𐑤 𐑦𐑑, 𐑲 𐑜𐑧𐑕.”

“𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑤𐑹𐑛,” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑲, 𐑜𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑳𐑐 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑨𐑟 𐑒𐑵𐑤 𐑨𐑟 ·𐑥𐑑 ·𐑣𐑧𐑒𐑤𐑩 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑕𐑯𐑴-𐑕𐑑𐑹𐑥—“𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑤𐑹𐑛, 𐑕𐑑𐑪𐑐 𐑢𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙. 𐑿 𐑯 𐑲 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑩𐑯𐑳𐑞𐑼, 𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑑𐑵 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑱. 𐑲 𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑑 𐑘𐑹 𐑣𐑬𐑕 𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑯𐑑 𐑩 𐑚𐑧𐑛; 𐑿 𐑑𐑧𐑤 𐑥𐑰 𐑿 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑜𐑦𐑝 𐑥𐑰 𐑣𐑭𐑓 𐑩 𐑢𐑳𐑯; 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑣𐑭𐑓 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑪𐑙𐑟 𐑑 𐑩 𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑽. 𐑯 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑽, 𐑣𐑵𐑥 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑯, 𐑿 𐑐𐑼𐑕𐑦𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑑𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑰 𐑞 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑓𐑲𐑦𐑙 𐑯 𐑦𐑜𐑟𐑨𐑕𐑐𐑼𐑱𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑑𐑹𐑦𐑟 𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑜𐑧𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑰 𐑩𐑯 𐑳𐑯𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑓𐑼𐑑𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑓𐑰𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑑𐑩𐑢𐑹𐑛𐑟 𐑞 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑣𐑵𐑥 𐑿 𐑛𐑦𐑟𐑲𐑯 𐑓 𐑥𐑲 𐑚𐑧𐑛𐑓𐑧𐑤𐑴—𐑩 𐑕𐑹𐑑 𐑝 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑧𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯, 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑤𐑹𐑛, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑦𐑟 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑥𐑩𐑑 𐑯 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑓𐑦𐑛𐑧𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑣𐑲𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑜𐑮𐑰. 𐑲 𐑯𐑬 𐑛𐑦𐑥𐑭𐑯𐑛 𐑝 𐑿 𐑑 𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑒 𐑬𐑑 𐑯 𐑑𐑧𐑤 𐑥𐑰 𐑣𐑵 𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑽 𐑦𐑟, 𐑯 𐑢𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑲 𐑖𐑨𐑤 𐑚𐑰 𐑦𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑕 𐑕𐑱𐑓 𐑑 𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑞 𐑯𐑲𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑥. 𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕, 𐑿 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑚𐑰 𐑕𐑴 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑨𐑟 𐑑 𐑳𐑯𐑕𐑱 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑹𐑦 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑧𐑛, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑦𐑓 𐑑𐑮𐑵 𐑲 𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑧𐑝𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑽 𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑒 𐑥𐑨𐑛, 𐑯 𐑲'𐑝 𐑯𐑴 𐑲𐑛𐑾 𐑝 𐑕𐑤𐑰𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑥𐑨𐑛𐑥𐑩𐑯; 𐑯 𐑿, 𐑕𐑻, 𐑿 𐑲 𐑥𐑰𐑯, 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑤𐑹𐑛, 𐑿, 𐑕𐑻, 𐑚𐑲 𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑿𐑕 𐑥𐑰 𐑑 𐑛𐑵 𐑕𐑴 𐑯𐑴𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦, 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑞𐑺𐑚𐑲 𐑮𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑘𐑹𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑤𐑲𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑑 𐑩 𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑖𐑩𐑯.”

“𐑢𐑷𐑤,” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑞 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑤𐑹𐑛, 𐑓𐑧𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑚𐑮𐑧𐑔, “𐑞𐑨𐑑'𐑕 𐑩 𐑐𐑻𐑑𐑦 𐑤𐑪𐑙 ·𐑕𐑸𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑓 𐑩 𐑗𐑨𐑐 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑕 𐑩 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑯𐑬 𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑰𐑟𐑦, 𐑚𐑰 𐑰𐑟𐑦, 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑣𐑽 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑽 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑑𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑯' 𐑿 𐑝 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑡𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑼𐑲𐑝𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑕𐑬𐑔 𐑕𐑰𐑟, 𐑢𐑺 𐑣𐑰 𐑚𐑷𐑑 𐑳𐑐 𐑩 𐑤𐑪𐑑 𐑝 '𐑚𐑭𐑥𐑛 ·𐑯𐑿 ·𐑟𐑰𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑟 (𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑒𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑦𐑴𐑟, 𐑿 𐑯𐑴), 𐑯 𐑣𐑰'𐑟 𐑕𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑷𐑤 𐑪𐑯 '𐑩𐑥 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯, 𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑣𐑰'𐑟 𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑕𐑧𐑤 𐑑-𐑯𐑲𐑑, 𐑒𐑷𐑟 𐑑-𐑥𐑪𐑮𐑴'𐑟 𐑕𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑱, 𐑯 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑛𐑵 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑯' 𐑣𐑿𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑟 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑰𐑑𐑕 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑓𐑴𐑒𐑕 𐑦𐑟 𐑜𐑴𐑦𐑯' 𐑑 𐑗𐑻𐑗𐑩𐑟. 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑑, 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑱, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑲 𐑕𐑑𐑪𐑐𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑡𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑜𐑴𐑦𐑯' 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑛𐑹 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑓𐑹 𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑙 𐑪𐑯 𐑩 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑙, 𐑓 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 ·𐑱𐑻𐑔 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑙 𐑝 ·𐑦𐑯𐑾𐑯𐑟.”

𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑩𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑 𐑒𐑤𐑽𐑛 𐑳𐑐 𐑞 𐑳𐑞𐑼𐑢𐑲𐑟 𐑳𐑯𐑩𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑦, 𐑯 𐑖𐑴𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑤𐑹𐑛, 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑷𐑤, 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑯𐑴 𐑲𐑛𐑾 𐑝 𐑓𐑵𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑰—𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑲 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒 𐑝 𐑩 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑽 𐑣𐑵 𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑛 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑩 𐑕𐑨𐑑𐑼𐑛𐑱 𐑯𐑲𐑑 𐑒𐑤𐑰𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑦 ·𐑕𐑨𐑚𐑩𐑔, 𐑦𐑯𐑜𐑱𐑡𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑚𐑦𐑟𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑨𐑟 𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑟 𐑝 𐑛𐑧𐑛 𐑲𐑛𐑪𐑤𐑩𐑑𐑼𐑟?

“𐑛𐑦𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑦𐑑, 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑤𐑹𐑛, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑽 𐑦𐑟 𐑩 𐑛𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑼𐑩𐑕 𐑥𐑨𐑯.”

“𐑣𐑰 𐑐𐑱𐑟 𐑮𐑰𐑜'𐑤𐑸,” 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞 𐑮𐑦𐑡𐑶𐑯𐑛𐑼. “𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑒𐑳𐑥, 𐑦𐑑'𐑕 𐑜𐑧𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑛𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑤𐑱𐑑, 𐑿 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑧𐑑𐑼 𐑚𐑰 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑤𐑵𐑒𐑕—𐑦𐑑'𐑕 𐑩 𐑯𐑲𐑕 𐑚𐑧𐑛; ·𐑕𐑨𐑤 𐑯 𐑥𐑰 𐑕𐑤𐑧𐑐𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑺 𐑚𐑧𐑛 𐑞 𐑯𐑲𐑑 𐑢𐑰 𐑢𐑻 𐑕𐑐𐑤𐑲𐑕𐑑. 𐑞𐑺'𐑟 𐑐𐑤𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑦 𐑝 𐑮𐑵𐑥 𐑓 𐑑𐑵 𐑑 𐑒𐑦𐑒 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑚𐑧𐑛; 𐑦𐑑'𐑕 𐑩𐑯 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑲𐑑𐑦 𐑚𐑦𐑜 𐑚𐑧𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑. 𐑢𐑲, 𐑩𐑓𐑹 𐑢𐑰 𐑜𐑦𐑝 𐑦𐑑 𐑳𐑐, ·𐑕𐑨𐑤 𐑿𐑕𐑑 𐑑 𐑐𐑫𐑑 𐑬𐑼 ·𐑕𐑨𐑥 𐑯 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 ·𐑡𐑪𐑯𐑦 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑫𐑑 𐑝 𐑦𐑑. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑲 𐑜𐑪𐑑 𐑩 𐑛𐑮𐑰𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑯 𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑷𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑯𐑲𐑑, 𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑣𐑬, ·𐑕𐑨𐑥 𐑜𐑪𐑑 𐑐𐑦𐑗𐑑 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑤𐑹, 𐑯 𐑒𐑱𐑥 𐑯𐑽 𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑸𐑥. 𐑸𐑑𐑼 𐑞𐑨𐑑, ·𐑕𐑨𐑤 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑫𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑛𐑵. 𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑣𐑽, 𐑲'𐑤 𐑜𐑦𐑝 𐑘𐑰 𐑩 𐑜𐑤𐑦𐑥 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑡𐑦𐑓𐑦;” 𐑯 𐑕𐑴 𐑕𐑱𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑰 𐑤𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑩 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑤 𐑯 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑛 𐑦𐑑 𐑑𐑩𐑢𐑹𐑛𐑟 𐑥𐑰, 𐑪𐑓𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑤𐑰𐑛 𐑞 𐑢𐑱. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑲 𐑕𐑑𐑫𐑛 𐑦𐑮𐑧𐑟𐑩𐑤𐑵𐑑; 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑨𐑑 𐑩 𐑒𐑤𐑪𐑒 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑒𐑹𐑯𐑼, 𐑣𐑰 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑒𐑤𐑱𐑥𐑛 “𐑲 𐑝𐑳𐑥 𐑦𐑑'𐑕 𐑕𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑱—𐑿 𐑢𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑕𐑰 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑽 𐑑-𐑯𐑲𐑑; 𐑣𐑰'𐑟 𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑑 𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑼 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑢𐑺—𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑞𐑧𐑯; 𐑛𐑵 𐑒𐑳𐑥; 𐑢𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑘𐑰 𐑒𐑳𐑥?”

𐑲 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑼𐑛 𐑞 𐑥𐑨𐑑𐑼 𐑩 𐑥𐑴𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑, 𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑳𐑐 𐑕𐑑𐑺𐑟 𐑢𐑰 𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑑, 𐑯 𐑲 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑳𐑖𐑼𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑩 𐑕𐑥𐑷𐑤 𐑮𐑵𐑥, 𐑒𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑨𐑟 𐑩 𐑒𐑤𐑨𐑥, 𐑯 𐑓𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑖𐑑, 𐑖𐑫𐑼 𐑦𐑯𐑳𐑓, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑛𐑦𐑡𐑩𐑕 𐑚𐑧𐑛, 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑜 𐑦𐑯𐑳𐑓 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑰𐑛 𐑓 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑓𐑹 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑽𐑟 𐑑 𐑕𐑤𐑰𐑐 𐑩𐑚𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑑.

“𐑞𐑺,” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑞 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑤𐑹𐑛, 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑤 𐑪𐑯 𐑩 𐑒𐑮𐑱𐑟𐑦 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑕𐑰 𐑗𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑛𐑳𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑛𐑿𐑑𐑦 𐑨𐑟 𐑩 𐑢𐑪𐑖-𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑯 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑼 𐑑𐑱𐑚𐑩𐑤; “𐑞𐑺, 𐑥𐑱𐑒 𐑘𐑹𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑓𐑼𐑑𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑯𐑬, 𐑯 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑯𐑲𐑑 𐑑 𐑘𐑰.” 𐑲 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑛 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑲𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑚𐑧𐑛, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑩𐑐𐑽𐑛.

𐑓𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑨𐑒 𐑞 𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑐𐑱𐑯, 𐑲 𐑕𐑑𐑵𐑐𐑑 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑞 𐑚𐑧𐑛. 𐑞𐑴 𐑯𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑜𐑩𐑯𐑑, 𐑦𐑑 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑫𐑛 𐑞 𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑵𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑦 𐑑𐑪𐑤𐑼𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑢𐑧𐑤. 𐑲 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑜𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑞 𐑮𐑵𐑥; 𐑯 𐑚𐑦𐑕𐑲𐑛𐑟 𐑞 𐑚𐑧𐑛𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑛 𐑯 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑼 𐑑𐑱𐑚𐑩𐑤, 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑕𐑰 𐑯𐑴 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑓𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑗𐑼 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑪𐑙𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑞 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑩 𐑮𐑵𐑛 𐑖𐑧𐑤𐑓, 𐑞 𐑓𐑹 𐑢𐑷𐑤𐑟, 𐑯 𐑩 𐑐𐑱𐑐𐑼𐑛 𐑓𐑲𐑼𐑚𐑹𐑛 𐑮𐑧𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑢𐑱𐑤. 𐑝 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑐𐑼𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑪𐑙𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑞 𐑮𐑵𐑥, 𐑞𐑺 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩 𐑣𐑨𐑥𐑩𐑒 𐑤𐑨𐑖𐑑 𐑳𐑐, 𐑯 𐑔𐑮𐑴𐑯 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑤𐑹 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑒𐑹𐑯𐑼; 𐑷𐑤𐑕𐑴 𐑩 𐑤𐑸𐑡 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑩𐑯'𐑟 𐑚𐑨𐑜, 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑱𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑽'𐑟 𐑢𐑹𐑛𐑮𐑴𐑚, 𐑯𐑴 𐑛𐑬𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑤𐑵 𐑝 𐑩 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑙𐑒. 𐑤𐑲𐑒𐑢𐑲𐑟, 𐑞𐑺 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩 𐑐𐑸𐑕𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑬𐑑𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑖 𐑚𐑴𐑯 𐑓𐑦𐑖 𐑣𐑫𐑒𐑕 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑖𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑞 𐑓𐑲𐑼-𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕, 𐑯 𐑩 𐑑𐑷𐑤 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑝 𐑞 𐑚𐑧𐑛.

𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑗𐑧𐑕𐑑? 𐑲 𐑑𐑫𐑒 𐑦𐑑 𐑳𐑐, 𐑯 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑛 𐑦𐑑 𐑒𐑤𐑴𐑕 𐑑 𐑞 𐑤𐑲𐑑, 𐑯 𐑓𐑧𐑤𐑑 𐑦𐑑, 𐑯 𐑕𐑥𐑧𐑤𐑑 𐑦𐑑, 𐑯 𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑛 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑢𐑱 𐑐𐑪𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑑 𐑼𐑲𐑝 𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑕𐑨𐑑𐑦𐑕𐑓𐑨𐑒𐑑𐑼𐑦 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑒𐑤𐑵𐑠𐑩𐑯 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑑. 𐑲 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑺 𐑦𐑑 𐑑 𐑯𐑳𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑩 𐑤𐑸𐑡 𐑛𐑹 𐑥𐑨𐑑, 𐑹𐑯𐑩𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑧𐑡𐑩𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑑𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑑𐑨𐑜𐑟 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑯𐑛 𐑐𐑹𐑒𐑿𐑐𐑲𐑯 𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑤𐑟 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑩𐑯 ·𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑾𐑯 𐑥𐑪𐑒𐑩𐑕𐑦𐑯. 𐑞𐑺 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩 𐑣𐑴𐑤 𐑹 𐑕𐑤𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑥𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑥𐑨𐑑, 𐑨𐑟 𐑿 𐑕𐑰 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑦𐑯 ·𐑕𐑬𐑔 ·𐑩𐑥𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑐𐑪𐑯𐑗𐑴𐑟. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑦𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑐𐑪𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑕𐑴𐑚𐑼 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑽 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑜𐑧𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑩 𐑛𐑹 𐑥𐑨𐑑, 𐑯 𐑐𐑼𐑱𐑛 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑰𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑧𐑯𐑦 ·𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑗𐑩𐑯 𐑑𐑬𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑹𐑑 𐑝 𐑜𐑲𐑟? 𐑲 𐑐𐑫𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑪𐑯, 𐑑 𐑑𐑮𐑲 𐑦𐑑, 𐑯 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑛 𐑥𐑰 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑣𐑨𐑥𐑐𐑼, 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑳𐑯𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑖𐑨𐑜𐑦 𐑯 𐑔𐑦𐑒, 𐑯 𐑲 𐑔𐑷𐑑 𐑩 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑛𐑨𐑥𐑐, 𐑨𐑟 𐑞𐑴 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑽𐑾𐑕 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑽 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑢𐑺𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑑 𐑝 𐑩 𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑦 𐑛𐑱. 𐑲 𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑳𐑐 𐑦𐑯 𐑦𐑑 𐑑 𐑩 𐑚𐑦𐑑 𐑝 𐑜𐑤𐑭𐑕 𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑒 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑞 𐑢𐑷𐑤, 𐑯 𐑲 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑕𐑷 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩 𐑕𐑲𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑲 𐑤𐑲𐑓. 𐑲 𐑑𐑹 𐑥𐑲𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩 𐑣𐑳𐑮𐑦 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑲 𐑜𐑱𐑝 𐑥𐑲𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑩 𐑒𐑦𐑙𐑒 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑯𐑧𐑒.

𐑲 𐑕𐑨𐑑 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑝 𐑞 𐑚𐑧𐑛, 𐑯 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑣𐑧𐑛-𐑐𐑧𐑛𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑽, 𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑛𐑹 𐑥𐑨𐑑. 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑧𐑛-𐑕𐑲𐑛, 𐑲 𐑜𐑪𐑑 𐑳𐑐 𐑯 𐑑𐑫𐑒 𐑪𐑓 𐑥𐑲 𐑥𐑳𐑙𐑒𐑦 𐑡𐑨𐑒𐑩𐑑, 𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑫𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑥𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑞 𐑮𐑵𐑥 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑦𐑙. 𐑲 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑑𐑫𐑒 𐑪𐑓 𐑥𐑲 𐑒𐑴𐑑, 𐑯 𐑔𐑷𐑑 𐑩 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑥𐑹 𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑲 𐑖𐑻𐑑 𐑕𐑤𐑰𐑝𐑟. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑜𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑓𐑰𐑤 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑒𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑯𐑬, 𐑣𐑭𐑓 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑲 𐑢𐑪𐑟, 𐑯 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑧𐑥𐑚𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑞 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑤𐑹𐑛 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑞 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑽'𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑴𐑥 𐑨𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑯𐑲𐑑, 𐑦𐑑 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑴 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑤𐑱𐑑, 𐑲 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑯𐑴 𐑥𐑹 𐑩𐑛𐑵, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑡𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑑 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑥𐑲 𐑐𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑵𐑯𐑟 𐑯 𐑚𐑵𐑑𐑕, 𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑚𐑤𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑬𐑑 𐑞 𐑤𐑲𐑑 𐑑𐑳𐑥𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑚𐑧𐑛, 𐑯 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑥𐑲𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑑 𐑞 𐑒𐑺 𐑝 𐑣𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑯.

𐑢𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑨𐑑𐑮𐑩𐑕 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑓𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑒𐑹𐑯-𐑒𐑪𐑚𐑟 𐑹 𐑚𐑮𐑴𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑒𐑮𐑪𐑒𐑼𐑦, 𐑞𐑺 𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑴 𐑑𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑙, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑲 𐑮𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑩 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑛𐑰𐑤, 𐑯 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑤𐑰𐑐 𐑓 𐑩 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑑𐑲𐑥. 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑲 𐑕𐑤𐑦𐑛 𐑪𐑓 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑩 𐑤𐑲𐑑 𐑛𐑴𐑟, 𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑯𐑽𐑤𐑦 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑩 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑪𐑓𐑦𐑙 𐑑𐑩𐑢𐑹𐑛𐑟 𐑞 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑝 ·𐑯𐑪𐑛, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑲 𐑣𐑻𐑛 𐑩 𐑣𐑧𐑝𐑦 𐑓𐑫𐑑𐑓𐑷𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑐𐑨𐑕𐑦𐑡, 𐑯 𐑕𐑷 𐑩 𐑜𐑤𐑦𐑥𐑼 𐑝 𐑤𐑲𐑑 𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑮𐑵𐑥 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑞 𐑛𐑹.

𐑤𐑹𐑛 𐑕𐑱𐑝 𐑥𐑰, 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑕 𐑲, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑞 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑽, 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑓𐑻𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑣𐑧𐑛-𐑐𐑧𐑛𐑩𐑤𐑼. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑲 𐑤𐑱 𐑐𐑻𐑓𐑦𐑒𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤, 𐑯 𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑪𐑤𐑝𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑑 𐑕𐑱 𐑩 𐑢𐑻𐑛 𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑕𐑐𐑴𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑑. 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑤𐑲𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛, 𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑲𐑛𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 ·𐑯𐑿 ·𐑟𐑰𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑳𐑞𐑼, 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑼 𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑛 𐑞 𐑮𐑵𐑥, 𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑 𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑑𐑩𐑢𐑹𐑛𐑟 𐑞 𐑚𐑧𐑛, 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑤 𐑩 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑢𐑱 𐑪𐑓 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑥𐑰 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑤𐑹 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑒𐑹𐑯𐑼, 𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑚𐑦𐑜𐑨𐑯 𐑢𐑻𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑢𐑱 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑯𐑪𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑒𐑹𐑛𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑤𐑸𐑡 𐑚𐑨𐑜 𐑲 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑕𐑐𐑴𐑒 𐑝 𐑨𐑟 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑮𐑵𐑥. 𐑲 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑷𐑤 𐑰𐑜𐑼𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑑 𐑕𐑰 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑱𐑕, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑧𐑐𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑩𐑝𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑓 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑶𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑳𐑯𐑤𐑱𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑚𐑨𐑜'𐑟 𐑥𐑬𐑔. 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑩𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑦𐑖𐑑, 𐑣𐑬𐑧𐑝𐑼, 𐑣𐑰 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑛 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛—𐑢𐑧𐑯, 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑣𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑯𐑟! 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑩 𐑕𐑲𐑑! 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩 𐑓𐑱𐑕! 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑝 𐑩 𐑛𐑸𐑒, 𐑐𐑻𐑐𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑖, 𐑘𐑧𐑤𐑴 𐑒𐑳𐑤𐑼, 𐑣𐑽 𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑒 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑤𐑸𐑡 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑒𐑦𐑖 𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑒𐑢𐑺𐑟. 𐑘𐑧𐑕, 𐑦𐑑'𐑕 𐑡𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑲 𐑔𐑷𐑑, 𐑣𐑰'𐑟 𐑩 𐑑𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑚𐑧𐑛𐑓𐑧𐑤𐑴; 𐑣𐑰'𐑟 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑓𐑲𐑑, 𐑜𐑪𐑑 𐑛𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑓𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑳𐑑, 𐑯 𐑣𐑽 𐑣𐑰 𐑦𐑟, 𐑡𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑕𐑻𐑡𐑩𐑯. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑴𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑗𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑑 𐑑𐑻𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑱𐑕 𐑕𐑴 𐑑𐑩𐑢𐑹𐑛𐑟 𐑞 𐑤𐑲𐑑, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑲 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑷 𐑞𐑱 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑦𐑙-𐑐𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑟 𐑨𐑑 𐑷𐑤, 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑒 𐑕𐑒𐑢𐑺𐑟 𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑗𐑰𐑒𐑕. 𐑞𐑱 𐑢𐑻 𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑕𐑹𐑑 𐑹 𐑳𐑞𐑼. 𐑨𐑑 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑲 𐑯𐑿 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑑 𐑥𐑱𐑒 𐑝 𐑞𐑦𐑕; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑕𐑵𐑯 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑞 𐑑𐑮𐑵𐑔 𐑩𐑒𐑻𐑛 𐑑 𐑥𐑰. 𐑲 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑧𐑥𐑚𐑼𐑛 𐑩 𐑕𐑑𐑹𐑦 𐑝 𐑩 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑥𐑨𐑯—𐑩 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑑𐑵—𐑣𐑵, 𐑓𐑷𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑞 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑟, 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑑𐑩𐑑𐑵𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑞𐑧𐑥. 𐑲 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑒𐑤𐑵𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑽, 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑒𐑹𐑕 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑝𐑶𐑦𐑡𐑩𐑟, 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑥𐑧𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑕𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑤𐑼 𐑩𐑛𐑝𐑧𐑯𐑗𐑼. 𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑑, 𐑔𐑷𐑑 𐑲, 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑷𐑤! 𐑦𐑑'𐑕 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑬𐑑𐑕𐑲𐑛; 𐑩 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑚𐑰 𐑪𐑯𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑕𐑹𐑑 𐑝 𐑕𐑒𐑦𐑯. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑑 𐑥𐑱𐑒 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑳𐑯𐑻𐑔𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑧𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑐𐑸𐑑 𐑝 𐑦𐑑, 𐑲 𐑥𐑰𐑯, 𐑤𐑲𐑦𐑙 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑, 𐑯 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑰𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑒𐑢𐑺𐑟 𐑝 𐑑𐑩𐑑𐑵𐑦𐑙. 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑖𐑫𐑼, 𐑦𐑑 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑯𐑳𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑩 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑒𐑴𐑑 𐑝 𐑑𐑮𐑪𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑙; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑲 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑣𐑻𐑛 𐑝 𐑩 𐑣𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑯'𐑟 𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑩 𐑐𐑻𐑐𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑖 𐑘𐑧𐑤𐑴 𐑢𐑳𐑯. 𐑣𐑬𐑧𐑝𐑼, 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑬𐑔 ·𐑕𐑰𐑟; 𐑯 𐑐𐑼𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑕 𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑛𐑿𐑕𐑑 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑹𐑛𐑦𐑯𐑼𐑦 𐑦𐑓𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑕 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑒𐑦𐑯. 𐑯𐑬, 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑲𐑛𐑾𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑐𐑭𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑥𐑰 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑤𐑲𐑑𐑯𐑦𐑙, 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑽 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑯𐑴𐑑𐑦𐑕𐑑 𐑥𐑰 𐑨𐑑 𐑷𐑤. 𐑚𐑳𐑑, 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑛𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑒𐑳𐑤𐑑𐑦 𐑣𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑴𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑨𐑜, 𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑓𐑳𐑥𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑦𐑑, 𐑯 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑫𐑤𐑛 𐑬𐑑 𐑩 𐑕𐑹𐑑 𐑝 𐑑𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑣𐑷𐑒, 𐑯 𐑩 𐑕𐑰𐑤-𐑕𐑒𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑤𐑩𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑣𐑺 𐑪𐑯. 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑗𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑥𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑞 𐑮𐑵𐑥, 𐑣𐑰 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑑𐑫𐑒 𐑞 ·𐑯𐑿 ·𐑟𐑰𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑣𐑧𐑛—𐑩 𐑜𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯𐑳𐑓—𐑯 𐑒𐑮𐑨𐑥𐑛 𐑦𐑑 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑚𐑨𐑜. 𐑣𐑰 𐑯𐑬 𐑑𐑫𐑒 𐑪𐑓 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑑—𐑩 𐑯𐑿 𐑚𐑰𐑝𐑼 𐑣𐑨𐑑—𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑲 𐑒𐑱𐑥 𐑯𐑲 𐑕𐑦𐑙𐑦𐑙 𐑬𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑖 𐑕𐑼𐑐𐑮𐑲𐑟. 𐑞𐑺 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑴 𐑣𐑺 𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑧𐑛—𐑯𐑳𐑯 𐑑 𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑒 𐑝 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑰𐑕𐑑—𐑯𐑳𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑩 𐑕𐑥𐑷𐑤 𐑕𐑒𐑨𐑤𐑐-𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑑𐑢𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑳𐑐 𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑛. 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑷𐑤𐑛 𐑐𐑻𐑐𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑖 𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑯𐑬 𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑑 𐑓 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑥𐑦𐑤𐑛𐑿𐑛 𐑕𐑒𐑳𐑤. 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑼 𐑕𐑑𐑫𐑛 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑢𐑰𐑯 𐑥𐑰 𐑯 𐑞 𐑛𐑹, 𐑲 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑚𐑴𐑤𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑦𐑑 𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑒𐑼 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑲 𐑚𐑴𐑤𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑩 𐑛𐑦𐑯𐑼.

𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟, 𐑲 𐑔𐑷𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑕𐑤𐑦𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑴, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞 𐑕𐑧𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑓𐑤𐑹 𐑚𐑨𐑒. 𐑲 𐑨𐑥 𐑯𐑴 𐑒𐑬𐑼𐑛, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑑 𐑥𐑱𐑒 𐑝 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑣𐑧𐑛-𐑐𐑧𐑛𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑐𐑻𐑐𐑩𐑤 𐑮𐑭𐑕𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑷𐑤𐑑𐑩𐑜𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑐𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑥𐑲 𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑣𐑧𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑯. 𐑦𐑜𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑦𐑟 𐑞 𐑐𐑺𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑓𐑽, 𐑯 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑰𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑯𐑪𐑯𐑐𐑤𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑯 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑼, 𐑲 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑓𐑧𐑕 𐑲 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑬 𐑨𐑟 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑩𐑓𐑮𐑱𐑛 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑓 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑤 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑣𐑵 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑞𐑳𐑕 𐑚𐑮𐑴𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑥𐑲 𐑮𐑵𐑥 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑛 𐑝 𐑯𐑲𐑑. 𐑦𐑯 𐑓𐑨𐑒𐑑, 𐑲 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑴 𐑩𐑓𐑮𐑱𐑛 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑲 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑜𐑱𐑥 𐑦𐑯𐑳𐑓 𐑡𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑑 𐑩𐑛𐑮𐑧𐑕 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑯 𐑛𐑦𐑥𐑭𐑯𐑛 𐑩 𐑕𐑨𐑑𐑦𐑕𐑓𐑨𐑒𐑑𐑼𐑦 𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑼 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑤𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥.

𐑥𐑰𐑯𐑢𐑲𐑤, 𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑿𐑛 𐑞 𐑚𐑦𐑟𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑦𐑙, 𐑯 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑖𐑴𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑗𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑯 𐑸𐑥𐑟. 𐑨𐑟 𐑲 𐑤𐑦𐑝, 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑒𐑳𐑝𐑼𐑛 𐑐𐑸𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑢𐑻 𐑗𐑧𐑒𐑼𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑕𐑒𐑢𐑺𐑟 𐑨𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑱𐑕; 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑨𐑒, 𐑑𐑵, 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑷𐑤 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑛𐑸𐑒 𐑕𐑒𐑢𐑺𐑟; 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 ·𐑔𐑻𐑑𐑦 ·𐑘𐑽𐑟' ·𐑢𐑹, 𐑯 𐑡𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑱𐑐𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑦𐑙-𐑐𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑼 𐑖𐑻𐑑. 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑥𐑹, 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑤𐑧𐑜𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑥𐑸𐑒𐑑, 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑓 𐑩 𐑐𐑸𐑕𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑛𐑸𐑒 𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑜𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑮𐑳𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑳𐑐 𐑞 𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑙𐑒𐑕 𐑝 𐑘𐑳𐑙 𐑐𐑭𐑥𐑟. 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑬 𐑒𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑩𐑚𐑪𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑡 𐑹 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑑 𐑩𐑚𐑹𐑛 𐑝 𐑩 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑬𐑔 ·𐑕𐑰𐑟, 𐑯 𐑕𐑴 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 ·𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑗𐑩𐑯 𐑒𐑳𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑦. 𐑲 𐑒𐑢𐑱𐑒𐑑 𐑑 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒 𐑝 𐑦𐑑. 𐑩 𐑐𐑧𐑛𐑩𐑤𐑼 𐑝 𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑟 𐑑𐑵—𐑐𐑼𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑕 𐑞 𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑟 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑴𐑯 𐑚𐑮𐑳𐑞𐑼𐑟. 𐑣𐑰 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑩 𐑓𐑨𐑯𐑕𐑦 𐑑 𐑥𐑲𐑯—𐑣𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑯𐑟! 𐑤𐑫𐑒 𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑑𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑣𐑷𐑒!

𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑴 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑓 𐑖𐑳𐑛𐑼𐑦𐑙, 𐑓 𐑯𐑬 𐑞 𐑕𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑡 𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑰𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑓𐑨𐑕𐑦𐑯𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑥𐑲 𐑩𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑯, 𐑯 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑝𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑥𐑰 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑰𐑛 𐑚𐑰 𐑩 𐑣𐑰𐑞𐑩𐑯. 𐑜𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑧𐑝𐑦 ·𐑜𐑮𐑧𐑜𐑴, 𐑹 𐑮𐑨𐑐𐑷𐑤, 𐑹 𐑛𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑯𐑷𐑑, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑐𐑮𐑰𐑝𐑾𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑣𐑳𐑙 𐑪𐑯 𐑩 𐑗𐑺, 𐑣𐑰 𐑓𐑳𐑥𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑐𐑪𐑒𐑩𐑑𐑕, 𐑯 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑛𐑿𐑕𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑧𐑙𐑔 𐑩 𐑒𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑾𐑕 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑛𐑦𐑓𐑹𐑥𐑛 𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑡 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑗 𐑪𐑯 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑚𐑨𐑒, 𐑯 𐑦𐑜𐑟𐑨𐑒𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑞 𐑒𐑳𐑤𐑼 𐑝 𐑩 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑛𐑱𐑟' 𐑴𐑤𐑛 ·𐑒𐑪𐑙𐑜𐑴 𐑚𐑱𐑚𐑦. 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑧𐑥𐑚𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑦𐑥𐑚𐑭𐑥𐑛 𐑣𐑧𐑛, 𐑨𐑑 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑲 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑔𐑷𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑒 𐑥𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑒𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩 𐑮𐑾𐑤 𐑚𐑱𐑚𐑦 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑻𐑝𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑕𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑤𐑼 𐑥𐑨𐑯𐑼. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑤𐑦𐑥𐑚𐑼, 𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑜𐑤𐑦𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑩 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑛𐑰𐑤 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑐𐑪𐑤𐑦𐑖𐑑 𐑧𐑚𐑩𐑯𐑦, 𐑲 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑒𐑤𐑵𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑯𐑳𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑩 𐑢𐑫𐑛𐑩𐑯 𐑲𐑛𐑩𐑤, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑰𐑛 𐑦𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑵𐑝𐑛 𐑑 𐑚𐑰. 𐑓 𐑯𐑬 𐑞 𐑕𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑡 𐑜𐑴𐑟 𐑳𐑐 𐑑 𐑞 𐑧𐑥𐑐𐑑𐑦 𐑓𐑲𐑼-𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕, 𐑯 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑵𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑐𐑱𐑐𐑼𐑛 𐑓𐑲𐑼-𐑚𐑹𐑛, 𐑕𐑧𐑑𐑕 𐑳𐑐 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑗-𐑚𐑨𐑒𐑑 𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑡, 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑐𐑦𐑯, 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑢𐑰𐑯 𐑞 𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑲𐑼𐑯𐑟. 𐑞 𐑗𐑦𐑥𐑯𐑦 𐑡𐑨𐑥𐑟 𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑚𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑕 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑢𐑻 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑕𐑫𐑑𐑦, 𐑕𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑲 𐑔𐑷𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑓𐑲𐑼-𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑩 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑩𐑐𐑮𐑴𐑐𐑮𐑾𐑑 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑖𐑮𐑲𐑯 𐑹 𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑩𐑤 𐑓 𐑣𐑦𐑟 ·𐑒𐑪𐑙𐑜𐑴 𐑲𐑛𐑩𐑤.

𐑲 𐑯𐑬 𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑵𐑛 𐑥𐑲 𐑲𐑟 𐑣𐑸𐑛 𐑑𐑩𐑢𐑹𐑛𐑟 𐑞 𐑣𐑭𐑓 𐑣𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑡, 𐑓𐑰𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑤 𐑨𐑑 𐑰𐑟 𐑥𐑰𐑯𐑑𐑲𐑥—𐑑 𐑕𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑 𐑑 𐑓𐑪𐑤𐑴. 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑕 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑩 𐑛𐑳𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑓𐑫𐑤 𐑝 𐑖𐑱𐑝𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 ·𐑜𐑮𐑧𐑜𐑴 𐑐𐑪𐑒𐑩𐑑, 𐑯 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑒𐑺𐑓𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑞 𐑲𐑛𐑩𐑤; 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑤𐑱𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑚𐑦𐑑 𐑝 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑚𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑦𐑑 𐑪𐑯 𐑑𐑪𐑐 𐑯 𐑩𐑐𐑤𐑲𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑓𐑤𐑱𐑥 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑤𐑨𐑥𐑐, 𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑞 𐑖𐑱𐑝𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑩 𐑕𐑨𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑤 𐑚𐑤𐑱𐑟. 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦, 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑣𐑱𐑕𐑑𐑦 𐑕𐑯𐑨𐑗𐑩𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑓𐑲𐑼, 𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑣𐑱𐑕𐑑𐑽 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑛𐑮𐑷𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑼𐑟 (𐑢𐑺𐑚𐑲 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑕𐑒𐑹𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑚𐑨𐑛𐑤𐑦), 𐑣𐑰 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑩𐑒𐑕𐑰𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑛𐑮𐑷𐑦𐑙 𐑬𐑑 𐑞 𐑚𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑦𐑑; 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑚𐑤𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑪𐑓 𐑞 𐑣𐑰𐑑 𐑯 𐑨𐑖𐑩𐑟 𐑩 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤, 𐑣𐑰 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑩 𐑐𐑩𐑤𐑲𐑑 𐑪𐑓𐑼 𐑝 𐑦𐑑 𐑑 𐑞 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑯𐑰𐑜𐑮𐑴. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑛𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑤 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑥 𐑑 𐑓𐑨𐑯𐑕𐑦 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑛𐑮𐑲 𐑕𐑹𐑑 𐑝 𐑓𐑺 𐑨𐑑 𐑷𐑤; 𐑣𐑰 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑥𐑵𐑝𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑤𐑦𐑐𐑕. 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡 𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑕 𐑢𐑻 𐑩𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑼 𐑜𐑳𐑑𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑯𐑶𐑟𐑩𐑟 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑑𐑰, 𐑣𐑵 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑐𐑮𐑱𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑕𐑦𐑙-𐑕𐑪𐑙 𐑹 𐑧𐑤𐑕 𐑕𐑦𐑙𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑐𐑱𐑜𐑩𐑯 𐑕𐑭𐑥𐑩𐑛𐑦 𐑹 𐑳𐑞𐑼, 𐑛𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑱𐑕 𐑑𐑢𐑦𐑗𐑑 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑳𐑯𐑯𐑨𐑗𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑥𐑨𐑯𐑼. 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑢𐑦𐑖𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑓𐑲𐑼, 𐑣𐑰 𐑑𐑫𐑒 𐑞 𐑲𐑛𐑩𐑤 𐑳𐑐 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑳𐑯𐑕𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑾𐑕𐑤𐑦, 𐑯 𐑚𐑨𐑜𐑛 𐑦𐑑 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 ·𐑜𐑮𐑧𐑜𐑴 𐑐𐑪𐑒𐑩𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑒𐑺𐑤𐑩𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑓 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑻 𐑩 𐑕𐑐𐑹𐑑𐑕𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑚𐑨𐑜𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑛𐑧𐑛 𐑢𐑫𐑛𐑒𐑪𐑒.

𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑒𐑢𐑽 𐑐𐑮𐑴𐑕𐑰𐑛𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑮𐑰𐑕𐑑 𐑥𐑲 𐑳𐑯𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑓𐑼𐑑𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑯𐑩𐑕, 𐑯 𐑕𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑯𐑬 𐑦𐑜𐑟𐑦𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑪𐑙 𐑕𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑑𐑩𐑥𐑟 𐑝 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑒𐑤𐑵𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑦𐑟𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑪𐑐𐑼𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟, 𐑯 𐑡𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑚𐑧𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑥𐑰, 𐑲 𐑔𐑷𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑣𐑲 𐑑𐑲𐑥, 𐑯𐑬 𐑹 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼, 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑞 𐑤𐑲𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑐𐑫𐑑 𐑬𐑑, 𐑑 𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑒 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑕𐑴 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑚𐑬𐑯𐑛.

𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑝𐑩𐑤 𐑲 𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑚𐑼𐑱𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑑 𐑕𐑱, 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩 𐑓𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑳𐑯. 𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑳𐑐 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑑𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑣𐑷𐑒 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑑𐑱𐑚𐑩𐑤, 𐑣𐑰 𐑦𐑜𐑟𐑨𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑛 𐑞 𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑝 𐑦𐑑 𐑓 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑, 𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑑 𐑑 𐑞 𐑤𐑲𐑑, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑬𐑔 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑤, 𐑣𐑰 𐑐𐑳𐑓𐑑 𐑬𐑑 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑒𐑤𐑬𐑛𐑟 𐑝 𐑑𐑩𐑚𐑨𐑒𐑴 𐑕𐑥𐑴𐑒. 𐑞 𐑯𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑 𐑥𐑴𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑞 𐑤𐑲𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑢𐑦𐑖𐑑, 𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑲𐑤𐑛 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑚𐑩𐑤, 𐑑𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑣𐑷𐑒 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑢𐑰𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑑𐑰𐑔, 𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑨𐑙 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑚𐑧𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑥𐑰. 𐑲 𐑕𐑨𐑙 𐑬𐑑, 𐑲 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑐 𐑦𐑑 𐑯𐑬; 𐑯 𐑜𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑕𐑳𐑛𐑩𐑯 𐑜𐑮𐑳𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑩𐑕𐑑𐑪𐑯𐑦𐑖𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑚𐑦𐑜𐑨𐑯 𐑓𐑰𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑰.

𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑥𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑬𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑔𐑦𐑙, 𐑲 𐑯𐑿 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑑, 𐑲 𐑮𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑩𐑢𐑱 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑞 𐑢𐑷𐑤, 𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑒𐑳𐑯𐑡𐑼𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑣𐑵𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑹 𐑢𐑪𐑑𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑣𐑰 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑚𐑰, 𐑑 𐑒𐑰𐑐 𐑒𐑢𐑲𐑩𐑑, 𐑯 𐑤𐑧𐑑 𐑥𐑰 𐑜𐑧𐑑 𐑳𐑐 𐑯 𐑤𐑲𐑑 𐑞 𐑤𐑨𐑥𐑐 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑜𐑳𐑑𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑕𐑨𐑑𐑦𐑕𐑓𐑲𐑛 𐑥𐑰 𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑕 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑤 𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑣𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑥𐑲 𐑥𐑰𐑯𐑦𐑙.

“𐑣𐑵-𐑰 𐑛𐑰𐑚𐑧𐑤 𐑿?”—𐑣𐑰 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑧𐑛—“𐑿 𐑯𐑴 𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑒-𐑰, 𐑛𐑨𐑥-𐑥𐑰, 𐑲 𐑒𐑦𐑤-𐑰.” 𐑯 𐑕𐑴 𐑕𐑱𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑤𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑑𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑣𐑷𐑒 𐑚𐑦𐑜𐑨𐑯 𐑓𐑤𐑳𐑮𐑦𐑖𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑥𐑰 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑛𐑸𐑒.

“𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑤𐑹𐑛, 𐑓 ·𐑜𐑪𐑛'𐑟 𐑕𐑱𐑒, ·𐑐𐑰𐑑𐑼 ·𐑒𐑪𐑓𐑦𐑯!” 𐑖𐑬𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑲. “𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑤𐑹𐑛! 𐑢𐑪𐑗! 𐑒𐑪𐑓𐑦𐑯! 𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑩𐑤𐑟! 𐑕𐑱𐑝 𐑥𐑰!”

“𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑒-𐑰! 𐑑𐑧𐑤-ee 𐑥𐑰 𐑣𐑵-ee 𐑚𐑰, 𐑹 𐑛𐑨𐑥-𐑥𐑰, 𐑲 𐑒𐑦𐑤-𐑰!” 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯 𐑜𐑮𐑬𐑤𐑛 𐑞 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑚𐑩𐑤, 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑛 𐑓𐑤𐑳𐑮𐑦𐑖𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑑𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑣𐑷𐑒 𐑕𐑒𐑨𐑑𐑼𐑛 𐑞 𐑣𐑪𐑑 𐑑𐑩𐑚𐑨𐑒𐑴 𐑨𐑖𐑩𐑟 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑥𐑰 𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑲 𐑔𐑷𐑑 𐑥𐑲 𐑤𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑜𐑧𐑑 𐑪𐑯 𐑓𐑲𐑼. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑔𐑨𐑙𐑒 𐑣𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑯, 𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑴𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑞 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑤𐑹𐑛 𐑒𐑱𐑥 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑮𐑵𐑥 𐑤𐑲𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛, 𐑯 𐑤𐑰𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑚𐑧𐑛 𐑲 𐑮𐑨𐑯 𐑳𐑐 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥.

“𐑛𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑩𐑓𐑮𐑱𐑛 𐑯𐑬,” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑣𐑰, 𐑜𐑮𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯, “·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜 𐑣𐑽 𐑢𐑫𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑣𐑸𐑥 𐑩 𐑣𐑺 𐑝 𐑘𐑹 𐑣𐑧𐑛.”

“𐑕𐑑𐑪𐑐 𐑘𐑹 𐑜𐑮𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑙,” 𐑖𐑬𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑲, “𐑯 𐑢𐑲 𐑛𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑿 𐑑𐑧𐑤 𐑥𐑰 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑓𐑻𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑽 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑚𐑩𐑤?”

“𐑲 𐑔𐑷𐑑 𐑘𐑰 𐑯𐑴'𐑛 𐑦𐑑;—𐑛𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑲 𐑑𐑧𐑤 𐑘𐑰, 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩 𐑐𐑧𐑛𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑯' 𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑟 𐑼𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑑𐑬𐑯?—𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑑𐑻𐑯 𐑓𐑤𐑵𐑒𐑕 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯 𐑯 𐑜𐑴 𐑑 𐑕𐑤𐑰𐑐. ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜, 𐑤𐑫𐑒 𐑣𐑽—𐑿 𐑕𐑨𐑚𐑰 𐑥𐑰, 𐑲 𐑕𐑨𐑚𐑰—𐑿 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑕𐑤𐑰𐑐 𐑿—𐑿 𐑕𐑨𐑚𐑰?”

“𐑥𐑰 𐑕𐑨𐑚𐑰 𐑐𐑤𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑦”—𐑜𐑮𐑳𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜, 𐑐𐑳𐑓𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑢𐑱 𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑲𐑐 𐑯 𐑕𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑳𐑐 𐑦𐑯 𐑚𐑧𐑛.

“𐑿 𐑜𐑧𐑑𐑰 𐑦𐑯,” 𐑣𐑰 𐑨𐑛𐑩𐑛, 𐑥𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑥𐑰 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑑𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑣𐑷𐑒, 𐑯 𐑔𐑮𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑒𐑤𐑴𐑞𐑟 𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑕𐑲𐑛. 𐑣𐑰 𐑮𐑾𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑩 𐑕𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑤 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑩 𐑮𐑾𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑯 𐑗𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑱. 𐑲 𐑕𐑑𐑫𐑛 𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑩 𐑥𐑴𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑. 𐑓 𐑷𐑤 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑑𐑩𐑑𐑵𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑣𐑴𐑤 𐑩 𐑒𐑤𐑰𐑯, 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑤𐑦 𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑚𐑩𐑤. 𐑢𐑪𐑑'𐑕 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑓𐑳𐑕 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑥𐑱𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑, 𐑔𐑷𐑑 𐑲 𐑑 𐑥𐑲𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓—𐑞 𐑥𐑨𐑯'𐑟 𐑩 𐑣𐑿𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑡𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑲 𐑨𐑥: 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑡𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑮𐑰𐑟𐑩𐑯 𐑑 𐑓𐑽 𐑥𐑰, 𐑨𐑟 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑓 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑩𐑓𐑮𐑱𐑛 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑥. 𐑚𐑧𐑑𐑼 𐑕𐑤𐑰𐑐 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑕𐑴𐑚𐑼 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑩 𐑛𐑮𐑳𐑙𐑒𐑩𐑯 ·𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑗𐑩𐑯.

“𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑤𐑹𐑛,” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑲, “𐑑𐑧𐑤 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑖 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑑𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑣𐑷𐑒 𐑞𐑺, 𐑹 𐑐𐑲𐑐, 𐑹 𐑢𐑪𐑑𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑿 𐑒𐑷𐑤 𐑦𐑑; 𐑑𐑧𐑤 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑪𐑐 𐑕𐑥𐑴𐑒𐑦𐑙, 𐑦𐑯 𐑖𐑹𐑑, 𐑯 𐑲 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑑𐑻𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑥. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑲 𐑛𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑓𐑨𐑯𐑕𐑦 𐑣𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑕𐑥𐑴𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑚𐑧𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑥𐑰. 𐑦𐑑'𐑕 𐑛𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑼𐑩𐑕. 𐑚𐑦𐑕𐑲𐑛𐑟, 𐑲 𐑱𐑯𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑖𐑫𐑼𐑛.”

𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑑𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑑 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜, 𐑣𐑰 𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑕 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑲𐑛, 𐑯 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯 𐑐𐑩𐑤𐑲𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑥𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑥𐑰 𐑑 𐑜𐑧𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑚𐑧𐑛—𐑮𐑴𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑨𐑟 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑨𐑟 𐑑 𐑕𐑱—“𐑲 𐑢𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑑𐑳𐑗 𐑩 𐑤𐑧𐑜 𐑝 𐑘𐑰.”

“𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑯𐑲𐑑, 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑤𐑹𐑛,” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑲, “𐑿 𐑥𐑱 𐑜𐑴.”

𐑲 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑯, 𐑯 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑕𐑤𐑧𐑐𐑑 𐑚𐑧𐑑𐑼 𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑲 𐑤𐑲𐑓.

·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 4. 𐑞 ·𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑐𐑱𐑯.

𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑢𐑱𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑯𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑 𐑥𐑹𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑛𐑱𐑤𐑲𐑑, 𐑲 𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜'𐑟 𐑸𐑥 𐑔𐑮𐑴𐑯 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑥𐑰 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑤𐑳𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑯 𐑩𐑓𐑧𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑑 𐑥𐑨𐑯𐑼. 𐑿 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑔𐑷𐑑 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑲𐑓. 𐑞 𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑐𐑱𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑝 𐑐𐑨𐑗𐑢𐑻𐑒, 𐑓𐑫𐑤 𐑝 𐑪𐑛 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑐𐑸𐑑𐑦-𐑒𐑳𐑤𐑼𐑛 𐑕𐑒𐑢𐑺𐑟 𐑯 𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑨𐑙𐑜𐑩𐑤𐑟; 𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑸𐑥 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑑𐑩𐑑𐑵𐑛 𐑷𐑤 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑻𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 ·𐑒𐑮𐑰𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑤𐑨𐑚𐑼𐑦𐑯𐑔 𐑝 𐑩 𐑓𐑦𐑜𐑼, 𐑯𐑴 𐑑𐑵 𐑐𐑸𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑢𐑻 𐑝 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑲𐑕 𐑖𐑱𐑛—𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑲 𐑕𐑩𐑐𐑴𐑟 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑰𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑸𐑥 𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑰 𐑳𐑯𐑥𐑦𐑔𐑪𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑯 𐑯 𐑖𐑱𐑛, 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑖𐑻𐑑 𐑕𐑤𐑰𐑝𐑟 𐑦𐑮𐑧𐑜𐑿𐑤𐑼𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑳𐑐 𐑨𐑑 𐑝𐑺𐑾𐑕 𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟—𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑸𐑥 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟, 𐑲 𐑕𐑱, 𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑑 𐑓 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑐 𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑐𐑨𐑗𐑢𐑻𐑒 𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑤𐑑. 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑰𐑛, 𐑐𐑸𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑤𐑲𐑦𐑙 𐑪𐑯 𐑦𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑸𐑥 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑲 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑩𐑢𐑴𐑒, 𐑲 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑣𐑸𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑑𐑧𐑤 𐑦𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑤𐑑, 𐑞𐑱 𐑕𐑴 𐑚𐑤𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑞𐑺 𐑣𐑿𐑟 𐑑𐑩𐑜𐑧𐑞𐑼; 𐑯 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑕 𐑝 𐑢𐑱𐑑 𐑯 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑖𐑼 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑲 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑑𐑧𐑤 𐑞𐑨𐑑 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑣𐑳𐑜𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑰.

𐑥𐑲 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑕𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡. 𐑤𐑧𐑑 𐑥𐑰 𐑑𐑮𐑲 𐑑 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑥. 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑲 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩 𐑗𐑲𐑤𐑛, 𐑲 𐑢𐑧𐑤 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑧𐑥𐑚𐑼 𐑩 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑤𐑼 𐑕𐑻𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑕 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑧𐑤 𐑥𐑰; 𐑢𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩 𐑮𐑦𐑨𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑹 𐑩 𐑛𐑮𐑰𐑥, 𐑲 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑲𐑼𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑧𐑑𐑩𐑤. 𐑞 𐑕𐑻𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑕 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞𐑦𐑕. 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑒𐑳𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑳𐑐 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑒𐑱𐑐𐑼 𐑹 𐑳𐑞𐑼—𐑲 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑒𐑮𐑷𐑤 𐑳𐑐 𐑞 𐑗𐑦𐑥𐑯𐑦, 𐑨𐑟 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑕𐑰𐑯 𐑩 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑢𐑰𐑐 𐑛𐑵 𐑩 𐑓𐑿 𐑛𐑱𐑟 𐑐𐑮𐑰𐑝𐑾𐑕; 𐑯 𐑥𐑲 𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑐𐑥𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑣𐑵, 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑣𐑬 𐑹 𐑳𐑞𐑼, 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑢𐑦𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑰, 𐑹 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑰 𐑑 𐑚𐑧𐑛 𐑕𐑳𐑐𐑼𐑤𐑩𐑕,—𐑥𐑲 𐑥𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑛𐑮𐑨𐑜𐑛 𐑥𐑰 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑤𐑧𐑜𐑟 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑗𐑦𐑥𐑯𐑦 𐑯 𐑐𐑨𐑒𐑑 𐑥𐑰 𐑪𐑓 𐑑 𐑚𐑧𐑛, 𐑞𐑴 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑑𐑵 𐑴'𐑒𐑤𐑪𐑒 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼𐑯𐑵𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 21𐑕𐑑 𐑡𐑵𐑯, 𐑞 𐑤𐑪𐑙𐑜𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑛𐑱 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑘𐑽 𐑦𐑯 𐑬𐑼 𐑣𐑧𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑓𐑽. 𐑲 𐑓𐑧𐑤𐑑 𐑛𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑓𐑩𐑤𐑦. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑴 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑐 𐑓 𐑦𐑑, 𐑕𐑴 𐑳𐑐 𐑕𐑑𐑺𐑟 𐑲 𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑑 𐑥𐑲 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑮𐑵𐑥 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑔𐑻𐑛 𐑓𐑤𐑹, 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑥𐑲𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑨𐑟 𐑕𐑤𐑴𐑤𐑦 𐑨𐑟 𐑐𐑪𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑴 𐑨𐑟 𐑑 𐑒𐑦𐑤 𐑑𐑲𐑥, 𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑼 𐑕𐑲 𐑜𐑪𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑢𐑰𐑯 𐑞 𐑖𐑰𐑑𐑕.

𐑲 𐑤𐑱 𐑞𐑺 𐑛𐑦𐑟𐑥𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑨𐑤𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑱𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑰𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑲𐑼 𐑬𐑼𐑟 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑤𐑨𐑐𐑕 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑲 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑣𐑴𐑐 𐑓 𐑩 𐑮𐑧𐑟𐑼𐑧𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯. 𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑰𐑯 𐑬𐑼𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑚𐑧𐑛! 𐑞 𐑕𐑥𐑷𐑤 𐑝 𐑥𐑲 𐑚𐑨𐑒 𐑱𐑒𐑑 𐑑 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒 𐑝 𐑦𐑑. 𐑯 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑴 𐑤𐑲𐑑 𐑑𐑵; 𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑯 𐑖𐑲𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑴, 𐑯 𐑩 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑮𐑨𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑒𐑴𐑗𐑩𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑰𐑑𐑕, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑝 𐑜𐑱 𐑝𐑶𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑷𐑤 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑞 𐑣𐑬𐑕. 𐑲 𐑓𐑧𐑤𐑑 𐑢𐑻𐑕 𐑯 𐑢𐑻𐑕—𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑲 𐑜𐑪𐑑 𐑳𐑐, 𐑛𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑑, 𐑯 𐑕𐑪𐑓𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑜𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑲 𐑕𐑑𐑪𐑒𐑦𐑙𐑛 𐑓𐑰𐑑, 𐑕𐑷𐑑 𐑬𐑑 𐑥𐑲 𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑐𐑥𐑳𐑞𐑼, 𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑥𐑲𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑻 𐑓𐑰𐑑, 𐑚𐑦𐑕𐑰𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑻 𐑨𐑟 𐑩 𐑐𐑼𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑼 𐑓𐑱𐑝𐑼 𐑑 𐑜𐑦𐑝 𐑥𐑰 𐑩 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑕𐑤𐑦𐑐𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑓 𐑥𐑲 𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑚𐑦𐑣𐑱𐑝𐑘𐑼; 𐑧𐑯𐑦𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑰𐑛 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑛𐑧𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑰 𐑑 𐑤𐑲 𐑩𐑚𐑧𐑛 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩𐑯 𐑳𐑯𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑻𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑤𐑧𐑙𐑔 𐑝 𐑑𐑲𐑥. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑖𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞 𐑚𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑯 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑖𐑦𐑧𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑐𐑥𐑳𐑞𐑼𐑟, 𐑯 𐑚𐑨𐑒 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑑 𐑜𐑴 𐑑 𐑥𐑲 𐑮𐑵𐑥. 𐑓 𐑕𐑧𐑝𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑬𐑼𐑟 𐑲 𐑤𐑱 𐑞𐑺 𐑚𐑮𐑷𐑛 𐑩𐑢𐑱𐑒, 𐑓𐑰𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑛𐑰𐑤 𐑢𐑻𐑕 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑛𐑳𐑯 𐑕𐑦𐑯𐑕, 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑚𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑢𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑓𐑹𐑗𐑵𐑯𐑟. 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑲 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑓𐑷𐑤𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑩 𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑯𐑲𐑑𐑥𐑺 𐑝 𐑩 𐑛𐑴𐑟; 𐑯 𐑕𐑤𐑴𐑤𐑦 𐑢𐑱𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑦𐑑—𐑣𐑭𐑓 𐑕𐑑𐑰𐑐𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑛𐑮𐑰𐑥𐑟—𐑲 𐑴𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑥𐑲 𐑲𐑟, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑕𐑳𐑯-𐑤𐑦𐑑 𐑮𐑵𐑥 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑬 𐑮𐑨𐑐𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑬𐑑𐑼 𐑛𐑸𐑒𐑯𐑩𐑕. 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑲 𐑓𐑧𐑤𐑑 𐑩 𐑖𐑪𐑒 𐑮𐑳𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑷𐑤 𐑥𐑲 𐑓𐑮𐑱𐑥; 𐑯𐑳𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑕𐑰𐑯, 𐑯 𐑯𐑳𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑣𐑻𐑛; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑩 𐑕𐑵𐑐𐑼𐑯𐑨𐑗𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑲𐑯. 𐑥𐑲 𐑸𐑥 𐑣𐑳𐑙 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑞 𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑐𐑱𐑯, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑯𐑱𐑥𐑤𐑩𐑕, 𐑳𐑯𐑦𐑥𐑨𐑡𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤, 𐑕𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑓𐑹𐑥 𐑹 𐑓𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑥, 𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑞 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑪𐑙𐑛, 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑒𐑤𐑴𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑰𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑥𐑲 𐑚𐑧𐑛-𐑕𐑲𐑛. 𐑓 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑱𐑡𐑩𐑟 𐑐𐑲𐑤𐑛 𐑪𐑯 𐑱𐑡𐑩𐑟, 𐑲 𐑤𐑱 𐑞𐑺, 𐑓𐑮𐑴𐑟𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑷𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑓𐑽𐑟, 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑛𐑺𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑛𐑮𐑨𐑜 𐑩𐑢𐑱 𐑥𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛; 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑓 𐑲 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑻 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑕𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑯𐑗, 𐑞 𐑣𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑛 𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑤 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑚𐑰 𐑚𐑮𐑴𐑒𐑩𐑯. 𐑲 𐑯𐑿 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑣𐑬 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑕𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑜𐑤𐑲𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑩𐑢𐑱 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑥𐑰; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑥𐑹𐑯𐑦𐑙, 𐑲 𐑖𐑳𐑛𐑼𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑧𐑥𐑚𐑼𐑛 𐑦𐑑 𐑷𐑤, 𐑯 𐑓 𐑛𐑱𐑟 𐑯 𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑕 𐑯 𐑥𐑳𐑯𐑔𐑕 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼𐑢𐑼𐑛𐑟 𐑲 𐑤𐑪𐑕𐑑 𐑥𐑲𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑦𐑯 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑑𐑧𐑥𐑐𐑑𐑕 𐑑 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑯 𐑞 𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑦. 𐑯𐑱, 𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑬𐑼, 𐑲 𐑪𐑓𐑩𐑯 𐑐𐑳𐑟𐑩𐑤 𐑥𐑲𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑦𐑑.

𐑯𐑬, 𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑩𐑢𐑱 𐑞 𐑷𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑓𐑽, 𐑯 𐑥𐑲 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑕𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑨𐑑 𐑓𐑰𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑕𐑵𐑐𐑼𐑯𐑨𐑗𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑲𐑯 𐑢𐑻 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑕𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑤𐑼, 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑯𐑩𐑕, 𐑑 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑲 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑽𐑾𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑪𐑯 𐑢𐑱𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑳𐑐 𐑯 𐑕𐑰𐑦𐑙 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜'𐑟 𐑐𐑱𐑜𐑩𐑯 𐑸𐑥 𐑔𐑮𐑴𐑯 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑥𐑰. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑧𐑙𐑔 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑐𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑯𐑲𐑑'𐑕 𐑦𐑝𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑕𐑴𐑚𐑼𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑳𐑮𐑛, 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑚𐑲 𐑢𐑳𐑯, 𐑦𐑯 𐑓𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑨𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑦, 𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑲 𐑤𐑱 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑩𐑤𐑲𐑝 𐑑 𐑞 𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑. 𐑓 𐑞𐑴 𐑲 𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑛 𐑑 𐑥𐑵𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑸𐑥—𐑳𐑯𐑤𐑪𐑒 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑮𐑲𐑛𐑜𐑮𐑵𐑥 𐑒𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑐—𐑘𐑧𐑑, 𐑕𐑤𐑰𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑨𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟, 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑣𐑳𐑜𐑛 𐑥𐑰 𐑑𐑲𐑑𐑤𐑦, 𐑨𐑟 𐑞𐑴 𐑯𐑷𐑑 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑛𐑧𐑔 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑐𐑸𐑑 𐑳𐑕 𐑑𐑢𐑱𐑯. 𐑲 𐑯𐑬 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑴𐑝 𐑑 𐑮𐑬𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑥—“·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜!”—𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑼 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩 𐑕𐑯𐑹. 𐑲 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑮𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑴𐑝𐑼, 𐑥𐑲 𐑯𐑧𐑒 𐑓𐑰𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑓 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑻 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑣𐑹𐑕-𐑒𐑪𐑤𐑼; 𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑓𐑧𐑤𐑑 𐑩 𐑕𐑤𐑲𐑑 𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑨𐑗. 𐑔𐑮𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑞 𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑐𐑱𐑯, 𐑞𐑺 𐑤𐑱 𐑞 𐑑𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑣𐑷𐑒 𐑕𐑤𐑰𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑕𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑡'𐑩𐑟 𐑕𐑲𐑛, 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑓 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑻 𐑩 𐑣𐑨𐑗𐑩𐑑-𐑓𐑱𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑱𐑚𐑦. 𐑩 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤, 𐑑𐑮𐑵𐑤𐑦, 𐑔𐑷𐑑 𐑲; 𐑩𐑚𐑧𐑛 𐑣𐑽 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡 𐑣𐑬𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑮𐑷𐑛 𐑛𐑱, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑯 𐑩 𐑑𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑣𐑷𐑒! “·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜!—𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑯𐑱𐑥 𐑝 𐑜𐑫𐑛𐑯𐑩𐑕, ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜, 𐑢𐑱𐑒!” 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑧𐑙𐑔, 𐑚𐑲 𐑛𐑦𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑮𐑦𐑜𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙, 𐑯 𐑤𐑬𐑛 𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑪𐑕𐑗𐑩𐑤𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑳𐑯𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑦𐑙𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑳𐑜𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑓𐑧𐑤𐑴 𐑥𐑱𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑨𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑾𐑤 𐑕𐑹𐑑 𐑝 𐑕𐑑𐑲𐑤, 𐑲 𐑕𐑩𐑒𐑕𐑰𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑜𐑮𐑳𐑯𐑑; 𐑯 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦, 𐑣𐑰 𐑛𐑮𐑵 𐑚𐑨𐑒 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑸𐑥, 𐑖𐑫𐑒 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑷𐑤 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 ·𐑯𐑿𐑓𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑛𐑪𐑜 𐑡𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼, 𐑯 𐑕𐑨𐑑 𐑳𐑐 𐑦𐑯 𐑚𐑧𐑛, 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑓 𐑨𐑟 𐑩 𐑐𐑲𐑒-𐑕𐑑𐑭𐑓, 𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑰, 𐑯 𐑮𐑳𐑚𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑲𐑟 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑓 𐑣𐑰 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑷𐑤𐑑𐑩𐑜𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑧𐑥𐑚𐑼 𐑣𐑬 𐑲 𐑒𐑱𐑥 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑞𐑺, 𐑞𐑴 𐑩 𐑛𐑦𐑥 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑕𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑯𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑥𐑰 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑕𐑤𐑴𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑷𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑣𐑦𐑥. 𐑥𐑰𐑯𐑢𐑲𐑤, 𐑲 𐑤𐑱 𐑒𐑢𐑲𐑩𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑲𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑣𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑯𐑴 𐑕𐑽𐑾𐑕 𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑜𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑯𐑬, 𐑯 𐑚𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑯𐑼𐑴𐑤𐑦 𐑩𐑚𐑟𐑻𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑴 𐑒𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑾𐑕 𐑩 𐑒𐑮𐑰𐑗𐑼. 𐑢𐑧𐑯, 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑, 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑳𐑐 𐑑𐑳𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑒𐑨𐑮𐑩𐑒𐑑𐑼 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑧𐑛𐑓𐑧𐑤𐑴, 𐑯 𐑣𐑰 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑱𐑥, 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑻, 𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑲𐑤𐑛 𐑑 𐑞 𐑓𐑨𐑒𐑑; 𐑣𐑰 𐑡𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑑 𐑬𐑑 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑤𐑹, 𐑯 𐑚𐑲 𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑕𐑲𐑯𐑟 𐑯 𐑕𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑜𐑱𐑝 𐑥𐑰 𐑑 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑, 𐑦𐑓 𐑦𐑑 𐑐𐑤𐑰𐑟𐑛 𐑥𐑰, 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑛𐑮𐑧𐑕 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑤𐑰𐑝 𐑥𐑰 𐑑 𐑛𐑮𐑧𐑕 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼𐑢𐑼𐑛𐑟, 𐑤𐑰𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑣𐑴𐑤 𐑩𐑐𐑸𐑑𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑑 𐑥𐑲𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓. 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑕 𐑲, ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜, 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑞 𐑕𐑻𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟, 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑦𐑟 𐑩 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑕𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑤𐑲𐑟𐑛 𐑴𐑝𐑼𐑗𐑫𐑼; 𐑚𐑳𐑑, 𐑞 𐑑𐑮𐑵𐑔 𐑦𐑟, 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑕𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑡𐑩𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑱𐑑 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑕 𐑝 𐑛𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑕𐑦, 𐑕𐑱 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑿 𐑢𐑦𐑤; 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑸𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑣𐑬 𐑦𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑩𐑤𐑲𐑑 𐑞𐑱 𐑸. 𐑲 𐑐𐑱 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑐𐑼𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑼 𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑦𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑑 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜, 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑪𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑑𐑮𐑰𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑥𐑰 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑕𐑴 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑕𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑯 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑼𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯, 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑲 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑜𐑦𐑤𐑑𐑦 𐑝 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑮𐑵𐑛𐑯𐑩𐑕; 𐑕𐑑𐑺𐑦𐑙 𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑚𐑧𐑛, 𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑷𐑤 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑑𐑢𐑭𐑤𐑧𐑑 𐑥𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟; 𐑓 𐑞 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑥𐑲 𐑒𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑦𐑪𐑕𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑜𐑧𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑚𐑧𐑑𐑼 𐑝 𐑥𐑲 𐑚𐑮𐑰𐑛𐑦𐑙. 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼𐑞𐑩𐑤𐑧𐑕, 𐑩 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑤𐑲𐑒 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜 𐑿 𐑛𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑕𐑰 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑛𐑱, 𐑣𐑰 𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑱𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑢𐑧𐑤 𐑢𐑻𐑔 𐑳𐑯𐑿𐑠𐑵𐑩𐑤 𐑮𐑦𐑜𐑸𐑛𐑦𐑙.

𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑛𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑨𐑑 𐑑𐑪𐑐 𐑚𐑲 𐑛𐑪𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑰𐑝𐑼 𐑣𐑨𐑑, 𐑩 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑑𐑷𐑤 𐑢𐑳𐑯, 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑚𐑲, 𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯—𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑥𐑲𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑑𐑮𐑴𐑟𐑼𐑟—𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑳𐑐 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑵𐑑𐑕. 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑞 𐑣𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑦𐑑 𐑓, 𐑲 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑑𐑧𐑤, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑 𐑥𐑵𐑝𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑑 𐑒𐑮𐑳𐑖 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓—𐑚𐑵𐑑𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛, 𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑑 𐑪𐑯—𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑞 𐑚𐑧𐑛; 𐑢𐑧𐑯, 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑕𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑮𐑦 𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑜𐑭𐑕𐑐𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑦𐑙𐑟, 𐑲 𐑦𐑯𐑓𐑻𐑛 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑣𐑸𐑛 𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑻𐑒 𐑚𐑵𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓; 𐑞𐑴 𐑚𐑲 𐑯𐑴 𐑤𐑷 𐑝 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑐𐑮𐑲𐑩𐑑𐑦 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑲 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑣𐑻𐑛 𐑝, 𐑦𐑟 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑢𐑲𐑼𐑛 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑐𐑮𐑲𐑝𐑩𐑑 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑐𐑫𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑵𐑑𐑕. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜, 𐑛𐑵 𐑿 𐑕𐑰, 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩 𐑒𐑮𐑰𐑗𐑼 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑟𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑡—𐑯𐑲𐑞𐑼 𐑒𐑨𐑑𐑼𐑐𐑦𐑤𐑼 𐑯𐑹 𐑚𐑳𐑑𐑼𐑓𐑤𐑲. 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑡𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑳𐑓 𐑕𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑤𐑲𐑟𐑛 𐑑 𐑖𐑴 𐑪𐑓 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑬𐑑𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑖𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑐𐑪𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑥𐑨𐑯𐑼𐑟. 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑧𐑡𐑩𐑒𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑰𐑑𐑩𐑛. 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩𐑯 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑜𐑮𐑨𐑡𐑵𐑩𐑑. 𐑦𐑓 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑩 𐑕𐑥𐑷𐑤 𐑛𐑦𐑜𐑮𐑰 𐑕𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑤𐑲𐑟𐑛, 𐑣𐑰 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑚𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑚𐑵𐑑𐑕 𐑨𐑑 𐑷𐑤; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑦𐑓 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑩 𐑕𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑡, 𐑣𐑰 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑛𐑮𐑧𐑥𐑑 𐑝 𐑜𐑧𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑞 𐑚𐑧𐑛 𐑑 𐑐𐑫𐑑 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑪𐑯. 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑, 𐑣𐑰 𐑦𐑥𐑻𐑡𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑑 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑛𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑯 𐑒𐑮𐑳𐑖𐑑 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑲𐑟, 𐑯 𐑚𐑦𐑜𐑨𐑯 𐑒𐑮𐑰𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑯 𐑤𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑞 𐑮𐑵𐑥, 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑓, 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑩𐑒𐑳𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑥𐑛 𐑑 𐑚𐑵𐑑𐑕, 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑺 𐑝 𐑛𐑨𐑥𐑐, 𐑮𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑒𐑬𐑣𐑲𐑛 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑟—𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑚𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑑 𐑹𐑛𐑼 𐑲𐑞𐑼—𐑮𐑭𐑞𐑼 𐑐𐑦𐑯𐑗𐑑 𐑯 𐑑𐑹𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑜𐑴 𐑪𐑓 𐑝 𐑩 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑼 𐑒𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑥𐑹𐑯𐑦𐑙.

𐑕𐑰𐑦𐑙, 𐑯𐑬, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑢𐑻 𐑯𐑴 𐑒𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑑 𐑞 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑴, 𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑰𐑑 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑯𐑼𐑴, 𐑞 𐑣𐑬𐑕 𐑪𐑐𐑩𐑟𐑦𐑑 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑭𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑩 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑯 𐑝𐑿 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑮𐑵𐑥, 𐑯 𐑩𐑚𐑟𐑻𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑹 𐑯 𐑥𐑹 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑧𐑒𐑼𐑩𐑕 𐑓𐑦𐑜𐑼 𐑞𐑨𐑑 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜 𐑥𐑱𐑛, 𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑧𐑤𐑕 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑑 𐑯 𐑚𐑵𐑑𐑕 𐑪𐑯; 𐑲 𐑚𐑧𐑜𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑨𐑟 𐑢𐑧𐑤 𐑨𐑟 𐑲 𐑒𐑫𐑛, 𐑑 𐑩𐑒𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑼𐑱𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑑𐑶𐑤𐑩𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑢𐑪𐑑, 𐑯 𐑐𐑼𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑼𐑤𐑦 𐑑 𐑜𐑧𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑵𐑯𐑟 𐑨𐑟 𐑕𐑵𐑯 𐑨𐑟 𐑐𐑪𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤. 𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑲𐑛, 𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑐𐑮𐑴𐑕𐑰𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑖 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓. 𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑥𐑹𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑧𐑯𐑦 ·𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑗𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑢𐑪𐑖𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑱𐑕; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜, 𐑑 𐑥𐑲 𐑩𐑥𐑱𐑟𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑, 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑵𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑗𐑧𐑕𐑑, 𐑸𐑥𐑟, 𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟. 𐑣𐑰 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑛𐑪𐑯𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑱𐑕𐑑𐑒𐑴𐑑, 𐑯 𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑳𐑐 𐑩 𐑐𐑰𐑕 𐑝 𐑣𐑸𐑛 𐑕𐑴𐑐 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑪𐑖-𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑼 𐑑𐑱𐑚𐑩𐑤, 𐑛𐑦𐑐𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼 𐑯 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑞𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑱𐑕. 𐑲 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑢𐑪𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑕𐑰 𐑢𐑺 𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑧𐑐𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑮𐑱𐑟𐑼, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑤𐑴 𐑯 𐑚𐑦𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛, 𐑣𐑰 𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑕 𐑞 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑚𐑧𐑛 𐑒𐑹𐑯𐑼, 𐑕𐑤𐑦𐑐𐑕 𐑬𐑑 𐑞 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑢𐑫𐑛𐑩𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑪𐑒, 𐑳𐑯𐑖𐑰𐑞𐑟 𐑞 𐑣𐑧𐑛, 𐑢𐑧𐑑𐑕 𐑦𐑑 𐑩 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑵𐑑, 𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑳𐑐 𐑑 𐑞 𐑚𐑦𐑑 𐑝 𐑥𐑦𐑮𐑼 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑞 𐑢𐑷𐑤, 𐑚𐑦𐑜𐑦𐑯𐑟 𐑩 𐑝𐑦𐑜𐑼𐑩𐑕 𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑱𐑐𐑦𐑙, 𐑹 𐑮𐑭𐑞𐑼 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑗𐑰𐑒𐑕. 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑕 𐑲, ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜, 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑦𐑟 𐑿𐑟𐑦𐑙 ·𐑮𐑪𐑡𐑼𐑟'𐑩𐑟 𐑚𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑒𐑳𐑑𐑤𐑼𐑦 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑝𐑧𐑯𐑡𐑩𐑯𐑕. 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼𐑢𐑼𐑛𐑟 𐑲 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑛 𐑞 𐑤𐑧𐑕 𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑪𐑐𐑼𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑲 𐑒𐑱𐑥 𐑑 𐑯𐑴 𐑝 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑓𐑲𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑰𐑤 𐑞 𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑝 𐑩 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯 𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑱𐑛, 𐑯 𐑣𐑬 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑰𐑛𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑖𐑸𐑐 𐑞 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑧𐑡𐑩𐑟 𐑸 𐑷𐑤𐑢𐑱𐑟 𐑒𐑧𐑐𐑑.

𐑞 𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑑𐑶𐑤𐑩𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑵𐑯 𐑩𐑗𐑰𐑝𐑛, 𐑯 𐑣𐑰 𐑐𐑮𐑬𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑥𐑸𐑗𐑑 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑮𐑵𐑥, 𐑮𐑨𐑐𐑑 𐑳𐑐 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑐𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑑 𐑥𐑳𐑙𐑒𐑦 𐑡𐑨𐑒𐑩𐑑, 𐑯 𐑕𐑐𐑹𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑥𐑸𐑖𐑩𐑤'𐑟 𐑚𐑨𐑑𐑩𐑯.

·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 5. 𐑚𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑓𐑩𐑕𐑑.

𐑲 𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑦 𐑓𐑪𐑤𐑴𐑛 𐑕𐑵𐑑, 𐑯 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑚𐑸-𐑮𐑵𐑥 𐑩𐑒𐑪𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑤𐑹𐑛 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑐𐑤𐑧𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦. 𐑲 𐑗𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑖𐑑 𐑯𐑴 𐑥𐑨𐑤𐑦𐑕 𐑑𐑩𐑢𐑹𐑛𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑞𐑴 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑕𐑒𐑲𐑤𐑸𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑥𐑰 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑩 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑥𐑨𐑑𐑼 𐑝 𐑥𐑲 𐑚𐑧𐑛𐑓𐑧𐑤𐑴.

𐑣𐑬𐑧𐑝𐑼, 𐑩 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑤𐑭𐑓 𐑦𐑟 𐑩 𐑥𐑲𐑑𐑦 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑔𐑦𐑙, 𐑯 𐑮𐑭𐑞𐑼 𐑑𐑵 𐑕𐑒𐑺𐑕 𐑩 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑔𐑦𐑙; 𐑞 𐑥𐑹'𐑟 𐑞 𐑐𐑦𐑑𐑦. 𐑕𐑴, 𐑦𐑓 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑥𐑨𐑯, 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑴𐑯 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑐𐑼 𐑐𐑻𐑕𐑩𐑯, 𐑩𐑓𐑹𐑛 𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑓 𐑓 𐑩 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑡𐑴𐑒 𐑑 𐑧𐑯𐑦𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦, 𐑤𐑧𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑚𐑨𐑒𐑢𐑼𐑛, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑤𐑧𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑗𐑽𐑓𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑩𐑤𐑬 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑑 𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑯 𐑚𐑰 𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑱. 𐑯 𐑞 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑧𐑯𐑦𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑓𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑤𐑭𐑓𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑚𐑰 𐑖𐑫𐑼 𐑞𐑺 𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑹 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑿 𐑐𐑼𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑕 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒 𐑓.

𐑞 𐑚𐑸-𐑮𐑵𐑥 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑬 𐑓𐑫𐑤 𐑝 𐑞 𐑚𐑹𐑛𐑼𐑟 𐑣𐑵 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑛𐑮𐑪𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑯𐑲𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑰𐑝𐑾𐑕, 𐑯 𐑣𐑵𐑥 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑩 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑤𐑫𐑒 𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑱 𐑢𐑻 𐑯𐑽𐑤𐑦 𐑷𐑤 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑥𐑧𐑯; 𐑗𐑰𐑓 𐑥𐑱𐑑𐑕, 𐑯 𐑕𐑧𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑥𐑱𐑑𐑕, 𐑯 𐑔𐑻𐑛 𐑥𐑱𐑑𐑕, 𐑯 𐑕𐑰 𐑒𐑸𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑟, 𐑯 𐑕𐑰 𐑒𐑵𐑐𐑼𐑟, 𐑯 𐑕𐑰 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑒𐑕𐑥𐑦𐑔𐑕, 𐑯 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑽𐑟, 𐑯 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑒𐑰𐑐𐑼𐑟; 𐑩 𐑚𐑮𐑬𐑯 𐑯 𐑚𐑮𐑷𐑯𐑦 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑦, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑚𐑪𐑕𐑒𐑦 𐑚𐑽𐑛𐑟; 𐑩𐑯 𐑳𐑯𐑖𐑹𐑯, 𐑖𐑨𐑜𐑦 𐑕𐑧𐑑, 𐑷𐑤 𐑢𐑺𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑳𐑙𐑒𐑦 𐑡𐑨𐑒𐑩𐑑𐑕 𐑓 𐑥𐑹𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑜𐑬𐑯𐑟.

𐑿 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑑𐑧𐑤 𐑣𐑬 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑰𐑗 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑩𐑖𐑹. 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑘𐑳𐑙 𐑓𐑧𐑤𐑴'𐑟 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑔𐑦 𐑗𐑰𐑒 𐑦𐑟 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑕𐑳𐑯-𐑑𐑴𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑐𐑺 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑿, 𐑯 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑕𐑰𐑥 𐑑 𐑕𐑥𐑧𐑤 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑒𐑦; 𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑛𐑱𐑟 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑣𐑦𐑟 ·𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑾𐑯 𐑝𐑶𐑦𐑡. 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑯𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑕 𐑩 𐑓𐑿 𐑖𐑱𐑛𐑟 𐑤𐑲𐑑𐑼; 𐑿 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑕𐑱 𐑩 𐑑𐑳𐑗 𐑝 𐑕𐑨𐑑𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥. 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑧𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑩 𐑔𐑻𐑛 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑤𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑼𐑟 𐑩 𐑑𐑮𐑪𐑐𐑦𐑒 𐑑𐑷𐑯, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑕𐑤𐑲𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑤𐑰𐑗𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑷𐑤; 𐑣𐑰 𐑛𐑬𐑑𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑑𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑛 𐑣𐑴𐑤 𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑕 𐑩𐑖𐑹. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑣𐑵 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑖𐑴 𐑩 𐑗𐑰𐑒 𐑤𐑲𐑒 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜? 𐑢𐑦𐑗, 𐑚𐑸𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑝𐑺𐑾𐑕 𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑕, 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑞 ·𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑰𐑟' 𐑢𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑯 𐑕𐑤𐑴𐑐, 𐑑 𐑖𐑴 𐑓𐑹𐑔 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑼𐑱, 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑒𐑤𐑲𐑥𐑩𐑑𐑕, 𐑟𐑴𐑯 𐑚𐑲 𐑟𐑴𐑯.

“𐑜𐑮𐑳𐑚, 𐑣𐑴!” 𐑯𐑬 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 𐑞 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑤𐑹𐑛, 𐑓𐑤𐑦𐑙𐑦𐑙 𐑴𐑐𐑩𐑯 𐑩 𐑛𐑹, 𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑰 𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑑 𐑚𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑓𐑩𐑕𐑑.

𐑞𐑱 𐑕𐑱 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑣𐑵 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑕𐑰𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛, 𐑞𐑺𐑚𐑲 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑒𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑰𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑨𐑯𐑼, 𐑒𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓-𐑐𐑩𐑟𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑦. 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑷𐑤𐑢𐑱𐑟, 𐑞𐑴: 𐑤𐑰𐑛𐑘𐑸𐑛, 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 ·𐑯𐑿 ·𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑼, 𐑯 ·𐑥𐑳𐑙𐑜𐑴 ·𐑐𐑸𐑒, 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑒𐑪𐑗 𐑢𐑳𐑯; 𐑝 𐑷𐑤 𐑥𐑧𐑯, 𐑞𐑱 𐑐𐑩𐑟𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑞 𐑤𐑰𐑕𐑑 𐑩𐑖𐑫𐑼𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑐𐑸𐑤𐑼. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑐𐑼𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑕 𐑞 𐑥𐑽 𐑒𐑮𐑪𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑝 ·𐑕𐑲𐑚𐑽𐑾 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑕𐑤𐑧𐑡 𐑛𐑮𐑷𐑯 𐑚𐑲 𐑛𐑪𐑜𐑟 𐑨𐑟 ·𐑤𐑰𐑛𐑘𐑸𐑛 𐑛𐑦𐑛, 𐑹 𐑞 𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑕𐑪𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑼𐑦 𐑢𐑷𐑒 𐑪𐑯 𐑩𐑯 𐑧𐑥𐑐𐑑𐑦 𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑥𐑩𐑒, 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑯𐑰𐑜𐑮𐑴 𐑣𐑸𐑑 𐑝 ·𐑨𐑓𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑩, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑝 𐑐𐑫𐑼 ·𐑥𐑳𐑙𐑜𐑴'𐑟 𐑐𐑼𐑓𐑹𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟—𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑒𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑝 𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑝𐑩𐑤, 𐑲 𐑕𐑱, 𐑥𐑱 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑞 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑚𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑥𐑴𐑛 𐑝 𐑩𐑑𐑱𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑣𐑲 𐑕𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑤 𐑐𐑪𐑤𐑦𐑖. 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤, 𐑓 𐑞 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑐𐑸𐑑, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑹𐑑 𐑝 𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑟 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑧𐑯𐑦𐑢𐑺.

𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑮𐑦𐑓𐑤𐑧𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑡𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑽 𐑸 𐑩𐑒𐑱𐑠𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑕𐑻𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑕 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑢𐑰 𐑢𐑻 𐑷𐑤 𐑕𐑰𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑑𐑱𐑚𐑩𐑤, 𐑯 𐑲 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑺𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑣𐑽 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑕𐑑𐑹𐑦𐑟 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙; 𐑑 𐑥𐑲 𐑯𐑴 𐑕𐑥𐑷𐑤 𐑕𐑼𐑐𐑮𐑲𐑟, 𐑯𐑽𐑤𐑦 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑥𐑱𐑯𐑑𐑱𐑯𐑛 𐑩 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑕𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑕. 𐑯 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑞𐑨𐑑, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞𐑱 𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑑 𐑦𐑥𐑚𐑨𐑮𐑩𐑕𐑑. 𐑘𐑧𐑕, 𐑣𐑽 𐑢𐑻 𐑩 𐑕𐑧𐑑 𐑝 𐑕𐑰-𐑛𐑪𐑜𐑟, 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑝 𐑣𐑵𐑥 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑤𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑨𐑖𐑓𐑩𐑤𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑹𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑣𐑲 𐑕𐑰𐑟—𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑲𐑼 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑼𐑟 𐑑 𐑞𐑧𐑥—𐑯 𐑛𐑿𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑛𐑧𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑦𐑙; 𐑯 𐑘𐑧𐑑, 𐑣𐑽 𐑞𐑱 𐑕𐑨𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑩 𐑕𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑤 𐑚𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑓𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑑𐑱𐑚𐑩𐑤—𐑷𐑤 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑦𐑙, 𐑷𐑤 𐑝 𐑒𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑛 𐑑𐑱𐑕𐑑𐑕—𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑨𐑟 𐑖𐑰𐑐𐑦𐑖𐑤𐑦 𐑨𐑑 𐑰𐑗 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑨𐑟 𐑞𐑴 𐑞𐑱 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑕𐑲𐑑 𐑝 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑖𐑰𐑐𐑓𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑞 ·𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑯 ·𐑥𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑟. 𐑩 𐑒𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑾𐑕 𐑕𐑲𐑑; 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑚𐑨𐑖𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑚𐑺𐑟, 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑑𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑛 𐑢𐑹𐑽 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑥𐑧𐑯!

𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑓 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜—𐑢𐑲, ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜 𐑕𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑞𐑧𐑥—𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑝 𐑞 𐑑𐑱𐑚𐑩𐑤, 𐑑𐑵, 𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑴 𐑗𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑑; 𐑨𐑟 𐑒𐑵𐑤 𐑨𐑟 𐑩𐑯 𐑲𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤. 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑖𐑫𐑼 𐑲 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑱 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑓 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑮𐑰𐑛𐑦𐑙. 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑩𐑛𐑥𐑲𐑼𐑼 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑒𐑹𐑛𐑾𐑤𐑦 𐑡𐑳𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑓𐑲𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑮𐑦𐑙𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑚𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑓𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑯 𐑿𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑 𐑕𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑦; 𐑮𐑰𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑞 𐑑𐑱𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑦𐑑, 𐑑 𐑞 𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑡𐑧𐑐𐑼𐑛𐑦 𐑝 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑟, 𐑯 𐑜𐑮𐑨𐑐𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑚𐑰𐑓𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑕 𐑑𐑩𐑢𐑹𐑛𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑥. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑒𐑵𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑳𐑯 𐑚𐑲 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑯 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑯𐑴𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑐𐑰𐑐𐑩𐑤'𐑟 𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑥𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯, 𐑑 𐑛𐑵 𐑧𐑯𐑦𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑒𐑵𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑟 𐑑 𐑛𐑵 𐑦𐑑 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑰𐑤𐑦.

𐑢𐑰 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑒 𐑝 𐑷𐑤 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜'𐑟 𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑦𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑽; 𐑣𐑬 𐑣𐑰 𐑦𐑕𐑗𐑵𐑛 𐑒𐑪𐑓𐑦 𐑯 𐑣𐑪𐑑 𐑮𐑴𐑤𐑟, 𐑯 𐑩𐑐𐑤𐑲𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑝𐑲𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑩𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑑 𐑚𐑰𐑓𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑕, 𐑛𐑳𐑯 𐑮𐑺. 𐑦𐑯𐑳𐑓, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑚𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑓𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑛𐑮𐑵 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑞 𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑐𐑳𐑚𐑤𐑦𐑒 𐑮𐑵𐑥, 𐑤𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑑𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑣𐑷𐑒-𐑐𐑲𐑐, 𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑺 𐑒𐑢𐑲𐑩𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑲𐑡𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑯 𐑕𐑥𐑴𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑧𐑐𐑼𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑣𐑨𐑑 𐑪𐑯, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑲 𐑕𐑨𐑤𐑦𐑛 𐑬𐑑 𐑓 𐑩 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑴𐑤.

·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 6. 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑰𐑑.

𐑦𐑓 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑩𐑕𐑑𐑪𐑯𐑦𐑖𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑒𐑨𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑜𐑤𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑕 𐑝 𐑕𐑴 𐑬𐑑𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑖 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑡𐑵𐑩𐑤 𐑨𐑟 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜 𐑕𐑻𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑱𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑞 𐑐𐑩𐑤𐑲𐑑 𐑕𐑩𐑕𐑲𐑩𐑑𐑦 𐑝 𐑩 𐑕𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑤𐑲𐑟𐑛 𐑑𐑬𐑯, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑩𐑕𐑑𐑪𐑯𐑦𐑖𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑕𐑵𐑯 𐑛𐑦𐑐𐑸𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑲 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑛𐑱𐑤𐑲𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑴𐑤 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑰𐑑𐑕 𐑝 ·𐑯𐑿 ·𐑚𐑧𐑛𐑓𐑼𐑛.

𐑦𐑯 𐑔𐑳𐑮𐑴𐑓𐑺𐑟 𐑯𐑲 𐑞 𐑛𐑪𐑒𐑕, 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑼𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑰𐑐𐑹𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑓𐑮𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑪𐑓𐑼 𐑑 𐑝𐑿 𐑞 𐑒𐑢𐑽𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑯𐑪𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑑𐑕 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑓𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑯 𐑐𐑸𐑑𐑕. 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯 ·𐑚𐑮𐑷𐑛𐑢𐑱 𐑯 ·𐑗𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑯𐑳𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑰𐑑𐑕, ·𐑥𐑧𐑛𐑦𐑑𐑼𐑱𐑯𐑾𐑯 𐑥𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑯𐑼𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑡𐑪𐑕𐑩𐑤 𐑞 𐑩𐑓𐑮𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑤𐑱𐑛𐑦𐑟. 𐑮𐑰𐑡𐑩𐑯𐑑 ·𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑰𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑳𐑯𐑯𐑴𐑯 𐑑 ·𐑤𐑨𐑕𐑒𐑼𐑟 𐑯 ·𐑥𐑩𐑤𐑱𐑟; 𐑯 𐑨𐑑 ·𐑚𐑪𐑥𐑚𐑱, 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑤𐑴 ·𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑯, 𐑤𐑦𐑝 ·𐑘𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑪𐑓𐑩𐑯 𐑕𐑒𐑺𐑛 𐑞 𐑯𐑱𐑑𐑦𐑝𐑟. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 ·𐑯𐑿 ·𐑚𐑧𐑛𐑓𐑼𐑛 𐑚𐑰𐑑𐑕 𐑷𐑤 ·𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼 ·𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑰𐑑 𐑯 ·𐑢𐑪𐑐𐑦𐑙. 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑-𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑣𐑷𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑿 𐑕𐑰 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑼𐑟; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑯 ·𐑯𐑿 ·𐑚𐑧𐑛𐑓𐑼𐑛, 𐑨𐑒𐑗𐑵𐑩𐑤 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑗𐑨𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑰𐑑 𐑒𐑹𐑯𐑼𐑟; 𐑕𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑡𐑩𐑟 𐑬𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑑; 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑝 𐑣𐑵𐑥 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑒𐑨𐑮𐑦 𐑪𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑚𐑴𐑯𐑟 𐑳𐑯𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑦 𐑓𐑤𐑧𐑖. 𐑦𐑑 𐑥𐑱𐑒𐑕 𐑩 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑼 𐑕𐑑𐑺.

𐑚𐑳𐑑, 𐑚𐑦𐑕𐑲𐑛𐑟 𐑞 ·𐑝𐑰𐑡𐑰𐑩𐑯𐑕, ·𐑑𐑪𐑙𐑱𐑑𐑴𐑚𐑵𐑼𐑟, ·𐑻𐑩𐑥𐑨𐑙𐑴𐑩𐑯𐑟, ·𐑐𐑨𐑯𐑨𐑙𐑾𐑯𐑟, 𐑯 ·𐑚𐑮𐑦𐑜𐑦𐑜𐑾𐑯𐑕, 𐑯, 𐑚𐑦𐑕𐑲𐑛𐑟 𐑞 𐑢𐑲𐑤𐑛 𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙-𐑒𐑮𐑭𐑓𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑳𐑯𐑣𐑰𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑮𐑰𐑤 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑰𐑑𐑕, 𐑿 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑕𐑰 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑕𐑲𐑑𐑕 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑥𐑹 𐑒𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑾𐑕, 𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑥𐑹 𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤. 𐑞𐑺 𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑤𐑦 𐑼𐑲𐑝 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑑𐑬𐑯 𐑕𐑒𐑹𐑟 𐑝 𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑯 ·𐑝𐑼𐑥𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑟 𐑯 ·𐑯𐑿 ·𐑣𐑨𐑥𐑐𐑖𐑼 𐑥𐑧𐑯, 𐑷𐑤 𐑩𐑔𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑓 𐑜𐑱𐑯 𐑯 𐑜𐑤𐑹𐑦 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑼𐑦. 𐑞𐑱 𐑸 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑘𐑳𐑙, 𐑝 𐑕𐑑𐑷𐑤𐑢𐑼𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑱𐑥𐑟; 𐑓𐑧𐑤𐑴𐑟 𐑣𐑵 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑓𐑧𐑤𐑛 𐑓𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑕, 𐑯 𐑯𐑬 𐑕𐑰𐑒 𐑑 𐑛𐑮𐑪𐑐 𐑞 𐑨𐑒𐑕 𐑯 𐑕𐑯𐑨𐑗 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤-𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑕. 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑸 𐑨𐑟 𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑯 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 ·𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑯 ·𐑥𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑕 𐑞𐑱 𐑒𐑱𐑥. 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑿 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑩 𐑓𐑿 𐑬𐑼𐑟 𐑴𐑤𐑛. 𐑤𐑫𐑒 𐑞𐑺! 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑗𐑨𐑐 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑞 𐑒𐑹𐑯𐑼. 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑺𐑟 𐑩 𐑚𐑰𐑝𐑼 𐑣𐑨𐑑 𐑯 𐑕𐑢𐑪𐑤𐑴-𐑑𐑱𐑤𐑛 𐑒𐑴𐑑, 𐑜𐑻𐑛𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑼-𐑚𐑧𐑤𐑑 𐑯 𐑖𐑰𐑔-𐑯𐑲𐑓. 𐑣𐑽 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑟 𐑩𐑯𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑕𐑵'-𐑢𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑼 𐑯 𐑩 𐑚𐑪𐑥𐑚𐑩𐑟𐑰𐑯 𐑒𐑤𐑴𐑒.

𐑯𐑴 𐑑𐑬𐑯-𐑚𐑮𐑧𐑛 𐑛𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑦 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑺 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑒𐑳𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑦-𐑚𐑮𐑧𐑛 𐑢𐑳𐑯—𐑲 𐑥𐑰𐑯 𐑩 𐑛𐑬𐑯𐑮𐑲𐑑 𐑚𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑒𐑦𐑯 𐑛𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑦—𐑩 𐑓𐑧𐑤𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑, 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑛𐑪𐑜-𐑛𐑱𐑟, 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑥𐑴 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑑𐑵 𐑱𐑒𐑼𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑚𐑳𐑒𐑕𐑒𐑦𐑯 𐑜𐑤𐑳𐑝𐑟 𐑓 𐑓𐑽 𐑝 𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟. 𐑯𐑬 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑩 𐑒𐑳𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑦 𐑛𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑦 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑕 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑑 𐑥𐑱𐑒 𐑩 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑢𐑦𐑖𐑑 𐑮𐑧𐑐𐑿𐑑𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯, 𐑯 𐑡𐑶𐑯𐑟 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑤-𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑼𐑦, 𐑿 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑕𐑰 𐑞 𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑛𐑳𐑟 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑮𐑰𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑕𐑰𐑐𐑹𐑑. 𐑦𐑯 𐑚𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑰-𐑬𐑑𐑓𐑦𐑑, 𐑣𐑰 𐑹𐑛𐑼𐑟 𐑚𐑧𐑤-𐑚𐑳𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑱𐑕𐑑𐑒𐑴𐑑𐑕; 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑐𐑕 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑝𐑩𐑕 𐑑𐑮𐑴𐑟𐑼𐑟. 𐑭, 𐑐𐑫𐑼 ·𐑣𐑱-·𐑕𐑰𐑛! 𐑣𐑬 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑼𐑤𐑦 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑚𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑐𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑬𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑜𐑱𐑤, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑞𐑬 𐑸𐑑 𐑛𐑮𐑦𐑝𐑩𐑯, 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑐𐑕, 𐑚𐑳𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑟, 𐑯 𐑷𐑤, 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑞 𐑔𐑮𐑴𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑑𐑧𐑥𐑐𐑦𐑕𐑑.

𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑓𐑱𐑥𐑩𐑕 𐑑𐑬𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑽𐑟, 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑟, 𐑯 𐑚𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑒𐑦𐑯𐑟 𐑑 𐑖𐑴 𐑣𐑻 𐑝𐑦𐑟𐑦𐑑𐑼𐑟. 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑷𐑤. 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 ·𐑯𐑿 ·𐑚𐑧𐑛𐑓𐑼𐑛 𐑦𐑟 𐑩 𐑒𐑢𐑽 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕. 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑦𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑓 𐑳𐑕 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑥𐑧𐑯, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑒𐑑 𐑝 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑛𐑱 𐑐𐑼𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑕 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑨𐑟 𐑣𐑬𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑒𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑝 ·𐑤𐑨𐑚𐑮𐑩𐑛𐑹. 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟, 𐑐𐑸𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑣𐑻 𐑚𐑨𐑒 𐑒𐑳𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑦 𐑸 𐑦𐑯𐑳𐑓 𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯, 𐑞𐑱 𐑤𐑫𐑒 𐑕𐑴 𐑚𐑴𐑯𐑦. 𐑞 𐑑𐑬𐑯 𐑦𐑑𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑼𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑕 𐑞 𐑛𐑽𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕 𐑑 𐑤𐑦𐑝 𐑦𐑯, 𐑦𐑯 𐑷𐑤 ·𐑯𐑿 ·𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛. 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑩 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑝 𐑶𐑤, 𐑑𐑮𐑵 𐑦𐑯𐑳𐑓: 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑤𐑲𐑒 ·𐑒𐑱𐑯𐑩𐑯; 𐑩 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛, 𐑷𐑤𐑕𐑴, 𐑝 𐑒𐑹𐑯 𐑯 𐑢𐑲𐑯. 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑰𐑑𐑕 𐑛𐑵 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑮𐑳𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑥𐑦𐑤𐑒; 𐑯𐑹 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑙-𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑛𐑵 𐑞𐑱 𐑐𐑱𐑝 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑖 𐑧𐑜𐑟. 𐑘𐑧𐑑, 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑐𐑲𐑑 𐑝 𐑞𐑦𐑕, 𐑯𐑴𐑢𐑺 𐑦𐑯 𐑷𐑤 ·𐑩𐑥𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑩 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑿 𐑓𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑥𐑹 𐑐𐑩𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯-𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑣𐑬𐑟𐑩𐑟; 𐑐𐑸𐑒𐑕 𐑯 𐑜𐑸𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑥𐑹 𐑪𐑐𐑿𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑑, 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑦𐑯 ·𐑯𐑿 ·𐑚𐑧𐑛𐑓𐑼𐑛. 𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑕 𐑒𐑱𐑥 𐑞𐑱? 𐑣𐑬 𐑐𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑕 𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑨𐑜𐑦 𐑕𐑒𐑹𐑾 𐑝 𐑩 𐑒𐑳𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑦?

𐑜𐑴 𐑯 𐑜𐑱𐑟 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑲𐑼𐑯 𐑧𐑥𐑚𐑤𐑩𐑥𐑨𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑟 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑘𐑪𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑤𐑪𐑓𐑑𐑦 𐑥𐑨𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑯, 𐑯 𐑘𐑹 𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑕𐑗𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑚𐑰 𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑼𐑛. 𐑘𐑧𐑕; 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑝 𐑣𐑬𐑟𐑩𐑟 𐑯 𐑓𐑤𐑬𐑼𐑦 𐑜𐑸𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑒𐑱𐑥 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 ·𐑩𐑑𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑒, ·𐑐𐑩𐑕𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑒, 𐑯 ·𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑾𐑯 𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟. 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑯 𐑷𐑤, 𐑞𐑱 𐑢𐑻 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑛 𐑯 𐑛𐑮𐑨𐑜𐑛 𐑳𐑐 𐑣𐑦𐑞𐑼 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑚𐑪𐑑𐑩𐑥 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑰. 𐑒𐑨𐑯 ·𐑣𐑧𐑮 ·𐑨𐑤𐑦𐑜𐑟𐑭𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑐𐑼𐑓𐑹𐑥 𐑩 𐑓𐑰𐑑 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑞𐑨𐑑?

𐑦𐑯 ·𐑯𐑿 ·𐑚𐑧𐑛𐑓𐑼𐑛, 𐑓𐑭𐑞𐑼𐑟, 𐑞𐑱 𐑕𐑱, 𐑜𐑦𐑝 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑓 𐑛𐑬𐑼𐑟 𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑛𐑷𐑑𐑼𐑟, 𐑯 𐑐𐑹𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑪𐑓 𐑞𐑺 𐑯𐑰𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑓𐑿 𐑐𐑹𐑐𐑩𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑩-𐑐𐑰𐑕. 𐑿 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑜𐑴 𐑑 ·𐑯𐑿 ·𐑚𐑧𐑛𐑓𐑼𐑛 𐑑 𐑕𐑰 𐑩 𐑚𐑮𐑦𐑤𐑾𐑯𐑑 𐑢𐑧𐑛𐑦𐑙; 𐑓, 𐑞𐑱 𐑕𐑱, 𐑞𐑱 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑮𐑧𐑟𐑼𐑝𐑢𐑸𐑟 𐑝 𐑶𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑣𐑬𐑕, 𐑯 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑯𐑲𐑑 𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑤𐑩𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑻𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑤𐑧𐑙𐑔𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥𐑩𐑕𐑧𐑑𐑦 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑤𐑟.

𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑼 𐑑𐑲𐑥, 𐑞 𐑑𐑬𐑯 𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑢𐑰𐑑 𐑑 𐑕𐑰; 𐑓𐑫𐑤 𐑝 𐑓𐑲𐑯 𐑥𐑱𐑐𐑩𐑤𐑟—𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑨𐑝𐑩𐑯𐑿𐑟 𐑝 𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑯 𐑯 𐑜𐑴𐑤𐑛. 𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑷𐑜𐑩𐑕𐑑, 𐑣𐑲 𐑦𐑯 𐑺, 𐑞 𐑚𐑿𐑑𐑦𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑯 𐑚𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑣𐑹𐑕-𐑗𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑯𐑳𐑑𐑕, 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑤𐑭𐑚𐑮𐑩-𐑢𐑲𐑟, 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑓𐑼 𐑞 𐑐𐑭𐑕𐑼-𐑚𐑲 𐑞𐑺 𐑑𐑱𐑐𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑳𐑐𐑮𐑲𐑑 𐑒𐑴𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑒𐑪𐑙𐑜𐑮𐑦𐑜𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑤𐑪𐑕𐑩𐑥𐑟. 𐑕𐑴 𐑪𐑥𐑯𐑦𐑐𐑩𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑸𐑑; 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑩 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑑 𐑝 ·𐑯𐑿 ·𐑚𐑧𐑛𐑓𐑼𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑕𐑵𐑐𐑼𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑿𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑮𐑲𐑑 𐑑𐑧𐑮𐑩𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑝 𐑓𐑤𐑬𐑼𐑟 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑨𐑮𐑩𐑯 𐑮𐑧𐑓𐑿𐑕 𐑮𐑪𐑒𐑕 𐑔𐑮𐑴𐑯 𐑩𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑨𐑑 𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯'𐑟 𐑓𐑲𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑛𐑱.

𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑯 𐑝 ·𐑯𐑿 ·𐑚𐑧𐑛𐑓𐑼𐑛, 𐑞𐑱 𐑚𐑤𐑵𐑥 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑞𐑺 𐑴𐑯 𐑮𐑧𐑛 𐑮𐑴𐑟𐑩𐑟. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑮𐑴𐑟𐑩𐑟 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑤𐑵𐑥 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑼; 𐑢𐑺𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑓𐑲𐑯 𐑒𐑸𐑯𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑞𐑺 𐑗𐑰𐑒𐑕 𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑼𐑧𐑯𐑾𐑤 𐑨𐑟 𐑕𐑳𐑯𐑤𐑲𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑯𐑔 𐑣𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑯𐑟. 𐑧𐑤𐑕𐑢𐑺 𐑥𐑨𐑗 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑚𐑤𐑵𐑥 𐑝 𐑞𐑺𐑟, 𐑘𐑰 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑪𐑑, 𐑕𐑱𐑝 𐑦𐑯 ·𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑩𐑥, 𐑢𐑺 𐑞𐑱 𐑑𐑧𐑤 𐑥𐑰 𐑞 𐑘𐑳𐑙 𐑜𐑻𐑤𐑟 𐑚𐑮𐑰𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑒, 𐑞𐑺 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑼 𐑕𐑢𐑰𐑑𐑣𐑸𐑑𐑕 𐑕𐑥𐑧𐑤 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑥𐑲𐑤𐑟 𐑪𐑓 𐑖𐑹, 𐑨𐑟 𐑞𐑴 𐑞𐑱 𐑢𐑻 𐑛𐑮𐑷𐑦𐑙 𐑯𐑲 𐑞 𐑴𐑛𐑼𐑩𐑕 ·𐑥𐑩𐑤𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑛 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑦𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑒 𐑕𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟.

·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 7. 𐑞 ·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑩𐑤.

𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑕𐑱𐑥 ·𐑯𐑿 ·𐑚𐑧𐑛𐑓𐑼𐑛 𐑞𐑺 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑩 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑥𐑩𐑯'𐑟 ·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑩𐑤, 𐑯 𐑓𐑿 𐑸 𐑞 𐑥𐑵𐑛𐑦 𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑼𐑥𐑧𐑯, 𐑖𐑹𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑓 𐑞 ·𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑾𐑯 ·𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑹 ·𐑐𐑩𐑕𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑒, 𐑣𐑵 𐑓𐑱𐑤 𐑑 𐑥𐑱𐑒 𐑩 𐑕𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑱 𐑝𐑦𐑟𐑦𐑑 𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑪𐑑. 𐑲 𐑨𐑥 𐑖𐑫𐑼 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑲 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑.

𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑥𐑲 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑥𐑹𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑴𐑤, 𐑲 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯 𐑕𐑨𐑤𐑦𐑛 𐑬𐑑 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑤 𐑧𐑮𐑩𐑯𐑛. 𐑞 𐑕𐑒𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑗𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑒𐑤𐑽, 𐑕𐑳𐑯𐑦 𐑒𐑴𐑤𐑛, 𐑑 𐑛𐑮𐑲𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑤𐑰𐑑 𐑯 𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑑. 𐑮𐑨𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑲𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑲 𐑖𐑨𐑜𐑦 𐑡𐑨𐑒𐑩𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑒𐑤𐑪𐑔 𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑛 𐑚𐑺𐑕𐑒𐑦𐑯, 𐑲 𐑓𐑷𐑑 𐑥𐑲 𐑢𐑱 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚𐑼𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑹𐑥. 𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑦𐑙, 𐑲 𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑩 𐑕𐑥𐑷𐑤 𐑕𐑒𐑨𐑑𐑼𐑛 𐑒𐑪𐑙𐑜𐑮𐑦𐑜𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑼𐑟, 𐑯 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑼𐑟' 𐑢𐑲𐑝𐑟 𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑛𐑴𐑟. 𐑩 𐑥𐑳𐑓𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑕𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑛, 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑮𐑴𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑨𐑑 𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑖𐑮𐑰𐑒𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑹𐑥. 𐑰𐑗 𐑕𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑢𐑻𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑼 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑐𐑻𐑐𐑩𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑐𐑸𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑳𐑞𐑼, 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑓 𐑰𐑗 𐑕𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑓 𐑢𐑻 𐑦𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑤𐑼 𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑿𐑯𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤. 𐑞 𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑤𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑼𐑲𐑝𐑛; 𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑕𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑝 𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑛𐑓𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑲𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑧𐑝𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑥𐑸𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑑𐑨𐑚𐑤𐑩𐑑𐑕, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑒 𐑚𐑹𐑛𐑼𐑟, 𐑥𐑱𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑢𐑷𐑤 𐑪𐑯 𐑲𐑞𐑼 𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑞 𐑐𐑫𐑤𐑐𐑦𐑑. 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑝 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑮𐑨𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑞 𐑓𐑪𐑤𐑴𐑦𐑙, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑲 𐑛𐑵 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑑 𐑒𐑢𐑴𐑑:—

·𐑕𐑱𐑒𐑮𐑩𐑛 𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑥𐑧𐑥𐑼𐑦 𐑝 ·𐑡𐑪𐑯 ·𐑑𐑷𐑤𐑚𐑩𐑑, 𐑣𐑵, 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑱𐑡 𐑝 𐑱𐑑𐑰𐑯, 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑤𐑪𐑕𐑑 𐑴𐑝𐑼𐑚𐑹𐑛, ·𐑯𐑽 𐑞 ·𐑲𐑤 𐑝 ·𐑛𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑤𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯, 𐑪𐑓 ·𐑐𐑨𐑑𐑩𐑜𐑴𐑯𐑾, 𐑯𐑴𐑝𐑧𐑥𐑚𐑼 1𐑕𐑑, 1836. 𐑞𐑦𐑕 ·𐑑𐑨𐑚𐑤𐑩𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 ·𐑥𐑧𐑥𐑼𐑦 𐑚𐑲 𐑣𐑦𐑟 ·𐑕𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑼.

·𐑕𐑱𐑒𐑮𐑩𐑛 𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑥𐑧𐑥𐑼𐑦 𐑝 ·𐑮𐑪𐑚𐑼𐑑 ·𐑤𐑪𐑙, ·𐑢𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑕 ·𐑧𐑤𐑼𐑦, ·𐑯𐑱𐑔𐑩𐑯 ·𐑒𐑴𐑤𐑥𐑩𐑯, ·𐑢𐑷𐑤𐑑𐑼 ·𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑦, ·𐑕𐑧𐑔 ·𐑥𐑱𐑕𐑦, 𐑯 ·𐑕𐑨𐑥𐑿𐑩𐑤 ·𐑜𐑤𐑰𐑜, ·𐑓𐑹𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕' 𐑒𐑮𐑵𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑖𐑦𐑐 ·𐑦𐑤𐑲𐑟𐑩 𐑣𐑵 𐑢𐑻 𐑑𐑴𐑛 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑕𐑲𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑩 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑪𐑓-𐑖𐑹 ·𐑜𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑩𐑕𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑒, 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑧𐑥𐑚𐑼 31𐑕𐑑, 1839. 𐑞𐑦𐑕 ·𐑥𐑸𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑽 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑞𐑺 𐑕𐑼𐑝𐑲𐑝𐑦𐑙 ·𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑥𐑱𐑑𐑕.

·𐑕𐑱𐑒𐑮𐑩𐑛 𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑥𐑧𐑥𐑼𐑦 𐑝 𐑞 𐑤𐑱𐑑 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 ·𐑦𐑟𐑰𐑒𐑾𐑤 ·𐑣𐑸𐑛𐑦, 𐑣𐑵 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑬𐑟 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑴𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑒𐑦𐑤𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑩 ·𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑒𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑝 ·𐑡𐑩𐑐𐑨𐑯, 𐑷𐑜𐑩𐑕𐑑 3d, 1833. 𐑞𐑦𐑕 ·𐑑𐑨𐑚𐑤𐑩𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 ·𐑥𐑧𐑥𐑼𐑦 𐑚𐑲 𐑣𐑦𐑟 ·𐑢𐑦𐑛𐑴.

𐑖𐑱𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑪𐑓 𐑞 𐑕𐑤𐑰𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑥𐑲 𐑲𐑕-𐑜𐑤𐑱𐑟𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑑 𐑯 𐑡𐑨𐑒𐑩𐑑, 𐑲 𐑕𐑰𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑥𐑲𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑯𐑽 𐑞 𐑛𐑹, 𐑯 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑲𐑛𐑢𐑱𐑟 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑼𐑐𐑮𐑲𐑟𐑛 𐑑 𐑕𐑰 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜 𐑯𐑽 𐑥𐑰. 𐑩𐑓𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑕𐑩𐑤𐑧𐑥𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑰𐑯, 𐑞𐑺 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑜𐑱𐑟 𐑝 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑮𐑧𐑡𐑵𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑒𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑦𐑪𐑕𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑯𐑕. 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑕𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑡 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑻𐑕𐑩𐑯 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑣𐑵 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑑 𐑯𐑴𐑑𐑦𐑕 𐑥𐑲 𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑩𐑯𐑕; 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑪𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑣𐑵 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑮𐑰𐑛, 𐑯, 𐑞𐑺𐑓𐑹, 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑮𐑰𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑓𐑮𐑦𐑡𐑦𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑷𐑤. 𐑢𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑝 𐑞 𐑮𐑧𐑤𐑩𐑑𐑦𐑝𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑣𐑵𐑟 𐑯𐑱𐑥𐑟 𐑩𐑐𐑽𐑛 𐑞𐑺 𐑢𐑻 𐑯𐑬 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑞 𐑒𐑪𐑙𐑜𐑮𐑦𐑜𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯, 𐑲 𐑯𐑿 𐑯𐑪𐑑; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑕𐑴 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑸 𐑞 𐑳𐑯𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑹𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑨𐑒𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑼𐑦, 𐑯 𐑕𐑴 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑕𐑧𐑝𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑯 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑢𐑺 𐑞 𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑦𐑓 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑞 𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑐𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑝 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑳𐑯𐑕𐑰𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑓, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑲 𐑓𐑰𐑤 𐑖𐑫𐑼 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑽 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑥𐑰 𐑢𐑻 𐑩𐑕𐑧𐑥𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑞𐑴𐑟, 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑵𐑟 𐑳𐑯𐑣𐑰𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑸𐑑𐑕 𐑞 𐑕𐑲𐑑 𐑝 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑚𐑤𐑰𐑒 𐑑𐑨𐑚𐑤𐑩𐑑𐑕 𐑕𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑔𐑧𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑷𐑟𐑛 𐑞 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑢𐑵𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑑 𐑚𐑤𐑰𐑛 𐑩𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑖.

𐑴! 𐑘𐑰 𐑣𐑵𐑟 𐑛𐑧𐑛 𐑤𐑲 𐑚𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑛 𐑚𐑦𐑯𐑰𐑔 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑯 𐑜𐑮𐑭𐑕; 𐑣𐑵 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑓𐑤𐑬𐑼𐑟 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑕𐑱—𐑣𐑽, 𐑣𐑽 𐑤𐑲𐑟 𐑥𐑲 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑳𐑝𐑩𐑛; 𐑘𐑰 𐑯𐑴 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑤𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑚𐑮𐑵𐑛𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑚𐑫𐑟𐑩𐑥𐑟 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑞𐑰𐑟. 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑼 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑒-𐑚𐑹𐑛𐑼𐑛 𐑥𐑸𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑒𐑳𐑝𐑼 𐑯𐑴 𐑨𐑖𐑩𐑟! 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑺 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑦𐑥𐑵𐑝𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟! 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑛𐑧𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑝𐑶𐑛𐑟 𐑯 𐑳𐑯𐑚𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑓𐑦𐑛𐑨𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑤𐑲𐑯𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑥 𐑑 𐑯𐑷 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑷𐑤 ·𐑓𐑱𐑔, 𐑯 𐑮𐑦𐑓𐑿𐑟 𐑮𐑧𐑟𐑼𐑧𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑑 𐑞 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑣𐑵 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕𐑤𐑩𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑖𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑 𐑩 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑝. 𐑨𐑟 𐑢𐑧𐑤 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑑𐑨𐑚𐑤𐑩𐑑𐑕 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑒𐑱𐑝 𐑝 ·𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑓𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑩 𐑨𐑟 𐑣𐑽.

𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑤𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑒𐑮𐑰𐑗𐑼𐑟, 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑛 𐑝 𐑥𐑨𐑯𐑒𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑸 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑤𐑵𐑛𐑩𐑛; 𐑢𐑲 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑩 𐑿𐑯𐑦𐑝𐑻𐑕𐑩𐑤 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑝𐑻𐑚 𐑕𐑧𐑟 𐑝 𐑞𐑧𐑥, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑱 𐑑𐑧𐑤 𐑯𐑴 𐑑𐑱𐑤𐑟, 𐑞𐑴 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑱𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑹 𐑕𐑰𐑒𐑮𐑩𐑑𐑕 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑜𐑫𐑛𐑢𐑦𐑯 ·𐑕𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟; 𐑣𐑬 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑱𐑥 𐑣𐑵 𐑘𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑛𐑱 𐑛𐑦𐑐𐑸𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑓 𐑞 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛, 𐑢𐑰 𐑐𐑮𐑰𐑓𐑦𐑒𐑕 𐑕𐑴 𐑕𐑦𐑜𐑯𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑓𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑤 𐑩 𐑢𐑻𐑛, 𐑯 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑛𐑵 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑞𐑳𐑕 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑦𐑓 𐑣𐑰 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑥𐑚𐑸𐑒𐑕 𐑓 𐑞 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑴𐑑𐑩𐑕𐑑 ·𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑟 𐑝 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑤𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑻𐑔; 𐑢𐑲 𐑞 ·𐑤𐑲𐑓 ·𐑦𐑯𐑖𐑫𐑼𐑩𐑯𐑕 ·𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑱 𐑛𐑧𐑔-𐑓𐑹𐑓𐑦𐑗𐑼𐑟 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑦𐑥𐑹𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑟; 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑦𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑩𐑤, 𐑳𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑻𐑦𐑙 𐑐𐑼𐑨𐑤𐑩𐑕𐑦𐑕, 𐑯 𐑛𐑧𐑛𐑤𐑦, 𐑣𐑴𐑐𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑑𐑮𐑭𐑯𐑕, 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑤𐑲𐑟 𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑰𐑒 ·𐑨𐑛𐑩𐑥 𐑣𐑵 𐑛𐑲𐑛 𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑦 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑗𐑼𐑦𐑟 𐑩𐑜𐑴; 𐑣𐑬 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑰 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑮𐑦𐑓𐑿𐑟 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑓𐑼𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑓 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑣𐑵 𐑢𐑰 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼𐑞𐑩𐑤𐑧𐑕 𐑥𐑱𐑯𐑑𐑱𐑯 𐑸 𐑛𐑢𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑳𐑯𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑚𐑤𐑦𐑕; 𐑢𐑲 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑤𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑴 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑝 𐑑 𐑣𐑳𐑖 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑛; 𐑢𐑺𐑓𐑹 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞 𐑮𐑵𐑥𐑼 𐑝 𐑩 𐑯𐑪𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑑𐑵𐑥 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑑𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑓𐑲 𐑩 𐑣𐑴𐑤 𐑕𐑦𐑑𐑦. 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑸 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑥𐑰𐑯𐑦𐑙𐑟.

𐑚𐑳𐑑 ·𐑓𐑱𐑔, 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑡𐑨𐑒𐑩𐑤, 𐑓𐑰𐑛𐑟 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑞 𐑑𐑵𐑥𐑟, 𐑯 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑛𐑧𐑛 𐑛𐑬𐑑𐑕 𐑖𐑰 𐑜𐑨𐑞𐑼𐑟 𐑣𐑻 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑝𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑣𐑴𐑐.

𐑦𐑑 𐑯𐑰𐑛𐑟 𐑕𐑒𐑺𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑑𐑴𐑤𐑛, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑓𐑰𐑤𐑦𐑙𐑟, 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑰𐑝 𐑝 𐑩 ·𐑯𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑑 𐑝𐑶𐑦𐑡, 𐑲 𐑮𐑦𐑜𐑸𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑥𐑸𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑑𐑨𐑚𐑤𐑩𐑑𐑕, 𐑯 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑥𐑻𐑒𐑦 𐑤𐑲𐑑 𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑛𐑸𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑛, 𐑛𐑴𐑤𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑛𐑱 𐑮𐑧𐑛 𐑞 𐑓𐑱𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑣𐑵 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑜𐑪𐑯 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑥𐑰. 𐑘𐑧𐑕, ·𐑦𐑖𐑥𐑱𐑩𐑤, 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑓𐑱𐑑 𐑥𐑱 𐑚𐑰 𐑞𐑲𐑯. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑣𐑬 𐑲 𐑜𐑮𐑵 𐑥𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯. 𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑲𐑑𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑿𐑕𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑑 𐑦𐑥𐑚𐑸𐑒, 𐑓𐑲𐑯 𐑗𐑭𐑯𐑕 𐑓 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑥𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯, 𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑟—𐑲, 𐑩 𐑕𐑑𐑴𐑝 𐑚𐑴𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑥𐑱𐑒 𐑥𐑰 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑥𐑹𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑚𐑲 𐑚𐑮𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑑. 𐑘𐑧𐑕, 𐑞𐑺 𐑦𐑟 𐑛𐑧𐑔 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑚𐑦𐑟𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙—𐑩 𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑗𐑤𐑩𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑒 𐑒𐑱𐑪𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑚𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑩 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 ·𐑦𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑦. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑞𐑧𐑯? 𐑥𐑦𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑕 𐑢𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑣𐑿𐑡𐑤𐑦 𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑥𐑨𐑑𐑼 𐑝 ·𐑤𐑲𐑓 𐑯 ·𐑛𐑧𐑔. 𐑥𐑦𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑕 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑞𐑱 𐑒𐑷𐑤 𐑥𐑲 𐑖𐑨𐑛𐑴 𐑣𐑽 𐑪𐑯 𐑻𐑔 𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑲 𐑑𐑮𐑵 𐑕𐑳𐑚𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕. 𐑥𐑦𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑕 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑨𐑑 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑕𐑐𐑦𐑮𐑦𐑗𐑵𐑩𐑤, 𐑢𐑰 𐑸 𐑑𐑵 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑶𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑟 𐑩𐑚𐑟𐑻𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑯 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑞 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼, 𐑯 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑔𐑦𐑒 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼 𐑞 𐑔𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑝 𐑺. 𐑥𐑦𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑕 𐑥𐑲 𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦 𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞 𐑤𐑰𐑟 𐑝 𐑥𐑲 𐑚𐑧𐑑𐑼 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙. 𐑦𐑯 𐑓𐑨𐑒𐑑 𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑥𐑲 𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦 𐑣𐑵 𐑢𐑦𐑤, 𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑦𐑑 𐑲 𐑕𐑱, 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑥𐑰. 𐑯 𐑞𐑺𐑓𐑹 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑗𐑽𐑟 𐑓 ·𐑯𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑑; 𐑯 𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑩 𐑕𐑑𐑴𐑝 𐑚𐑴𐑑 𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑴𐑝 𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑞𐑱 𐑢𐑦𐑤, 𐑓 𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑝 𐑥𐑲 𐑕𐑴𐑤, ·𐑡𐑴𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑪𐑑.

·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 8. 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑫𐑤𐑐𐑦𐑑.

𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑕𐑰𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑺 𐑩 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑝 𐑩 𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑝𐑧𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑮𐑴𐑚𐑳𐑕𐑑𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑛; 𐑦𐑥𐑰𐑛𐑾𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑹𐑥-𐑐𐑧𐑤𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑛𐑹 𐑓𐑤𐑵 𐑚𐑨𐑒 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑩𐑛𐑥𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑩 𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑒 𐑮𐑦𐑜𐑸𐑛𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑲𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑚𐑲 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑒𐑪𐑙𐑜𐑮𐑦𐑜𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯, 𐑕𐑩𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑩𐑑𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑓𐑲𐑯 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞 𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑤𐑦𐑯. 𐑘𐑧𐑕, 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞 𐑓𐑱𐑥𐑩𐑕 ·𐑓𐑭𐑞𐑼 ·𐑥𐑱𐑐𐑩𐑤, 𐑕𐑴 𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑥𐑧𐑯, 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑣𐑵𐑥 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑓𐑱𐑝𐑼𐑦𐑑. 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑩 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑼 𐑯 𐑩 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑽 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑿𐑔, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑓 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑘𐑽𐑟 𐑐𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑛𐑧𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑤𐑲𐑓 𐑑 𐑞 𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑦. 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑲 𐑯𐑬 𐑮𐑲𐑑 𐑝, ·𐑓𐑭𐑞𐑼 ·𐑥𐑱𐑐𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑣𐑸𐑛𐑦 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼 𐑝 𐑩 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑔𐑦 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑱𐑡; 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑹𐑑 𐑝 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑱𐑡 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑟 𐑥𐑻𐑡𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑩 𐑕𐑧𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑓𐑤𐑬𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑿𐑔, 𐑓 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑼𐑟 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑮𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑟, 𐑞𐑺 𐑖𐑪𐑯 𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑥𐑲𐑤𐑛 𐑜𐑤𐑰𐑥𐑟 𐑝 𐑩 𐑯𐑿𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑦𐑝𐑧𐑤𐑩𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑤𐑵𐑥—𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑙 𐑝𐑻𐑡𐑼 𐑐𐑰𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑹𐑔 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑚𐑦𐑯𐑰𐑔 𐑓𐑧𐑚𐑮𐑵𐑺𐑦'𐑟 𐑕𐑯𐑴. 𐑯𐑴 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑐𐑮𐑰𐑝𐑾𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑣𐑻𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑦, 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑓 𐑞 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑚𐑦𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛 ·𐑓𐑭𐑞𐑼 ·𐑥𐑱𐑐𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑 𐑞 𐑳𐑑𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑩𐑕𐑑, 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑪𐑟 𐑞𐑺 𐑢𐑻 𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑜𐑮𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑒𐑤𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑦𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑟 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑿𐑑𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑩𐑛𐑝𐑧𐑯𐑗𐑼𐑩𐑕 𐑥𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑤𐑲𐑓 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑤𐑧𐑛. 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑣𐑰 𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑛 𐑲 𐑩𐑚𐑟𐑻𐑝𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑛 𐑯𐑴 𐑳𐑥𐑚𐑮𐑧𐑤𐑩, 𐑯 𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑡, 𐑓 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑑𐑸𐑐𐑷𐑤𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑑 𐑮𐑨𐑯 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑥𐑧𐑤𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑤𐑰𐑑, 𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑐𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑑 𐑒𐑤𐑪𐑔 𐑡𐑨𐑒𐑩𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑑 𐑛𐑮𐑨𐑜 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑑 𐑞 𐑓𐑤𐑹 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼 𐑦𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑩𐑚𐑕𐑹𐑚𐑛. 𐑣𐑬𐑧𐑝𐑼, 𐑣𐑨𐑑 𐑯 𐑒𐑴𐑑 𐑯 𐑴𐑝𐑼𐑖𐑵𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑚𐑲 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑵𐑝𐑛, 𐑯 𐑣𐑳𐑙 𐑳𐑐 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑐𐑱𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑩𐑯 𐑩𐑡𐑱𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑒𐑹𐑯𐑼; 𐑢𐑧𐑯, 𐑼𐑱𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑛𐑰𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑕𐑵𐑑, 𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑢𐑲𐑩𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑩𐑐𐑮𐑴𐑗𐑑 𐑞 𐑐𐑫𐑤𐑐𐑦𐑑.

𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑓𐑨𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑐𐑫𐑤𐑐𐑦𐑑𐑕, 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑤𐑪𐑓𐑑𐑦 𐑢𐑳𐑯, 𐑯 𐑕𐑦𐑯𐑕 𐑩 𐑮𐑧𐑜𐑿𐑤𐑼 𐑕𐑑𐑺𐑟 𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩 𐑣𐑲𐑑 𐑢𐑫𐑛, 𐑚𐑲 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑨𐑙𐑜𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑓𐑤𐑹, 𐑕𐑽𐑾𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑒𐑑 𐑞 𐑷𐑤𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑦 𐑕𐑥𐑷𐑤 𐑺𐑾 𐑝 𐑞 𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑩𐑤, 𐑞 𐑸𐑒𐑦𐑑𐑧𐑒𐑑, 𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛, 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑨𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑯𐑑 𐑝 ·𐑓𐑭𐑞𐑼 ·𐑥𐑱𐑐𐑩𐑤, 𐑯 𐑓𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑖𐑑 𐑞 𐑐𐑫𐑤𐑐𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑 𐑩 𐑕𐑑𐑺𐑟, 𐑕𐑳𐑚𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑑𐑿𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑐𐑻𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑼 𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑤𐑨𐑛𐑼, 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑿𐑟𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑩 𐑚𐑴𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑰. 𐑞 𐑢𐑲𐑓 𐑝 𐑩 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑝𐑲𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑞 𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑕𐑩𐑥 𐑐𐑺 𐑝 𐑮𐑧𐑛 𐑢𐑫𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑥𐑨𐑯-𐑮𐑴𐑐𐑕 𐑓 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑤𐑨𐑛𐑼, 𐑢𐑦𐑗, 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑑𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑯𐑲𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑩𐑛, 𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑯𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑥𐑩𐑣𐑪𐑜𐑩𐑯𐑦 𐑒𐑳𐑤𐑼, 𐑞 𐑣𐑴𐑤 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑝𐑩𐑯𐑕, 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑥𐑨𐑯𐑼 𐑝 𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟, 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑯𐑴 𐑥𐑰𐑯𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑚𐑨𐑛 𐑑𐑱𐑕𐑑. 𐑣𐑷𐑤𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑓 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑓𐑫𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑤𐑨𐑛𐑼, 𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑔 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑜𐑮𐑭𐑕𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑹𐑯𐑩𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑯𐑪𐑚𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑥𐑨𐑯-𐑮𐑴𐑐𐑕, ·𐑓𐑭𐑞𐑼 ·𐑥𐑱𐑐𐑩𐑤 𐑒𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑩 𐑤𐑫𐑒 𐑳𐑐𐑢𐑼𐑛𐑟, 𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑑𐑮𐑵𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑼-𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑮𐑧𐑝𐑼𐑧𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑤 𐑛𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑦, 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛, 𐑥𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑐𐑕 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑓 𐑩𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑥𐑱𐑯-𐑑𐑪𐑐 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑝𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑤.

𐑞 𐑐𐑻𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑼 𐑐𐑸𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑤𐑨𐑛𐑼, 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑟 𐑿𐑠𐑵𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑞 𐑒𐑱𐑕 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑕𐑢𐑦𐑙𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑟, 𐑢𐑻 𐑝 𐑒𐑤𐑪𐑔-𐑒𐑳𐑝𐑼𐑛 𐑮𐑴𐑐, 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑞 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑝 𐑢𐑫𐑛, 𐑕𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑐 𐑞𐑺 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩 𐑡𐑶𐑯𐑑. 𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑲 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑜𐑤𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑐𐑫𐑤𐑐𐑦𐑑, 𐑦𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑱𐑐𐑑 𐑥𐑰 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑬𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑝𐑰𐑯𐑾𐑯𐑑 𐑓 𐑩 𐑖𐑦𐑐, 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑡𐑶𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑳𐑯𐑯𐑧𐑕𐑦𐑕𐑺𐑦. 𐑓 𐑲 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑺𐑛 𐑑 𐑕𐑰 ·𐑓𐑭𐑞𐑼 ·𐑥𐑱𐑐𐑩𐑤 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑣𐑲𐑑, 𐑕𐑤𐑴𐑤𐑦 𐑑𐑻𐑯 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛, 𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑵𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑞 𐑐𐑫𐑤𐑐𐑦𐑑, 𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑚𐑼𐑩𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑮𐑨𐑜 𐑳𐑐 𐑞 𐑤𐑨𐑛𐑼 𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑐 𐑚𐑲 𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑐, 𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑞 𐑣𐑴𐑤 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑛𐑦𐑐𐑪𐑟𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑦𐑯, 𐑤𐑰𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑜𐑯𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 ·𐑒𐑢𐑩𐑚𐑧𐑒.

𐑲 𐑐𐑪𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑛 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑 𐑓𐑫𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑣𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑮𐑰𐑟𐑩𐑯 𐑓 𐑞𐑦𐑕. 𐑓𐑭𐑞𐑼 ·𐑥𐑱𐑐𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑯𐑡𐑶𐑛 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩 𐑢𐑲𐑛 𐑮𐑧𐑐𐑿𐑑𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑓 𐑕𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑯 𐑕𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑑𐑦, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑲 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑩𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑝 𐑒𐑹𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑯𐑴𐑑𐑼𐑲𐑩𐑑𐑦 𐑚𐑲 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑥𐑽 𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑡. 𐑯𐑴, 𐑔𐑷𐑑 𐑲, 𐑞𐑺 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑕𐑴𐑚𐑼 𐑮𐑰𐑟𐑩𐑯 𐑓 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑔𐑦𐑙; 𐑓𐑻𐑞𐑼𐑥𐑹, 𐑦𐑑 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑦𐑥𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑲𐑟 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑳𐑯𐑕𐑰𐑯. 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑦𐑑 𐑚𐑰, 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑨𐑒𐑑 𐑝 𐑓𐑦𐑟𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑲𐑕𐑩𐑤𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯, 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑦𐑜𐑯𐑦𐑓𐑲𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑐𐑦𐑮𐑦𐑗𐑵𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑛𐑮𐑷𐑩𐑤 𐑓 𐑞 𐑑𐑲𐑥, 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑷𐑤 𐑬𐑑𐑢𐑼𐑛 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑑𐑲𐑟 𐑯 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑧𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟? 𐑘𐑧𐑕, 𐑓 𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑤𐑧𐑯𐑦𐑖𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑥𐑰𐑑 𐑯 𐑢𐑲𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑻𐑛, 𐑑 𐑞 𐑓𐑱𐑔𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑝 ·𐑜𐑪𐑛, 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑐𐑫𐑤𐑐𐑦𐑑, 𐑲 𐑕𐑰, 𐑦𐑟 𐑩 𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓-𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑱𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑪𐑙𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛—𐑩 𐑤𐑪𐑓𐑑𐑦 ·𐑲𐑮𐑩𐑯𐑚𐑮𐑲𐑖𐑑𐑲𐑯, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑐𐑼𐑧𐑯𐑾𐑤 𐑢𐑧𐑤 𐑝 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑷𐑤𐑟.

𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑤𐑨𐑛𐑼 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑞 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡 𐑓𐑰𐑗𐑼 𐑝 𐑞 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕, 𐑚𐑪𐑮𐑴𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑤𐑦𐑯'𐑟 𐑓𐑹𐑥𐑼 𐑕𐑰-𐑓𐑺𐑦𐑙𐑟. 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑢𐑰𐑯 𐑞 𐑥𐑸𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑩𐑑𐑭𐑓𐑕 𐑪𐑯 𐑲𐑞𐑼 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑝 𐑞 𐑐𐑫𐑤𐑐𐑦𐑑, 𐑞 𐑢𐑷𐑤 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑓𐑹𐑥𐑛 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑚𐑨𐑒 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩𐑛𐑹𐑯𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑤𐑸𐑡 𐑐𐑱𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑮𐑧𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑜𐑨𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑚𐑰𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑩 𐑑𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑑𐑹𐑥 𐑪𐑓 𐑩 𐑤𐑰 𐑒𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑝 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑒 𐑮𐑪𐑒𐑕 𐑯 𐑕𐑯𐑴𐑦 𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑒𐑼𐑟. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑣𐑲 𐑩𐑚𐑳𐑝 𐑞 𐑓𐑤𐑲𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑒𐑳𐑛 𐑯 𐑛𐑸𐑒-𐑮𐑴𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑒𐑤𐑬𐑛𐑟, 𐑞𐑺 𐑓𐑤𐑴𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑩 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑲𐑤 𐑝 𐑕𐑳𐑯𐑤𐑲𐑑, 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑚𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑓𐑹𐑔 𐑩𐑯 𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑩𐑤'𐑟 𐑓𐑱𐑕; 𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑚𐑮𐑲𐑑 𐑓𐑱𐑕 𐑖𐑧𐑛 𐑩 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑑 𐑕𐑐𐑪𐑑 𐑝 𐑮𐑱𐑛𐑾𐑯𐑕 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐'𐑕 𐑑𐑪𐑕𐑑 𐑛𐑧𐑒, 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑦𐑤𐑝𐑼 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑑 𐑯𐑬 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 ·𐑝𐑦𐑒𐑑𐑼𐑦'𐑟 𐑐𐑤𐑨𐑙𐑒 𐑢𐑺 ·𐑯𐑧𐑤𐑕𐑩𐑯 𐑓𐑧𐑤. “𐑭, 𐑯𐑴𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑖𐑦𐑐,” 𐑞 𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑑 𐑕𐑱, “𐑚𐑰𐑑 𐑪𐑯, 𐑚𐑰𐑑 𐑪𐑯, 𐑞𐑬 𐑯𐑴𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑖𐑦𐑐, 𐑯 𐑚𐑺 𐑩 𐑣𐑸𐑛𐑦 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑥; 𐑓 𐑤𐑴! 𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑯 𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑔𐑮𐑵; 𐑞 𐑒𐑤𐑬𐑛𐑟 𐑸 𐑮𐑴𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑪𐑓—𐑕𐑼𐑰𐑯𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑨𐑠𐑼 𐑦𐑟 𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛.”

𐑯𐑹 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞 𐑐𐑫𐑤𐑐𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑑𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑 𐑩 𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑕𐑰-𐑑𐑱𐑕𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑩𐑗𐑰𐑝𐑛 𐑞 𐑤𐑨𐑛𐑼 𐑯 𐑞 𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑗𐑼. 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑐𐑨𐑯𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑳𐑯𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑤𐑲𐑒𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑩 𐑖𐑦𐑐'𐑕 𐑚𐑤𐑳𐑓 𐑚𐑬𐑟, 𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑦 ·𐑚𐑲𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑪𐑯 𐑩 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑡𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑐𐑰𐑕 𐑝 𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑴𐑤 𐑢𐑻𐑒, 𐑓𐑨𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑩 𐑖𐑦𐑐'𐑕 𐑓𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑤-𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑰𐑒.

𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑚𐑰 𐑥𐑹 𐑓𐑫𐑤 𐑝 𐑥𐑰𐑯𐑦𐑙?—𐑓 𐑞 𐑐𐑫𐑤𐑐𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑻𐑔'𐑕 𐑓𐑹𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑐𐑸𐑑; 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑮𐑽; 𐑞 𐑐𐑫𐑤𐑐𐑦𐑑 𐑤𐑰𐑛𐑟 𐑞 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛. 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞𐑧𐑯𐑕 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑹𐑥 𐑝 ·𐑜𐑪𐑛'𐑟 𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑒 𐑮𐑪𐑔 𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑬 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑺 𐑞 𐑻𐑤𐑾𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑮𐑳𐑯𐑑. 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞𐑧𐑯𐑕 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑞 ·𐑜𐑪𐑛 𐑝 𐑚𐑮𐑰𐑟𐑩𐑟 𐑓𐑺 𐑹 𐑓𐑬𐑤 𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑴𐑒𐑑 𐑓 𐑓𐑱𐑝𐑼𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑟. 𐑘𐑧𐑕, 𐑞 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛'𐑟 𐑩 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑪𐑯 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑐𐑨𐑕𐑦𐑡 𐑬𐑑, 𐑯 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑩 𐑝𐑶𐑦𐑡 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑰𐑑; 𐑯 𐑞 𐑐𐑫𐑤𐑐𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑐𐑮𐑬.

·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 9. 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑻𐑥𐑩𐑯.

𐑓𐑭𐑞𐑼 ·𐑥𐑱𐑐𐑩𐑤 𐑮𐑴𐑟, 𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑥𐑲𐑤𐑛 𐑝𐑶𐑕 𐑝 𐑳𐑯𐑩𐑕𐑿𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑷𐑔𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑹𐑛𐑼𐑛 𐑞 𐑕𐑒𐑨𐑑𐑼𐑛 𐑐𐑰𐑐𐑩𐑤 𐑑 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑛𐑧𐑯𐑕. “𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑼𐑛 𐑜𐑨𐑙𐑢𐑱, 𐑞𐑺! 𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑩𐑢𐑱 𐑑 𐑤𐑸𐑚𐑼𐑛—𐑤𐑸𐑚𐑼𐑛 𐑜𐑨𐑙𐑢𐑱 𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑼𐑛! 𐑥𐑦𐑛𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑕! 𐑥𐑦𐑛𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑕!”

𐑞𐑺 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩 𐑤𐑴 𐑮𐑳𐑥𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑣𐑧𐑝𐑦 𐑕𐑰-𐑚𐑵𐑑𐑕 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑞 𐑚𐑧𐑯𐑗𐑩𐑟, 𐑯 𐑩 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑕𐑤𐑲𐑑𐑼 𐑖𐑳𐑓𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑢𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑯'𐑟 𐑖𐑵𐑟, 𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑒𐑢𐑲𐑩𐑑 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯, 𐑯 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑲 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑰𐑗𐑼.

𐑣𐑰 𐑐𐑷𐑟𐑛 𐑩 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤; 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑯𐑰𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑐𐑫𐑤𐑐𐑦𐑑'𐑕 𐑚𐑬𐑟, 𐑓𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑤𐑸𐑡 𐑚𐑮𐑬𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑩𐑒𐑮𐑪𐑕 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑗𐑧𐑕𐑑, 𐑳𐑐𐑤𐑦𐑓𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑤𐑴𐑟𐑛 𐑲𐑟, 𐑯 𐑪𐑓𐑼𐑛 𐑩 𐑐𐑮𐑱𐑼 𐑕𐑴 𐑛𐑰𐑐𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑦𐑝𐑬𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑯𐑰𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑯 𐑐𐑮𐑱𐑦𐑙 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑚𐑪𐑑𐑩𐑥 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑰.

𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛, 𐑦𐑯 𐑐𐑮𐑴𐑤𐑪𐑙𐑛 𐑕𐑪𐑤𐑩𐑥 𐑑𐑴𐑯𐑟, 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑞 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑿𐑩𐑤 𐑑𐑴𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑩 𐑚𐑧𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑰 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑓𐑪𐑜—𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑑𐑴𐑯𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑮𐑰𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑓𐑪𐑤𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑥; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑗𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑨𐑯𐑼 𐑑𐑩𐑢𐑹𐑛𐑟 𐑞 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑒𐑤𐑵𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑟𐑩𐑟, 𐑚𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑓𐑹𐑔 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑐𐑰𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑧𐑜𐑟𐑳𐑤𐑑𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑯 𐑡𐑶—

𐑯𐑽𐑤𐑦 𐑷𐑤 𐑡𐑶𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑦𐑙𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑕𐑢𐑧𐑤𐑛 𐑣𐑲 𐑩𐑚𐑳𐑝 𐑞 𐑣𐑬𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑹𐑥. 𐑩 𐑚𐑮𐑰𐑓 𐑐𐑷𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑿𐑛; 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑰𐑗𐑼 𐑕𐑤𐑴𐑤𐑦 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑛 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑞 𐑤𐑰𐑝𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑚𐑲𐑚𐑩𐑤, 𐑯 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑, 𐑓𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑐𐑼 𐑐𐑱𐑡, 𐑕𐑧𐑛: “𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑳𐑝𐑩𐑛 𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑥𐑱𐑑𐑕, 𐑒𐑤𐑦𐑯𐑗 𐑞 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑝𐑻𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 𐑝 ·𐑡𐑴𐑯𐑩—'𐑯 ·𐑜𐑪𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑺𐑛 𐑩 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑓𐑦𐑖 𐑑 𐑕𐑢𐑪𐑤𐑴 𐑳𐑐 ·𐑡𐑴𐑯𐑩.'”

“𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑥𐑱𐑑𐑕, 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑚𐑫𐑒, 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑱𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑓𐑹 𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼𐑟—𐑓𐑹 𐑘𐑸𐑯𐑟—𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑥𐑷𐑤𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑥𐑲𐑑𐑦 𐑒𐑱𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑗𐑼𐑟. 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑛𐑧𐑐𐑔𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑴𐑤 𐑛𐑳𐑟 ·𐑡𐑴𐑯𐑩'𐑟 𐑛𐑰𐑐 𐑕𐑰𐑤𐑲𐑯 𐑕𐑬𐑯𐑛! 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑩 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑜𐑯𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑤𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑯 𐑑 𐑳𐑕 𐑦𐑟 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑓𐑩𐑑! 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑩 𐑯𐑴𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑦𐑖'𐑩𐑟 𐑚𐑧𐑤𐑦! 𐑣𐑬 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑴-𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑯 𐑚𐑶𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑩𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑜𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑛! 𐑢𐑰 𐑓𐑰𐑤 𐑞 𐑓𐑤𐑳𐑛𐑟 𐑕𐑻𐑡𐑦𐑙 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑳𐑕; 𐑢𐑰 𐑕𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑑 𐑞 𐑒𐑧𐑤𐑐𐑦 𐑚𐑪𐑑𐑩𐑥 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼𐑟; 𐑕𐑰-𐑢𐑰𐑛 𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑕𐑤𐑲𐑥 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑰 𐑦𐑟 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑳𐑕! 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑤𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑚𐑫𐑒 𐑝 ·𐑡𐑴𐑯𐑩 𐑑𐑰𐑗𐑩𐑟? 𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑥𐑱𐑑𐑕, 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑩 𐑑𐑵-𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑤𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑯; 𐑩 𐑤𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑯 𐑑 𐑳𐑕 𐑷𐑤 𐑨𐑟 𐑕𐑦𐑯𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑥𐑧𐑯, 𐑯 𐑩 𐑤𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑯 𐑑 𐑥𐑰 𐑨𐑟 𐑩 𐑐𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑤𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑙 ·𐑜𐑪𐑛. 𐑨𐑟 𐑕𐑦𐑯𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑥𐑧𐑯, 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑩 𐑤𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑯 𐑑 𐑳𐑕 𐑷𐑤, 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑪𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑩 𐑕𐑑𐑹𐑦 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑦𐑯, 𐑣𐑸𐑛-𐑣𐑸𐑑𐑩𐑛𐑯𐑩𐑕, 𐑕𐑳𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑩𐑢𐑱𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑓𐑽𐑟, 𐑞 𐑕𐑢𐑦𐑓𐑑 𐑐𐑳𐑯𐑦𐑖𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑, 𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕, 𐑐𐑮𐑱𐑼𐑟, 𐑯 𐑓𐑲𐑯𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑞 𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑝𐑼𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑯 𐑡𐑶 𐑝 ·𐑡𐑴𐑯𐑩. 𐑨𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑷𐑤 𐑕𐑦𐑯𐑼𐑟 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑥𐑧𐑯, 𐑞 𐑕𐑦𐑯 𐑝 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑕𐑳𐑯 𐑝 ·𐑱𐑥𐑦𐑑𐑲 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑤𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑴𐑚𐑰𐑛𐑾𐑯𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑭𐑯𐑛 𐑝 ·𐑜𐑪𐑛—𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑥𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑯𐑬 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑭𐑯𐑛 𐑢𐑪𐑟, 𐑹 𐑣𐑬 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑝𐑱𐑛—𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑣𐑰 𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑩 𐑣𐑸𐑛 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑭𐑯𐑛. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 ·𐑜𐑪𐑛 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑳𐑕 𐑛𐑵 𐑸 𐑣𐑸𐑛 𐑓 𐑳𐑕 𐑑 𐑛𐑵—𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑧𐑥𐑚𐑼 𐑞𐑨𐑑—𐑯 𐑣𐑧𐑯𐑕, 𐑣𐑰 𐑪𐑓𐑩𐑯𐑼 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑭𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑳𐑕 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑧𐑝𐑼𐑟 𐑑 𐑐𐑼𐑕𐑢𐑱𐑛. 𐑯 𐑦𐑓 𐑢𐑰 𐑴𐑚𐑱 ·𐑜𐑪𐑛, 𐑢𐑰 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑴𐑚𐑱 𐑬𐑼𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑝𐑟; 𐑯 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑴𐑚𐑱𐑦𐑙 𐑬𐑼𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑝𐑟, 𐑢𐑺𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑣𐑸𐑛𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑴𐑚𐑱𐑦𐑙 ·𐑜𐑪𐑛 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑕.

“𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑕𐑦𐑯 𐑝 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑴𐑚𐑰𐑛𐑾𐑯𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥, ·𐑡𐑴𐑯𐑩 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑓𐑻𐑞𐑼 𐑓𐑤𐑬𐑑𐑕 𐑨𐑑 ·𐑜𐑪𐑛, 𐑚𐑲 𐑕𐑰𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑓𐑤𐑰 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑣𐑦𐑥. 𐑣𐑰 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑕 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑩 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑒𐑨𐑮𐑦 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑒𐑳𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑺 ·𐑜𐑪𐑛 𐑛𐑳𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑮𐑱𐑯, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑞 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑻𐑔. 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑒𐑳𐑤𐑒𐑕 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑞 𐑢𐑹𐑝𐑟 𐑝 ·𐑡𐑪𐑐𐑩, 𐑯 𐑕𐑰𐑒𐑕 𐑩 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑞𐑨𐑑'𐑕 𐑚𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑓 ·𐑑𐑸𐑖𐑦𐑖. 𐑞𐑺 𐑤𐑻𐑒𐑕, 𐑐𐑼𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑕, 𐑩 𐑣𐑦𐑞𐑼𐑑𐑵 𐑳𐑯𐑣𐑰𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑥𐑰𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑽. 𐑚𐑲 𐑷𐑤 𐑩𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑕 ·𐑑𐑸𐑖𐑦𐑖 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑯𐑴 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑕𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑞 𐑥𐑪𐑛𐑼𐑯 ·𐑒𐑩𐑛𐑦𐑟. 𐑞𐑨𐑑'𐑕 𐑞 𐑩𐑐𐑦𐑯𐑘𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑤𐑻𐑯𐑛 𐑥𐑧𐑯. 𐑯 𐑢𐑺 𐑦𐑟 ·𐑒𐑩𐑛𐑦𐑟, 𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑥𐑱𐑑𐑕? ·𐑒𐑩𐑛𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑯 ·𐑕𐑐𐑱𐑯; 𐑨𐑟 𐑓𐑸 𐑚𐑲 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼, 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 ·𐑡𐑪𐑐𐑩, 𐑨𐑟 ·𐑡𐑴𐑯𐑩 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑐𐑪𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑱𐑯𐑗𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑛𐑱𐑟, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑩𐑑𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩𐑯 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑳𐑯𐑯𐑴𐑯 𐑕𐑰. 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑪𐑟 ·𐑡𐑪𐑐𐑩, 𐑞 𐑥𐑪𐑛𐑼𐑯 ·𐑡𐑨𐑓𐑩, 𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑥𐑱𐑑𐑕, 𐑦𐑟 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑰𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑥𐑧𐑛𐑦𐑑𐑼𐑱𐑯𐑾𐑯, 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑦𐑮𐑾𐑯; 𐑯 ·𐑑𐑸𐑖𐑦𐑖 𐑹 ·𐑒𐑩𐑛𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑹 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑑𐑵 𐑔𐑬𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑥𐑲𐑤𐑟 𐑑 𐑞 𐑢𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑢𐑼𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞𐑨𐑑, 𐑡𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑬𐑑𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑑𐑕 𐑝 ·𐑡𐑦𐑚𐑮𐑷𐑤𐑑𐑼. 𐑕𐑰 𐑘𐑰 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑥𐑱𐑑𐑕, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 ·𐑡𐑴𐑯𐑩 𐑕𐑷𐑑 𐑑 𐑓𐑤𐑰 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛-𐑢𐑲𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 ·𐑜𐑪𐑛? 𐑥𐑦𐑟𐑼𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑥𐑨𐑯! 𐑴! 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑥𐑐𐑑𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑯 𐑢𐑻𐑞𐑦 𐑝 𐑷𐑤 𐑕𐑒𐑹𐑯; 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑕𐑤𐑬𐑗𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑑 𐑯 𐑜𐑦𐑤𐑑𐑦 𐑲, 𐑕𐑒𐑳𐑤𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑣𐑦𐑟 ·𐑜𐑪𐑛; 𐑐𐑮𐑬𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑝𐑲𐑤 𐑚𐑻𐑜𐑩𐑤𐑼 𐑣𐑱𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑒𐑮𐑪𐑕 𐑞 𐑕𐑰𐑟. 𐑕𐑴 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑹𐑛𐑼𐑛, 𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓-𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑛𐑧𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑤𐑫𐑒, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑞𐑺 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑐𐑩𐑤𐑰𐑕𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑛𐑱𐑟, ·𐑡𐑴𐑯𐑩, 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑥𐑽 𐑕𐑩𐑕𐑐𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑮𐑪𐑙, 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑼𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑺 𐑣𐑰 𐑑𐑳𐑗𐑑 𐑩 𐑛𐑧𐑒. 𐑣𐑬 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑣𐑰'𐑟 𐑩 𐑓𐑿𐑡𐑩𐑑𐑦𐑝! 𐑯𐑴 𐑚𐑨𐑜𐑦𐑡, 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑩 𐑣𐑨𐑑-𐑚𐑪𐑒𐑕, 𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑰𐑟, 𐑹 𐑒𐑸𐑐𐑩𐑑-𐑚𐑨𐑜,—𐑯𐑴 𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑩𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑦 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑑 𐑞 𐑢𐑹𐑓 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞𐑺 𐑩𐑛𐑿𐑟. 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑, 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑛𐑪𐑡𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑻𐑗, 𐑣𐑰 𐑓𐑲𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑞 ·𐑑𐑸𐑖𐑦𐑖 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑰𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑥𐑟 𐑝 𐑣𐑻 𐑒𐑸𐑜𐑴; 𐑯 𐑨𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑐𐑕 𐑪𐑯 𐑚𐑹𐑛 𐑑 𐑕𐑰 𐑦𐑑𐑕 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑒𐑨𐑚𐑦𐑯, 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑼𐑟 𐑓 𐑞 𐑥𐑴𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑟𐑦𐑕𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑣𐑶𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑜𐑫𐑛𐑟, 𐑑 𐑥𐑸𐑒 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑼'𐑟 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑤 𐑲. ·𐑡𐑴𐑯𐑩 𐑕𐑰𐑟 𐑞𐑦𐑕; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑝𐑱𐑯 𐑣𐑰 𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑟 𐑑 𐑤𐑫𐑒 𐑷𐑤 𐑰𐑟 𐑯 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑓𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑕; 𐑦𐑯 𐑝𐑱𐑯 𐑧𐑕𐑱𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑮𐑧𐑗𐑩𐑛 𐑕𐑥𐑲𐑤. 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑪𐑙 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑿𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑩𐑖𐑫𐑼 𐑞 𐑥𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑯𐑼𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑚𐑰 𐑯𐑴 𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑑. 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑜𐑱𐑥𐑕𐑩𐑥 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑕𐑽𐑾𐑕 𐑢𐑱, 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑼𐑟 𐑑 𐑞 𐑳𐑞𐑼—“𐑡𐑨𐑒, 𐑣𐑰'𐑟 𐑮𐑪𐑚𐑛 𐑩 𐑢𐑦𐑛𐑴;” 𐑹, “·𐑡𐑴, 𐑛𐑵 𐑿 𐑥𐑸𐑒 𐑣𐑦𐑥; 𐑣𐑰'𐑟 𐑩 𐑚𐑦𐑜𐑩𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑑;” 𐑹, “𐑣𐑨𐑮𐑦 𐑤𐑨𐑛, 𐑲 𐑜𐑧𐑕 𐑣𐑰'𐑟 𐑞 𐑩𐑛𐑳𐑤𐑑𐑼𐑼 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑚𐑮𐑴𐑒 𐑡𐑱𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑴𐑤𐑛 ·𐑜𐑩𐑥𐑹𐑩, 𐑹 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑲𐑒, 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑻𐑛𐑼𐑼𐑟 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 ·𐑕𐑪𐑛𐑩𐑥.” 𐑩𐑯𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑮𐑳𐑯𐑟 𐑑 𐑮𐑰𐑛 𐑞 𐑚𐑦𐑤 𐑞𐑨𐑑'𐑕 𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑒 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑲𐑤 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑹𐑓 𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑫𐑼𐑛, 𐑪𐑓𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑲𐑝 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑛 𐑜𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑒𐑶𐑯𐑟 𐑓 𐑞 𐑨𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑣𐑧𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑩 𐑐𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑲𐑛, 𐑯 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑱𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑻𐑕𐑩𐑯. 𐑣𐑰 𐑮𐑰𐑛𐑟, 𐑯 𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑕 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 ·𐑡𐑴𐑯𐑩 𐑑 𐑞 𐑚𐑦𐑤; 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑷𐑤 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑔𐑧𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑥𐑱𐑑𐑕 𐑯𐑬 𐑒𐑮𐑬𐑛 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 ·𐑡𐑴𐑯𐑩, 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑺𐑛 𐑑 𐑤𐑱 𐑞𐑺 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥. 𐑓𐑮𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑛 ·𐑡𐑴𐑯𐑩 𐑑𐑮𐑧𐑥𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑟, 𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑷𐑤 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑱𐑕, 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑕 𐑕𐑴 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑞 𐑥𐑹 𐑩 𐑒𐑬𐑼𐑛. 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑓𐑧𐑕 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑕𐑩𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑛; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑑𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑪𐑙 𐑕𐑩𐑕𐑐𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯. 𐑕𐑴 𐑣𐑰 𐑥𐑱𐑒𐑕 𐑞 𐑚𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑝 𐑦𐑑; 𐑯 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑼𐑟 𐑓𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑞 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑨𐑛𐑝𐑻𐑑𐑲𐑟𐑛, 𐑞𐑱 𐑤𐑧𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑐𐑭𐑕, 𐑯 𐑣𐑰 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑒𐑨𐑚𐑦𐑯.

“'𐑣𐑵'𐑟 𐑞𐑺?' 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑟 𐑞 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑦𐑟𐑦 𐑛𐑧𐑕𐑒, 𐑣𐑳𐑮𐑦𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑥𐑱𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑬𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑱𐑐𐑼𐑟 𐑓 𐑞 ·𐑒𐑳𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑥𐑟—'𐑣𐑵'𐑟 𐑞𐑺?' 𐑴! 𐑣𐑬 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑸𐑥𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑕𐑗𐑩𐑯 𐑥𐑨𐑙𐑜𐑩𐑤𐑟 ·𐑡𐑴𐑯𐑩! 𐑓 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑟 𐑑 𐑓𐑤𐑰 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑮𐑨𐑤𐑦𐑟. '𐑲 𐑕𐑰𐑒 𐑩 𐑐𐑨𐑕𐑦𐑡 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑑 ·𐑑𐑸𐑖𐑦𐑖; 𐑣𐑬 𐑕𐑵𐑯 𐑕𐑱𐑤 𐑘𐑰, 𐑕𐑻?' 𐑞𐑳𐑕 𐑓𐑸 𐑞 𐑚𐑦𐑟𐑦 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑑 𐑳𐑐 𐑑 ·𐑡𐑴𐑯𐑩, 𐑞𐑴 𐑞 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑯𐑬 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑣𐑦𐑥; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑯𐑴 𐑕𐑵𐑯𐑼 𐑛𐑳𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑽 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑪𐑤𐑴 𐑝𐑶𐑕, 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑣𐑰 𐑛𐑸𐑑𐑕 𐑩 𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑵𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑲𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑜𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑕. '𐑢𐑰 𐑕𐑱𐑤 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑯𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑑𐑲𐑛,' 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑤𐑴𐑤𐑦 𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑼𐑛, 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑲𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑥. '𐑯𐑴 𐑕𐑵𐑯𐑼, 𐑕𐑻?'—'𐑕𐑵𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑳𐑓 𐑓 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑪𐑯𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑜𐑴𐑟 𐑩 𐑐𐑨𐑕𐑦𐑯𐑡𐑼.' 𐑣𐑭! ·𐑡𐑴𐑯𐑩, 𐑞𐑨𐑑'𐑕 𐑩𐑯𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑚. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑢𐑦𐑓𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑟 𐑩𐑢𐑱 𐑞 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑑. '𐑲'𐑤 𐑕𐑱𐑤 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑘𐑰,'—𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑧𐑟,—'𐑞 𐑐𐑨𐑕𐑦𐑡 𐑥𐑳𐑯𐑦 𐑣𐑬 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑦𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑?—𐑲'𐑤 𐑐𐑱 𐑯𐑬.' 𐑓 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑼𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑼𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑯, 𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑥𐑱𐑑𐑕, 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑓 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑻 𐑩 𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑴𐑝𐑼𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑣𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑦, '𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑐𐑱𐑛 𐑞 𐑓𐑺 𐑞𐑺𐑪𐑝' 𐑺 𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑭𐑓𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑕𐑱𐑤. 𐑯 𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑, 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑫𐑤 𐑝 𐑥𐑰𐑯𐑦𐑙.

“𐑯𐑬 ·𐑡𐑴𐑯𐑩'𐑟 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯, 𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑥𐑱𐑑𐑕, 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑣𐑵𐑟 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑻𐑯𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑑𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑕 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑥 𐑦𐑯 𐑧𐑯𐑦, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑣𐑵𐑟 𐑒𐑿𐑐𐑦𐑛𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑴𐑟𐑩𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑦𐑤𐑩𐑕. 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛, 𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑥𐑱𐑑𐑕, 𐑕𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑐𐑱𐑟 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑢𐑱 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑝𐑩𐑤 𐑓𐑮𐑰𐑤𐑦, 𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑 𐑩 𐑐𐑭𐑕𐑐𐑹𐑑; 𐑢𐑺𐑨𐑟 ·𐑝𐑻𐑗𐑵, 𐑦𐑓 𐑩 𐑐𐑷𐑐𐑼, 𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑪𐑐𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑓𐑮𐑳𐑯𐑑𐑽𐑟. 𐑕𐑴 ·𐑡𐑴𐑯𐑩'𐑟 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑺𐑟 𐑑 𐑑𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑞 𐑤𐑧𐑙𐑔 𐑝 ·𐑡𐑴𐑯𐑩'𐑟 𐑐𐑻𐑕, 𐑺 𐑣𐑰 𐑡𐑳𐑡 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑴𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑦. 𐑣𐑰 𐑗𐑸𐑡𐑩𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑔𐑮𐑲𐑕 𐑞 𐑿𐑠𐑵𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑳𐑥; 𐑯 𐑦𐑑'𐑕 𐑩𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑑. 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 𐑯𐑴𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 ·𐑡𐑴𐑯𐑩 𐑦𐑟 𐑩 𐑓𐑿𐑡𐑩𐑑𐑦𐑝; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑪𐑤𐑝𐑟 𐑑 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑐 𐑩 𐑓𐑤𐑲𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑐𐑱𐑝𐑟 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑮𐑽 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑜𐑴𐑤𐑛. 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑢𐑧𐑯 ·𐑡𐑴𐑯𐑩 𐑓𐑺𐑤𐑦 𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑕 𐑬𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑻𐑕, 𐑐𐑮𐑵𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑕𐑩𐑕𐑐𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑥𐑩𐑤𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯. 𐑣𐑰 𐑮𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑒𐑶𐑯 𐑑 𐑓𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑩 𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑓𐑦𐑑. 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑩 𐑓𐑹𐑡𐑼, 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑢𐑱, 𐑣𐑰 𐑥𐑳𐑑𐑼𐑟; 𐑯 ·𐑡𐑴𐑯𐑩 𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑫𐑑 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑓 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑨𐑕𐑦𐑡. '𐑐𐑶𐑯𐑑 𐑬𐑑 𐑥𐑲 𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑑-𐑮𐑵𐑥, ·𐑕𐑻,' 𐑕𐑧𐑟 ·𐑡𐑴𐑯𐑩 𐑯𐑬, '𐑲'𐑥 𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑝𐑩𐑤-𐑢𐑽𐑦; 𐑲 𐑯𐑰𐑛 𐑕𐑤𐑰𐑐.' '𐑞𐑬 𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑦𐑑,' 𐑕𐑧𐑟 𐑞 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯, '𐑞𐑺'𐑟 𐑞𐑲 𐑮𐑵𐑥.' ·𐑡𐑴𐑯𐑩 𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑟, 𐑯 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑤𐑪𐑒 𐑞 𐑛𐑹, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞 𐑤𐑪𐑒 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑱𐑯𐑟 𐑯𐑴 𐑒𐑰. 𐑣𐑽𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑓𐑵𐑤𐑦𐑖𐑤𐑦 𐑓𐑳𐑥𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑺, 𐑞 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 𐑤𐑭𐑓𐑕 𐑤𐑴𐑤𐑦 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓, 𐑯 𐑥𐑳𐑑𐑼𐑟 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑞 𐑛𐑹𐑟 𐑝 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑝𐑦𐑒𐑑𐑕' 𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑟 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑩𐑤𐑬𐑛 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑤𐑪𐑒𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑦𐑯. 𐑷𐑤 𐑛𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑯 𐑛𐑳𐑕𐑑𐑦 𐑨𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑦𐑟, ·𐑡𐑴𐑯𐑩 𐑔𐑮𐑴𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑻𐑔, 𐑯 𐑓𐑲𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑞 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑑-𐑮𐑵𐑥 𐑕𐑰𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑛. 𐑞 𐑺 𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑤𐑴𐑕, 𐑯 ·𐑡𐑴𐑯𐑩 𐑜𐑭𐑕𐑐𐑕. 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑣𐑴𐑤, 𐑕𐑳𐑙𐑒, 𐑑𐑵, 𐑚𐑦𐑯𐑰𐑔 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐'𐑕 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼-𐑤𐑲𐑯, ·𐑡𐑴𐑯𐑩 𐑓𐑰𐑤𐑟 𐑞 𐑣𐑧𐑮𐑩𐑤𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑲𐑓𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑬𐑼, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑖𐑨𐑤 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑥𐑷𐑤𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑬𐑩𐑤𐑟' 𐑢𐑹𐑛𐑟.

“𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑵𐑛 𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑨𐑒𐑕𐑦𐑕 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑲𐑛, 𐑩 𐑕𐑢𐑦𐑙𐑦𐑙 𐑤𐑨𐑥𐑐 𐑕𐑤𐑲𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑪𐑕𐑦𐑤𐑱𐑑𐑕 𐑦𐑯 ·𐑡𐑴𐑯𐑩'𐑟 𐑮𐑵𐑥; 𐑯 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐, 𐑣𐑰𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑑𐑩𐑢𐑹𐑛𐑟 𐑞 𐑢𐑹𐑓 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑰𐑝𐑛, 𐑞 𐑤𐑨𐑥𐑐, 𐑓𐑤𐑱𐑥 𐑯 𐑷𐑤, 𐑞𐑴 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑤𐑲𐑑 𐑥𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯, 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑥𐑱𐑯𐑑𐑱𐑯𐑟 𐑩 𐑐𐑻𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑴𐑚𐑤𐑦𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑮𐑧𐑓𐑼𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑑 𐑞 𐑮𐑵𐑥; 𐑞𐑴, 𐑦𐑯 𐑑𐑮𐑵𐑔, 𐑦𐑯𐑓𐑨𐑤𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑦𐑑𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓, 𐑦𐑑 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑪𐑚𐑝𐑾𐑕 𐑞 𐑓𐑷𐑤𐑕, 𐑤𐑲𐑦𐑙 𐑤𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑦𐑑 𐑣𐑳𐑙. 𐑞 𐑤𐑨𐑥𐑐 𐑩𐑤𐑸𐑥𐑟 𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑟 ·𐑡𐑴𐑯𐑩; 𐑨𐑟 𐑤𐑲𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑻𐑔 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑑𐑹𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑲𐑟 𐑮𐑴𐑤 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑞 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕, 𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑞𐑳𐑕 𐑓𐑸 𐑕𐑩𐑒𐑕𐑧𐑕𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑓𐑿𐑡𐑩𐑑𐑦𐑝 𐑓𐑲𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑯𐑴 𐑮𐑧𐑓𐑿𐑡 𐑓 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑜𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑕. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑩𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑤𐑨𐑥𐑐 𐑥𐑹 𐑯 𐑥𐑹 𐑩𐑐𐑷𐑤𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑥. 𐑞 𐑓𐑤𐑹, 𐑞 𐑕𐑰𐑤𐑦𐑙, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑲𐑛, 𐑸 𐑷𐑤 𐑼𐑲. '𐑴! 𐑕𐑴 𐑥𐑲 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑣𐑨𐑙𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑰!' 𐑣𐑰 𐑜𐑮𐑴𐑯𐑟, '𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑳𐑐𐑢𐑼𐑛𐑟, 𐑕𐑴 𐑦𐑑 𐑚𐑻𐑯𐑟; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞 𐑗𐑱𐑥𐑚𐑼𐑟 𐑝 𐑥𐑲 𐑕𐑴𐑤 𐑸 𐑷𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑒𐑮𐑫𐑒𐑩𐑛𐑯𐑩𐑕!'

“𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑣𐑵 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑩 𐑯𐑲𐑑 𐑝 𐑛𐑮𐑳𐑙𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑮𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑮𐑦 𐑣𐑲𐑟 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑧𐑛, 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑮𐑰𐑤𐑦𐑙, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑐𐑤𐑳𐑯𐑡𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑮𐑴𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑮𐑱𐑕-𐑣𐑹𐑕 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑕𐑴 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑞 𐑥𐑹 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑒 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑰𐑤 𐑑𐑨𐑜𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑣𐑦𐑥; 𐑨𐑟 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑣𐑵 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑦𐑟𐑼𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑐𐑤𐑲𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑟 𐑯 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑜𐑦𐑛𐑦 𐑨𐑙𐑜𐑢𐑦𐑖, 𐑐𐑮𐑱𐑦𐑙 ·𐑜𐑪𐑛 𐑓 𐑩𐑯𐑲𐑩𐑤𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑞 𐑓𐑦𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑐𐑭𐑕𐑑; 𐑯 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑩𐑥𐑦𐑛 𐑞 𐑢𐑻𐑤 𐑝 𐑢𐑴 𐑣𐑰 𐑓𐑰𐑤𐑟, 𐑩 𐑛𐑰𐑐 𐑕𐑑𐑿𐑐𐑼 𐑕𐑑𐑰𐑤𐑟 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑨𐑟 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑞 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑣𐑵 𐑚𐑤𐑰𐑛𐑟 𐑑 𐑛𐑧𐑔, 𐑓 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑦𐑟 𐑞 𐑢𐑵𐑯𐑛, 𐑯 𐑞𐑺'𐑟 𐑯𐑷𐑑 𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑷𐑯𐑗 𐑦𐑑; 𐑕𐑴, 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑕𐑹 𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑻𐑔, ·𐑡𐑴𐑯𐑩'𐑟 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑛𐑦𐑡𐑦 𐑝 𐑐𐑪𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑩𐑕 𐑥𐑦𐑟𐑼𐑦 𐑛𐑮𐑨𐑜𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑛𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑑 𐑕𐑤𐑰𐑐.

“𐑯 𐑯𐑬 𐑞 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑝 𐑑𐑲𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑒𐑳𐑥; 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑒𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑕 𐑪𐑓 𐑣𐑻 𐑒𐑱𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑟; 𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑛𐑦𐑟𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑹𐑓 𐑞 𐑳𐑯𐑗𐑽𐑛 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑓 ·𐑑𐑸𐑖𐑦𐑖, 𐑷𐑤 𐑒𐑼𐑰𐑯𐑦𐑙, 𐑜𐑤𐑲𐑛𐑟 𐑑 𐑕𐑰. 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑖𐑦𐑐, 𐑥𐑲 𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑟, 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑝 𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑹𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑕𐑥𐑳𐑜𐑩𐑤𐑼𐑟! 𐑞 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑩𐑚𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑢𐑪𐑟 ·𐑡𐑴𐑯𐑩. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑰 𐑮𐑧𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑟; 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑚𐑺 𐑞 𐑢𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑻𐑛𐑩𐑯. 𐑩 𐑛𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑑𐑹𐑥 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑟 𐑪𐑯, 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑦𐑟 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑑 𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑒. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑯𐑬 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑕𐑩𐑯 𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑟 𐑷𐑤 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑑 𐑤𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑣𐑻; 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑚𐑪𐑒𐑕𐑩𐑟, 𐑚𐑱𐑤𐑟, 𐑯 𐑡𐑸𐑟 𐑸 𐑒𐑤𐑨𐑑𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑴𐑝𐑼𐑚𐑹𐑛; 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑟 𐑖𐑮𐑰𐑒𐑦𐑙, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑸 𐑘𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑙, 𐑯 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑐𐑤𐑨𐑙𐑒 𐑔𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑰𐑑 𐑮𐑲𐑑 𐑴𐑝𐑼 ·𐑡𐑴𐑯𐑩'𐑟 𐑣𐑧𐑛; 𐑦𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑮𐑱𐑡𐑦𐑙 𐑑𐑿𐑥𐑳𐑤𐑑, ·𐑡𐑴𐑯𐑩 𐑕𐑤𐑰𐑐𐑕 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑛𐑾𐑕 𐑕𐑤𐑰𐑐. 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑰𐑟 𐑯𐑴 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑒 𐑕𐑒𐑲 𐑯 𐑮𐑱𐑡𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑰, 𐑓𐑰𐑤𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑞 𐑮𐑰𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑑𐑦𐑥𐑚𐑼𐑟, 𐑯 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑣𐑽𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑹 𐑣𐑰𐑛𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑞 𐑓𐑸 𐑮𐑳𐑖 𐑝 𐑞 𐑥𐑲𐑑𐑦 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑯𐑬 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑴𐑐𐑩𐑯 𐑥𐑬𐑔 𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑤𐑰𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑕𐑰𐑟 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑣𐑦𐑥. 𐑲, 𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑥𐑱𐑑𐑕, ·𐑡𐑴𐑯𐑩 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑜𐑪𐑯 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑕𐑲𐑛𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐—𐑩 𐑚𐑻𐑔 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑒𐑨𐑚𐑦𐑯 𐑨𐑟 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑑, 𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑓𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑩𐑕𐑤𐑰𐑐. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞 𐑓𐑮𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑼 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑟 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑯 𐑖𐑮𐑰𐑒𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑛𐑧𐑛 𐑽, '𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑥𐑰𐑯𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑞𐑬, 𐑴, 𐑕𐑤𐑰𐑐𐑼! 𐑼𐑲𐑟!' 𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑤𐑧𐑔𐑼𐑡𐑦 𐑚𐑲 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑛𐑲𐑼𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑒𐑮𐑲, ·𐑡𐑴𐑯𐑩 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑜𐑼𐑟 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑰𐑑, 𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑥𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑒, 𐑜𐑮𐑭𐑕𐑐𐑕 𐑩 𐑖𐑮𐑬𐑛, 𐑑 𐑤𐑫𐑒 𐑬𐑑 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑰. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑴𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑳𐑙 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑚𐑲 𐑩 𐑐𐑨𐑯𐑔𐑼 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑴 𐑤𐑰𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑞 𐑚𐑫𐑤𐑢𐑼𐑒𐑕. 𐑢𐑱𐑝 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑢𐑱𐑝 𐑞𐑳𐑕 𐑤𐑰𐑐𐑕 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐, 𐑯 𐑓𐑲𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑯𐑴 𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑛𐑦 𐑝𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑮𐑳𐑯𐑟 𐑮𐑹𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑹 𐑯 𐑭𐑓𐑑, 𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑞 𐑥𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑯𐑼𐑟 𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑯𐑲 𐑑 𐑛𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑩𐑓𐑤𐑴𐑑. 𐑯 𐑧𐑝𐑼, 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑥𐑵𐑯 𐑖𐑴𐑟 𐑣𐑻 𐑩𐑓𐑮𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑓𐑱𐑕 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑰𐑐 𐑜𐑳𐑤𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑒𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑴𐑝𐑼𐑣𐑧𐑛, 𐑩𐑜𐑭𐑕𐑑 ·𐑡𐑴𐑯𐑩 𐑕𐑰𐑟 𐑞 𐑮𐑽𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑴𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑑 𐑐𐑶𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑲 𐑳𐑐𐑢𐑼𐑛, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑕𐑵𐑯 𐑚𐑰𐑑 𐑛𐑬𐑯𐑢𐑼𐑛 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯 𐑑𐑩𐑢𐑹𐑛𐑟 𐑞 𐑑𐑹𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑛𐑰𐑐.

“𐑑𐑧𐑮𐑼𐑟 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑑𐑧𐑮𐑼𐑟 𐑮𐑳𐑯 𐑖𐑬𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑴𐑤. 𐑦𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑯𐑡𐑦𐑙 𐑨𐑑𐑦𐑑𐑿𐑛𐑟, 𐑞 ·𐑜𐑪𐑛-𐑓𐑿𐑡𐑩𐑑𐑦𐑝 𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑬 𐑑𐑵 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑯𐑴𐑯. 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑼𐑟 𐑥𐑸𐑒 𐑣𐑦𐑥; 𐑥𐑹 𐑯 𐑥𐑹 𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑜𐑮𐑴 𐑞𐑺 𐑕𐑩𐑕𐑐𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑯 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑, 𐑓𐑫𐑤𐑦 𐑑 𐑑𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑞 𐑑𐑮𐑵𐑔, 𐑚𐑲 𐑮𐑦𐑓𐑻𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑣𐑴𐑤 𐑥𐑨𐑑𐑼 𐑑 𐑣𐑲 ·𐑣𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑯, 𐑞𐑱 𐑓𐑷𐑤 𐑑 𐑒𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑤𐑪𐑑𐑕, 𐑑 𐑕𐑰 𐑓 𐑣𐑵𐑟 𐑒𐑷𐑟 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑑𐑧𐑥𐑐𐑦𐑕𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑥. 𐑞 𐑤𐑪𐑑 𐑦𐑟 ·𐑡𐑴𐑯𐑩'𐑟; 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑳𐑝𐑼𐑛, 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑣𐑬 𐑓𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑾𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑞𐑱 𐑥𐑪𐑚 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞𐑺 𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑕𐑗𐑩𐑯𐑟. '𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑞𐑲𐑯 𐑪𐑒𐑿𐑐𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯? 𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑕 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑞𐑬? 𐑞𐑲 𐑒𐑳𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑦? 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑐𐑰𐑐𐑩𐑤? 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑥𐑸𐑒 𐑯𐑬, 𐑥𐑲 𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑥𐑱𐑑𐑕, 𐑞 𐑚𐑦𐑣𐑱𐑝𐑘𐑼 𐑝 𐑐𐑫𐑼 ·𐑡𐑴𐑯𐑩. 𐑞 𐑰𐑜𐑼 𐑥𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑯𐑼𐑟 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑭𐑕𐑒 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑣𐑵 𐑣𐑰 𐑦𐑟, 𐑯 𐑢𐑺 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥; 𐑢𐑺𐑨𐑟, 𐑞𐑱 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑰𐑝 𐑩𐑯 𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑼 𐑑 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑕𐑗𐑩𐑯𐑟, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑤𐑲𐑒𐑢𐑲𐑟 𐑩𐑯𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑼 𐑑 𐑩 𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑕𐑗𐑩𐑯 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑐𐑫𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑞𐑧𐑥, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞 𐑳𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑕𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑼 𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑹𐑕𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 ·𐑡𐑴𐑯𐑩 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑣𐑸𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑝 ·𐑜𐑪𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥.

“'𐑲 𐑨𐑥 𐑩 ·𐑣𐑰𐑚𐑮𐑵,' 𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑟—𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯—'𐑲 𐑓𐑽 𐑞 ·𐑤𐑹𐑛 𐑞 ·𐑜𐑪𐑛 𐑝 ·𐑣𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑣𐑵 𐑣𐑨𐑔 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑞 𐑕𐑰 𐑯 𐑞 𐑛𐑮𐑲 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛!' 𐑓𐑽 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑴 ·𐑡𐑴𐑯𐑩? 𐑲, 𐑢𐑧𐑤 𐑥𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑞𐑬 𐑓𐑽 𐑞 ·𐑤𐑹𐑛 ·𐑜𐑪𐑛 𐑞𐑧𐑯! 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑑𐑢𐑱, 𐑣𐑰 𐑯𐑬 𐑜𐑴𐑟 𐑪𐑯 𐑑 𐑥𐑱𐑒 𐑩 𐑓𐑫𐑤 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑓𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑯; 𐑢𐑺𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑥𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑯𐑼𐑟 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑱𐑥 𐑥𐑹 𐑯 𐑥𐑹 𐑩𐑐𐑷𐑤𐑛, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑸 𐑐𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑓𐑩𐑤. 𐑓 𐑢𐑧𐑯 ·𐑡𐑴𐑯𐑩, 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑐𐑤𐑦𐑒𐑱𐑑𐑦𐑙 ·𐑜𐑪𐑛 𐑓 𐑥𐑻𐑕𐑦, 𐑕𐑦𐑯𐑕 𐑣𐑰 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑑𐑵 𐑢𐑧𐑤 𐑯𐑿 𐑞 𐑛𐑸𐑒𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑛𐑧𐑟𐑼𐑑𐑕,—𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑮𐑧𐑗𐑩𐑛 ·𐑡𐑴𐑯𐑩 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑟 𐑬𐑑 𐑑 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑑 𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑯 𐑒𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑓𐑹𐑔 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑕𐑰, 𐑓 𐑣𐑰 𐑯𐑿 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑓 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑱𐑒 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑑𐑧𐑥𐑐𐑦𐑕𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑥; 𐑞𐑱 𐑥𐑻𐑕𐑦𐑓𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑑𐑻𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑯 𐑕𐑰𐑒 𐑚𐑲 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑥𐑰𐑯𐑟 𐑑 𐑕𐑱𐑝 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑝𐑱𐑯; 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑜𐑯𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑜𐑱𐑤 𐑣𐑬𐑤𐑟 𐑤𐑬𐑛𐑼; 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑮𐑱𐑟𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑴𐑒𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑑 ·𐑜𐑪𐑛, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑞𐑱 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑳𐑯𐑮𐑦𐑤𐑳𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑤𐑱 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑝 ·𐑡𐑴𐑯𐑩.

“𐑯 𐑯𐑬 𐑚𐑦𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛 ·𐑡𐑴𐑯𐑩 𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑳𐑐 𐑨𐑟 𐑩𐑯 𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑼 𐑯 𐑛𐑮𐑪𐑐𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑕𐑰; 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑩𐑯 𐑶𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑭𐑥𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑓𐑤𐑴𐑑𐑕 𐑬𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑰𐑕𐑑, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑰 𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤, 𐑨𐑟 ·𐑡𐑴𐑯𐑩 𐑒𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑟 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑞 𐑜𐑱𐑤 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑤𐑰𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑥𐑵𐑞 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼 𐑚𐑦𐑣𐑲𐑯𐑛. 𐑣𐑰 𐑜𐑴𐑟 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑸𐑑 𐑝 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑒𐑺𐑕 𐑣𐑰𐑛𐑟 𐑞 𐑥𐑴𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑣𐑰 𐑛𐑮𐑪𐑐𐑕 𐑕𐑰𐑞𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑘𐑷𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑡𐑷𐑟 𐑩𐑢𐑱𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑥; 𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑖𐑵𐑑𐑕-𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑲𐑝𐑼𐑦 𐑑𐑰𐑔, 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑕𐑴 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑚𐑴𐑤𐑑𐑕, 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑩𐑯. 𐑞𐑧𐑯 ·𐑡𐑴𐑯𐑩 𐑐𐑮𐑱𐑛 𐑳𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 ·𐑤𐑹𐑛 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑓𐑦𐑖'𐑩𐑟 𐑚𐑧𐑤𐑦. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑩𐑚𐑟𐑻𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑮𐑱𐑼, 𐑯 𐑤𐑻𐑯 𐑩 𐑢𐑱𐑑𐑦 𐑤𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑯. 𐑓 𐑕𐑦𐑯𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑨𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑦𐑟, ·𐑡𐑴𐑯𐑩 𐑛𐑳𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑢𐑰𐑐 𐑯 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑓 𐑛𐑦𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑝𐑼𐑩𐑯𐑕. 𐑣𐑰 𐑓𐑰𐑤𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑛𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑐𐑳𐑯𐑦𐑖𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑡𐑳𐑕𐑑. 𐑣𐑰 𐑤𐑰𐑝𐑟 𐑷𐑤 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑝𐑼𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑑 ·𐑜𐑪𐑛, 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞𐑦𐑕, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑐𐑲𐑑 𐑝 𐑷𐑤 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑱𐑯𐑟 𐑯 𐑐𐑨𐑙𐑟, 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑤𐑫𐑒 𐑑𐑩𐑢𐑹𐑛𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑦 𐑑𐑧𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑤. 𐑯 𐑣𐑽, 𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑥𐑱𐑑𐑕, 𐑦𐑟 𐑑𐑮𐑵 𐑯 𐑓𐑱𐑔𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕; 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑒𐑤𐑨𐑥𐑼𐑩𐑕 𐑓 𐑐𐑸𐑛𐑩𐑯, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑓 𐑐𐑳𐑯𐑦𐑖𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑. 𐑯 𐑣𐑬 𐑐𐑤𐑰𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑑 ·𐑜𐑪𐑛 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑛𐑳𐑒𐑑 𐑦𐑯 ·𐑡𐑴𐑯𐑩, 𐑦𐑟 𐑖𐑴𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑦𐑝𐑧𐑯𐑗𐑵𐑩𐑤 𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑝𐑼𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑕𐑰 𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤. 𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑥𐑱𐑑𐑕, 𐑲 𐑛𐑵 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕 ·𐑡𐑴𐑯𐑩 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑿 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑒𐑪𐑐𐑦𐑛 𐑓 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑦𐑯 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑲 𐑛𐑵 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑿 𐑨𐑟 𐑩 𐑥𐑪𐑛𐑩𐑤 𐑓 𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕. 𐑕𐑦𐑯 𐑯𐑪𐑑; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑓 𐑿 𐑛𐑵, 𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑣𐑰𐑛 𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑦𐑑 𐑤𐑲𐑒 ·𐑡𐑴𐑯𐑩.”

𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑢𐑻𐑛𐑟, 𐑞 𐑣𐑬𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑞 𐑖𐑮𐑰𐑒𐑦𐑙, 𐑕𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑑𐑹𐑥 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑑 𐑨𐑛 𐑯𐑿 𐑐𐑬𐑼 𐑑 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑰𐑗𐑼, 𐑣𐑵, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑚𐑦𐑙 ·𐑡𐑴𐑯𐑩'𐑟 𐑕𐑰-𐑕𐑑𐑹𐑥, 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑑𐑪𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑩 𐑕𐑑𐑹𐑥 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓. 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑛𐑰𐑐 𐑗𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑰𐑝𐑛 𐑨𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑜𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛-𐑕𐑢𐑧𐑤; 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑑𐑪𐑕𐑑 𐑸𐑥𐑟 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑞 𐑢𐑹𐑦𐑙 𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑻𐑒; 𐑯 𐑞 𐑔𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑮𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑩𐑢𐑱 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑪𐑓 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑢𐑹𐑞𐑦 𐑚𐑮𐑬, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑤𐑲𐑑 𐑤𐑰𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑲, 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑷𐑤 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑤 𐑣𐑽𐑼𐑟 𐑤𐑫𐑒 𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑒 𐑓𐑽 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡 𐑑 𐑞𐑧𐑥.

𐑞𐑺 𐑯𐑬 𐑒𐑱𐑥 𐑩 𐑤𐑳𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑤𐑫𐑒, 𐑨𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑛 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑞 𐑤𐑰𐑝𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑚𐑫𐑒 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑕 𐑥𐑹; 𐑯, 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑, 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑩𐑕, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑒𐑤𐑴𐑟𐑛 𐑲𐑟, 𐑓 𐑞 𐑥𐑴𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑, 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑿𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑦𐑞 ·𐑜𐑪𐑛 𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓.

𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯 𐑣𐑰 𐑤𐑰𐑯𐑛 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑑𐑩𐑢𐑹𐑛𐑟 𐑞 𐑐𐑰𐑐𐑩𐑤, 𐑯 𐑚𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑤𐑴𐑤𐑦, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩𐑯 𐑨𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑛𐑰𐑐𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑥𐑨𐑯𐑤𐑾𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑿𐑥𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑦, 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑐𐑱𐑒 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑢𐑻𐑛𐑟:

“𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑥𐑱𐑑𐑕, ·𐑜𐑪𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑤𐑱𐑛 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑿; 𐑚𐑴𐑔 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑕 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑥𐑰. 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑮𐑧𐑛 𐑘𐑰 𐑚𐑲 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑥𐑻𐑒𐑦 𐑤𐑲𐑑 𐑥𐑱 𐑚𐑰 𐑥𐑲𐑯 𐑞 𐑤𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 ·𐑡𐑴𐑯𐑩 𐑑𐑰𐑗𐑩𐑟 𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑕𐑦𐑯𐑼𐑟; 𐑯 𐑞𐑺𐑓𐑹 𐑑 𐑘𐑰, 𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑥𐑹 𐑑 𐑥𐑰, 𐑓 𐑲 𐑨𐑥 𐑩 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑𐑼 𐑕𐑦𐑯𐑼 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑘𐑰. 𐑯 𐑯𐑬 𐑣𐑬 𐑜𐑤𐑨𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑲 𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑-𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑯 𐑕𐑦𐑑 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑣𐑨𐑗𐑩𐑟 𐑞𐑺 𐑢𐑺 𐑿 𐑕𐑦𐑑, 𐑯 𐑤𐑦𐑕𐑩𐑯 𐑨𐑟 𐑿 𐑤𐑦𐑕𐑩𐑯, 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑿 𐑮𐑰𐑛𐑟 𐑥𐑰 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑯 𐑥𐑹 𐑷𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑤𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑗 ·𐑡𐑴𐑯𐑩 𐑑𐑰𐑗𐑩𐑟 𐑑 𐑥𐑰, 𐑨𐑟 𐑩 𐑐𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑤𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑙 ·𐑜𐑪𐑛. 𐑣𐑬 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑯 𐑩𐑯𐑶𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑐𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑑-𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑓𐑩𐑑, 𐑹 𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑼 𐑝 𐑑𐑮𐑵 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑟, 𐑯 𐑚𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑯 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 ·𐑤𐑹𐑛 𐑑 𐑕𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑳𐑯𐑢𐑧𐑤𐑒𐑩𐑥 𐑑𐑮𐑵𐑞𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑽𐑟 𐑝 𐑩 𐑢𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑛 ·𐑯𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑝𐑩, ·𐑡𐑴𐑯𐑩, 𐑩𐑐𐑷𐑤𐑛 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑣𐑪𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑣𐑰 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑮𐑱𐑟, 𐑓𐑤𐑧𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯, 𐑯 𐑕𐑷𐑑 𐑑 𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑱𐑐 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑛𐑿𐑑𐑦 𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 ·𐑜𐑪𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑨𐑑 ·𐑡𐑪𐑐𐑩. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 ·𐑜𐑪𐑛 𐑦𐑟 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦𐑢𐑺; ·𐑑𐑸𐑖𐑦𐑖 𐑣𐑰 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑮𐑰𐑗𐑑. 𐑨𐑟 𐑢𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑕𐑰𐑯, ·𐑜𐑪𐑛 𐑒𐑱𐑥 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑯 𐑕𐑢𐑪𐑤𐑴𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑑 𐑤𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑜𐑳𐑤𐑓𐑕 𐑝 𐑛𐑵𐑥, 𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑕𐑢𐑦𐑓𐑑 𐑕𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑑𐑹 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑙 '𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑥𐑦𐑛𐑕𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑰𐑟,' 𐑢𐑺 𐑞 𐑧𐑛𐑦𐑦𐑙 𐑛𐑧𐑐𐑔𐑕 𐑕𐑳𐑒𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑑𐑧𐑯 𐑔𐑬𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑓𐑨𐑞𐑩𐑥𐑟 𐑛𐑬𐑯, 𐑯 '𐑞 𐑢𐑰𐑛𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑮𐑨𐑐𐑑 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑧𐑛,' 𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼𐑦 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛 𐑝 𐑢𐑴 𐑚𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑣𐑦𐑥. 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑚𐑦𐑘𐑪𐑯𐑛 𐑞 𐑮𐑰𐑗 𐑝 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑐𐑤𐑳𐑥𐑩𐑑—'𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑚𐑧𐑤𐑦 𐑝 𐑣𐑧𐑤'—𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑜𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯'𐑟 𐑳𐑑𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑴𐑯𐑟, 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯, ·𐑜𐑪𐑛 𐑣𐑻𐑛 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑜𐑳𐑤𐑓𐑑, 𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑓𐑩𐑑 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛. 𐑞𐑧𐑯 ·𐑜𐑪𐑛 𐑕𐑐𐑱𐑒 𐑳𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑓𐑦𐑖; 𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑖𐑳𐑛𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑒𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑯 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑒𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑰, 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑒𐑱𐑥 𐑚𐑮𐑰𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑳𐑐 𐑑𐑩𐑢𐑹𐑛𐑟 𐑞 𐑢𐑹𐑥 𐑯 𐑐𐑤𐑧𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑯, 𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑲𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑺 𐑯 𐑻𐑔; 𐑯 '𐑝𐑪𐑥𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑬𐑑 ·𐑡𐑴𐑯𐑩 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑛𐑮𐑲 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛;' 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑻𐑛 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑤𐑹𐑛 𐑒𐑱𐑥 𐑩 𐑕𐑧𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑑𐑲𐑥; 𐑯 ·𐑡𐑴𐑯𐑩, 𐑚𐑮𐑵𐑟𐑛 𐑯 𐑚𐑰𐑑𐑩𐑯—𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑽𐑟, 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑑𐑵 𐑕𐑰-𐑖𐑧𐑤𐑟, 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑥𐑳𐑤𐑑𐑦𐑑𐑿𐑛𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑥𐑻𐑥𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑞 𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯—·𐑡𐑴𐑯𐑩 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑞 ·𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑲𐑑𐑦'𐑟 𐑚𐑦𐑛𐑦𐑙. 𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑, 𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑥𐑱𐑑𐑕? 𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑰𐑗 𐑞 ·𐑑𐑮𐑵𐑔 𐑑 𐑞 𐑓𐑱𐑕 𐑝 ·𐑓𐑷𐑤𐑕𐑣𐑫𐑛! 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑦𐑑!

“𐑞𐑦𐑕, 𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑥𐑱𐑑𐑕, 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑦𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑤𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑯; 𐑯 𐑢𐑴 𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑐𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑤𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑙 ·𐑜𐑪𐑛 𐑣𐑵 𐑕𐑤𐑲𐑑𐑕 𐑦𐑑. 𐑢𐑴 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑣𐑵𐑥 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛 𐑗𐑸𐑥𐑟 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 ·𐑜𐑪𐑕𐑐𐑩𐑤 𐑛𐑿𐑑𐑦! 𐑢𐑴 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑣𐑵 𐑕𐑰𐑒𐑕 𐑑 𐑐𐑹 𐑶𐑤 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼𐑟 𐑢𐑧𐑯 ·𐑜𐑪𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑚𐑮𐑵𐑛 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑩 𐑜𐑱𐑤! 𐑢𐑴 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑣𐑵 𐑕𐑰𐑒𐑕 𐑑 𐑐𐑤𐑰𐑟 𐑮𐑭𐑞𐑼 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑑 𐑩𐑐𐑷𐑤! 𐑢𐑴 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑣𐑵𐑟 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑯𐑱𐑥 𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑹 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑜𐑫𐑛𐑯𐑩𐑕! 𐑢𐑴 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑣𐑵, 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛, 𐑒𐑹𐑑𐑕 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑪𐑯𐑼! 𐑢𐑴 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑣𐑵 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑑𐑮𐑵, 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑞𐑴 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑓𐑷𐑤𐑕 𐑢𐑻 𐑕𐑨𐑤𐑝𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯! 𐑘𐑱, 𐑢𐑴 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑣𐑵, 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 ·𐑐𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑑 ·𐑐𐑷𐑤 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑑, 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑐𐑮𐑰𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑳𐑞𐑼𐑟 𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑩 𐑒𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑢𐑱!”

𐑣𐑰 𐑛𐑮𐑪𐑐𐑑 𐑯 𐑓𐑧𐑤 𐑩𐑢𐑱 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑓 𐑩 𐑥𐑴𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑; 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑤𐑦𐑓𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑱𐑕 𐑑 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯, 𐑖𐑴𐑛 𐑩 𐑛𐑰𐑐 𐑡𐑶 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑲𐑟, 𐑨𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 𐑬𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑣𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑯𐑔𐑿𐑟𐑦𐑨𐑟𐑩𐑥,—“𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑴! 𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑥𐑱𐑑𐑕! 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑼𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑝 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑢𐑴, 𐑞𐑺 𐑦𐑟 𐑩 𐑖𐑫𐑼 𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑲𐑑; 𐑯 𐑣𐑲𐑼 𐑞 𐑑𐑪𐑐 𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑲𐑑, 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑪𐑑𐑩𐑥 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑴 𐑦𐑟 𐑛𐑰𐑐. 𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑞 𐑥𐑱𐑯-𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑒 𐑣𐑲𐑼 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑞 𐑒𐑧𐑤𐑕𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑟 𐑤𐑴? 𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑲𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥—𐑩 𐑓𐑸, 𐑓𐑸 𐑳𐑐𐑢𐑼𐑛, 𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑢𐑼𐑛 𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑲𐑑—𐑣𐑵 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑬𐑛 𐑜𐑪𐑛𐑟 𐑯 𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑛𐑹𐑟 𐑝 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑻𐑔, 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑓𐑹𐑔 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑴𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑼𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓. 𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑲𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑣𐑵𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑪𐑙 𐑸𐑥𐑟 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑕𐑩𐑐𐑹𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑝 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑚𐑱𐑕 𐑑𐑮𐑧𐑗𐑼𐑩𐑕 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑜𐑪𐑯 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑚𐑦𐑯𐑰𐑔 𐑣𐑦𐑥. 𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑲𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑣𐑵 𐑜𐑦𐑝𐑟 𐑯𐑴 𐑒𐑢𐑹𐑑𐑼 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑑𐑮𐑵𐑔, 𐑯 𐑒𐑦𐑤𐑟, 𐑚𐑻𐑯𐑟, 𐑯 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑶𐑟 𐑷𐑤 𐑕𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑴 𐑣𐑰 𐑐𐑤𐑳𐑒 𐑦𐑑 𐑬𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑞 𐑮𐑴𐑚𐑟 𐑝 ·𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑩𐑑𐑼𐑟 𐑯 ·𐑡𐑳𐑡𐑩𐑟. 𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑲𐑑,—𐑑𐑪𐑐-𐑜𐑨𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑲𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑣𐑵 𐑩𐑒𐑯𐑪𐑤𐑦𐑡𐑩𐑟 𐑯𐑴 𐑤𐑷 𐑹 𐑤𐑹𐑛, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑤𐑹𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 ·𐑜𐑪𐑛, 𐑯 𐑦𐑟 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑩 𐑐𐑨𐑑𐑮𐑾𐑑 𐑑 𐑣𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑯. 𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑲𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑣𐑵𐑥 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑝𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑴𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑰𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑚𐑶𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑩𐑕 𐑥𐑪𐑚 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑖𐑱𐑒 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑖𐑫𐑼 ·𐑒𐑰𐑤 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑱𐑡𐑩𐑟. 𐑯 𐑦𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑲𐑑 𐑯 𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑕𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑚𐑰 𐑣𐑦𐑟, 𐑣𐑵 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑤𐑱 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑛𐑬𐑯, 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑕𐑱 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑲𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑚𐑮𐑧𐑔—𐑴 ·𐑓𐑭𐑞𐑼!—𐑗𐑰𐑓𐑤𐑦 𐑯𐑴𐑯 𐑑 𐑥𐑰 𐑚𐑲 ·𐑞𐑲 𐑮𐑪𐑛—𐑥𐑹𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑹 𐑦𐑥𐑹𐑑𐑩𐑤, 𐑣𐑽 𐑲 𐑛𐑲. 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 ·𐑞𐑲𐑯, 𐑥𐑹 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛'𐑟, 𐑹 𐑥𐑲𐑯 𐑴𐑯. 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑳𐑔𐑦𐑙: 𐑲 𐑤𐑰𐑝 𐑦𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑑 ·𐑞𐑰; 𐑓 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑤𐑦𐑝 𐑬𐑑 𐑞 𐑤𐑲𐑓𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 ·𐑜𐑪𐑛?”

𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑯𐑴 𐑥𐑹, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑕𐑤𐑴𐑤𐑦 𐑢𐑱𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑚𐑧𐑯𐑦𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯, 𐑒𐑳𐑝𐑼𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑱𐑕 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟, 𐑯 𐑕𐑴 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑱𐑯𐑛 𐑯𐑰𐑤𐑦𐑙, 𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑐𐑰𐑐𐑩𐑤 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑛𐑦𐑐𐑸𐑑𐑩𐑛, 𐑯 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑤𐑧𐑓𐑑 𐑩𐑤𐑴𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕.

·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 10. 𐑩 ·𐑚𐑫𐑟𐑩𐑥 ·𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑯𐑛.

𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑐𐑬𐑑𐑼-·𐑦𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 ·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑩𐑤, 𐑲 𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜 𐑞𐑺 𐑒𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑩𐑤𐑴𐑯; 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑤𐑧𐑓𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑩𐑤 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑞 𐑚𐑧𐑯𐑦𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑑𐑲𐑥. 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑪𐑯 𐑩 𐑚𐑧𐑯𐑗 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑞 𐑓𐑲𐑼, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑰𐑑 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑴𐑝 𐑣𐑸𐑔, 𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑒𐑤𐑴𐑕 𐑳𐑐 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑱𐑕 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑯𐑰𐑜𐑮𐑴 𐑲𐑛𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟; 𐑐𐑽𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑸𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑓𐑱𐑕, 𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑡𐑨𐑒-𐑯𐑲𐑓 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑢𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑢𐑱 𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑯𐑴𐑟, 𐑥𐑰𐑯𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑣𐑳𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑰𐑞𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑖 𐑢𐑱.

𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑯𐑬 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑳𐑐𐑑𐑩𐑛, 𐑣𐑰 𐑐𐑫𐑑 𐑳𐑐 𐑞 𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑡; 𐑯 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑕𐑵𐑯, 𐑜𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑞 𐑑𐑱𐑚𐑩𐑤, 𐑑𐑫𐑒 𐑳𐑐 𐑩 𐑤𐑸𐑡 𐑚𐑫𐑒 𐑞𐑺, 𐑯 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑑 𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑤𐑨𐑐 𐑚𐑦𐑜𐑨𐑯 𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑐𐑱𐑡𐑩𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑚𐑼𐑩𐑑 𐑮𐑧𐑜𐑿𐑤𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑦; 𐑨𐑑 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑓𐑦𐑓𐑑𐑾𐑔 𐑐𐑱𐑡—𐑨𐑟 𐑲 𐑓𐑨𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑛—𐑕𐑑𐑪𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑥𐑴𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑, 𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑝𐑱𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑼𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑯 𐑜𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑳𐑑𐑼𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑑 𐑩 𐑤𐑪𐑙-𐑛𐑮𐑷𐑯 𐑜𐑻𐑜𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑦𐑕𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑩𐑕𐑑𐑪𐑯𐑦𐑖𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑. 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑚𐑦𐑜𐑦𐑯 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑯𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑 𐑓𐑦𐑓𐑑𐑦; 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑕 𐑨𐑑 𐑯𐑳𐑥𐑚𐑼 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑰𐑗 𐑑𐑲𐑥, 𐑨𐑟 𐑞𐑴 𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑 𐑥𐑹 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑓𐑦𐑓𐑑𐑦, 𐑯 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑲 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩 𐑤𐑸𐑡 𐑯𐑳𐑥𐑚𐑼 𐑝 𐑓𐑦𐑓𐑑𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑑𐑩𐑜𐑧𐑞𐑼, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑩𐑕𐑑𐑪𐑯𐑦𐑖𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑥𐑳𐑤𐑑𐑦𐑑𐑿𐑛 𐑝 𐑐𐑱𐑡𐑩𐑟 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑛.

𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑲 𐑕𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑥. 𐑕𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑡 𐑞𐑴 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟, 𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑛𐑾𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑥𐑸𐑛 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑞 𐑓𐑱𐑕—𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑰𐑕𐑑 𐑑 𐑥𐑲 𐑑𐑱𐑕𐑑—𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑩 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑚𐑲 𐑯𐑴 𐑥𐑰𐑯𐑟 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑩𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤. 𐑿 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑣𐑲𐑛 𐑞 𐑕𐑴𐑤. 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑷𐑤 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑳𐑯𐑻𐑔𐑤𐑦 𐑑𐑩𐑑𐑵𐑦𐑙𐑟, 𐑲 𐑔𐑷𐑑 𐑲 𐑕𐑷 𐑞 𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑝 𐑩 𐑕𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑤 𐑪𐑯𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑸𐑑; 𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑤𐑸𐑡, 𐑛𐑰𐑐 𐑲𐑟, 𐑓𐑲𐑼𐑦 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑒 𐑯 𐑚𐑴𐑤𐑛, 𐑞𐑺 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑑𐑴𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑩 𐑕𐑐𐑦𐑮𐑦𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑛𐑺 𐑩 𐑔𐑬𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑛𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑟. 𐑯 𐑚𐑦𐑕𐑲𐑛𐑟 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑦𐑕, 𐑞𐑺 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩 𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑤𐑪𐑓𐑑𐑦 𐑚𐑺𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑱𐑜𐑩𐑯, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑳𐑯𐑒𐑵𐑔𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑷𐑤𐑑𐑩𐑜𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑥𐑱𐑥. 𐑣𐑰 𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑑 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑣𐑵 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑯𐑡𐑛 𐑯 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑩 𐑒𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑦𐑑𐑼. 𐑢𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟, 𐑑𐑵, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑖𐑱𐑝𐑛, 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑛 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑛𐑮𐑷𐑯 𐑬𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑰𐑼 𐑯 𐑚𐑮𐑲𐑑𐑼 𐑮𐑦𐑤𐑰𐑓, 𐑯 𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑑 𐑥𐑹 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑨𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑦𐑑 𐑳𐑞𐑼𐑢𐑲𐑟 𐑢𐑫𐑛, 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑲 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑝𐑧𐑯𐑗𐑼 𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑲𐑛; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑯𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑡𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑦 𐑩𐑯 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑩𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯. 𐑦𐑑 𐑥𐑱 𐑕𐑰𐑥 𐑮𐑦𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑩𐑕, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑲𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑥𐑰 𐑝 ·𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑤 ·𐑢𐑪𐑖𐑦𐑙𐑑𐑩𐑯'𐑟 𐑣𐑧𐑛, 𐑨𐑟 𐑕𐑰𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑐𐑪𐑐𐑿𐑤𐑼 𐑚𐑳𐑕𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑥. 𐑦𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑮𐑧𐑜𐑿𐑤𐑼𐑤𐑦 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑮𐑰𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑤𐑴𐑐 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑩𐑚𐑳𐑝 𐑞 𐑚𐑮𐑬𐑟, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑢𐑻 𐑤𐑲𐑒𐑢𐑲𐑟 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑡𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑙, 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑑𐑵 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑦𐑟 𐑔𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑦 𐑢𐑫𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑪𐑯 𐑑𐑪𐑐. ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜 𐑢𐑪𐑟 ·𐑡𐑹𐑡 ·𐑢𐑪𐑖𐑦𐑙𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑦𐑝𐑧𐑤𐑩𐑐𐑑.

𐑢𐑲𐑤𐑕𐑑 𐑲 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞𐑳𐑕 𐑒𐑤𐑴𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑣𐑭𐑓-𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑰𐑯𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑬𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑹𐑥 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑒𐑱𐑕𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑, 𐑣𐑰 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑣𐑰𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑥𐑲 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑕, 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑕𐑴 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑨𐑟 𐑩 𐑕𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑩𐑤 𐑜𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑕; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑩𐑐𐑽𐑛 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑦 𐑪𐑒𐑿𐑐𐑲𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑐𐑱𐑡𐑩𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑥𐑸𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑚𐑫𐑒. 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑬 𐑕𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑢𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑕𐑤𐑰𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑑𐑩𐑜𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑞 𐑯𐑲𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑰𐑝𐑾𐑕, 𐑯 𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑩𐑓𐑧𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑑 𐑸𐑥 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑔𐑮𐑴𐑯 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑥𐑰 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑢𐑱𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑥𐑹𐑯𐑦𐑙, 𐑲 𐑔𐑷𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑓𐑼𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑕𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑡𐑩𐑟 𐑸 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙𐑟; 𐑨𐑑 𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑿 𐑛𐑵 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑯𐑴 𐑦𐑜𐑟𐑨𐑒𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑣𐑬 𐑑 𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑞𐑧𐑥. 𐑨𐑑 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑞𐑱 𐑸 𐑴𐑝𐑼𐑷𐑦𐑙; 𐑞𐑺 𐑒𐑭𐑥 𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓-𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑛𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑕𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑦𐑕𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑟 𐑩 ·𐑕𐑩𐑒𐑮𐑨𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑢𐑦𐑟𐑛𐑩𐑥. 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑯𐑴𐑑𐑦𐑕𐑑 𐑷𐑤𐑕𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑹𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑨𐑑 𐑷𐑤, 𐑹 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑦𐑯. 𐑣𐑰 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑯𐑴 𐑩𐑛𐑝𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑢𐑪𐑑𐑧𐑝𐑼; 𐑩𐑐𐑽𐑛 𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑯𐑴 𐑛𐑦𐑟𐑲𐑼 𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑤𐑸𐑡 𐑞 𐑕𐑻𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑩𐑒𐑢𐑱𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟. 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑒 𐑥𐑰 𐑨𐑟 𐑥𐑲𐑑𐑦 𐑕𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑿𐑤𐑼; 𐑘𐑧𐑑, 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑕𐑧𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑔𐑷𐑑𐑕, 𐑞𐑺 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑲𐑥 𐑦𐑯 𐑦𐑑. 𐑣𐑽 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑑𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑦 𐑔𐑬𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑥𐑲𐑤𐑟 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑣𐑴𐑥, 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑢𐑱 𐑝 ·𐑒𐑱𐑐 ·𐑣𐑹𐑯, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑟—𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑢𐑱 𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑜𐑧𐑑 𐑞𐑺—𐑔𐑮𐑴𐑯 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑐𐑰𐑐𐑩𐑤 𐑨𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑨𐑟 𐑞𐑴 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑻 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑐𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑩𐑑 ·𐑡𐑵𐑐𐑦𐑑𐑼; 𐑯 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑲𐑼𐑤𐑦 𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑰𐑟; 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑻𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑳𐑑𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑼𐑧𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑦; 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑴𐑯 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑨𐑯𐑘𐑩𐑯𐑖𐑦𐑐; 𐑷𐑤𐑢𐑱𐑟 𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑩𐑤 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓. 𐑖𐑫𐑼𐑤𐑦 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩 𐑑𐑳𐑗 𐑝 𐑓𐑲𐑯 𐑓𐑦𐑤𐑪𐑕𐑩𐑓𐑦; 𐑞𐑴 𐑯𐑴 𐑛𐑬𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑣𐑻𐑛 𐑞𐑺 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩 𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑨𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑. 𐑚𐑳𐑑, 𐑐𐑼𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑕, 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑑𐑮𐑵 𐑓𐑦𐑤𐑪𐑕𐑩𐑓𐑼𐑟, 𐑢𐑰 𐑥𐑹𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑕𐑴 𐑤𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑹 𐑕𐑴 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑝𐑦𐑙. 𐑕𐑴 𐑕𐑵𐑯 𐑨𐑟 𐑲 𐑣𐑽 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑹 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑜𐑦𐑝𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑬𐑑 𐑓 𐑩 𐑓𐑦𐑤𐑪𐑕𐑩𐑓𐑼, 𐑲 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑒𐑤𐑵𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑, 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑞 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑢𐑫𐑥𐑩𐑯, 𐑣𐑰 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 “𐑚𐑮𐑴𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑛𐑲𐑡𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑼.”

𐑨𐑟 𐑲 𐑕𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑯𐑬 𐑤𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑵𐑥; 𐑞 𐑓𐑲𐑼 𐑚𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑤𐑴, 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑲𐑤𐑛 𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑡 𐑢𐑧𐑯, 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑢𐑹𐑥𐑛 𐑞 𐑺, 𐑦𐑑 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑜𐑤𐑴𐑟 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑑 𐑨𐑑; 𐑞 𐑰𐑝𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑖𐑱𐑛𐑟 𐑯 𐑓𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑥𐑟 𐑜𐑨𐑞𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑞 𐑒𐑱𐑕𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕, 𐑯 𐑐𐑽𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑳𐑕 𐑕𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑑, 𐑕𐑪𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑼𐑦 𐑑𐑢𐑱𐑯; 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑹𐑥 𐑚𐑵𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑪𐑤𐑩𐑥 𐑕𐑢𐑧𐑤𐑟; 𐑲 𐑚𐑦𐑜𐑨𐑯 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡 𐑓𐑰𐑤𐑦𐑙𐑟. 𐑲 𐑓𐑧𐑤𐑑 𐑩 𐑥𐑧𐑤𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑰. 𐑯𐑴 𐑥𐑹 𐑥𐑲 𐑕𐑐𐑤𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑛 𐑣𐑸𐑑 𐑯 𐑥𐑨𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑢𐑻 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑛 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑞 𐑢𐑫𐑤𐑓𐑦𐑖 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛. 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑕𐑵𐑞𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑡 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑮𐑦𐑛𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑦𐑑. 𐑞𐑺 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑨𐑑, 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑓𐑼𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑯𐑱𐑗𐑼 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑞𐑺 𐑤𐑻𐑒𐑑 𐑯𐑴 𐑕𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑤𐑲𐑟𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑐𐑪𐑒𐑮𐑩𐑕𐑦𐑟 𐑯 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑰𐑑𐑕. 𐑢𐑲𐑤𐑛 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟; 𐑩 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑕𐑲𐑑 𐑝 𐑕𐑲𐑑𐑕 𐑑 𐑕𐑰; 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑲 𐑚𐑦𐑜𐑨𐑯 𐑑 𐑓𐑰𐑤 𐑥𐑲𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑽𐑾𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑮𐑷𐑯 𐑑𐑩𐑢𐑹𐑛𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑥. 𐑯 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑧𐑤𐑛 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑳𐑞𐑼𐑟, 𐑞𐑱 𐑢𐑻 𐑞 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑥𐑨𐑜𐑯𐑩𐑑𐑕 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑳𐑕 𐑛𐑮𐑵 𐑥𐑰. 𐑲'𐑤 𐑑𐑮𐑲 𐑩 𐑐𐑱𐑜𐑩𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑯𐑛, 𐑔𐑷𐑑 𐑲, 𐑕𐑦𐑯𐑕 ·𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑗𐑩𐑯 𐑒𐑲𐑯𐑛𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑐𐑮𐑵𐑝𐑛 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑣𐑪𐑤𐑴 𐑒𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑕𐑦. 𐑲 𐑛𐑮𐑵 𐑥𐑲 𐑚𐑧𐑯𐑗 𐑯𐑽 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑯 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑲𐑯𐑟 𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑕, 𐑛𐑵𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑲 𐑚𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑑 𐑑𐑷𐑒 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑥𐑰𐑯𐑢𐑲𐑤. 𐑨𐑑 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑯𐑴𐑑𐑦𐑕𐑑 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑩𐑛𐑝𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦, 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑥𐑲 𐑮𐑦𐑓𐑻𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑯𐑲𐑑'𐑕 𐑣𐑪𐑕𐑐𐑦𐑑𐑨𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑟, 𐑣𐑰 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑬𐑑 𐑑 𐑭𐑕𐑒 𐑥𐑰 𐑢𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑢𐑰 𐑢𐑻 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑚𐑧𐑛𐑓𐑧𐑤𐑴𐑟. 𐑲 𐑑𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑘𐑧𐑕; 𐑢𐑺𐑨𐑑 𐑲 𐑔𐑷𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑑 𐑐𐑤𐑰𐑟𐑛, 𐑐𐑼𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑕 𐑩 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑦𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛.

𐑢𐑰 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑛 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑞 𐑚𐑫𐑒 𐑑𐑩𐑜𐑧𐑞𐑼, 𐑯 𐑲 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑧𐑝𐑼𐑛 𐑑 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑯 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑞 𐑐𐑻𐑐𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑙, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑥𐑰𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑞 𐑓𐑿 𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑗𐑼𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑻 𐑦𐑯 𐑦𐑑. 𐑞𐑳𐑕 𐑲 𐑕𐑵𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑜𐑱𐑡𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑩𐑕𐑑; 𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑰 𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑑 𐑡𐑨𐑚𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑚𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑢𐑰 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑞 𐑝𐑺𐑾𐑕 𐑬𐑑𐑼 𐑕𐑲𐑑𐑕 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑕𐑰𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑓𐑱𐑥𐑩𐑕 𐑑𐑬𐑯. 𐑕𐑵𐑯 𐑲 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑐𐑴𐑟𐑛 𐑩 𐑕𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑥𐑴𐑒; 𐑯, 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑛𐑿𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑬𐑗 𐑯 𐑑𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑣𐑷𐑒, 𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑢𐑲𐑩𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑪𐑓𐑼𐑛 𐑥𐑰 𐑩 𐑐𐑳𐑓. 𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑢𐑰 𐑕𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑗𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑦𐑙 𐑐𐑳𐑓𐑕 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑲𐑤𐑛 𐑐𐑲𐑐 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟, 𐑯 𐑒𐑰𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑑 𐑮𐑧𐑜𐑿𐑤𐑼𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑭𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑢𐑰𐑯 𐑳𐑕.

𐑦𐑓 𐑞𐑺 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑤𐑻𐑒𐑑 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑲𐑕 𐑝 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑓𐑼𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑑𐑩𐑢𐑹𐑛𐑟 𐑥𐑰 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑱𐑜𐑩𐑯'𐑟 𐑚𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑑, 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑐𐑤𐑧𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑑, 𐑡𐑰𐑯𐑾𐑤 𐑕𐑥𐑴𐑒 𐑢𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛, 𐑕𐑵𐑯 𐑔𐑷𐑛 𐑦𐑑 𐑬𐑑, 𐑯 𐑤𐑧𐑓𐑑 𐑳𐑕 𐑒𐑮𐑴𐑯𐑦𐑟. 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑑 𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑑 𐑥𐑰 𐑒𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑯𐑨𐑗𐑼𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑯 𐑳𐑯𐑚𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑨𐑟 𐑲 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥; 𐑯 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑬𐑼 𐑕𐑥𐑴𐑒 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑴𐑝𐑼, 𐑣𐑰 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑛 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑥𐑲𐑯, 𐑒𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑐𐑑 𐑥𐑰 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑕𐑑, 𐑯 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑧𐑯𐑕𐑓𐑹𐑔 𐑢𐑰 𐑢𐑻 𐑥𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑛; 𐑥𐑰𐑯𐑦𐑙, 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑳𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑦'𐑟 𐑓𐑮𐑱𐑟, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑰 𐑢𐑻 𐑚𐑫𐑟𐑩𐑥 𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑟; 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑜𐑤𐑨𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑲 𐑓 𐑥𐑰, 𐑦𐑓 𐑯𐑰𐑛 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑚𐑰. 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑒𐑳𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑩𐑯, 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑕𐑳𐑛𐑩𐑯 𐑓𐑤𐑱𐑥 𐑝 𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑓𐑸 𐑑𐑵 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑥𐑩𐑗𐑫𐑼, 𐑩 𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑕𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑡 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑮𐑵𐑤𐑟 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑩𐑐𐑤𐑲.

𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑕𐑳𐑐𐑼, 𐑯 𐑩𐑯𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑕𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑤 𐑗𐑨𐑑 𐑯 𐑕𐑥𐑴𐑒, 𐑢𐑰 𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑑 𐑬𐑼 𐑮𐑵𐑥 𐑑𐑩𐑜𐑧𐑞𐑼. 𐑣𐑰 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑥𐑰 𐑩 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑥𐑚𐑭𐑥𐑛 𐑣𐑧𐑛; 𐑑𐑫𐑒 𐑬𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑹𐑥𐑩𐑕 𐑑𐑩𐑚𐑨𐑒𐑴 𐑢𐑪𐑤𐑩𐑑, 𐑯 𐑜𐑮𐑴𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑞 𐑑𐑩𐑚𐑨𐑒𐑴, 𐑛𐑮𐑵 𐑬𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑔𐑻𐑑𐑦 𐑛𐑪𐑤𐑼𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑦𐑤𐑝𐑼; 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑑𐑱𐑚𐑩𐑤, 𐑯 𐑥𐑦𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑦𐑝𐑲𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑑𐑵 𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑩𐑤 𐑐𐑹𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟, 𐑐𐑫𐑖𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑑𐑩𐑢𐑹𐑛𐑟 𐑥𐑰, 𐑯 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑥𐑲𐑯. 𐑲 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑜𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑑; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑥𐑰 𐑚𐑲 𐑐𐑹𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑥𐑲 𐑑𐑮𐑴𐑟𐑼𐑟' 𐑐𐑪𐑒𐑩𐑑𐑕. 𐑲 𐑤𐑧𐑑 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑕𐑑𐑱. 𐑣𐑰 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑰𐑝𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑐𐑮𐑱𐑼𐑟, 𐑑𐑫𐑒 𐑬𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑲𐑛𐑩𐑤, 𐑯 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑵𐑝𐑛 𐑞 𐑐𐑱𐑐𐑼 𐑓𐑲𐑼𐑚𐑹𐑛. 𐑚𐑲 𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑕𐑲𐑯𐑟 𐑯 𐑕𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑑𐑩𐑥𐑟, 𐑲 𐑔𐑷𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑕 𐑓 𐑥𐑰 𐑑 𐑡𐑶𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑧𐑤 𐑯𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑑 𐑓𐑪𐑤𐑴, 𐑲 𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑚𐑼𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑩 𐑥𐑴𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑢𐑧𐑞𐑼, 𐑦𐑯 𐑒𐑱𐑕 𐑣𐑰 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑥𐑰, 𐑲 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑲 𐑹 𐑳𐑞𐑼𐑢𐑲𐑟.

𐑲 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩 𐑜𐑫𐑛 ·𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑗𐑩𐑯; 𐑚𐑹𐑯 𐑯 𐑚𐑮𐑧𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑫𐑟𐑩𐑥 𐑝 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑓𐑨𐑤𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 ·𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑟𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑽𐑾𐑯 ·𐑗𐑻𐑗. 𐑣𐑬 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑲 𐑿𐑯𐑲𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑲𐑤𐑛 𐑲𐑛𐑪𐑤𐑩𐑑𐑼 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑻𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑰𐑕 𐑝 𐑢𐑫𐑛? 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑻𐑖𐑦𐑐? 𐑔𐑷𐑑 𐑲. 𐑛𐑵 𐑿 𐑕𐑩𐑐𐑴𐑟 𐑯𐑬, ·𐑦𐑖𐑥𐑱𐑩𐑤, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑥𐑨𐑜𐑯𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑥𐑩𐑕 ·𐑜𐑪𐑛 𐑝 𐑣𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑯 𐑻𐑔—𐑐𐑱𐑜𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑤𐑵𐑛𐑩𐑛—𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑐𐑪𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑰 𐑡𐑧𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑜𐑯𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑑 𐑝 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑒 𐑢𐑫𐑛? 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑪𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤! 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑻𐑖𐑦𐑐?—𐑑 𐑛𐑵 𐑞 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑝 ·𐑜𐑪𐑛—𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑻𐑖𐑦𐑐. 𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑞 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑝 ·𐑜𐑪𐑛?—𐑑 𐑛𐑵 𐑑 𐑥𐑲 𐑓𐑧𐑤𐑴 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑲 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑥𐑲 𐑓𐑧𐑤𐑴 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑑 𐑛𐑵 𐑑 𐑥𐑰—𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑞 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑝 ·𐑜𐑪𐑛. 𐑯𐑬, ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜 𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑲 𐑓𐑧𐑤𐑴 𐑥𐑨𐑯. 𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑛𐑵 𐑲 𐑢𐑦𐑖 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑛𐑵 𐑑 𐑥𐑰? 𐑢𐑲, 𐑿𐑯𐑲𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑥𐑰 𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑲 𐑐𐑼𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑼 ·𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑟𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑽𐑾𐑯 𐑓𐑹𐑥 𐑝 𐑢𐑻𐑖𐑦𐑐. 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑢𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦, 𐑲 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑿𐑯𐑲𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟; 𐑻𐑜𐑴, 𐑲 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑑𐑻𐑯 𐑲𐑛𐑪𐑤𐑩𐑑𐑼. 𐑕𐑴 𐑲 𐑒𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑞 𐑖𐑱𐑝𐑦𐑙𐑟; 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑐𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑐 𐑳𐑐 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑲𐑛𐑩𐑤; 𐑪𐑓𐑼𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑚𐑻𐑯𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜; 𐑕𐑩𐑤𐑭𐑥𐑛 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑑𐑢𐑲𐑕 𐑹 𐑔𐑮𐑲𐑕; 𐑒𐑦𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑴𐑟; 𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑛𐑳𐑯, 𐑢𐑰 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑯 𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑑 𐑚𐑧𐑛, 𐑨𐑑 𐑐𐑰𐑕 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑬𐑼 𐑴𐑯 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑰 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑜𐑴 𐑑 𐑕𐑤𐑰𐑐 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑗𐑨𐑑.

𐑣𐑬 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑲 𐑯𐑴 𐑯𐑪𐑑; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑴 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑚𐑧𐑛 𐑓 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑓𐑦𐑛𐑧𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑤 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑤𐑴𐑠𐑼𐑟 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑢𐑰𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑟. 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑯 𐑢𐑲𐑓, 𐑞𐑱 𐑕𐑱, 𐑞𐑺 𐑴𐑐𐑩𐑯 𐑞 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑚𐑪𐑑𐑩𐑥 𐑝 𐑞𐑺 𐑕𐑴𐑤𐑟 𐑑 𐑰𐑗 𐑳𐑞𐑼; 𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑒𐑳𐑐𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑪𐑓𐑩𐑯 𐑤𐑲 𐑯 𐑗𐑨𐑑 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑯𐑽𐑤𐑦 𐑥𐑹𐑯𐑦𐑙. 𐑞𐑳𐑕, 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑦𐑯 𐑬𐑼 𐑣𐑸𐑑𐑕' 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑦𐑥𐑵𐑯, 𐑤𐑱 𐑲 𐑯 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜—𐑩 𐑒𐑴𐑟𐑦, 𐑤𐑳𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑐𐑺.

·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 11. 𐑯𐑲𐑑𐑜𐑬𐑯.

𐑢𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑤𐑱𐑯 𐑞𐑳𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑚𐑧𐑛, 𐑗𐑨𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑯 𐑯𐑨𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑨𐑑 𐑖𐑹𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑟, 𐑯 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜 𐑯𐑬 𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑩𐑓𐑧𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑔𐑮𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑮𐑬𐑯 𐑑𐑩𐑑𐑵𐑛 𐑤𐑧𐑜𐑟 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑥𐑲𐑯, 𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑛𐑮𐑷𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑚𐑨𐑒; 𐑕𐑴 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑲𐑼𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑰 𐑯 𐑰𐑟𐑦 𐑢𐑻 𐑢𐑰; 𐑢𐑧𐑯, 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑, 𐑚𐑲 𐑮𐑰𐑟𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑬𐑼 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑓𐑨𐑚𐑿𐑤𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟, 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑯𐑨𐑐𐑦𐑖𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑱𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑳𐑕 𐑷𐑤𐑑𐑩𐑜𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑛𐑦𐑐𐑸𐑑𐑩𐑛, 𐑯 𐑢𐑰 𐑓𐑧𐑤𐑑 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑜𐑧𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑳𐑐 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯, 𐑞𐑴 𐑛𐑱-𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑒 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑢𐑱 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑿𐑗𐑼.

𐑘𐑧𐑕, 𐑢𐑰 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑱𐑥 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑢𐑱𐑒𐑓𐑩𐑤; 𐑕𐑴 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑕𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑬𐑼 𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑚𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑐𐑩𐑟𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑚𐑦𐑜𐑨𐑯 𐑑 𐑜𐑮𐑴 𐑢𐑽𐑦𐑕𐑩𐑥, 𐑯 𐑚𐑲 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑯 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑰 𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑬𐑼𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑝𐑟 𐑕𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑳𐑐; 𐑞 𐑒𐑤𐑴𐑞𐑟 𐑢𐑧𐑤 𐑑𐑳𐑒𐑑 𐑼𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑳𐑕, 𐑤𐑰𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑞 𐑣𐑧𐑛-𐑚𐑹𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑬𐑼 𐑓𐑹 𐑯𐑰𐑟 𐑛𐑮𐑷𐑯 𐑳𐑐 𐑒𐑤𐑴𐑕 𐑑𐑩𐑜𐑧𐑞𐑼, 𐑯 𐑬𐑼 𐑑𐑵 𐑯𐑴𐑟𐑩𐑟 𐑚𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑞𐑧𐑥, 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑓 𐑬𐑼 𐑯𐑰𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑢𐑹𐑥𐑦𐑙-𐑐𐑨𐑯𐑟. 𐑢𐑰 𐑓𐑧𐑤𐑑 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑯𐑲𐑕 𐑯 𐑕𐑯𐑳𐑜, 𐑞 𐑥𐑹 𐑕𐑴 𐑕𐑦𐑯𐑕 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑴 𐑗𐑦𐑤𐑦 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑛𐑹𐑟; 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑰𐑛 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑚𐑧𐑛-𐑒𐑤𐑴𐑞𐑟 𐑑𐑵, 𐑕𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑴 𐑓𐑲𐑼 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑮𐑵𐑥. 𐑞 𐑥𐑹 𐑕𐑴, 𐑲 𐑕𐑱, 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑪𐑟 𐑑𐑮𐑵𐑤𐑦 𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑡𐑶 𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑦 𐑢𐑹𐑥𐑔, 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑕𐑥𐑷𐑤 𐑐𐑸𐑑 𐑝 𐑿 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑒𐑴𐑤𐑛, 𐑓 𐑞𐑺 𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑴 𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑽𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑲 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑭𐑕𐑑. 𐑯𐑳𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑜𐑟𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑦𐑑𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓. 𐑦𐑓 𐑿 𐑓𐑤𐑨𐑑𐑼 𐑘𐑹𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑿 𐑸 𐑷𐑤 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑓𐑼𐑑𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤, 𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑕𐑴 𐑩 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑑𐑲𐑥, 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑿 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑓𐑼𐑑𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑥𐑹. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑓, 𐑤𐑲𐑒 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜 𐑯 𐑥𐑰 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑧𐑛, 𐑞 𐑑𐑦𐑐 𐑝 𐑘𐑹 𐑯𐑴𐑟 𐑹 𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑬𐑯 𐑝 𐑘𐑹 𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑚𐑰 𐑕𐑤𐑲𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑗𐑦𐑤𐑛, 𐑢𐑲 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑰𐑛, 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑕𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑿 𐑓𐑰𐑤 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑲𐑑𐑓𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑯 𐑳𐑯𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑢𐑹𐑥. 𐑓 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑮𐑰𐑟𐑩𐑯 𐑩 𐑕𐑤𐑰𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑐𐑸𐑑𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑚𐑰 𐑓𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑖𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑓𐑲𐑼, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑤𐑳𐑜𐑠𐑫𐑼𐑾𐑕 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑓𐑼𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑮𐑦𐑗. 𐑓 𐑞 𐑣𐑲𐑑 𐑝 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑕𐑹𐑑 𐑝 𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑕𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑦𐑟 𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑯𐑳𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑩𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑢𐑰𐑯 𐑿 𐑯 𐑘𐑹 𐑕𐑯𐑳𐑜𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑯 𐑞 𐑒𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑝 𐑞 𐑬𐑑𐑼 𐑺. 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑿 𐑤𐑲 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑞 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑢𐑹𐑥 𐑕𐑐𐑸𐑒 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑣𐑸𐑑 𐑝 𐑩𐑯 𐑸𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑤.

𐑢𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑕𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑒𐑮𐑬𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑨𐑯𐑼 𐑓 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑑𐑲𐑥, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑕 𐑲 𐑔𐑷𐑑 𐑲 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑴𐑐𐑩𐑯 𐑥𐑲 𐑲𐑟; 𐑓 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑢𐑰𐑯 𐑖𐑰𐑑𐑕, 𐑢𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑚𐑲 𐑛𐑱 𐑹 𐑚𐑲 𐑯𐑲𐑑, 𐑯 𐑢𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑩𐑕𐑤𐑰𐑐 𐑹 𐑩𐑢𐑱𐑒, 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑩 𐑢𐑱 𐑝 𐑷𐑤𐑢𐑱𐑟 𐑒𐑰𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑲 𐑲𐑟 𐑖𐑳𐑑, 𐑦𐑯 𐑹𐑛𐑼 𐑞 𐑥𐑹 𐑑 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑯𐑳𐑜𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑚𐑧𐑛. 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑴 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑓𐑰𐑤 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑴𐑯 𐑲𐑛𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑼𐑲𐑑 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑧𐑐𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑲𐑟 𐑚𐑰 𐑒𐑤𐑴𐑟𐑛; 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑓 𐑛𐑸𐑒𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑢𐑻 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑰𐑛 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑐𐑼 𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑬𐑼 𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟, 𐑞𐑴 𐑤𐑲𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑥𐑹 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑡𐑰𐑯𐑾𐑤 𐑑 𐑬𐑼 𐑒𐑤𐑱𐑦 𐑐𐑸𐑑. 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑴𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑲 𐑲𐑟 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑯 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑥𐑲 𐑴𐑯 𐑐𐑤𐑧𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑯 𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓-𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑛𐑸𐑒𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑴𐑟𐑛 𐑯 𐑒𐑹𐑕 𐑬𐑑𐑼 𐑜𐑤𐑵𐑥 𐑝 𐑞 𐑳𐑯𐑦𐑤𐑵𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑑𐑢𐑧𐑤𐑝-𐑴'𐑒𐑤𐑪𐑒-𐑨𐑑-𐑯𐑲𐑑, 𐑲 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑽𐑾𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑩 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑩𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑮𐑦𐑝𐑳𐑤𐑖𐑩𐑯. 𐑯𐑹 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑲 𐑨𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑪𐑚𐑡𐑧𐑒𐑑 𐑑 𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑯𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑐𐑼𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑕 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑻 𐑚𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑤𐑲𐑑, 𐑕𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑰 𐑢𐑻 𐑕𐑴 𐑢𐑲𐑛 𐑩𐑢𐑱𐑒; 𐑯 𐑚𐑦𐑕𐑲𐑛𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑓𐑧𐑤𐑑 𐑩 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑪𐑙 𐑛𐑦𐑟𐑲𐑼 𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑩 𐑓𐑿 𐑒𐑢𐑲𐑩𐑑 𐑐𐑳𐑓𐑕 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑣𐑦𐑟 ·𐑑𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑣𐑷𐑒. 𐑚𐑰 𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑧𐑛, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑴 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑓𐑧𐑤𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑪𐑙 𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑳𐑜𐑯𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑥𐑴𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑧𐑛 𐑞 𐑯𐑲𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹, 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑕𐑰 𐑣𐑬 𐑦𐑤𐑨𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑬𐑼 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑓 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑡𐑩𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑜𐑮𐑴 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑤𐑳𐑝 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑕 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑟 𐑑 𐑚𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑞𐑧𐑥. 𐑓 𐑯𐑬 𐑲 𐑤𐑲𐑒𐑑 𐑯𐑳𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑧𐑑𐑼 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜 𐑕𐑥𐑴𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑲 𐑥𐑰, 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑚𐑧𐑛, 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑪𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑓𐑫𐑤 𐑝 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑕𐑼𐑰𐑯 𐑣𐑬𐑕𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑡𐑶 𐑞𐑧𐑯. 𐑲 𐑯𐑴 𐑥𐑹 𐑓𐑧𐑤𐑑 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑿𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑻𐑯𐑛 𐑓 𐑞 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑤𐑹𐑛'𐑟 𐑐𐑪𐑤𐑩𐑕𐑦 𐑝 𐑦𐑯𐑖𐑫𐑼𐑩𐑯𐑕. 𐑲 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑩𐑤𐑲𐑝 𐑑 𐑞 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑛𐑧𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑓𐑦𐑛𐑧𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑤 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑓𐑼𐑑𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑖𐑺𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑐𐑲𐑐 𐑯 𐑩 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑩𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑮𐑾𐑤 𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑯𐑛. 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑬𐑼 𐑖𐑨𐑜𐑦 𐑡𐑨𐑒𐑩𐑑𐑕 𐑛𐑮𐑷𐑯 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑬𐑼 𐑖𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑼𐑟, 𐑢𐑰 𐑯𐑬 𐑐𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑑𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑣𐑷𐑒 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑑 𐑞 𐑳𐑞𐑼, 𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑕𐑤𐑴𐑤𐑦 𐑞𐑺 𐑜𐑮𐑵 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑳𐑕 𐑩 𐑚𐑤𐑵 𐑣𐑨𐑙𐑦𐑙 𐑑𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑼 𐑝 𐑕𐑥𐑴𐑒, 𐑦𐑤𐑵𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑓𐑤𐑱𐑥 𐑝 𐑞 𐑯𐑿-𐑤𐑦𐑑 𐑤𐑨𐑥𐑐.

𐑢𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑳𐑯𐑡𐑩𐑤𐑱𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑑𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑼 𐑮𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑞 𐑕𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑡 𐑩𐑢𐑱 𐑑 𐑓𐑸 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑯𐑟, 𐑲 𐑯𐑴 𐑯𐑪𐑑, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑯𐑬 𐑕𐑐𐑴𐑒 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑱𐑑𐑦𐑝 𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛; 𐑯, 𐑰𐑜𐑼 𐑑 𐑣𐑽 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑦, 𐑲 𐑚𐑧𐑜𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑑 𐑜𐑴 𐑪𐑯 𐑯 𐑑𐑧𐑤 𐑦𐑑. 𐑣𐑰 𐑜𐑤𐑨𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑲𐑛. 𐑞𐑴 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑲 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑤 𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑣𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑩 𐑓𐑿 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑻𐑛𐑟, 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑚𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑢𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑤𐑴𐑠𐑼𐑟, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑥𐑹 𐑓𐑩𐑥𐑦𐑤𐑽 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑮𐑴𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑱𐑟𐑦𐑪𐑤𐑩𐑡𐑦, 𐑯𐑬 𐑦𐑯𐑱𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑥𐑰 𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑞 𐑣𐑴𐑤 𐑕𐑑𐑹𐑦 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑥𐑱 𐑐𐑮𐑵𐑝 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑥𐑽 𐑕𐑒𐑧𐑤𐑩𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑲 𐑜𐑦𐑝.

·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 12. 𐑚𐑲𐑩𐑜𐑮𐑨𐑓𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤.

·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩 𐑯𐑱𐑑𐑦𐑝 𐑝 ·𐑮𐑴𐑒𐑴𐑝𐑩𐑒𐑴, 𐑩𐑯 𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑓𐑸 𐑩𐑢𐑱 𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑢𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑯 ·𐑕𐑬𐑔. 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑥𐑨𐑐; 𐑑𐑮𐑵 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑸.

𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑩 𐑯𐑿-𐑣𐑨𐑗𐑑 𐑕𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑡 𐑮𐑳𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑲𐑤𐑛 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑱𐑑𐑦𐑝 𐑢𐑫𐑛𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑜𐑮𐑭𐑕 𐑒𐑤𐑬𐑑, 𐑓𐑪𐑤𐑴𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑯𐑦𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑜𐑴𐑑𐑕, 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑓 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑻 𐑩 𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑯 𐑕𐑨𐑐𐑤𐑦𐑙; 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑦𐑯 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜'𐑟 𐑨𐑥𐑚𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑕 𐑕𐑴𐑤, 𐑤𐑻𐑒𐑑 𐑩 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑪𐑙 𐑛𐑦𐑟𐑲𐑼 𐑑 𐑕𐑰 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑹 𐑝 ·𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑥 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑩 𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑼 𐑹 𐑑𐑵. 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑭𐑞𐑼 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩 ·𐑣𐑲 ·𐑗𐑰𐑓, 𐑩 ·𐑒𐑦𐑙; 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑳𐑙𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑩 ·𐑣𐑲 ·𐑐𐑮𐑰𐑕𐑑; 𐑯 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑥𐑩𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑣𐑰 𐑚𐑴𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑭𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑣𐑵 𐑢𐑻 𐑞 𐑢𐑲𐑝𐑟 𐑝 𐑳𐑯𐑒𐑪𐑙𐑒𐑼𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑹𐑽𐑟. 𐑞𐑺 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑩𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑚𐑤𐑳𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑝𐑱𐑯𐑟—𐑮𐑶𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑓; 𐑞𐑴 𐑕𐑨𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑝𐑦𐑖𐑦𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛, 𐑲 𐑓𐑽, 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑣𐑰 𐑯𐑳𐑮𐑦𐑖𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑳𐑯𐑑𐑿𐑑𐑼𐑛 𐑿𐑔.

𐑩 ·𐑕𐑨𐑜 ·𐑣𐑸𐑚𐑼 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑝𐑦𐑟𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑭𐑞𐑼'𐑟 𐑚𐑱, 𐑯 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜 𐑕𐑷𐑑 𐑩 𐑐𐑨𐑕𐑦𐑡 𐑑 ·𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑗𐑩𐑯 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐, 𐑣𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑻 𐑓𐑫𐑤 𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑦𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑧𐑯, 𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑯𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑵𐑑; 𐑯 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 ·𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑭𐑞𐑼'𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑓𐑤𐑵𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑝𐑱𐑤. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜 𐑝𐑬𐑛 𐑩 𐑝𐑬. 𐑩𐑤𐑴𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑵, 𐑣𐑰 𐑐𐑨𐑛𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑪𐑓 𐑑 𐑩 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑑, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑣𐑰 𐑯𐑿 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑐𐑭𐑕 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑖𐑰 𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑞 𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛. 𐑪𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩 𐑒𐑪𐑮𐑩𐑤 𐑮𐑰𐑓; 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑩 𐑤𐑴 𐑑𐑳𐑙 𐑝 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛, 𐑒𐑳𐑝𐑼𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑥𐑨𐑙𐑜𐑮𐑴𐑝 𐑔𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑑𐑕 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑜𐑮𐑵 𐑬𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼. 𐑣𐑲𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑵, 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑩𐑓𐑤𐑴𐑑, 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑔𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑑𐑕, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑐𐑮𐑬 𐑕𐑰𐑢𐑼𐑛, 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑨𐑑 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑻𐑯, 𐑐𐑨𐑛𐑩𐑤 𐑤𐑴 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛; 𐑯 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑜𐑤𐑲𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑲, 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑓𐑤𐑨𐑖 𐑣𐑰 𐑛𐑸𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑬𐑑; 𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑛 𐑣𐑻 𐑕𐑲𐑛; 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑚𐑨𐑒𐑢𐑼𐑛 𐑛𐑨𐑖 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑫𐑑 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑕𐑲𐑟𐑛 𐑯 𐑕𐑨𐑙𐑒 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑵; 𐑒𐑤𐑲𐑥𐑛 𐑳𐑐 𐑞 𐑗𐑱𐑯𐑟; 𐑯 𐑔𐑮𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑨𐑑 𐑓𐑫𐑤 𐑤𐑧𐑙𐑔 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑒, 𐑜𐑮𐑨𐑐𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑩 𐑮𐑦𐑙-𐑚𐑴𐑤𐑑 𐑞𐑺, 𐑯 𐑕𐑢𐑹 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑑 𐑤𐑧𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑜𐑴, 𐑞𐑴 𐑣𐑨𐑒𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑐𐑰𐑕𐑩𐑟.

𐑦𐑯 𐑝𐑱𐑯 𐑞 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 𐑔𐑮𐑧𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑑 𐑔𐑮𐑴 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑴𐑝𐑼𐑚𐑹𐑛; 𐑕𐑩𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑩 𐑒𐑳𐑑𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑱𐑒𐑩𐑛 𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑕; ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑩 ·𐑒𐑦𐑙, 𐑯 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜 𐑚𐑳𐑡𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑. 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑒 𐑚𐑲 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑛𐑧𐑕𐑐𐑼𐑩𐑑 𐑛𐑷𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑩𐑕𐑯𐑩𐑕, 𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑲𐑤𐑛 𐑛𐑦𐑟𐑲𐑼 𐑑 𐑝𐑦𐑟𐑦𐑑 ·𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑥, 𐑞 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑤𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛, 𐑯 𐑑𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑣𐑰 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑥𐑱𐑒 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑴𐑥. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑓𐑲𐑯 𐑘𐑳𐑙 𐑕𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑡—𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑕𐑰 ·𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑯𐑕 𐑝 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟, 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑕𐑷 𐑞 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯'𐑟 𐑒𐑨𐑚𐑦𐑯. 𐑞𐑱 𐑐𐑫𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑼𐑟, 𐑯 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑩 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑥. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑤𐑲𐑒 ·𐑑𐑕𐑸 ·𐑐𐑰𐑑𐑼 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑑 𐑑𐑶𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑘𐑸𐑛𐑟 𐑝 𐑓𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑟, ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑛𐑱𐑯𐑛 𐑯𐑴 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑜𐑯𐑩𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑦, 𐑦𐑓 𐑞𐑺𐑚𐑲 𐑣𐑰 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑦𐑤𐑦 𐑜𐑱𐑯 𐑞 𐑐𐑬𐑼 𐑝 𐑦𐑯𐑤𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑳𐑯𐑑𐑿𐑑𐑼𐑛 𐑒𐑳𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑧𐑯. 𐑓 𐑨𐑑 𐑚𐑪𐑑𐑩𐑥—𐑕𐑴 𐑣𐑰 𐑑𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑥𐑰—𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑨𐑒𐑗𐑵𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑩 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑛𐑦𐑟𐑲𐑼 𐑑 𐑤𐑻𐑯 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑞 ·𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑗𐑩𐑯𐑟, 𐑞 𐑸𐑑𐑕 𐑢𐑺𐑚𐑲 𐑑 𐑥𐑱𐑒 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑰𐑐𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑽 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑞𐑱 𐑢𐑻; 𐑯 𐑥𐑹 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑, 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑚𐑧𐑑𐑼 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑞𐑱 𐑢𐑻. 𐑚𐑳𐑑, 𐑩𐑤𐑨𐑕! 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑨𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑝 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑕𐑵𐑯 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑝𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 ·𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑗𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑚𐑰 𐑚𐑴𐑔 𐑥𐑦𐑟𐑼𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑒𐑑; 𐑦𐑯𐑓𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑥𐑹 𐑕𐑴, 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑭𐑞𐑼'𐑟 𐑣𐑰𐑞𐑩𐑯𐑟. 𐑼𐑲𐑝𐑛 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑴𐑤𐑛 ·𐑕𐑨𐑜 ·𐑣𐑸𐑚𐑼; 𐑯 𐑕𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑼𐑟 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑞𐑺; 𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑜𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑪𐑯 𐑑 ·𐑯𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑑, 𐑯 𐑕𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑬 𐑞𐑱 𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑢𐑱𐑡𐑩𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕 𐑷𐑤𐑕𐑴, 𐑐𐑫𐑼 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜 𐑜𐑱𐑝 𐑦𐑑 𐑳𐑐 𐑓 𐑤𐑪𐑕𐑑. 𐑔𐑷𐑑 𐑣𐑰, 𐑦𐑑'𐑕 𐑩 𐑢𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑥𐑼𐑦𐑛𐑾𐑯𐑟; 𐑲'𐑤 𐑛𐑲 𐑩 𐑐𐑱𐑜𐑩𐑯.

𐑯 𐑞𐑳𐑕 𐑩𐑯 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑲𐑛𐑪𐑤𐑩𐑑𐑼 𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑸𐑑, 𐑣𐑰 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑤𐑦𐑝𐑛 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑞𐑰𐑟 ·𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑗𐑩𐑯𐑟, 𐑢𐑹 𐑞𐑺 𐑒𐑤𐑴𐑞𐑟, 𐑯 𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑛 𐑑 𐑑𐑷𐑒 𐑞𐑺 𐑡𐑦𐑚𐑼𐑦𐑖. 𐑣𐑧𐑯𐑕 𐑞 𐑒𐑢𐑽 𐑢𐑱𐑟 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑞𐑴 𐑯𐑬 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑣𐑴𐑥.

𐑚𐑲 𐑣𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑕, 𐑲 𐑭𐑕𐑒𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑢𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑣𐑰 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑐𐑴𐑟 𐑜𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑨𐑒, 𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑒𐑪𐑮𐑩𐑯𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯; 𐑕𐑦𐑯𐑕 𐑣𐑰 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑯𐑬 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑼 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑭𐑞𐑼 𐑛𐑧𐑛 𐑯 𐑜𐑪𐑯, 𐑣𐑰 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑯 𐑓𐑰𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑩𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑕. 𐑣𐑰 𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑼𐑛 𐑯𐑴, 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑘𐑧𐑑; 𐑯 𐑨𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑓𐑽𐑓𐑩𐑤 ·𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑦, 𐑹 𐑮𐑭𐑞𐑼 ·𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑗𐑩𐑯𐑟, 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑳𐑯𐑓𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑓 𐑩𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑐𐑘𐑫𐑼 𐑯 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑓𐑲𐑤𐑛 𐑔𐑮𐑴𐑯 𐑝 𐑔𐑻𐑑𐑦 𐑐𐑱𐑜𐑩𐑯 ·𐑒𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑣𐑦𐑥. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑯 𐑚𐑲, 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑧𐑛, 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑻𐑯,—𐑨𐑟 𐑕𐑵𐑯 𐑨𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑓𐑧𐑤𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑚𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑲𐑟𐑛 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯. 𐑓 𐑞 𐑯𐑪𐑯𐑕, 𐑣𐑬𐑧𐑝𐑼, 𐑣𐑰 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑐𐑴𐑟𐑛 𐑑 𐑕𐑱𐑤 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑, 𐑯 𐑕𐑴 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑲𐑤𐑛 𐑴𐑑𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑓𐑹 𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟. 𐑞𐑱 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑩 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑽 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑚𐑸𐑚𐑛 𐑲𐑼𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑤𐑵 𐑝 𐑩 𐑕𐑧𐑐𐑑𐑼 𐑯𐑬.

𐑲 𐑭𐑕𐑒𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑥𐑰𐑛𐑾𐑑 𐑐𐑻𐑐𐑩𐑕, 𐑑𐑳𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑿𐑗𐑼 𐑥𐑵𐑝𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕. 𐑣𐑰 𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑼𐑛, 𐑑 𐑜𐑴 𐑑 𐑕𐑰 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯, 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑝𐑴𐑒𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯. 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕, 𐑲 𐑑𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑥𐑲 𐑴𐑯 𐑛𐑦𐑟𐑲𐑯, 𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑓𐑹𐑥𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑝 𐑥𐑲 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑑 𐑕𐑱𐑤 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 ·𐑯𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑑, 𐑨𐑟 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑐𐑹𐑑 𐑓 𐑩𐑯 𐑩𐑛𐑝𐑧𐑯𐑗𐑼𐑩𐑕 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑑 𐑦𐑥𐑚𐑸𐑒 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥. 𐑣𐑰 𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑕 𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑪𐑤𐑝𐑛 𐑑 𐑩𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑦 𐑥𐑰 𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛, 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑩𐑚𐑹𐑛 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑝𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑤, 𐑜𐑧𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑢𐑪𐑗, 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑚𐑴𐑑, 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑥𐑧𐑕 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑥𐑰, 𐑦𐑯 𐑖𐑹𐑑 𐑑 𐑖𐑺 𐑥𐑲 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑣𐑨𐑐; 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑔 𐑥𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟, 𐑚𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑦𐑐 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑪𐑑𐑤𐑳𐑒 𐑝 𐑚𐑴𐑔 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛𐑟. 𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑲 𐑡𐑶𐑩𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑩𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛; 𐑓 𐑚𐑦𐑕𐑲𐑛𐑟 𐑞 𐑩𐑓𐑧𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑲 𐑯𐑬 𐑓𐑧𐑤𐑑 𐑓 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜, 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑽𐑾𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑽, 𐑯 𐑨𐑟 𐑕𐑳𐑗, 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑓𐑱𐑤 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑝 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑿𐑕𐑓𐑩𐑤𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯, 𐑣𐑵, 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑥𐑰, 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑜𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑦𐑟 𐑝 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙, 𐑞𐑴 𐑢𐑧𐑤 𐑩𐑒𐑢𐑱𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑕𐑰, 𐑨𐑟 𐑯𐑴𐑯 𐑑 𐑥𐑻𐑗𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑧𐑯.

𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑹𐑦 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑲𐑐'𐑕 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑛𐑲𐑦𐑙 𐑐𐑳𐑓, ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜 𐑦𐑥𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑕𐑑 𐑥𐑰, 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑛 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑥𐑲𐑯, 𐑯 𐑚𐑤𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑬𐑑 𐑞 𐑤𐑲𐑑, 𐑢𐑰 𐑮𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑰𐑗 𐑳𐑞𐑼, 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑱 𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑, 𐑯 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑕𐑵𐑯 𐑢𐑻 𐑕𐑤𐑰𐑐𐑦𐑙.

·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 13. 𐑢𐑰𐑤𐑚𐑨𐑮𐑴.

𐑯𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑 𐑥𐑹𐑯𐑦𐑙, 𐑥𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑱, 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑴𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑞 𐑦𐑥𐑚𐑭𐑥𐑛 𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑑 𐑩 𐑚𐑸𐑚𐑼, 𐑓 𐑩 𐑚𐑤𐑪𐑒, 𐑲 𐑕𐑧𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑥𐑲 𐑴𐑯 𐑯 𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑮𐑱𐑛'𐑟 𐑚𐑦𐑤; 𐑿𐑟𐑦𐑙, 𐑣𐑬𐑧𐑝𐑼, 𐑥𐑲 𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑮𐑱𐑛'𐑟 𐑥𐑳𐑯𐑦. 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑤𐑹𐑛, 𐑨𐑟 𐑢𐑧𐑤 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑚𐑹𐑛𐑼𐑟, 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑩𐑥𐑱𐑟𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑛𐑩𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑳𐑙 𐑳𐑐 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑢𐑰𐑯 𐑥𐑰 𐑯 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜—𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑨𐑟 ·𐑐𐑰𐑑𐑼 ·𐑒𐑪𐑓𐑦𐑯'𐑟 𐑒𐑪𐑒 𐑯 𐑚𐑫𐑤 𐑕𐑑𐑹𐑦𐑟 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑐𐑮𐑰𐑝𐑾𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑴 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑩𐑤𐑸𐑥𐑛 𐑥𐑰 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑐𐑻𐑕𐑩𐑯 𐑣𐑵𐑥 𐑲 𐑯𐑬 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞.

𐑢𐑰 𐑚𐑪𐑮𐑴𐑛 𐑩 𐑢𐑰𐑤𐑚𐑨𐑮𐑴, 𐑯 𐑦𐑥𐑚𐑸𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑬𐑼 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑟, 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑤𐑵𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑲 𐑴𐑯 𐑐𐑫𐑼 𐑒𐑸𐑐𐑩𐑑-𐑚𐑨𐑜, 𐑯 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜'𐑟 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑝𐑩𐑕 𐑕𐑨𐑒 𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑥𐑩𐑒, 𐑩𐑢𐑱 𐑢𐑰 𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑑 “𐑞 ·𐑥𐑪𐑕,” 𐑞 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 ·𐑯𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑑 𐑐𐑨𐑒𐑩𐑑 𐑕𐑒𐑵𐑯𐑼 𐑥𐑫𐑼𐑛 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑢𐑹𐑓. 𐑨𐑟 𐑢𐑰 𐑢𐑻 𐑜𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑞 𐑐𐑰𐑐𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑑𐑺𐑛; 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑨𐑑 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜 𐑕𐑴 𐑥𐑳𐑗—𐑓 𐑞𐑱 𐑢𐑻 𐑿𐑟𐑛 𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑰𐑑𐑕,—𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑯 𐑥𐑰 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑓𐑦𐑛𐑧𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑤 𐑑𐑻𐑥𐑟. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑰 𐑣𐑰𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑯𐑪𐑑, 𐑜𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑢𐑰𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑚𐑨𐑮𐑴 𐑚𐑲 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑟, 𐑯 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜 𐑯𐑬 𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑪𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑩𐑡𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑞 𐑖𐑰𐑔 𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯 𐑚𐑸𐑚𐑟. 𐑲 𐑭𐑕𐑒𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑢𐑲 𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑛 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩 𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑕𐑩𐑥 𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑩𐑖𐑹, 𐑯 𐑢𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑷𐑤 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑕 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑓𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑞𐑺 𐑴𐑯 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑟. 𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕, 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑚𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕, 𐑣𐑰 𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑤𐑲𐑛, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑴 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑲 𐑣𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑑𐑮𐑵 𐑦𐑯𐑳𐑓, 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑩 𐑐𐑼𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑼 𐑩𐑓𐑧𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑓 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑴𐑯 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯, 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑪𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑝 𐑩𐑖𐑫𐑼𐑛 𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑓, 𐑢𐑧𐑤 𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑩 𐑥𐑹𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑚𐑨𐑑, 𐑯 𐑛𐑰𐑐𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑥𐑩𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑣𐑸𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟. 𐑦𐑯 𐑖𐑹𐑑, 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑦𐑯𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑮𐑰𐑐𐑼𐑟 𐑯 𐑥𐑴𐑼𐑟, 𐑣𐑵 𐑜𐑴 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑓𐑸𐑥𐑼𐑟' 𐑥𐑧𐑛𐑴𐑟 𐑸𐑥𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞𐑺 𐑴𐑯 𐑕𐑲𐑞𐑟—𐑞𐑴 𐑦𐑯 𐑯𐑴 𐑢𐑲𐑟 𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑲𐑡𐑛 𐑑 𐑓𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑖 𐑞𐑧𐑥—𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑕𐑴, ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜, 𐑓 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑴𐑯 𐑐𐑮𐑲𐑝𐑩𐑑 𐑮𐑰𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑟, 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑓𐑻𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑴𐑯 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯.

𐑖𐑦𐑓𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑚𐑨𐑮𐑴 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑥𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟, 𐑣𐑰 𐑑𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑥𐑰 𐑩 𐑓𐑳𐑯𐑦 𐑕𐑑𐑹𐑦 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑞 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑢𐑰𐑤𐑚𐑨𐑮𐑴 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑕𐑰𐑯. 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑦𐑯 ·𐑕𐑨𐑜 ·𐑣𐑸𐑚𐑼. 𐑞 𐑴𐑯𐑼𐑟 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑖𐑦𐑐, 𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑟, 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑤𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑢𐑳𐑯, 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑑 𐑒𐑨𐑮𐑦 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑧𐑝𐑦 𐑗𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑹𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑬𐑕. 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑥 𐑦𐑜𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑞 𐑔𐑦𐑙—𐑞𐑴 𐑦𐑯 𐑑𐑮𐑵𐑔 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑲𐑼𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑴, 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑲𐑕 𐑢𐑱 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑑 𐑥𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑡 𐑞 𐑚𐑨𐑮𐑴—·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜 𐑐𐑫𐑑𐑕 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑗𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑦𐑑; 𐑤𐑨𐑖𐑩𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑓𐑭𐑕𐑑; 𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑖𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑼𐑟 𐑞 𐑚𐑨𐑮𐑴 𐑯 𐑥𐑸𐑗𐑩𐑟 𐑳𐑐 𐑞 𐑢𐑹𐑓. “𐑢𐑲,” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑲, “·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜, 𐑿 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑯𐑴𐑯 𐑚𐑧𐑑𐑼 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑, 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒. 𐑛𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑞 𐑐𐑰𐑐𐑩𐑤 𐑤𐑭𐑓?”

𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕, 𐑣𐑰 𐑑𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑥𐑰 𐑩𐑯𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑕𐑑𐑹𐑦. 𐑞 𐑐𐑰𐑐𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑝 ·𐑮𐑴𐑒𐑴𐑝𐑩𐑒𐑴, 𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑟, 𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑢𐑧𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑰𐑕𐑑𐑕 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑕 𐑞 𐑓𐑮𐑱𐑜𐑮𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼 𐑝 𐑘𐑳𐑙 𐑒𐑴𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑳𐑑𐑕 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑩 𐑤𐑸𐑡 𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑯𐑛 𐑒𐑨𐑤𐑩𐑚𐑨𐑖 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑐𐑳𐑯𐑗𐑚𐑴𐑤; 𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑐𐑳𐑯𐑗𐑚𐑴𐑤 𐑷𐑤𐑢𐑱𐑟 𐑓𐑹𐑥𐑟 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑩𐑤 𐑹𐑯𐑩𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑥𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑺 𐑞 𐑓𐑰𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑛. 𐑯𐑬 𐑩 𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑜𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑥𐑻𐑗𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑕 𐑑𐑳𐑗𐑑 𐑨𐑑 ·𐑮𐑴𐑒𐑴𐑝𐑩𐑒𐑴, 𐑯 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑭𐑯𐑛𐑼—𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑷𐑤 𐑩𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑕, 𐑩 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑳𐑙𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑤𐑾𐑕 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑥𐑩𐑯, 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑰𐑕𐑑 𐑓 𐑩 𐑕𐑰 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯—𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑭𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑑 𐑞 𐑢𐑧𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑰𐑕𐑑 𐑝 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜'𐑟 𐑕𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑼, 𐑩 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑘𐑳𐑙 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑧𐑕 𐑡𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑛 𐑝 𐑑𐑧𐑯. 𐑢𐑧𐑤; 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑢𐑧𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑜𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑕 𐑢𐑻 𐑩𐑕𐑧𐑥𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑚𐑮𐑲𐑛'𐑟 𐑚𐑨𐑥𐑚𐑵 𐑒𐑪𐑑𐑦𐑡, 𐑞𐑦𐑕 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑸𐑗𐑩𐑟 𐑦𐑯, 𐑯 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑕𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑞 𐑐𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑝 𐑪𐑯𐑼, 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑞 𐑐𐑳𐑯𐑗𐑚𐑴𐑤, 𐑯 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑢𐑰𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑣𐑲 ·𐑐𐑮𐑰𐑕𐑑 𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑨𐑡𐑩𐑕𐑑𐑦 𐑞 ·𐑒𐑦𐑙, ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜'𐑟 𐑓𐑭𐑞𐑼. 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑕 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑧𐑛,—𐑓 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑐𐑰𐑐𐑩𐑤 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑞𐑺 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑕 𐑨𐑟 𐑢𐑧𐑤 𐑨𐑟 𐑢𐑰—𐑞𐑴 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜 𐑑𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑥𐑰 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑳𐑯𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑳𐑕, 𐑣𐑵 𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑤𐑫𐑒 𐑛𐑬𐑯𐑢𐑼𐑛𐑟 𐑑 𐑬𐑼 𐑐𐑤𐑨𐑑𐑼𐑟, 𐑞𐑱, 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑺𐑦, 𐑒𐑪𐑐𐑦𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑛𐑳𐑒𐑕, 𐑜𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑕 𐑳𐑐𐑢𐑼𐑛𐑟 𐑑 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 ·𐑜𐑦𐑝𐑼 𐑝 𐑷𐑤 𐑓𐑰𐑕𐑑𐑕—·𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑕, 𐑲 𐑕𐑱, 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑧𐑛, 𐑞 ·𐑣𐑲 ·𐑐𐑮𐑰𐑕𐑑 𐑴𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑞 𐑚𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑢𐑩𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑦𐑥𐑩𐑥𐑹𐑾𐑤 𐑕𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑦 𐑝 𐑞 𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛; 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑟, 𐑛𐑦𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑮𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑯 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑮𐑱𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑼𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑤 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑞 𐑚𐑤𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑧𐑝𐑼𐑦𐑡 𐑕𐑻𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑱𐑑𐑕. 𐑕𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕𐑑 𐑯𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑮𐑰𐑕𐑑, 𐑯 𐑯𐑴𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑕𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑦, 𐑯 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓—𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 𐑝 𐑩 𐑖𐑦𐑐—𐑨𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑯 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑩 𐑥𐑽 𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛 ·𐑒𐑦𐑙, 𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑒𐑦𐑙'𐑟 𐑴𐑯 𐑣𐑬𐑕—𐑞 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 𐑒𐑵𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑮𐑴𐑕𐑰𐑛𐑟 𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑖 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑐𐑳𐑯𐑗𐑚𐑴𐑤;—𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑑 𐑲 𐑕𐑩𐑐𐑴𐑟 𐑓 𐑩 𐑣𐑿𐑡 𐑓𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑼-𐑜𐑤𐑭𐑕. “𐑯𐑬,” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜, “𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑿 𐑑𐑦𐑙𐑒 𐑯𐑬?—𐑛𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑬𐑼 𐑐𐑰𐑐𐑩𐑤 𐑤𐑭𐑓?”

𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑, 𐑐𐑨𐑕𐑦𐑡 𐑐𐑱𐑛, 𐑯 𐑤𐑳𐑜𐑦𐑡 𐑕𐑱𐑓, 𐑢𐑰 𐑕𐑑𐑫𐑛 𐑪𐑯 𐑚𐑹𐑛 𐑞 𐑕𐑒𐑵𐑯𐑼. 𐑣𐑶𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑱𐑤, 𐑦𐑑 𐑜𐑤𐑲𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑱𐑒𐑫𐑖𐑯𐑧𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑝𐑼. 𐑪𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑕𐑲𐑛, ·𐑯𐑿 ·𐑚𐑧𐑛𐑓𐑼𐑛 𐑮𐑴𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑑𐑧𐑮𐑩𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑝 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑰𐑑𐑕, 𐑞𐑺 𐑲𐑕-𐑒𐑳𐑝𐑼𐑛 𐑑𐑮𐑰𐑟 𐑷𐑤 𐑜𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑒𐑤𐑽, 𐑒𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑺. 𐑣𐑿𐑡 𐑣𐑦𐑤𐑟 𐑯 𐑥𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑒𐑭𐑕𐑒𐑕 𐑪𐑯 𐑒𐑭𐑕𐑒𐑕 𐑢𐑻 𐑐𐑲𐑤𐑛 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑻 𐑢𐑹𐑝𐑟, 𐑯 𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑞 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛-𐑢𐑪𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑕 𐑤𐑱 𐑕𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑯 𐑕𐑱𐑓𐑤𐑦 𐑥𐑫𐑼𐑛 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑; 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑳𐑞𐑼𐑟 𐑒𐑱𐑥 𐑩 𐑕𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑝 𐑒𐑸𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑟 𐑯 𐑒𐑵𐑐𐑼𐑟, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑚𐑤𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑯𐑶𐑟𐑩𐑟 𐑝 𐑓𐑲𐑼𐑟 𐑯 𐑓𐑹𐑡𐑩𐑟 𐑑 𐑥𐑧𐑤𐑑 𐑞 𐑐𐑦𐑗, 𐑷𐑤 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑴𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑯𐑿 𐑒𐑮𐑵𐑟𐑩𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑑; 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑐𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑯 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑝𐑶𐑦𐑡 𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛, 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑦𐑜𐑦𐑯𐑟 𐑩 𐑕𐑧𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑛; 𐑯 𐑩 𐑕𐑧𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛, 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑦𐑜𐑦𐑯𐑟 𐑩 𐑔𐑻𐑛, 𐑯 𐑕𐑴 𐑪𐑯, 𐑓 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑯 𐑓 𐑲. 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑦𐑟 𐑞 𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑤𐑩𐑕𐑯𐑩𐑕, 𐑘𐑱, 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑪𐑤𐑼𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑷𐑤 𐑻𐑔𐑤𐑦 𐑧𐑓𐑼𐑑.

𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑥𐑹 𐑴𐑐𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼, 𐑞 𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑮𐑰𐑟 𐑢𐑨𐑒𐑕𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑖; 𐑞 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 ·𐑥𐑪𐑕 𐑑𐑪𐑕𐑑 𐑞 𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑒 𐑓𐑴𐑥 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑣𐑻 𐑚𐑬𐑟, 𐑨𐑟 𐑩 𐑘𐑳𐑙 𐑒𐑴𐑤𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑯𐑹𐑑𐑦𐑙𐑟. 𐑣𐑬 𐑲 𐑕𐑯𐑳𐑓𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 ·𐑑𐑸𐑑𐑼 𐑺!—𐑣𐑬 𐑲 𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑯𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑐𐑲𐑒 𐑻𐑔!—𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑣𐑲𐑢𐑱 𐑷𐑤 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑛𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑥𐑸𐑒𐑕 𐑝 𐑕𐑤𐑱𐑝𐑦𐑖 𐑣𐑰𐑤𐑟 𐑯 𐑣𐑵𐑓𐑕; 𐑯 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑛 𐑥𐑰 𐑑 𐑩𐑛𐑥𐑲𐑼 𐑞 𐑥𐑨𐑜𐑯𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑰 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑐𐑼𐑥𐑦𐑑 𐑯𐑴 𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑹𐑛𐑟.

𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑓𐑴𐑥-𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑯, ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑑 𐑛𐑮𐑦𐑙𐑒 𐑯 𐑮𐑰𐑤 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑥𐑰. 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑛𐑳𐑕𐑒𐑦 𐑯𐑪𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑕𐑢𐑧𐑤𐑛 𐑩𐑐𐑸𐑑; 𐑣𐑰 𐑖𐑴𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑲𐑤𐑛 𐑯 𐑐𐑶𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑑𐑰𐑔. 𐑪𐑯, 𐑪𐑯 𐑢𐑰 𐑓𐑤𐑵; 𐑯 𐑬𐑼 𐑪𐑓𐑦𐑙 𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑛, 𐑞 ·𐑥𐑪𐑕 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑣𐑪𐑥𐑦𐑡 𐑑 𐑞 𐑚𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑; 𐑛𐑳𐑒𐑑 𐑯 𐑛𐑲𐑝𐑛 𐑣𐑻 𐑚𐑬𐑟 𐑨𐑟 𐑩 𐑕𐑤𐑱𐑝 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑳𐑤𐑑𐑩𐑯. 𐑕𐑲𐑛𐑢𐑱𐑟 𐑤𐑰𐑯𐑦𐑙, 𐑢𐑰 𐑕𐑲𐑛𐑢𐑱𐑟 𐑛𐑸𐑑𐑩𐑛; 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑮𐑴𐑐𐑽𐑯 𐑑𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑢𐑲𐑼; 𐑞 𐑑𐑵 𐑑𐑷𐑤 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑕 𐑚𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑤𐑲𐑒 ·𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑾𐑯 𐑒𐑱𐑯𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑑𐑹𐑯𐑱𐑛𐑴𐑟. 𐑕𐑴 𐑓𐑫𐑤 𐑝 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑮𐑰𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑰𐑯 𐑢𐑻 𐑢𐑰, 𐑨𐑟 𐑢𐑰 𐑕𐑑𐑫𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑐𐑤𐑳𐑯𐑡𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑴𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑑, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑓 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑢𐑰 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑯𐑴𐑑𐑦𐑕 𐑞 𐑡𐑽𐑦𐑙 𐑜𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑐𐑨𐑕𐑦𐑯𐑡𐑼𐑟, 𐑩 𐑤𐑳𐑚𐑼-𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩𐑕𐑧𐑥𐑚𐑤𐑦, 𐑣𐑵 𐑥𐑸𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑑𐑵 𐑓𐑧𐑤𐑴 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑚𐑰 𐑕𐑴 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑨𐑯𐑘𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤; 𐑨𐑟 𐑞𐑴 𐑩 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑢𐑻 𐑧𐑯𐑦𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑹 𐑛𐑦𐑜𐑯𐑦𐑓𐑲𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑩 𐑢𐑲𐑑𐑢𐑪𐑖𐑑 𐑯𐑰𐑜𐑮𐑴. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑢𐑻 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑚𐑵𐑚𐑦𐑟 𐑯 𐑚𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑒𐑦𐑯𐑟 𐑞𐑺, 𐑣𐑵, 𐑚𐑲 𐑞𐑺 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑕 𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑯𐑯𐑩𐑕, 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑣𐑸𐑑 𐑯 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑼 𐑝 𐑷𐑤 𐑝𐑻𐑡𐑼. ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜 𐑒𐑷𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑘𐑳𐑙 𐑕𐑨𐑐𐑤𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑥𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑚𐑦𐑣𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑨𐑒. 𐑲 𐑔𐑷𐑑 𐑞 𐑚𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑒𐑦𐑯'𐑟 𐑬𐑼 𐑝 𐑛𐑵𐑥 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑒𐑳𐑥. 𐑛𐑮𐑪𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯, 𐑞 𐑚𐑮𐑷𐑯𐑦 𐑕𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑡 𐑒𐑷𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑸𐑥𐑟, 𐑯 𐑚𐑲 𐑩𐑯 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑥𐑦𐑮𐑨𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑛𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑧𐑙𐑔, 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑣𐑲 𐑳𐑐 𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑺; 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑕𐑤𐑲𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑑𐑨𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑻𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑦𐑛-𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑼𐑕𐑧𐑑, 𐑞 𐑓𐑧𐑤𐑴 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑚𐑻𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑤𐑳𐑙𐑟 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑰𐑑, 𐑢𐑲𐑤 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜, 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑨𐑒 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑤𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑑𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑣𐑷𐑒 𐑐𐑲𐑐 𐑯 𐑐𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑑 𐑥𐑰 𐑓 𐑩 𐑐𐑳𐑓.

“𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑙! 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑙!” 𐑘𐑧𐑤𐑛 𐑞 𐑚𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑒𐑦𐑯, 𐑮𐑳𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑑𐑩𐑢𐑹𐑛𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑪𐑓𐑦𐑕𐑼; “𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑙, ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑙, 𐑣𐑽'𐑟 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑤.”

“𐑣𐑩𐑤𐑴, 𐑿 𐑕𐑻,” 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 𐑞 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯, 𐑩 𐑜𐑷𐑯𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑚 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑰, 𐑕𐑑𐑷𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑳𐑐 𐑑 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜, “𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑔𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑛𐑵 𐑿 𐑥𐑰𐑯 𐑚𐑲 𐑞𐑨𐑑? 𐑛𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑿 𐑯𐑴 𐑿 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑒𐑦𐑤𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑗𐑨𐑐?”

“𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑕𐑱?” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜, 𐑨𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑥𐑲𐑤𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑛 𐑑 𐑥𐑰.

“𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑱,” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑲, “𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑿 𐑒𐑱𐑥 𐑯𐑽 𐑒𐑦𐑤-𐑰 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑞𐑺,” 𐑐𐑶𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑖𐑦𐑝𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑯𐑣𐑹𐑯.

“𐑒𐑦𐑤-𐑰,” 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜, 𐑑𐑢𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑑𐑩𐑑𐑵𐑛 𐑓𐑱𐑕 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑩𐑯 𐑳𐑯𐑻𐑔𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑛𐑱𐑯, “𐑭! 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑚𐑧𐑝𐑦 𐑕𐑥𐑷𐑤-𐑰 𐑓𐑦𐑖-𐑰; ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜 𐑯𐑴 𐑒𐑦𐑤-𐑰 𐑕𐑴 𐑕𐑥𐑷𐑤-𐑰 𐑓𐑦𐑖-𐑰; ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜 𐑒𐑦𐑤-𐑰 𐑚𐑦𐑜 𐑢𐑱𐑤!”

“𐑤𐑫𐑒 𐑿,” 𐑮𐑹𐑛 𐑞 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯, “𐑲'𐑤 𐑒𐑦𐑤-𐑰 𐑿, 𐑿 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑚𐑩𐑤, 𐑦𐑓 𐑿 𐑑𐑮𐑲 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑥𐑹 𐑝 𐑘𐑹 𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑕 𐑩𐑚𐑹𐑛 𐑣𐑽; 𐑕𐑴 𐑥𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑘𐑹 𐑲.”

𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑴 𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑡𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑣𐑲 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑓 𐑞 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 𐑑 𐑥𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑴𐑯 𐑲. 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑛𐑦𐑡𐑩𐑕 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑥𐑱𐑯-𐑕𐑱𐑤 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑐𐑸𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑞 𐑢𐑧𐑞𐑼-𐑖𐑰𐑑, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑕 𐑚𐑵𐑥 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑬 𐑓𐑤𐑲𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑑 𐑕𐑲𐑛, 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑰𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑢𐑰𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑲𐑼 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑐𐑸𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑒. 𐑞 𐑐𐑫𐑼 𐑓𐑧𐑤𐑴 𐑣𐑵𐑥 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑕𐑴 𐑮𐑳𐑓𐑤𐑦, 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑢𐑧𐑐𐑑 𐑴𐑝𐑼𐑚𐑹𐑛; 𐑷𐑤 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑐𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑒; 𐑯 𐑑 𐑩𐑑𐑧𐑥𐑐𐑑 𐑕𐑯𐑨𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑚𐑵𐑥 𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑱 𐑦𐑑, 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑥𐑨𐑛𐑯𐑩𐑕. 𐑦𐑑 𐑓𐑤𐑵 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑮𐑲𐑑 𐑑 𐑤𐑧𐑓𐑑, 𐑯 𐑚𐑨𐑒 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯, 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑩 𐑢𐑪𐑗, 𐑯 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑐𐑶𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑕𐑯𐑨𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑕𐑐𐑤𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑟. 𐑯𐑳𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑛𐑳𐑯, 𐑯 𐑯𐑳𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑒𐑱𐑐𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑛𐑳𐑯; 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑪𐑯 𐑛𐑧𐑒 𐑮𐑳𐑖𐑑 𐑑𐑩𐑢𐑹𐑛𐑟 𐑞 𐑚𐑬𐑟, 𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑫𐑛 𐑲𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑚𐑵𐑥 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑓 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑻 𐑞 𐑤𐑴𐑼 𐑡𐑷 𐑝 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑜𐑟𐑨𐑕𐑐𐑼𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑱𐑤. 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑥𐑦𐑛𐑕𐑑 𐑝 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑯𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯, ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜 𐑛𐑮𐑪𐑐𐑑 𐑛𐑧𐑓𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑰𐑟, 𐑯 𐑒𐑮𐑷𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑞 𐑐𐑭𐑔 𐑝 𐑞 𐑚𐑵𐑥, 𐑢𐑦𐑐𐑑 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑝 𐑩 𐑮𐑴𐑐, 𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑛 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑑 𐑞 𐑚𐑫𐑤𐑢𐑼𐑒𐑕, 𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑓𐑤𐑦𐑙𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑤𐑨𐑕𐑵, 𐑒𐑷𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑞 𐑚𐑵𐑥 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑢𐑧𐑐𐑑 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑧𐑛, 𐑯 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑯𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑 𐑡𐑻𐑒, 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑸 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑱 𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑐𐑑, 𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑱𐑓. 𐑞 𐑕𐑒𐑵𐑯𐑼 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑮𐑳𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛, 𐑯 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑞 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑒𐑤𐑽𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑢𐑱 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑻𐑯 𐑚𐑴𐑑, ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜, 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑑 𐑑 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑕𐑑, 𐑛𐑸𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑤𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑸𐑒 𐑝 𐑩 𐑤𐑰𐑐. 𐑓 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑹 𐑥𐑹 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑰𐑯 𐑕𐑢𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑛𐑪𐑜, 𐑔𐑮𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑸𐑥𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑬𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑯 𐑚𐑲 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑟 𐑮𐑦𐑝𐑰𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑮𐑷𐑯𐑦 𐑖𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑼𐑟 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑞 𐑓𐑮𐑰𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑴𐑥. 𐑲 𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑯 𐑜𐑤𐑹𐑾𐑕 𐑓𐑧𐑤𐑴, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑕𐑷 𐑯𐑴 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑕𐑱𐑝𐑛. 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑯𐑣𐑹𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑜𐑪𐑯 𐑛𐑬𐑯. 𐑖𐑵𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑐𐑻𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑼𐑤𐑦 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼, ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜, 𐑯𐑬 𐑑𐑫𐑒 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑'𐑕 𐑜𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑕 𐑼𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑯 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑕𐑰 𐑡𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑬 𐑥𐑨𐑑𐑼𐑟 𐑢𐑻, 𐑛𐑲𐑝𐑛 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑯 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑩𐑐𐑽𐑛. 𐑩 𐑓𐑿 𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑥𐑹, 𐑯 𐑣𐑰 𐑮𐑴𐑟 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯, 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑸𐑥 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑬𐑑, 𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑛𐑮𐑨𐑜𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑤𐑲𐑓𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑓𐑹𐑥. 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑 𐑕𐑵𐑯 𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑑 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑳𐑐. 𐑞 𐑐𐑫𐑼 𐑚𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑒𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑹𐑛. 𐑷𐑤 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑝𐑴𐑑𐑩𐑛 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜 𐑩 𐑯𐑴𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑥𐑐; 𐑞 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 𐑚𐑧𐑜𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑸𐑛𐑩𐑯. 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑬𐑼 𐑲 𐑒𐑤𐑴𐑝 𐑑 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑚𐑸𐑯𐑩𐑒𐑩𐑤; 𐑘𐑱, 𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑐𐑫𐑼 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜 𐑑𐑫𐑒 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑛𐑲𐑝.

𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞𐑺 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑳𐑯𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑕𐑯𐑩𐑕? 𐑣𐑰 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑥 𐑑 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑨𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑛𐑦𐑟𐑻𐑝𐑛 𐑩 𐑥𐑧𐑛𐑩𐑤 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 ·𐑣𐑿𐑥𐑱𐑯 𐑯 ·𐑥𐑨𐑜𐑯𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑥𐑩𐑕 ·𐑕𐑩𐑕𐑲𐑩𐑑𐑦𐑟. 𐑣𐑰 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑭𐑕𐑒𐑑 𐑓 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼—𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑖 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼—𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑢𐑲𐑐 𐑞 𐑚𐑮𐑲𐑯 𐑪𐑓; 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑛𐑳𐑯, 𐑣𐑰 𐑐𐑫𐑑 𐑪𐑯 𐑛𐑮𐑲 𐑒𐑤𐑴𐑞𐑟, 𐑤𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑲𐑐, 𐑯 𐑤𐑰𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑞 𐑚𐑫𐑤𐑢𐑼𐑒𐑕, 𐑯 𐑥𐑲𐑤𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑲𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑼𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑕𐑱𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓—“𐑦𐑑'𐑕 𐑩 𐑥𐑿𐑗𐑵𐑩𐑤, 𐑡𐑶𐑯𐑑-𐑕𐑑𐑪𐑒 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛, 𐑦𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑥𐑼𐑦𐑛𐑾𐑯𐑟. 𐑢𐑰 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑐 𐑞𐑰𐑟 ·𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑗𐑩𐑯𐑟.”

·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 14. ·𐑯𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑑.

𐑯𐑳𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑹 𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑐𐑨𐑕𐑦𐑡 𐑢𐑻𐑞𐑦 𐑞 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑙; 𐑕𐑴, 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑩 𐑓𐑲𐑯 𐑮𐑳𐑯, 𐑢𐑰 𐑕𐑱𐑓𐑤𐑦 𐑼𐑲𐑝𐑛 𐑦𐑯 ·𐑯𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑑.

·𐑯𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑑! 𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑬𐑑 𐑘𐑹 𐑥𐑨𐑐 𐑯 𐑤𐑫𐑒 𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑑. 𐑕𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑩 𐑮𐑾𐑤 𐑒𐑹𐑯𐑼 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛 𐑦𐑑 𐑪𐑒𐑿𐑐𐑲𐑟; 𐑣𐑬 𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑞𐑺, 𐑩𐑢𐑱 𐑪𐑓 𐑖𐑹, 𐑥𐑹 𐑤𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑧𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑴𐑯 𐑤𐑲𐑑𐑣𐑬𐑕. 𐑤𐑫𐑒 𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑑—𐑩 𐑥𐑽 𐑣𐑦𐑤𐑩𐑒, 𐑯 𐑧𐑤𐑚𐑴 𐑝 𐑕𐑨𐑯𐑛; 𐑷𐑤 𐑚𐑰𐑗, 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑 𐑩 𐑚𐑨𐑒𐑜𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛. 𐑞𐑺 𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑹 𐑕𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑞𐑺 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑿 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑿𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑑𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑦 𐑘𐑽𐑟 𐑨𐑟 𐑩 𐑕𐑳𐑚𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑑𐑿𐑑 𐑓 𐑚𐑤𐑪𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑐𐑱𐑐𐑼. 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑜𐑱𐑥𐑕𐑩𐑥 𐑢𐑲𐑑𐑕 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑑𐑧𐑤 𐑿 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑱 𐑣𐑨𐑓 𐑑 𐑐𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑑 𐑢𐑰𐑛𐑟 𐑞𐑺, 𐑞𐑱 𐑛𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑜𐑮𐑴 𐑯𐑨𐑗𐑼𐑩𐑤𐑦; 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑱 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑹𐑑 ·𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑩𐑛𐑩 𐑔𐑦𐑕𐑩𐑤𐑟; 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑱 𐑣𐑨𐑓 𐑑 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑚𐑦𐑘𐑪𐑯𐑛 𐑕𐑰𐑟 𐑓 𐑩 𐑕𐑐𐑲𐑤 𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑪𐑐 𐑩 𐑤𐑰𐑒 𐑦𐑯 𐑩𐑯 𐑶𐑤 𐑒𐑭𐑕𐑒; 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑐𐑰𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑝 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑦𐑯 ·𐑯𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑑 𐑸 𐑒𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑛 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑑𐑮𐑵 𐑒𐑮𐑪𐑕 𐑦𐑯 ·𐑮𐑴𐑥; 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑐𐑰𐑐𐑩𐑤 𐑞𐑺 𐑐𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑑 𐑑𐑴𐑛𐑕𐑑𐑵𐑤𐑟 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑞𐑺 𐑣𐑬𐑟𐑩𐑟, 𐑑 𐑜𐑧𐑑 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑞 𐑖𐑱𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑼 𐑑𐑲𐑥; 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑚𐑤𐑱𐑛 𐑝 𐑜𐑮𐑭𐑕 𐑥𐑱𐑒𐑕 𐑩𐑯 𐑴𐑱𐑕𐑦𐑕, 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑚𐑤𐑱𐑛𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑛𐑱'𐑟 𐑢𐑷𐑒 𐑩 𐑐𐑮𐑺𐑦; 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑱 𐑢𐑺 𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑖𐑵𐑟, 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑤𐑲𐑒 ·𐑤𐑨𐑐𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑕𐑯𐑴-𐑖𐑵𐑟; 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑱 𐑸 𐑕𐑴 𐑖𐑳𐑑 𐑳𐑐, 𐑚𐑧𐑤𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑, 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑢𐑱 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑤𐑴𐑟𐑛, 𐑕𐑼𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛, 𐑯 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑩𐑯 𐑳𐑑𐑼 𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑝 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑗𐑺𐑟 𐑯 𐑑𐑱𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑕𐑥𐑷𐑤 𐑒𐑤𐑨𐑥𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑚𐑰 𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑨𐑛𐑣𐑽𐑦𐑙, 𐑨𐑟 𐑑 𐑞 𐑚𐑨𐑒𐑕 𐑝 𐑕𐑰 𐑑𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑟. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑝𐑩𐑜𐑨𐑯𐑟𐑩𐑟 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑖𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑 ·𐑯𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑴 ·𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑯𐑶.

𐑤𐑫𐑒 𐑯𐑬 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑕 𐑑𐑮𐑩𐑛𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑑𐑹𐑦 𐑝 𐑣𐑬 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑧𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑮𐑧𐑛-𐑥𐑧𐑯. 𐑞𐑳𐑕 𐑜𐑴𐑟 𐑞 𐑤𐑧𐑡𐑩𐑯𐑛. 𐑦𐑯 𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑩𐑯 𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑩𐑯 𐑰𐑜𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑢𐑵𐑐𐑑 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑯𐑿 ·𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑒𐑴𐑕𐑑, 𐑯 𐑒𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑛 𐑪𐑓 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑓𐑩𐑯𐑑 ·𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑾𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑑𐑨𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑟. 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑤𐑬𐑛 𐑤𐑨𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑞 𐑐𐑺𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑕𐑷 𐑞𐑺 𐑗𐑲𐑤𐑛 𐑚𐑹𐑯 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑕𐑲𐑑 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑞 𐑢𐑲𐑛 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼𐑟. 𐑞𐑱 𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑪𐑤𐑝𐑛 𐑑 𐑓𐑪𐑤𐑴 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑛𐑦𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯. 𐑕𐑧𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑬𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑵𐑟, 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑩 𐑐𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑐𐑨𐑕𐑦𐑡 𐑞𐑱 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑳𐑝𐑼𐑛 𐑞 𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛, 𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑞𐑱 𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑩𐑯 𐑧𐑥𐑐𐑑𐑦 𐑲𐑝𐑼𐑦 𐑒𐑭𐑕𐑒𐑩𐑑,—𐑞 𐑐𐑫𐑼 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 ·𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑾𐑯'𐑟 𐑕𐑒𐑧𐑤𐑩𐑑𐑩𐑯.

𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼, 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑰𐑟 ·𐑯𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑑𐑼𐑟, 𐑚𐑹𐑯 𐑪𐑯 𐑩 𐑚𐑰𐑗, 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑰 𐑓 𐑩 𐑤𐑲𐑝𐑤𐑦𐑣𐑫𐑛! 𐑞𐑱 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑒𐑷𐑑 𐑒𐑮𐑨𐑚𐑟 𐑯 𐑒𐑢𐑴𐑙𐑪𐑜𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑨𐑯𐑛; 𐑜𐑮𐑴𐑯 𐑚𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑼, 𐑞𐑱 𐑢𐑱𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑬𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑯𐑧𐑑𐑕 𐑓 𐑥𐑨𐑒𐑼𐑩𐑤; 𐑥𐑹 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑽𐑾𐑯𐑕𐑑, 𐑞𐑱 𐑐𐑫𐑖𐑑 𐑪𐑓 𐑦𐑯 𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕 𐑯 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑗𐑼𐑛 𐑒𐑪𐑛; 𐑯 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑, 𐑤𐑷𐑯𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑯𐑱𐑝𐑦 𐑝 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑕 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑰, 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑤𐑹𐑛 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼𐑦 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛; 𐑐𐑫𐑑 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑚𐑧𐑤𐑑 𐑝 𐑕𐑻𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑯𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑜𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑑; 𐑐𐑰𐑐𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑨𐑑 ·𐑚𐑺𐑦𐑙'𐑟 ·𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑑𐑕; 𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑕𐑰𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑺𐑛 𐑧𐑝𐑼𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑹 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑥𐑲𐑑𐑾𐑕𐑑 𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑥𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑥𐑨𐑕 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑕𐑼𐑝𐑲𐑝𐑛 𐑞 𐑓𐑤𐑳𐑛; 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑥𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑩𐑕 𐑯 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑥𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑕! 𐑞𐑨𐑑 ·𐑙𐑦𐑥𐑩𐑤𐑱𐑩𐑯, 𐑕𐑷𐑤𐑑-𐑕𐑰 ·𐑥𐑨𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛𐑪𐑯, 𐑒𐑤𐑴𐑞𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑐𐑹𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑕𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑳𐑯𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑕 𐑐𐑬𐑼, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑐𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑒𐑕 𐑸 𐑥𐑹 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑛𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑓𐑽𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑯 𐑥𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑕 𐑩𐑕𐑷𐑤𐑑𐑕!

𐑯 𐑞𐑳𐑕 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑯𐑱𐑒𐑩𐑛 ·𐑯𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑑𐑼𐑟, 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑕𐑰 𐑣𐑻𐑥𐑦𐑑𐑕, 𐑦𐑖𐑿𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞𐑺 𐑨𐑯𐑑-𐑣𐑦𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑰, 𐑴𐑝𐑼𐑮𐑳𐑯 𐑯 𐑒𐑪𐑙𐑒𐑼𐑛 𐑞 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼𐑦 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑕𐑴 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 ·𐑨𐑤𐑦𐑜𐑟𐑭𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑟; 𐑐𐑸𐑕𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑬𐑑 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑞 ·𐑩𐑑𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑒, ·𐑐𐑩𐑕𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑒, 𐑯 ·𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑾𐑯 𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟, 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑐𐑲𐑮𐑩𐑑 𐑐𐑬𐑼𐑟 𐑛𐑦𐑛 ·𐑐𐑴𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛. 𐑤𐑧𐑑 ·𐑩𐑥𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑩 𐑨𐑛 ·𐑥𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑴 𐑑 ·𐑑𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑩𐑕, 𐑯 𐑐𐑲𐑤 ·𐑒𐑿𐑚𐑩 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 ·𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑩𐑛𐑩; 𐑤𐑧𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑤𐑦𐑖 𐑴𐑝𐑼𐑕𐑢𐑹𐑥 𐑷𐑤 ·𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑾, 𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑙 𐑬𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑚𐑤𐑱𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑨𐑯𐑼 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑯; 𐑑𐑵 𐑔𐑻𐑛𐑟 𐑝 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑑𐑧𐑮𐑩𐑒𐑢𐑾𐑕 𐑜𐑤𐑴𐑚 𐑸 𐑞 ·𐑯𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑑𐑼'𐑟. 𐑓 𐑞 𐑕𐑰 𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑟; 𐑣𐑰 𐑴𐑯𐑟 𐑦𐑑, 𐑨𐑟 ·𐑧𐑥𐑐𐑼𐑼𐑟 𐑴𐑯 𐑧𐑥𐑐𐑲𐑼𐑟; 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑩 𐑮𐑲𐑑 𐑝 𐑢𐑱 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑦𐑑. 𐑥𐑻𐑗𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑕 𐑸 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑚𐑮𐑦𐑡𐑩𐑟; 𐑸𐑥𐑛 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑟 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑓𐑤𐑴𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑹𐑑𐑕; 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑐𐑲𐑮𐑩𐑑𐑕 𐑯 𐑐𐑮𐑲𐑝𐑩𐑑𐑽𐑟, 𐑞𐑴 𐑓𐑪𐑤𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑕𐑰 𐑨𐑟 𐑣𐑲𐑢𐑱𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑞 𐑮𐑴𐑛, 𐑞𐑱 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑐𐑤𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑕, 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑓𐑮𐑨𐑜𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑞𐑧𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑝𐑟, 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑛𐑮𐑷 𐑞𐑺 𐑤𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑚𐑪𐑑𐑩𐑥𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑛𐑰𐑐 𐑦𐑑𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓. 𐑞 ·𐑯𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑑𐑼, 𐑣𐑰 𐑩𐑤𐑴𐑯 𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑲𐑛𐑟 𐑯 𐑮𐑲𐑩𐑑𐑕 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑰; 𐑣𐑰 𐑩𐑤𐑴𐑯, 𐑦𐑯 ·𐑚𐑲𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑤𐑨𐑙𐑜𐑢𐑦𐑡, 𐑜𐑴𐑟 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑕; 𐑑 𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑴 𐑐𐑤𐑬𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑴𐑯 𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑤 𐑐𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑑𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯. 𐑞𐑺 𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑴𐑥; 𐑞𐑺 𐑤𐑲𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑦𐑟𐑯𐑩𐑕, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑩 ·𐑯𐑴𐑩'𐑟 𐑓𐑤𐑳𐑛 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑳𐑐𐑑, 𐑞𐑴 𐑦𐑑 𐑴𐑝𐑼𐑢𐑧𐑤𐑥𐑛 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑥𐑦𐑤𐑾𐑯𐑟 𐑦𐑯 ·𐑗𐑲𐑯𐑩. 𐑣𐑰 𐑤𐑦𐑝𐑟 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑰, 𐑨𐑟 𐑐𐑮𐑺𐑦 𐑒𐑪𐑒𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑺𐑦; 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑲𐑛𐑟 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑝𐑟, 𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑤𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑨𐑟 𐑖𐑨𐑥𐑢𐑭 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑟 𐑒𐑤𐑲𐑥 𐑞 ·𐑨𐑤𐑐𐑕. 𐑓 𐑘𐑽𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑯𐑴𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑞 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛; 𐑕𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑟 𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑, 𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑥𐑧𐑤𐑟 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩𐑯𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛, 𐑥𐑹 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑤𐑦 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑞 𐑥𐑵𐑯 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑑 𐑩𐑯 ·𐑻𐑔𐑕𐑥𐑩𐑯. 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑜𐑳𐑤, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑯𐑕𐑧𐑑 𐑓𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑟 𐑣𐑻 𐑢𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑯 𐑦𐑟 𐑮𐑪𐑒𐑑 𐑑 𐑕𐑤𐑰𐑐 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑢𐑰𐑯 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑴𐑟; 𐑕𐑴 𐑨𐑑 𐑯𐑲𐑑𐑓𐑷𐑤, 𐑞 ·𐑯𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑑𐑼, 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑕𐑲𐑑 𐑝 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛, 𐑓𐑻𐑤𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑟, 𐑯 𐑤𐑱𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑑, 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑐𐑦𐑤𐑴 𐑮𐑳𐑖 𐑣𐑻𐑛𐑟 𐑝 𐑢𐑷𐑤𐑮𐑩𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑯 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟.

·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 15. 𐑗𐑬𐑛𐑼.

𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑒𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑤𐑱𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑰𐑝𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑞 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 ·𐑥𐑪𐑕 𐑒𐑱𐑥 𐑕𐑯𐑳𐑜𐑤𐑦 𐑑 𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑼, 𐑯 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜 𐑯 𐑲 𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑩𐑖𐑹; 𐑕𐑴 𐑢𐑰 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑩𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑑 𐑯𐑴 𐑚𐑦𐑟𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑛𐑱, 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑰𐑕𐑑 𐑯𐑳𐑯 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑩 𐑕𐑳𐑐𐑼 𐑯 𐑩 𐑚𐑧𐑛. 𐑞 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑤𐑹𐑛 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑐𐑬𐑑𐑼-·𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑳𐑕 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑳𐑟𐑩𐑯 ·𐑣𐑴𐑟𐑱𐑩 ·𐑣𐑳𐑕𐑦 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑑𐑮𐑲 ·𐑐𐑪𐑑𐑕, 𐑣𐑵𐑥 𐑣𐑰 𐑩𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑐𐑮𐑲𐑩𐑑𐑼 𐑝 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑚𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑒𐑧𐑐𐑑 𐑣𐑴𐑑𐑧𐑤𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑷𐑤 ·𐑯𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑑, 𐑯 𐑥𐑹𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑩𐑖𐑫𐑼𐑛 𐑳𐑕 𐑞𐑨𐑑 ·𐑒𐑳𐑟𐑩𐑯 ·𐑣𐑴𐑟𐑱𐑩, 𐑨𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑓𐑱𐑥𐑩𐑕 𐑓 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑗𐑬𐑛𐑼𐑟. 𐑦𐑯 𐑖𐑹𐑑, 𐑣𐑰 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑣𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑰 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑐𐑪𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑵 𐑚𐑧𐑑𐑼 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑑𐑮𐑲 𐑐𐑪𐑑-𐑤𐑳𐑒 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑑𐑮𐑲 ·𐑐𐑪𐑑𐑕. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞 𐑛𐑦𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑜𐑦𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑳𐑕 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑒𐑰𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑘𐑧𐑤𐑴 𐑢𐑺𐑣𐑬𐑕 𐑪𐑯 𐑬𐑼 𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑼𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑢𐑰 𐑴𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑩 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑗𐑻𐑗 𐑑 𐑞 𐑤𐑸𐑚𐑼𐑛, 𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑒𐑰𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑤𐑸𐑚𐑼𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑢𐑰 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑩 𐑒𐑹𐑯𐑼 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑐𐑶𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑼𐑛, 𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑛𐑳𐑯, 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑭𐑕𐑒 𐑞 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑢𐑰 𐑥𐑧𐑑 𐑢𐑺 𐑞 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕 𐑢𐑪𐑟: 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑒𐑮𐑫𐑒𐑩𐑛 𐑛𐑦𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑐𐑳𐑟𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑳𐑕 𐑨𐑑 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑, 𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑨𐑟, 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑬𐑑𐑕𐑧𐑑, ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑘𐑧𐑤𐑴 𐑢𐑺𐑣𐑬𐑕—𐑬𐑼 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑐𐑶𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑛𐑦𐑐𐑸𐑗𐑼—𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑤𐑧𐑓𐑑 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑤𐑸𐑚𐑼𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛, 𐑢𐑺𐑨𐑟 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑕𐑑𐑫𐑛 ·𐑐𐑰𐑑𐑼 ·𐑒𐑪𐑓𐑦𐑯 𐑑 𐑕𐑱 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑼𐑛. 𐑣𐑬𐑧𐑝𐑼, 𐑚𐑲 𐑛𐑦𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑩 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑛𐑸𐑒, 𐑯 𐑯𐑬 𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑯𐑪𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑳𐑐 𐑩 𐑐𐑰𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑯𐑣𐑨𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑢𐑲𐑼 𐑞 𐑢𐑱, 𐑢𐑰 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑒𐑱𐑥 𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑞𐑺 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑴 𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑦𐑙.

𐑑𐑵 𐑦𐑯𐑹𐑥𐑩𐑕 𐑢𐑫𐑛𐑩𐑯 𐑐𐑪𐑑𐑕 𐑐𐑱𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑒, 𐑯 𐑕𐑩𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑨𐑕𐑩𐑟' 𐑽𐑟, 𐑕𐑢𐑳𐑙 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑪𐑕-𐑑𐑮𐑰𐑟 𐑝 𐑩𐑯 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑑𐑪𐑐-𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑, 𐑐𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑳𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑩𐑯 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑛𐑹𐑢𐑱. 𐑞 𐑣𐑹𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑪𐑕-𐑑𐑮𐑰𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑕𐑷𐑛 𐑪𐑓 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑕𐑲𐑛, 𐑕𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑑𐑪𐑐-𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑩 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑜𐑨𐑤𐑴𐑟. 𐑐𐑼𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑕 𐑲 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑝 𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑑𐑲𐑥, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑲 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑐 𐑕𐑑𐑺𐑦𐑙 𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑜𐑨𐑤𐑴𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑝𐑱𐑜 𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑜𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑙. 𐑩 𐑕𐑹𐑑 𐑝 𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑒 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑲 𐑯𐑧𐑒 𐑨𐑟 𐑲 𐑜𐑱𐑟𐑛 𐑳𐑐 𐑑 𐑞 𐑑𐑵 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑱𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑹𐑯𐑟; 𐑘𐑧𐑕, 𐑑𐑵 𐑝 𐑞𐑧𐑥, 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑓 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜, 𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑓 𐑥𐑰. 𐑦𐑑'𐑕 𐑪𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑕, 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑕 𐑲. 𐑩 ·𐑒𐑪𐑓𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑲 ·𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑰𐑐𐑼 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑲 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑐𐑹𐑑; 𐑑𐑵𐑥𐑕𐑑𐑴𐑯𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑺𐑦𐑙 𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑰 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑥𐑧𐑯'𐑟 𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑩𐑤; 𐑯 𐑣𐑽 𐑩 𐑜𐑨𐑤𐑴𐑟! 𐑯 𐑩 𐑐𐑺 𐑝 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑛𐑦𐑡𐑩𐑕 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑒 𐑐𐑪𐑑𐑕 𐑑𐑵! 𐑸 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑔𐑮𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑬𐑑 𐑴𐑚𐑤𐑰𐑒 𐑣𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑑𐑳𐑗𐑦𐑙 ·𐑑𐑪𐑐𐑣𐑧𐑑?

𐑲 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑮𐑦𐑓𐑤𐑧𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑕𐑲𐑑 𐑝 𐑩 𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑢𐑫𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑘𐑧𐑤𐑴 𐑣𐑺 𐑯 𐑩 𐑘𐑧𐑤𐑴 𐑜𐑬𐑯, 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑐𐑹𐑗 𐑝 𐑞 𐑦𐑯, 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑩 𐑛𐑳𐑤 𐑮𐑧𐑛 𐑤𐑨𐑥𐑐 𐑕𐑢𐑦𐑙𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑺, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑑 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑡𐑼𐑛 𐑲, 𐑯 𐑒𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑦𐑙 𐑪𐑯 𐑩 𐑚𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑒 𐑕𐑒𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑐𐑻𐑐𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑫𐑤𐑩𐑯 𐑖𐑻𐑑.

“𐑜𐑧𐑑 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑘𐑰,” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑖𐑰 𐑑 𐑞 𐑥𐑨𐑯, “𐑹 𐑲'𐑤 𐑚𐑰 𐑒𐑴𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑘𐑰!”

“𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑪𐑯, ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜,” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑲, “𐑷𐑤 𐑮𐑲𐑑. 𐑞𐑺'𐑟 ·𐑥𐑕𐑟 ·𐑣𐑳𐑕𐑦.”

𐑯 𐑕𐑴 𐑦𐑑 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑛 𐑬𐑑; ·𐑥𐑼 ·𐑣𐑴𐑟𐑱𐑩 ·𐑣𐑳𐑕𐑦 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑣𐑴𐑥, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑤𐑰𐑝𐑦𐑙 ·𐑥𐑕𐑟 ·𐑣𐑳𐑕𐑦 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑲𐑼𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑐𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑑 𐑩𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑩𐑓𐑺𐑟. 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑥𐑱𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑯𐑴𐑯 𐑬𐑼 𐑛𐑦𐑟𐑲𐑼𐑟 𐑓 𐑩 𐑕𐑳𐑐𐑼 𐑯 𐑩 𐑚𐑧𐑛, ·𐑥𐑕𐑟 ·𐑣𐑳𐑕𐑦, 𐑐𐑴𐑕𐑑𐑐𐑴𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑻𐑞𐑼 𐑕𐑒𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑓 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑑, 𐑳𐑖𐑼𐑛 𐑳𐑕 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑩 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑮𐑵𐑥, 𐑯 𐑕𐑰𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑳𐑕 𐑨𐑑 𐑩 𐑑𐑱𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑮𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑒𐑕 𐑝 𐑩 𐑮𐑰𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑒𐑤𐑵𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑭𐑕𐑑, 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑛 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑑 𐑳𐑕 𐑯 𐑕𐑧𐑛—“𐑒𐑤𐑨𐑥 𐑹 ·𐑒𐑪𐑛?”

“𐑢𐑪𐑑'𐑕 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 ·𐑒𐑪𐑛𐑟, 𐑥𐑨𐑥?” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑲, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑐𐑩𐑤𐑲𐑑𐑯𐑩𐑕.

“𐑒𐑤𐑨𐑥 𐑹 ·𐑒𐑪𐑛?” 𐑖𐑰 𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑰𐑑𐑩𐑛.

“𐑩 𐑒𐑤𐑨𐑥 𐑓 𐑕𐑳𐑐𐑼? 𐑩 𐑒𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑒𐑤𐑨𐑥; 𐑦𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑿 𐑥𐑰𐑯, ·𐑥𐑕𐑟 ·𐑣𐑳𐑕𐑦?” 𐑕𐑧𐑟 𐑲, “𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑'𐑕 𐑩 𐑮𐑭𐑞𐑼 𐑒𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑯 𐑒𐑤𐑨𐑥𐑦 𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑧𐑐𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼 𐑑𐑲𐑥, 𐑱𐑯𐑑 𐑦𐑑, ·𐑥𐑕𐑟 ·𐑣𐑳𐑕𐑦?”

𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑣𐑳𐑮𐑦 𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑿𐑥 𐑕𐑒𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑐𐑻𐑐𐑩𐑤 ·𐑖𐑻𐑑, 𐑣𐑵 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑢𐑱𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑓 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑦, 𐑯 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑣𐑽 𐑯𐑳𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞 𐑢𐑻𐑛 “𐑒𐑤𐑨𐑥,” ·𐑥𐑕𐑟 ·𐑣𐑳𐑕𐑦 𐑣𐑳𐑮𐑦𐑛 𐑑𐑩𐑢𐑹𐑛𐑟 𐑩𐑯 𐑴𐑐𐑩𐑯 𐑛𐑹 𐑤𐑰𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑞 𐑒𐑦𐑗𐑦𐑯, 𐑯 𐑚𐑷𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑬𐑑 “𐑒𐑤𐑨𐑥 𐑓 𐑑𐑵,” 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑩𐑐𐑽𐑛.

“·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜,” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑲, “𐑛𐑵 𐑿 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑰 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑥𐑱𐑒 𐑬𐑑 𐑩 𐑕𐑳𐑐𐑼 𐑓 𐑳𐑕 𐑚𐑴𐑔 𐑪𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑒𐑤𐑨𐑥?”

𐑣𐑬𐑧𐑝𐑼, 𐑩 𐑢𐑹𐑥 𐑕𐑱𐑝𐑼𐑦 𐑕𐑑𐑰𐑥 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑒𐑦𐑗𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑻𐑝𐑛 𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑲 𐑞 𐑩𐑐𐑨𐑮𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑗𐑽𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑳𐑕. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑥𐑴𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑗𐑬𐑛𐑼 𐑒𐑱𐑥 𐑦𐑯, 𐑞 𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑦 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑲𐑑𐑓𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑯𐑛. 𐑴, 𐑕𐑢𐑰𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑟! 𐑣𐑸𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑑 𐑥𐑰. 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑝 𐑕𐑥𐑷𐑤 𐑡𐑵𐑕𐑦 𐑒𐑤𐑨𐑥𐑟, 𐑕𐑒𐑺𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑦𐑜𐑼 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑣𐑱𐑟𐑩𐑤 𐑯𐑳𐑑𐑕, 𐑥𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑐𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑚𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑦𐑑, 𐑯 𐑕𐑷𐑤𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑐𐑹𐑒 𐑒𐑳𐑑 𐑳𐑐 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑓𐑤𐑱𐑒𐑕; 𐑞 𐑣𐑴𐑤 𐑦𐑯𐑮𐑦𐑗𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑚𐑳𐑑𐑼, 𐑯 𐑐𐑤𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑓𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑰𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑐𐑧𐑐𐑼 𐑯 𐑕𐑷𐑤𐑑. 𐑬𐑼 𐑨𐑐𐑩𐑑𐑲𐑑𐑕 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑖𐑸𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑕𐑑𐑦 𐑝𐑶𐑦𐑡, 𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑐𐑼𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑼, ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜 𐑕𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑱𐑝𐑼𐑦𐑑 𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑵𐑛 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑗𐑬𐑛𐑼 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑼𐑐𐑭𐑕𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑩𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑑, 𐑢𐑰 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑨𐑗𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑦𐑛𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯: 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑤𐑰𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑨𐑒 𐑩 𐑥𐑴𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑯 𐑚𐑦𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑰 𐑝 ·𐑥𐑕𐑟 ·𐑣𐑳𐑕𐑦'𐑟 𐑒𐑤𐑨𐑥 𐑯 𐑒𐑪𐑛 𐑩𐑯𐑬𐑯𐑕𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑, 𐑲 𐑔𐑷𐑑 𐑲 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑑𐑮𐑲 𐑩 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑. 𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑞 𐑒𐑦𐑗𐑦𐑯 𐑛𐑹, 𐑲 𐑳𐑑𐑼𐑛 𐑞 𐑢𐑻𐑛 “𐑒𐑪𐑛” 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑧𐑥𐑓𐑩𐑕𐑦𐑕, 𐑯 𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑿𐑥𐑛 𐑥𐑲 𐑕𐑰𐑑. 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑓𐑿 𐑥𐑴𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑝𐑼𐑦 𐑕𐑑𐑰𐑥 𐑒𐑱𐑥 𐑓𐑹𐑔 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑛𐑦𐑓𐑼𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑓𐑤𐑱𐑝𐑼, 𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑩 𐑓𐑲𐑯 𐑒𐑪𐑛-𐑗𐑬𐑛𐑼 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑳𐑕.

𐑢𐑰 𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑿𐑥𐑛 𐑚𐑦𐑟𐑯𐑩𐑕; 𐑯 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑐𐑤𐑲𐑦𐑙 𐑬𐑼 𐑕𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑤, 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑕 𐑲 𐑑 𐑥𐑲𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓, 𐑲 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑯𐑬 𐑦𐑓 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑣𐑽 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑦𐑓𐑧𐑒𐑑 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑣𐑧𐑛? 𐑢𐑪𐑑'𐑕 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑤𐑑𐑦𐑓𐑲𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑱𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑗𐑬𐑛𐑼-𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑐𐑰𐑐𐑩𐑤? “𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑤𐑫𐑒, ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜, 𐑱𐑯𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑩 𐑤𐑲𐑝 𐑰𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑘𐑹 𐑚𐑴𐑤? 𐑢𐑺'𐑟 𐑘𐑹 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯?”

𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑾𐑕𐑑 𐑝 𐑷𐑤 𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑦 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞 ·𐑑𐑮𐑲 ·𐑐𐑪𐑑𐑕, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑢𐑧𐑤 𐑛𐑦𐑟𐑻𐑝𐑛 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑯𐑱𐑥; 𐑓 𐑞 𐑐𐑪𐑑𐑕 𐑞𐑺 𐑢𐑻 𐑷𐑤𐑢𐑱𐑟 𐑚𐑶𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑗𐑬𐑛𐑼𐑟. 𐑗𐑬𐑛𐑼 𐑓 𐑚𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑓𐑩𐑕𐑑, 𐑯 𐑗𐑬𐑛𐑼 𐑓 𐑛𐑦𐑯𐑼, 𐑯 𐑗𐑬𐑛𐑼 𐑓 𐑕𐑳𐑐𐑼, 𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑿 𐑚𐑦𐑜𐑨𐑯 𐑑 𐑤𐑫𐑒 𐑓 𐑓𐑦𐑖-𐑚𐑴𐑯𐑟 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑘𐑹 𐑒𐑤𐑴𐑞𐑟. 𐑞 𐑺𐑾 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑞 𐑣𐑬𐑕 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑐𐑱𐑝𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑒𐑤𐑨𐑥-𐑖𐑧𐑤𐑟. ·𐑥𐑕𐑟 ·𐑣𐑳𐑕𐑦 𐑢𐑹 𐑩 𐑐𐑪𐑤𐑦𐑖𐑑 𐑯𐑧𐑒𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑒𐑪𐑛𐑓𐑦𐑖 𐑝𐑻𐑑𐑦𐑚𐑮𐑩; 𐑯 ·𐑣𐑴𐑟𐑱𐑩 ·𐑣𐑳𐑕𐑦 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑩𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑 𐑚𐑫𐑒𐑕 𐑚𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑵𐑐𐑽𐑽 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑖𐑸𐑒-𐑕𐑒𐑦𐑯. 𐑞𐑺 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩 𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑦 𐑓𐑤𐑱𐑝𐑼 𐑑 𐑞 𐑥𐑦𐑤𐑒, 𐑑𐑵, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑲 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑩𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑 𐑓, 𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑥𐑹𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑩 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑴𐑤 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑞 𐑚𐑰𐑗 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑼𐑥𐑧𐑯'𐑟 𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕, 𐑲 𐑕𐑷 ·𐑣𐑴𐑟𐑱𐑩'𐑟 𐑚𐑮𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑒𐑬 𐑓𐑰𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑪𐑯 𐑓𐑦𐑖 𐑮𐑧𐑥𐑯𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕, 𐑯 𐑥𐑸𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑞 𐑕𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑰𐑗 𐑓𐑫𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑒𐑪𐑛'𐑟 𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑦𐑑𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑣𐑧𐑛, 𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑕𐑤𐑦𐑐-𐑖𐑪𐑛, 𐑲 𐑩𐑖𐑫𐑼 𐑘𐑰.

𐑕𐑳𐑐𐑼 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑒𐑤𐑵𐑛𐑩𐑛, 𐑢𐑰 𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑰𐑝𐑛 𐑩 𐑤𐑨𐑥𐑐, 𐑯 𐑛𐑦𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 ·𐑥𐑕𐑟 ·𐑣𐑳𐑕𐑦 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑯𐑽𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑢𐑱 𐑑 𐑚𐑧𐑛; 𐑚𐑳𐑑, 𐑨𐑟 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑰𐑛 𐑥𐑰 𐑳𐑐 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑺𐑟, 𐑞 𐑤𐑱𐑛𐑦 𐑮𐑰𐑗𐑑 𐑓𐑹𐑔 𐑣𐑻 𐑸𐑥, 𐑯 𐑛𐑦𐑥𐑭𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯; 𐑖𐑰 𐑩𐑤𐑬𐑛 𐑯𐑴 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑻 𐑗𐑱𐑥𐑚𐑼𐑟. “𐑢𐑲 𐑯𐑪𐑑?” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑲; “𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑑𐑮𐑵 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑕𐑤𐑰𐑐𐑕 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯—𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑲 𐑯𐑪𐑑?” “𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑪𐑟 𐑦𐑑'𐑕 𐑛𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑼𐑩𐑕,” 𐑕𐑧𐑟 𐑖𐑰. “𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑕𐑦𐑯𐑕 𐑘𐑳𐑙 ·𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑜𐑟 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑳𐑯𐑓𐑹𐑑'𐑯𐑑 v'y'ge 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑜𐑪𐑯 𐑓𐑹 𐑘𐑽𐑟 𐑯 𐑩 𐑣𐑭𐑓, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑚𐑨𐑮𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑝 𐑰𐑤, 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑛𐑧𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑲 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑓𐑤𐑹 𐑚𐑨𐑒, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑲𐑛; 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑕𐑦𐑯𐑕 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑲 𐑩𐑤𐑬 𐑯𐑴 𐑚𐑹𐑛𐑼𐑟 𐑑 𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑑𐑦𐑗 𐑛𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑼𐑩𐑕 𐑢𐑰𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑮𐑵𐑥𐑟 𐑨𐑑 𐑯𐑲𐑑. 𐑕𐑴, ·𐑥𐑼 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜” (𐑓 𐑖𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑤𐑻𐑯𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑱𐑥), “𐑲 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑡𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑣𐑽 𐑲𐑼𐑯, 𐑯 𐑒𐑰𐑐 𐑦𐑑 𐑓 𐑿 𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑥𐑹𐑯𐑦𐑙. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞 𐑗𐑬𐑛𐑼; 𐑒𐑤𐑨𐑥 𐑹 𐑒𐑪𐑛 𐑑-𐑥𐑪𐑮𐑴 𐑓 𐑚𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑓𐑩𐑕𐑑, 𐑥𐑧𐑯?”

“𐑚𐑴𐑔,” 𐑕𐑧𐑟 𐑲; “𐑯 𐑤𐑧𐑑'𐑕 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑩 𐑒𐑳𐑐𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑕𐑥𐑴𐑒𐑑 𐑣𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑲 𐑢𐑱 𐑝 𐑝𐑼𐑲𐑩𐑑𐑦.”

·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 16. 𐑞 ·𐑖𐑦𐑐.

𐑦𐑯 𐑚𐑧𐑛 𐑢𐑰 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑒𐑪𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑬𐑼 𐑐𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑟 𐑓 𐑞 𐑥𐑪𐑮𐑴. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑑 𐑥𐑲 𐑕𐑼𐑐𐑮𐑲𐑟 𐑯 𐑯𐑴 𐑕𐑥𐑷𐑤 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑻𐑯, ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜 𐑯𐑬 𐑜𐑱𐑝 𐑥𐑰 𐑑 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑡𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑳𐑤𐑑𐑦𐑙 ·𐑘𐑴𐑡𐑴—𐑞 𐑯𐑱𐑥 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑒 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑜𐑪𐑛—𐑯 ·𐑘𐑴𐑡𐑴 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑑𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑑𐑵 𐑹 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑴𐑝𐑼, 𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑪𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑦𐑑 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦𐑢𐑱, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑛 𐑝 𐑬𐑼 𐑜𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑑𐑩𐑜𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙-𐑓𐑤𐑰𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑸𐑚𐑼, 𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑼𐑑 𐑕𐑦𐑤𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑬𐑼 𐑒𐑮𐑭𐑓𐑑; 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑛 𐑝 𐑞𐑦𐑕, 𐑲 𐑕𐑱, ·𐑘𐑴𐑡𐑴 𐑻𐑯𐑩𐑕𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑯𐑡𐑶𐑯𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑦𐑤𐑧𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑦 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑥𐑰, 𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑟𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑨𐑟 ·𐑘𐑴𐑡𐑴 𐑐𐑻𐑐𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑳𐑕; 𐑯, 𐑦𐑯 𐑹𐑛𐑼 𐑑 𐑛𐑵 𐑕𐑴, 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑷𐑤𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑦 𐑐𐑦𐑗𐑑 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑩 𐑝𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑤, 𐑢𐑦𐑗, 𐑦𐑓 𐑤𐑧𐑓𐑑 𐑑 𐑥𐑲𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓, 𐑲, ·𐑦𐑖𐑥𐑱𐑩𐑤, 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑓𐑨𐑤𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑤𐑲𐑑 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯, 𐑓 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛 𐑨𐑟 𐑞𐑴 𐑦𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑛 𐑬𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑗𐑭𐑯𐑕; 𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑝𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑤 𐑲 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑥𐑰𐑛𐑾𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑥𐑲𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓, 𐑓 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑦𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑝 𐑝 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜.

𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑓𐑼𐑜𐑪𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑑 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑, 𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑟, ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕𐑑 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑓𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑩𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑝 ·𐑘𐑴𐑡𐑴'𐑟 𐑡𐑳𐑡𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑯 𐑕𐑼𐑐𐑮𐑲𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑹𐑒𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑝 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑟; 𐑯 𐑗𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑖𐑑 ·𐑘𐑴𐑡𐑴 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑼𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑰𐑥, 𐑨𐑟 𐑩 𐑮𐑭𐑞𐑼 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑕𐑹𐑑 𐑝 𐑜𐑪𐑛, 𐑣𐑵 𐑐𐑼𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑕 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑢𐑧𐑤 𐑦𐑯𐑳𐑓 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑣𐑴𐑤, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑒𐑱𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑩𐑒𐑕𐑰𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑦𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑟𐑲𐑯𐑟.

𐑯𐑬, 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑐𐑤𐑨𐑯 𐑝 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜'𐑟, 𐑹 𐑮𐑭𐑞𐑼 ·𐑘𐑴𐑡𐑴'𐑟, 𐑑𐑳𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑕𐑦𐑤𐑧𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑬𐑼 𐑒𐑮𐑭𐑓𐑑; 𐑲 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑐𐑤𐑨𐑯 𐑨𐑑 𐑷𐑤. 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑩 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑮𐑦𐑤𐑲𐑛 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜'𐑟 𐑕𐑩𐑜𐑨𐑕𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑑 𐑐𐑶𐑯𐑑 𐑬𐑑 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑼 𐑚𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑓𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑑 𐑒𐑨𐑮𐑦 𐑳𐑕 𐑯 𐑬𐑼 𐑓𐑹𐑗𐑵𐑯𐑟 𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑤𐑦. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑷𐑤 𐑥𐑲 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑛𐑿𐑕𐑑 𐑯𐑴 𐑦𐑓𐑧𐑒𐑑 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜, 𐑲 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑲𐑡𐑛 𐑑 𐑨𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑧𐑕; 𐑯 𐑩𐑒𐑹𐑛𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑺𐑛 𐑑 𐑕𐑧𐑑 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑚𐑦𐑟𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑛𐑦𐑑𐑻𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑛 𐑮𐑳𐑖𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑹𐑑 𐑝 𐑧𐑯𐑼𐑡𐑦 𐑯 𐑝𐑦𐑜𐑼, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑧𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑓𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑩𐑓𐑺. 𐑯𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑 𐑥𐑹𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑻𐑤𐑦, 𐑤𐑰𐑝𐑦𐑙 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜 𐑖𐑳𐑑 𐑳𐑐 𐑢𐑦𐑞 ·𐑘𐑴𐑡𐑴 𐑦𐑯 𐑬𐑼 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑚𐑧𐑛𐑮𐑵𐑥—𐑓 𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑕𐑹𐑑 𐑝 ·𐑤𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑹 ·𐑮𐑭𐑥𐑩𐑛𐑭𐑯, 𐑹 𐑛𐑱 𐑝 𐑓𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙, 𐑣𐑿𐑥𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯, 𐑯 𐑐𐑮𐑱𐑼 𐑢𐑦𐑞 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜 𐑯 ·𐑘𐑴𐑡𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑛𐑱; 𐑣𐑬 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑲 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑓𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑬𐑑, 𐑓, 𐑞𐑴 𐑲 𐑩𐑐𐑤𐑲𐑛 𐑥𐑲𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑧𐑝𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟, 𐑲 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑼 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑼𐑡𐑦𐑟 𐑯 XXXIX ·𐑸𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑟—𐑤𐑰𐑝𐑦𐑙 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜, 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑓𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑑𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑣𐑷𐑒 𐑐𐑲𐑐, 𐑯 ·𐑘𐑴𐑡𐑴 𐑢𐑹𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑨𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑤 𐑓𐑲𐑼 𐑝 𐑖𐑱𐑝𐑦𐑙𐑟, 𐑲 𐑕𐑨𐑤𐑦𐑛 𐑬𐑑 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑦𐑙. 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑐𐑮𐑴𐑤𐑪𐑙𐑛 𐑕𐑷𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑯 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑥 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑢𐑲𐑼𐑦𐑟, 𐑲 𐑤𐑻𐑯𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑢𐑻 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑕 𐑳𐑐 𐑓 𐑔𐑮𐑰-𐑘𐑽𐑟' 𐑝𐑶𐑦𐑡𐑩𐑟—𐑞 ·𐑛𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑤-𐑛𐑨𐑥, 𐑞 ·𐑑𐑦𐑑-𐑚𐑦𐑑, 𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛. 𐑛𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑤-·𐑛𐑨𐑥, 𐑲 𐑛𐑵 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑯𐑴 𐑞 𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑡𐑦𐑯 𐑝; ·𐑑𐑦𐑑-𐑚𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑪𐑚𐑝𐑾𐑕; ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛, 𐑿 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑯𐑴 𐑛𐑬𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑧𐑥𐑚𐑼, 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞 𐑯𐑱𐑥 𐑝 𐑩 𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑩𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑚 𐑝 ·𐑥𐑨𐑕𐑩𐑗𐑵𐑕𐑩𐑑𐑕 ·𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑾𐑯𐑟; 𐑯𐑬 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑱𐑯𐑗𐑩𐑯𐑑 ·𐑥𐑰𐑛𐑟. 𐑲 𐑐𐑽𐑛 𐑯 𐑐𐑮𐑲𐑛 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑛𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑤-𐑛𐑨𐑥; 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑣𐑻, 𐑣𐑪𐑐𐑑 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑑𐑦𐑑-𐑚𐑦𐑑; 𐑯 𐑓𐑲𐑯𐑩𐑤𐑦, 𐑜𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑪𐑯 𐑚𐑹𐑛 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛, 𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑑 𐑼𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑣𐑻 𐑓 𐑩 𐑥𐑴𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑, 𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑲𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑓 𐑳𐑕.

𐑿 𐑥𐑱 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑕𐑰𐑯 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑩 𐑒𐑢𐑱𐑯𐑑 𐑒𐑮𐑭𐑓𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑘𐑹 𐑛𐑱, 𐑓 𐑷𐑑 𐑲 𐑯𐑴;—𐑕𐑒𐑢𐑺-𐑑𐑴𐑛 𐑤𐑳𐑜𐑼𐑟; 𐑥𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑕 ·𐑡𐑨𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑰𐑟 𐑡𐑳𐑙𐑒𐑕; 𐑚𐑳𐑑𐑼-𐑚𐑪𐑒𐑕 𐑜𐑨𐑤𐑦𐑪𐑑𐑕, 𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑑; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑥𐑲 𐑢𐑻𐑛 𐑓 𐑦𐑑, 𐑿 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑕𐑷 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩 𐑮𐑺 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑒𐑮𐑭𐑓𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑮𐑺 𐑴𐑤𐑛 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛. 𐑖𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑝 𐑞 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑕𐑒𐑵𐑤, 𐑮𐑭𐑞𐑼 𐑕𐑥𐑷𐑤 𐑦𐑓 𐑧𐑯𐑦𐑔𐑦𐑙; 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩𐑯 𐑴𐑤𐑛-𐑓𐑨𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑒𐑤𐑷-𐑓𐑫𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑤𐑫𐑒 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑣𐑻. 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑕𐑰𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑯 𐑢𐑧𐑞𐑼-𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑑𐑲𐑓𐑵𐑯𐑟 𐑯 𐑒𐑭𐑥𐑟 𐑝 𐑷𐑤 𐑓𐑹 𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟, 𐑣𐑻 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑣𐑳𐑤'𐑟 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑧𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑛𐑸𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 ·𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑯𐑗 𐑜𐑮𐑧𐑯𐑩𐑛𐑽'𐑟, 𐑣𐑵 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑩𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑓𐑷𐑑 𐑦𐑯 ·𐑰𐑡𐑦𐑐𐑑 𐑯 ·𐑕𐑲𐑚𐑽𐑾. 𐑣𐑻 𐑝𐑧𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑚𐑬𐑟 𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑑 𐑚𐑽𐑛𐑩𐑛. 𐑣𐑻 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑕—𐑒𐑳𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑢𐑺 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑒𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑝 ·𐑡𐑩𐑐𐑨𐑯, 𐑢𐑺 𐑣𐑻 𐑼𐑦𐑡𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑤𐑪𐑕𐑑 𐑴𐑝𐑼𐑚𐑹𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑜𐑱𐑤—𐑣𐑻 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑕 𐑕𐑑𐑫𐑛 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑓𐑤𐑦 𐑳𐑐 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑲𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑒𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑝 ·𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑴𐑯. 𐑣𐑻 𐑱𐑯𐑗𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑛𐑧𐑒𐑕 𐑢𐑻 𐑢𐑹𐑯 𐑯 𐑮𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑛, 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑞 𐑐𐑦𐑤𐑜𐑮𐑦𐑥-𐑢𐑻𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑑 𐑓𐑤𐑨𐑜-𐑕𐑑𐑴𐑯 𐑦𐑯 ·𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑚𐑼𐑦 ·𐑒𐑩𐑔𐑰𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑺 ·𐑚𐑧𐑒𐑩𐑑 𐑚𐑤𐑧𐑛. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑣𐑻 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑟, 𐑢𐑻 𐑨𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑯𐑿 𐑯 𐑥𐑸𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑓𐑰𐑗𐑼𐑟, 𐑐𐑼𐑑𐑱𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑞 𐑢𐑲𐑤𐑛 𐑚𐑦𐑟𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑓 𐑥𐑹 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑣𐑭𐑓 𐑩 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑗𐑼𐑦 𐑖𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑓𐑪𐑤𐑴𐑛. 𐑴𐑤𐑛 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 ·𐑐𐑰𐑤𐑧𐑜, 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑘𐑽𐑟 𐑣𐑻 𐑗𐑰𐑓-𐑥𐑱𐑑, 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑭𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑩𐑯𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑝𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑴𐑯, 𐑯 𐑯𐑬 𐑩 𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑲𐑼𐑛 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑩𐑯, 𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑐𐑩𐑤 𐑴𐑯𐑼𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛,—𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑴𐑤𐑛 ·𐑐𐑰𐑤𐑧𐑜, 𐑛𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑑𐑻𐑥 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑗𐑰𐑓-𐑥𐑱𐑑𐑖𐑦𐑐, 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑑 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑻 𐑼𐑦𐑡𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑜𐑮𐑴𐑑𐑧𐑕𐑒𐑯𐑩𐑕, 𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑤𐑱𐑛 𐑦𐑑, 𐑷𐑤 𐑴𐑝𐑼, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑒𐑢𐑱𐑯𐑑𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑚𐑴𐑔 𐑝 𐑥𐑩𐑑𐑽𐑾𐑤 𐑯 𐑛𐑦𐑝𐑲𐑕, 𐑳𐑯𐑥𐑨𐑗𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑧𐑯𐑦𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑧𐑐𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑚𐑰 ·𐑔𐑹𐑒𐑦𐑤-·𐑣𐑱𐑒'𐑕 𐑒𐑸𐑝𐑛 𐑚𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑼 𐑹 𐑚𐑧𐑛𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑛. 𐑖𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩𐑐𐑨𐑮𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑚𐑸𐑚𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑒 ·𐑰𐑔𐑦𐑴𐑐𐑾𐑯 𐑧𐑥𐑐𐑼𐑼, 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑧𐑒 𐑣𐑧𐑝𐑦 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑐𐑪𐑤𐑦𐑖𐑑 𐑲𐑝𐑼𐑦. 𐑖𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩 𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑑𐑮𐑴𐑓𐑦𐑟. 𐑩 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑩 𐑒𐑮𐑭𐑓𐑑, 𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑻𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑓𐑹𐑔 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑗𐑱𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑴𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑣𐑻 𐑧𐑯𐑩𐑥𐑦𐑟. 𐑷𐑤 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛, 𐑣𐑻 𐑳𐑯𐑐𐑨𐑯𐑩𐑤𐑛, 𐑴𐑐𐑩𐑯 𐑚𐑫𐑤𐑢𐑼𐑒𐑕 𐑢𐑻 𐑜𐑸𐑯𐑦𐑖𐑑 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑿𐑩𐑕 𐑡𐑷, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑖𐑸𐑐 𐑑𐑰𐑔 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑞𐑺 𐑓 𐑐𐑦𐑯𐑟, 𐑑 𐑓𐑭𐑕𐑩𐑯 𐑣𐑻 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑣𐑧𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑯 𐑔𐑿𐑟 𐑯 𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑑. 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑔𐑿𐑟 𐑮𐑨𐑯 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑚𐑱𐑕 𐑚𐑤𐑪𐑒𐑕 𐑝 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑢𐑫𐑛, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑛𐑧𐑓𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑖𐑰𐑝𐑟 𐑝 𐑕𐑰-𐑲𐑝𐑼𐑦. 𐑕𐑒𐑹𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑲𐑤 𐑢𐑰𐑤 𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑻 𐑮𐑧𐑝𐑼𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑥, 𐑖𐑰 𐑕𐑐𐑹𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑞𐑺 𐑩 𐑑𐑦𐑤𐑼; 𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑑𐑦𐑤𐑼 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑥𐑨𐑕, 𐑒𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑾𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑸𐑝𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑯𐑼𐑴 𐑤𐑴𐑼 𐑡𐑷 𐑝 𐑣𐑻 𐑣𐑼𐑧𐑛𐑦𐑑𐑼𐑦 𐑓𐑴. 𐑞 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑥𐑟𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑣𐑵 𐑕𐑑𐑽𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑑𐑦𐑤𐑼 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑑𐑧𐑥𐑐𐑦𐑕𐑑, 𐑓𐑧𐑤𐑑 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑞 ·𐑑𐑸𐑑𐑼, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑟 𐑚𐑨𐑒 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑲𐑼𐑦 𐑕𐑑𐑰𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑒𐑤𐑳𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑡𐑷. 𐑩 𐑯𐑴𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑒𐑮𐑭𐑓𐑑, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑣𐑬 𐑩 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑥𐑧𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑒𐑪𐑤𐑦! 𐑷𐑤 𐑯𐑴𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑸 𐑑𐑳𐑗𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞𐑨𐑑.

𐑯𐑬 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑲 𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑑 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑞 𐑒𐑢𐑹𐑑𐑼-𐑛𐑧𐑒, 𐑓 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑷𐑔𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑦, 𐑦𐑯 𐑹𐑛𐑼 𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑐𐑴𐑟 𐑥𐑲𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑨𐑟 𐑩 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑑 𐑓 𐑞 𐑝𐑶𐑦𐑡, 𐑨𐑑 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑲 𐑕𐑷 𐑯𐑴𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑲 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑢𐑧𐑤 𐑴𐑝𐑼𐑤𐑫𐑒 𐑩 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡 𐑕𐑹𐑑 𐑝 𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑑, 𐑹 𐑮𐑭𐑞𐑼 𐑢𐑦𐑜𐑢𐑭𐑥, 𐑐𐑦𐑗𐑑 𐑩 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑚𐑦𐑣𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑞 𐑥𐑱𐑯-𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑. 𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑩 𐑑𐑧𐑥𐑐𐑼𐑼𐑦 𐑦𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑿𐑟𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑐𐑹𐑑. 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑝 𐑩 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑖𐑱𐑐, 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑑𐑧𐑯 𐑓𐑰𐑑 𐑣𐑲; 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑞 𐑤𐑪𐑙, 𐑣𐑿𐑡 𐑕𐑤𐑨𐑚𐑟 𐑝 𐑤𐑦𐑥𐑚𐑼 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑒 𐑚𐑴𐑯 𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑥𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑤 𐑯 𐑣𐑲𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑐𐑸𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑡𐑷𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑮𐑲𐑑-𐑢𐑱𐑤. 𐑐𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞𐑺 𐑚𐑮𐑷𐑛 𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑒, 𐑩 𐑕𐑻𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑕𐑤𐑨𐑚𐑟 𐑤𐑱𐑕𐑑 𐑑𐑩𐑜𐑧𐑞𐑼, 𐑥𐑿𐑗𐑵𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑤𐑴𐑐𐑑 𐑑𐑩𐑢𐑹𐑛𐑟 𐑰𐑗 𐑳𐑞𐑼, 𐑯 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑱𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑕 𐑿𐑯𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑑𐑳𐑓𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑐𐑶𐑯𐑑, 𐑢𐑺 𐑞 𐑤𐑵𐑕 𐑣𐑺𐑦 𐑓𐑲𐑚𐑼𐑟 𐑢𐑱𐑝𐑛 𐑑 𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑴 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑞 𐑑𐑪𐑐-𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑪𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑴𐑤𐑛 ·𐑐𐑪𐑑𐑴𐑪𐑑𐑱𐑥𐑦 ·𐑕𐑱𐑗𐑩𐑥'𐑟 𐑣𐑧𐑛. 𐑩 𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑨𐑙𐑜𐑿𐑤𐑼 𐑴𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑱𐑕𐑑 𐑑𐑩𐑢𐑹𐑛𐑟 𐑞 𐑚𐑬𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐, 𐑕𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑲𐑛𐑼 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑭𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑩 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑰𐑑 𐑝𐑿 𐑓𐑹𐑢𐑼𐑛.

𐑯 𐑣𐑭𐑓 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑰𐑤𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑒𐑢𐑽 𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑩𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑, 𐑲 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑧𐑙𐑔 𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑣𐑵 𐑚𐑲 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑨𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑷𐑔𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑦; 𐑯 𐑣𐑵, 𐑦𐑑 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑯𐑵𐑯, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐'𐑕 𐑢𐑻𐑒 𐑕𐑩𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛, 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑬 𐑦𐑯𐑡𐑶𐑦𐑙 𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑐𐑲𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑚𐑻𐑛𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑭𐑯𐑛. 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑰𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑪𐑯 𐑩𐑯 𐑴𐑤𐑛-𐑓𐑨𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑴𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑗𐑺, 𐑮𐑦𐑜𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑷𐑤 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑒𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑾𐑕 𐑒𐑸𐑝𐑦𐑙; 𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑪𐑑𐑩𐑥 𐑝 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑓𐑹𐑥𐑛 𐑝 𐑩 𐑕𐑑𐑬𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑤𐑱𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑦𐑤𐑨𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑓 𐑝 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑞 𐑢𐑦𐑜𐑢𐑭𐑥 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑛.

𐑞𐑺 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑳𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑴 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑐𐑼𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑼, 𐑐𐑼𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑕, 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑞 𐑩𐑐𐑽𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑧𐑤𐑛𐑼𐑤𐑦 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑲 𐑕𐑷; 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑚𐑮𐑬𐑯 𐑯 𐑚𐑮𐑷𐑯𐑦, 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑧𐑯, 𐑯 𐑣𐑧𐑝𐑦𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑳𐑐 𐑦𐑯 𐑚𐑤𐑵 𐑐𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑑-𐑒𐑤𐑪𐑔, 𐑒𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑒𐑢𐑱𐑒𐑼 𐑕𐑑𐑲𐑤; 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑞𐑺 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩 𐑓𐑲𐑯 𐑯 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑥𐑲𐑒𐑮𐑩𐑕𐑒𐑪𐑐𐑦𐑒 𐑯𐑧𐑑-𐑢𐑻𐑒 𐑝 𐑞 𐑥𐑲𐑯𐑿𐑑𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑤𐑱𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑲𐑟, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑼𐑦𐑟𐑩𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑿𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑣𐑸𐑛 𐑜𐑱𐑤𐑟, 𐑯 𐑷𐑤𐑢𐑱𐑟 𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑢𐑼𐑛;—𐑓 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑒𐑷𐑟𐑩𐑟 𐑞 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑞 𐑲𐑟 𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑐𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑑𐑩𐑜𐑧𐑞𐑼. 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑲-𐑮𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑸 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑦𐑓𐑧𐑒𐑗𐑵𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑕𐑒𐑬𐑤.

“𐑦𐑟 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑞 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛?” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑲, 𐑩𐑛𐑝𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑞 𐑛𐑹 𐑝 𐑞 𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑑.

“𐑕𐑩𐑐𐑴𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑞 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛, 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑛𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑞𐑬 𐑢𐑪𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑥?” 𐑣𐑰 𐑛𐑦𐑥𐑭𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛.

“𐑲 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑦𐑙.”

“𐑞𐑬 𐑢𐑪𐑕𐑑, 𐑢𐑪𐑕𐑑 𐑞𐑬? 𐑲 𐑕𐑰 𐑞𐑬 𐑸𐑑 𐑯𐑴 ·𐑯𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑑𐑼—𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑕𐑑𐑴𐑝 𐑚𐑴𐑑?”

“𐑯𐑴, ·𐑕𐑻, 𐑲 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑣𐑨𐑝.”

“𐑛𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑯𐑴 𐑯𐑳𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑨𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙, 𐑲 𐑛𐑺 𐑕𐑱—𐑱?

“𐑯𐑳𐑔𐑦𐑙, ·𐑕𐑻; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑯𐑴 𐑛𐑬𐑑 𐑲 𐑖𐑨𐑤 𐑕𐑵𐑯 𐑤𐑻𐑯. 𐑲'𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑕𐑧𐑝𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑝𐑶𐑦𐑡𐑩𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑥𐑻𐑗𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑕𐑻𐑝𐑦𐑕, 𐑯 𐑲 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒 𐑞𐑨𐑑—”

“𐑥𐑻𐑗𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑕𐑻𐑝𐑦𐑕 𐑚𐑰 𐑛𐑨𐑥𐑛. 𐑑𐑷𐑒 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑴 𐑑 𐑥𐑰. 𐑛𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑰 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑧𐑜?—𐑲'𐑤 𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑧𐑜 𐑩𐑢𐑱 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞𐑲 𐑕𐑑𐑻𐑯, 𐑦𐑓 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑞𐑬 𐑑𐑷𐑒𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑥𐑸𐑗𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑕𐑻𐑝𐑦𐑕 𐑑 𐑥𐑰 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯. 𐑥𐑸𐑗𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑕𐑻𐑝𐑦𐑕 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑰𐑛! 𐑲 𐑕𐑩𐑐𐑴𐑟 𐑯𐑬 𐑘𐑰 𐑓𐑰𐑤 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑼𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑐𐑮𐑬𐑛 𐑝 𐑣𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑻𐑝𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑥𐑸𐑗𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑕. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑓𐑤𐑵𐑒𐑕! 𐑥𐑨𐑯, 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑥𐑱𐑒𐑕 𐑞𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑯𐑑 𐑑 𐑜𐑴 𐑩 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙, 𐑱?—𐑦𐑑 𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑕 𐑩 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑩𐑕𐑐𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑕, 𐑛𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑦𐑑, 𐑱?—𐑣𐑨𐑕𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑩 𐑐𐑲𐑮𐑩𐑑, 𐑣𐑨𐑕𐑑 𐑞𐑬?—𐑛𐑦𐑛𐑕𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑮𐑪𐑚 𐑞𐑲 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯, 𐑛𐑦𐑛𐑕𐑑 𐑞𐑬?—𐑛𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒 𐑝 𐑥𐑻𐑛𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑪𐑓𐑦𐑕𐑼𐑟 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑞𐑬 𐑜𐑧𐑑𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑑 𐑕𐑰?”

𐑲 𐑐𐑮𐑴𐑑𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑥𐑲 𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑝 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑟. 𐑲 𐑕𐑷 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑞 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑒 𐑝 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑣𐑭𐑓 𐑣𐑿𐑥𐑼𐑩𐑕 𐑦𐑯𐑿𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑴𐑟, 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑩𐑯, 𐑨𐑟 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑿𐑤𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 ·𐑒𐑢𐑱𐑒𐑼𐑦𐑖 ·𐑯𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑑𐑼, 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑓𐑫𐑤 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑤𐑼 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑡𐑩𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑩𐑟, 𐑯 𐑮𐑭𐑞𐑼 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑕𐑑𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑷𐑤 𐑱𐑤𐑾𐑯𐑟, 𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑧𐑕 𐑞𐑱 𐑣𐑱𐑤𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 ·𐑒𐑱𐑐 ·𐑒𐑪𐑛 𐑹 𐑞 ·𐑝𐑦𐑯𐑘𐑼𐑛.

“𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑕 𐑞𐑰 𐑩-𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙? 𐑲 𐑢𐑪𐑯𐑑 𐑑 𐑯𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑲 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒 𐑝 𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑘𐑰.”

“𐑢𐑧𐑤, 𐑕𐑻, 𐑲 𐑢𐑪𐑯𐑑 𐑑 𐑕𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑟. 𐑲 𐑢𐑪𐑯𐑑 𐑑 𐑕𐑰 𐑞 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛.”

“𐑢𐑪𐑯𐑑 𐑑 𐑕𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑟, 𐑱? 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑘𐑰 𐑒𐑤𐑨𐑐𐑑 𐑲 𐑪𐑯 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚?”

“𐑣𐑵 𐑦𐑟 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚, 𐑕𐑻?”

“𐑲, 𐑲, 𐑲 𐑔𐑷𐑑 𐑕𐑴. 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑦𐑟 𐑞 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 𐑝 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑖𐑦𐑐.”

“𐑲 𐑨𐑥 𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯. 𐑲 𐑔𐑷𐑑 𐑲 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓.”

“𐑞𐑬 𐑸𐑑 𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑑 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 ·𐑐𐑰𐑤𐑧𐑜—𐑞𐑨𐑑'𐑕 𐑣𐑵 𐑘𐑰 𐑸 𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑑, 𐑘𐑳𐑙 𐑥𐑨𐑯. 𐑦𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑪𐑙𐑟 𐑑 𐑥𐑰 𐑯 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 ·𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑛𐑨𐑛 𐑑 𐑕𐑰 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛 𐑓𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑬𐑑 𐑓 𐑞 𐑝𐑶𐑦𐑡, 𐑯 𐑕𐑩𐑐𐑤𐑲𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑷𐑤 𐑣𐑻 𐑯𐑰𐑛𐑟, 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑤𐑵𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑒𐑮𐑵. 𐑢𐑰 𐑸 𐑐𐑸𐑑 𐑴𐑯𐑼𐑟 𐑯 𐑱𐑡𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑲 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑜𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑕𐑱, 𐑦𐑓 𐑞𐑬 𐑢𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑑 𐑯𐑴 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑟, 𐑨𐑟 𐑞𐑬 𐑑𐑧𐑤𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑘𐑰 𐑛𐑵, 𐑲 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑐𐑫𐑑 𐑘𐑰 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑢𐑱 𐑝 𐑓𐑲𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑑 𐑬𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑘𐑰 𐑚𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑘𐑹𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑑 𐑦𐑑, 𐑐𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑨𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑬𐑑. 𐑒𐑤𐑨𐑐 𐑲 𐑪𐑯 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚, 𐑘𐑳𐑙 𐑥𐑨𐑯, 𐑯 𐑞𐑬 𐑢𐑦𐑤𐑑 𐑓𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑤𐑧𐑜.”

“𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑛𐑵 𐑿 𐑥𐑰𐑯, 𐑕𐑻? 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑤𐑪𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑩 𐑢𐑱𐑤?”

“𐑤𐑪𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑩 𐑢𐑱𐑤! 𐑘𐑳𐑙 𐑥𐑨𐑯, 𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑯𐑽𐑼 𐑑 𐑥𐑰: 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑛𐑦𐑝𐑬𐑼𐑛, 𐑗𐑵𐑛 𐑳𐑐, 𐑒𐑮𐑳𐑯𐑗𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑥𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑩𐑕𐑩𐑕𐑑 ·𐑐𐑸𐑥𐑩𐑕𐑧𐑑𐑦 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑗𐑦𐑐𐑑 𐑩 𐑚𐑴𐑑!—𐑭, 𐑭!”

𐑲 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑩𐑤𐑸𐑥𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑧𐑯𐑼𐑡𐑦, 𐑐𐑼𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑕 𐑷𐑤𐑕𐑴 𐑩 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑑𐑳𐑗𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑣𐑸𐑑𐑦 𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑓 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑒𐑤𐑵𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑒𐑤𐑩𐑥𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑨𐑟 𐑒𐑭𐑥𐑤𐑦 𐑨𐑟 𐑲 𐑒𐑫𐑛, “𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑿 𐑕𐑱 𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑴 𐑛𐑬𐑑 𐑑𐑮𐑵 𐑦𐑯𐑳𐑓, 𐑕𐑻; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑣𐑬 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑲 𐑯𐑴 𐑞𐑺 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑽 𐑓𐑼𐑪𐑕𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑐𐑼𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑼 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑞𐑴 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑰𐑛 𐑲 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑦𐑯𐑓𐑻𐑛 𐑨𐑟 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑕𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑤 𐑓𐑨𐑒𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑨𐑒𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑑.”

“𐑤𐑫𐑒 𐑘𐑰 𐑯𐑬, 𐑘𐑳𐑙 𐑥𐑨𐑯, 𐑞𐑲 𐑤𐑳𐑙𐑟 𐑸 𐑩 𐑕𐑹𐑑 𐑝 𐑕𐑪𐑓𐑑, 𐑛'𐑘𐑰 𐑕𐑰; 𐑞𐑬 𐑛𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑑𐑷𐑒 𐑖𐑸𐑒 𐑩 𐑚𐑦𐑑. 𐑖𐑫𐑼, 𐑘𐑰'𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑑 𐑕𐑰 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑯𐑬; 𐑖𐑫𐑼 𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑?”

“𐑕𐑻,” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑲, “𐑲 𐑔𐑷𐑑 𐑲 𐑑𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑿 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑓𐑹 𐑝𐑶𐑦𐑡𐑩𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑥𐑻𐑗𐑩𐑯𐑑—”

“𐑣𐑸𐑛 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑! 𐑥𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑲 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑞 𐑥𐑸𐑗𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑕𐑻𐑝𐑦𐑕—𐑛𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑨𐑜𐑮𐑩𐑝𐑱𐑑 𐑥𐑰—𐑲 𐑢𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑦𐑑. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑤𐑧𐑑 𐑳𐑕 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑰𐑗 𐑳𐑞𐑼. 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑜𐑦𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑞𐑰 𐑩 𐑣𐑦𐑯𐑑 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑟; 𐑛𐑵 𐑘𐑰 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑓𐑰𐑤 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑤𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑓 𐑦𐑑?”

“𐑲 𐑛𐑵, 𐑕𐑻.”

“𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑜𐑫𐑛. 𐑯𐑬, 𐑸𐑑 𐑞𐑬 𐑞 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑑 𐑐𐑦𐑗 𐑩 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑩 𐑤𐑲𐑝 𐑢𐑱𐑤'𐑟 𐑔𐑮𐑴𐑑, 𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑡𐑳𐑥𐑐 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑦𐑑? 𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑼, 𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑒!”

“𐑲 𐑨𐑥, 𐑕𐑻, 𐑦𐑓 𐑦𐑑 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑚𐑰 𐑐𐑪𐑟𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑝𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑑 𐑛𐑵 𐑕𐑴; 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑜𐑪𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑛 𐑝, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑟; 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑲 𐑛𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑞 𐑓𐑨𐑒𐑑.”

“𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯. 𐑯𐑬 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑞𐑬 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑢𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑑 𐑜𐑴 𐑩-𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙, 𐑑 𐑓𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑬𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑽𐑾𐑯𐑕 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑟, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑘𐑰 𐑷𐑤𐑕𐑴 𐑢𐑪𐑯𐑑 𐑑 𐑜𐑴 𐑦𐑯 𐑹𐑛𐑼 𐑑 𐑕𐑰 𐑞 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛? 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑘𐑰 𐑕𐑧𐑛? 𐑲 𐑔𐑷𐑑 𐑕𐑴. 𐑢𐑧𐑤 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑡𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑐 𐑓𐑹𐑢𐑼𐑛 𐑞𐑺, 𐑯 𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑩 𐑐𐑰𐑐 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑞 𐑢𐑧𐑞𐑼-𐑚𐑬, 𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑚𐑨𐑒 𐑑 𐑥𐑰 𐑯 𐑑𐑧𐑤 𐑥𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑘𐑰 𐑕𐑰 𐑞𐑺.”

𐑓 𐑩 𐑥𐑴𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑲 𐑕𐑑𐑫𐑛 𐑩 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑐𐑳𐑟𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑒𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑾𐑕 𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑕𐑑, 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑯𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑜𐑟𐑨𐑒𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑣𐑬 𐑑 𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑦𐑑, 𐑢𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑣𐑿𐑥𐑼𐑩𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑹 𐑦𐑯 𐑻𐑯𐑩𐑕𐑑. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑷𐑤 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑮𐑴'𐑟 𐑓𐑰𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑕𐑒𐑬𐑤, ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 ·𐑐𐑰𐑤𐑧𐑜 𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑥𐑰 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑧𐑮𐑩𐑯𐑛.

𐑜𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑹𐑢𐑼𐑛 𐑯 𐑜𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑞 𐑢𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑚𐑬, 𐑲 𐑐𐑼𐑕𐑰𐑝𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑕𐑢𐑦𐑙𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑣𐑻 𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑼 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑓𐑤𐑳𐑛-𐑑𐑲𐑛, 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑬 𐑴𐑚𐑤𐑰𐑒𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑶𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑑𐑩𐑢𐑹𐑛𐑟 𐑞 𐑴𐑐𐑩𐑯 𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯. 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑳𐑯𐑤𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑛, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑰𐑛𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑪𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑯 𐑓𐑼𐑚𐑦𐑛𐑦𐑙; 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑤𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑝𐑼𐑲𐑩𐑑𐑦 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑲 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑕𐑰.

“𐑢𐑧𐑤, 𐑢𐑪𐑑'𐑕 𐑞 𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑹𐑑?” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 ·𐑐𐑰𐑤𐑧𐑜 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑲 𐑒𐑱𐑥 𐑚𐑨𐑒; “𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑘𐑰 𐑕𐑰?”

“𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑥𐑳𐑗,” 𐑲 𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑤𐑲𐑛—“𐑯𐑳𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼; 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑼𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑣𐑼𐑲𐑟𐑩𐑯 𐑞𐑴, 𐑯 𐑞𐑺'𐑟 𐑩 𐑕𐑒𐑢𐑷𐑤 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑳𐑐, 𐑲 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒.”

“𐑢𐑧𐑤, 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑛𐑳𐑟 𐑞𐑬 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑝 𐑕𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛? 𐑛𐑵 𐑘𐑰 𐑢𐑦𐑖 𐑑 𐑜𐑴 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 ·𐑒𐑱𐑐 ·𐑣𐑹𐑯 𐑑 𐑕𐑰 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑥𐑹 𐑝 𐑦𐑑, 𐑱? 𐑒𐑭𐑯𐑑 𐑘𐑰 𐑕𐑰 𐑞 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛 𐑢𐑺 𐑿 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛?”

𐑲 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑜𐑼𐑛, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑜𐑴 𐑩-𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑲 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑, 𐑯 𐑲 𐑢𐑫𐑛; 𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑨𐑟 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑩 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑨𐑟 𐑧𐑯𐑦—𐑲 𐑔𐑷𐑑 𐑞 𐑚𐑧𐑕𐑑—𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑲 𐑯𐑬 𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑰𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑑 ·𐑐𐑰𐑤𐑧𐑜. 𐑕𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑰 𐑕𐑴 𐑛𐑦𐑑𐑻𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑛, 𐑣𐑰 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑙𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑑 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑥𐑰.

“𐑯 𐑞𐑬 𐑥𐑱𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑢𐑧𐑤 𐑕𐑲𐑯 𐑞 𐑐𐑱𐑐𐑼𐑟 𐑮𐑲𐑑 𐑪𐑓,” 𐑣𐑰 𐑨𐑛𐑩𐑛—“𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑘𐑰.” 𐑯 𐑕𐑴 𐑕𐑱𐑦𐑙, 𐑣𐑰 𐑤𐑧𐑛 𐑞 𐑢𐑱 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑴 𐑛𐑧𐑒 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑒𐑨𐑚𐑦𐑯.

𐑕𐑰𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑥 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑑 𐑥𐑰 𐑩 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑳𐑯𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑯 𐑕𐑼𐑐𐑮𐑲𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑦𐑜𐑼. 𐑦𐑑 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑛 𐑬𐑑 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 ·𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑛𐑨𐑛, 𐑣𐑵 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑢𐑦𐑞 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 ·𐑐𐑰𐑤𐑧𐑜 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑤𐑸𐑡𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑴𐑯𐑼𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑝𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑤; 𐑞 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑖𐑺𐑟, 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑞 𐑒𐑱𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑐𐑹𐑑𐑕, 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑩 𐑒𐑮𐑬𐑛 𐑝 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑨𐑯𐑿𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕; 𐑢𐑦𐑛𐑴𐑟, 𐑓𐑭𐑞𐑼𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑗𐑦𐑤𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑯, 𐑯 𐑗𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑼𐑦 𐑢𐑹𐑛𐑟; 𐑰𐑗 𐑴𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑞 𐑝𐑨𐑤𐑿 𐑝 𐑩 𐑑𐑦𐑥𐑚𐑼 𐑣𐑧𐑛, 𐑹 𐑩 𐑓𐑫𐑑 𐑝 𐑐𐑤𐑨𐑙𐑒, 𐑹 𐑩 𐑯𐑱𐑤 𐑹 𐑑𐑵 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐. 𐑐𐑰𐑐𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑯 ·𐑯𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑥𐑳𐑯𐑦 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑝𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑤𐑟, 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑢𐑱 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑿 𐑛𐑵 𐑘𐑹𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑩𐑐𐑮𐑵𐑝𐑛 𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑪𐑒𐑕 𐑚𐑮𐑦𐑙𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑩𐑕𐑑.

𐑯𐑬, ·𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑛𐑨𐑛, 𐑤𐑲𐑒 ·𐑐𐑰𐑤𐑧𐑜, 𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑰𐑛 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑳𐑞𐑼 ·𐑯𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑑𐑼𐑟, 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩 ·𐑒𐑢𐑱𐑒𐑼, 𐑞 𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑼𐑦𐑡𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑧𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑧𐑒𐑑; 𐑯 𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑛𐑱 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑦𐑯𐑣𐑨𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑱𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑩𐑯 𐑳𐑯𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑥𐑧𐑠𐑼 𐑞 𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑦𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑒𐑢𐑱𐑒𐑼, 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑝𐑺𐑾𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑯 𐑩𐑯𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑤𐑩𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑥𐑪𐑛𐑦𐑓𐑲𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑷𐑤𐑑𐑩𐑜𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑱𐑤𐑾𐑯 𐑯 𐑣𐑧𐑑𐑼𐑩𐑡𐑰𐑯𐑾𐑕. 𐑓 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑝 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑕𐑱𐑥 ·𐑒𐑢𐑱𐑒𐑼𐑟 𐑸 𐑞 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑨𐑙𐑜𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑼𐑦 𐑝 𐑷𐑤 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑼𐑟 𐑯 𐑢𐑱𐑤-𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑟. 𐑞𐑱 𐑸 𐑓𐑲𐑑𐑦𐑙 ·𐑒𐑢𐑱𐑒𐑼𐑟; 𐑞𐑱 𐑸 ·𐑒𐑢𐑱𐑒𐑼𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑝𐑧𐑯𐑡𐑩𐑯𐑕.

𐑕𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑸 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑝 𐑥𐑧𐑯, 𐑣𐑵, 𐑯𐑱𐑥𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 ·𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑗𐑼 𐑯𐑱𐑥𐑟—𐑩 𐑕𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑿𐑤𐑼𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑓𐑨𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛—𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑗𐑲𐑤𐑛𐑣𐑫𐑛 𐑯𐑨𐑗𐑼𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑥𐑚𐑲𐑚𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑥𐑨𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑞𐑰 𐑯 𐑞𐑬 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑒𐑢𐑱𐑒𐑼 𐑦𐑛𐑾𐑥; 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤, 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑷𐑛𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑕, 𐑛𐑺𐑦𐑙, 𐑯 𐑚𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑩𐑛𐑝𐑧𐑯𐑗𐑼 𐑝 𐑞𐑺 𐑕𐑳𐑚𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑢𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑤𐑲𐑝𐑟, 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑤𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑳𐑯𐑬𐑑𐑜𐑮𐑴𐑯 𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑦𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑟, 𐑩 𐑔𐑬𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑚𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑛𐑨𐑖𐑩𐑟 𐑝 𐑒𐑨𐑮𐑩𐑒𐑑𐑼, 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑳𐑯𐑢𐑻𐑞𐑦 𐑩 ·𐑕𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑯𐑱𐑝𐑾𐑯 𐑕𐑰-𐑒𐑦𐑙, 𐑹 𐑩 𐑐𐑴𐑧𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 ·𐑐𐑱𐑜𐑩𐑯 ·𐑮𐑴𐑥𐑩𐑯. 𐑯 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑿𐑯𐑲𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑝 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑵𐑐𐑽𐑽 𐑯𐑨𐑗𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑓𐑹𐑕, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑜𐑤𐑪𐑚𐑿𐑤𐑼 𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑯 𐑯 𐑩 𐑐𐑪𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑩𐑕 𐑣𐑸𐑑; 𐑣𐑵 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑷𐑤𐑕𐑴 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑯 𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑵𐑠𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑯𐑲𐑑-𐑢𐑪𐑗𐑩𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑴𐑑𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼𐑟, 𐑯 𐑚𐑦𐑯𐑰𐑔 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑕𐑰𐑯 𐑣𐑽 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑯𐑹𐑔, 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑤𐑧𐑛 𐑑 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒 𐑳𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑩𐑛𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦; 𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑰𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑷𐑤 𐑯𐑱𐑗𐑼'𐑟 𐑕𐑢𐑰𐑑 𐑹 𐑕𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑡 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑖 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑣𐑻 𐑴𐑯 𐑝𐑻𐑡𐑦𐑯 𐑝𐑪𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑦 𐑯 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑓𐑲𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑑, 𐑯 𐑞𐑺𐑚𐑲 𐑗𐑰𐑓𐑤𐑦, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑐 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑨𐑒𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑩𐑛𐑝𐑭𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑡𐑩𐑟, 𐑑 𐑤𐑻𐑯 𐑩 𐑚𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑯 𐑯𐑻𐑝𐑩𐑕 𐑤𐑪𐑓𐑑𐑦 𐑤𐑨𐑙𐑜𐑢𐑦𐑡—𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑥𐑱𐑒𐑕 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑣𐑴𐑤 𐑯𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯'𐑟 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑕—𐑩 𐑥𐑲𐑑𐑦 𐑐𐑨𐑡𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑒𐑮𐑰𐑗𐑼, 𐑓𐑹𐑥𐑛 𐑓 𐑯𐑴𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑡𐑩𐑛𐑦𐑟. 𐑯𐑹 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑦𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑛𐑦𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑒𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑥𐑨𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑦𐑜𐑸𐑛𐑩𐑛, 𐑦𐑓 𐑲𐑞𐑼 𐑚𐑲 𐑚𐑻𐑔 𐑹 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑕𐑻𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟, 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑟 𐑩 𐑣𐑭𐑓 𐑢𐑦𐑤𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑴𐑝𐑼𐑮𐑵𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑹𐑚𐑦𐑛𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑚𐑪𐑑𐑩𐑥 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑱𐑗𐑼. 𐑓 𐑷𐑤 𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑡𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑦 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑸 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑕𐑴 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑩 𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑥𐑹𐑚𐑦𐑛𐑯𐑩𐑕. 𐑚𐑰 𐑖𐑫𐑼 𐑝 𐑞𐑦𐑕, 𐑴 𐑘𐑳𐑙 𐑨𐑥𐑚𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯, 𐑷𐑤 𐑥𐑹𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑟𐑰𐑟. 𐑚𐑳𐑑, 𐑨𐑟 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑢𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑑 𐑛𐑵 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑒𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑩𐑯𐑳𐑞𐑼; 𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑩 𐑥𐑨𐑯, 𐑣𐑵, 𐑦𐑓 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑰𐑛 𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑽, 𐑦𐑑 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑳𐑤𐑑𐑕 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑩𐑯𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑓𐑱𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑒𐑢𐑱𐑒𐑼, 𐑥𐑪𐑛𐑦𐑓𐑲𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑡𐑵𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑻𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟.

𐑤𐑲𐑒 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 ·𐑐𐑰𐑤𐑧𐑜, ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 ·𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑛𐑨𐑛 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩 𐑢𐑧𐑤-𐑑-𐑛𐑵, 𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑲𐑼𐑛 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑥𐑩𐑯. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑳𐑯𐑤𐑲𐑒 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 ·𐑐𐑰𐑤𐑧𐑜—𐑣𐑵 𐑒𐑺𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑩 𐑮𐑳𐑖 𐑓 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑸 𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑛 𐑕𐑽𐑾𐑕 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑟, 𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑰𐑛 𐑛𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓-𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑕𐑽𐑾𐑕 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑞 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑾𐑕𐑑 𐑝 𐑷𐑤 𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑓𐑩𐑤𐑟—·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 ·𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑛𐑨𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑼𐑦𐑡𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑧𐑡𐑩𐑒𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑩𐑒𐑹𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑧𐑒𐑑 𐑝 ·𐑯𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑑 ·𐑒𐑢𐑱𐑒𐑼𐑦𐑟𐑩𐑥, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑳𐑚𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑢𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑤𐑲𐑓, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑲𐑑 𐑝 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑳𐑯𐑒𐑤𐑨𐑛, 𐑤𐑳𐑝𐑤𐑦 𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑒𐑮𐑰𐑗𐑼𐑟, 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑞 ·𐑣𐑹𐑯—𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑥𐑵𐑝𐑛 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑯𐑱𐑑𐑦𐑝 𐑚𐑹𐑯 ·𐑒𐑢𐑱𐑒𐑼 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑕𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑩𐑤 𐑡𐑪𐑑, 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑴 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑨𐑟 𐑷𐑤𐑑𐑼𐑛 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑨𐑙𐑜𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑝𐑧𐑕𐑑. 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤, 𐑓 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑦𐑥𐑿𐑑𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑯𐑩𐑕, 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞𐑺 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑤𐑨𐑒 𐑝 𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑢𐑻𐑞𐑦 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 ·𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑛𐑨𐑛. 𐑞𐑴 𐑮𐑦𐑓𐑿𐑟𐑦𐑙, 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑖𐑦𐑧𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑕 𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑵𐑐𐑩𐑤𐑟, 𐑑 𐑚𐑺 𐑸𐑥𐑟 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑱𐑛𐑼𐑟, 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑱𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑞 ·𐑩𐑑𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑯 ·𐑐𐑩𐑕𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑒; 𐑯 𐑞𐑴 𐑩 𐑕𐑢𐑹𐑯 𐑓𐑴 𐑑 𐑣𐑿𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑚𐑤𐑳𐑛𐑖𐑧𐑛, 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑣𐑰 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑑-𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑒𐑴𐑑, 𐑕𐑐𐑦𐑤𐑛 𐑑𐑳𐑯𐑟 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑑𐑳𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑤𐑩𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑔𐑩𐑯 𐑜𐑹. 𐑣𐑬 𐑯𐑬 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑩𐑑𐑦𐑝 𐑰𐑝𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑛𐑱𐑟, 𐑞 𐑐𐑲𐑩𐑕 ·𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑛𐑨𐑛 𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑲𐑤𐑛 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑮𐑧𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑕, 𐑲 𐑛𐑵 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑯𐑴; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑥 𐑑 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑻𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑥𐑳𐑗, 𐑯 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑚𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑕𐑦𐑯𐑕 𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑡 𐑯 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑒𐑤𐑵𐑠𐑩𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑩 𐑥𐑨𐑯'𐑟 𐑮𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑡𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑔𐑦𐑙, 𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑐𐑮𐑨𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛 𐑒𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑩𐑯𐑳𐑞𐑼. 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛 𐑐𐑱𐑟 𐑛𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑛𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑟. 𐑮𐑲𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑩 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑒𐑨𐑚𐑦𐑯-𐑚𐑶 𐑦𐑯 𐑖𐑹𐑑 𐑒𐑤𐑴𐑞𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑛𐑮𐑨𐑚𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑛𐑮𐑨𐑚, 𐑑 𐑩 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑽 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑚𐑮𐑷𐑛 𐑖𐑨𐑛-𐑚𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑛 𐑢𐑱𐑕𐑑𐑒𐑴𐑑; 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑴𐑑-𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑼, 𐑗𐑰𐑓-𐑥𐑱𐑑, 𐑯 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯, 𐑯 𐑓𐑲𐑯𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑩 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑴𐑯𐑼; ·𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑛𐑨𐑛, 𐑨𐑟 𐑲 𐑣𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹, 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑒𐑤𐑵𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑩𐑛𐑝𐑧𐑯𐑗𐑼𐑩𐑕 𐑒𐑼𐑽 𐑚𐑲 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑲𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑨𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑝 𐑤𐑲𐑓 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑜𐑫𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑱𐑡 𐑝 𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑦, 𐑯 𐑛𐑧𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑱𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑱𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑛𐑱𐑟 𐑑 𐑞 𐑒𐑢𐑲𐑩𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑰𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑧𐑤-𐑻𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑳𐑥.

𐑯𐑬, ·𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑛𐑨𐑛, 𐑲 𐑨𐑥 𐑕𐑪𐑮𐑦 𐑑 𐑕𐑱, 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑞 𐑮𐑧𐑐𐑿𐑑𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑡𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑣𐑳𐑙𐑒𐑕, 𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑰-𐑜𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑛𐑱𐑟, 𐑩 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑼, 𐑣𐑸𐑛 𐑑𐑭𐑕𐑒-𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑼. 𐑞𐑱 𐑑𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑥𐑰 𐑦𐑯 ·𐑯𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑑, 𐑞𐑴 𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑟 𐑩 𐑒𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑾𐑕 𐑕𐑑𐑹𐑦, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑛 𐑞 𐑴𐑤𐑛 ·𐑒𐑨𐑑𐑩𐑜𐑫𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑥𐑩𐑯, 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑮𐑵, 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑼𐑲𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑴𐑥, 𐑢𐑻 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑷𐑤 𐑒𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑛 𐑩𐑖𐑹 𐑑 𐑞 𐑣𐑪𐑕𐑐𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤, 𐑕𐑹 𐑦𐑜𐑟𐑷𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑯 𐑢𐑹𐑯 𐑬𐑑. 𐑓 𐑩 𐑐𐑲𐑩𐑕 𐑥𐑨𐑯, 𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑓 𐑩 ·𐑒𐑢𐑱𐑒𐑼, 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑭𐑞𐑼 𐑣𐑸𐑛-𐑣𐑸𐑑𐑩𐑛, 𐑑 𐑕𐑱 𐑞 𐑤𐑰𐑕𐑑. 𐑣𐑰 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑿𐑕𐑑 𐑑 𐑕𐑢𐑺, 𐑞𐑴, 𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑧𐑯, 𐑞𐑱 𐑕𐑧𐑛; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑣𐑬 𐑣𐑰 𐑜𐑪𐑑 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑹𐑛𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑑 𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑝 𐑒𐑮𐑵𐑩𐑤, 𐑳𐑯𐑥𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑜𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑣𐑸𐑛 𐑢𐑻𐑒 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑞𐑧𐑥. 𐑢𐑧𐑯 ·𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑛𐑨𐑛 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩 𐑗𐑰𐑓-𐑥𐑱𐑑, 𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑛𐑮𐑨𐑚-𐑒𐑳𐑤𐑼𐑛 𐑲 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑨𐑑 𐑿, 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑿 𐑓𐑰𐑤 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑰𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑯𐑻𐑝𐑩𐑕, 𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑿 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑒𐑤𐑳𐑗 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑔𐑦𐑙—𐑩 𐑣𐑨𐑥𐑼 𐑹 𐑩 𐑥𐑸𐑤𐑦𐑙-𐑕𐑐𐑲𐑒, 𐑯 𐑜𐑴 𐑑 𐑢𐑻𐑒 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑥𐑨𐑛, 𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑹 𐑳𐑞𐑼, 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑥𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑢𐑪𐑑. 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑯 𐑲𐑛𐑩𐑤𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑐𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑖𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑣𐑦𐑥. 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑴𐑯 𐑐𐑻𐑕𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞 𐑦𐑜𐑟𐑨𐑒𐑑 𐑦𐑥𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑿𐑑𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑼𐑾𐑯 𐑒𐑨𐑮𐑩𐑒𐑑𐑼. 𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑤𐑪𐑙, 𐑜𐑷𐑯𐑑 𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦, 𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑛 𐑯𐑴 𐑕𐑐𐑺 𐑓𐑤𐑧𐑖, 𐑯𐑴 𐑕𐑵𐑐𐑻𐑓𐑤𐑵𐑩𐑕 𐑚𐑽𐑛, 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑗𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑕𐑪𐑓𐑑, 𐑰𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑪𐑥𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑯𐑨𐑐 𐑑 𐑦𐑑, 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑞 𐑢𐑹𐑯 𐑯𐑨𐑐 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑮𐑷𐑛-𐑚𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑑.

𐑕𐑳𐑗, 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞 𐑐𐑻𐑕𐑩𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑲 𐑕𐑷 𐑕𐑰𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑥 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑲 𐑓𐑪𐑤𐑴𐑛 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 ·𐑐𐑰𐑤𐑧𐑜 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑒𐑨𐑚𐑦𐑯. 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑱𐑕 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑢𐑰𐑯 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑒𐑕 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑥𐑷𐑤; 𐑯 𐑞𐑺, 𐑚𐑴𐑤𐑑-𐑳𐑐𐑮𐑲𐑑, 𐑕𐑨𐑑 𐑴𐑤𐑛 ·𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑛𐑨𐑛, 𐑣𐑵 𐑷𐑤𐑢𐑱𐑟 𐑕𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑴, 𐑯 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑤𐑰𐑯𐑛, 𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑑 𐑕𐑱𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑴𐑑 𐑑𐑱𐑤𐑟. 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑮𐑷𐑛-𐑚𐑮𐑦𐑥 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥; 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑤𐑧𐑜𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑓𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑮𐑪𐑕𐑑; 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑛𐑮𐑨𐑚 𐑝𐑧𐑕𐑗𐑼 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑚𐑳𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑳𐑐 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑗𐑦𐑯; 𐑯 𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑪𐑯 𐑯𐑴𐑟, 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑩𐑚𐑕𐑹𐑚𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑮𐑰𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑩 𐑐𐑪𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑩𐑕 𐑝𐑪𐑤𐑿𐑥.

“·𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑛𐑨𐑛,” 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 ·𐑐𐑰𐑤𐑧𐑜, “𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯, ·𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑛𐑨𐑛, 𐑱? 𐑘𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑛𐑦𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑴𐑟 ·𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑗𐑼𐑟, 𐑯𐑬, 𐑓 𐑞 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑔𐑻𐑑𐑦 𐑘𐑽𐑟, 𐑑 𐑥𐑲 𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑯𐑪𐑤𐑦𐑡. 𐑣𐑬 𐑓𐑸 𐑘𐑰 𐑜𐑪𐑑, ·𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑛𐑨𐑛?”

𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑓 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑣𐑩𐑚𐑦𐑗𐑵𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑐𐑮𐑴𐑓𐑱𐑯 𐑑𐑷𐑒 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑥𐑱𐑑, ·𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑛𐑨𐑛, 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑 𐑯𐑴𐑑𐑦𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑦𐑮𐑧𐑝𐑼𐑩𐑯𐑕, 𐑒𐑢𐑲𐑩𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑑 𐑳𐑐, 𐑯 𐑕𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑰, 𐑜𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑢𐑲𐑼𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑑𐑩𐑢𐑹𐑛𐑟 ·𐑐𐑰𐑤𐑧𐑜.

“𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑧𐑟 𐑣𐑰'𐑟 𐑬𐑼 𐑥𐑨𐑯, ·𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑛𐑨𐑛,” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 ·𐑐𐑰𐑤𐑧𐑜, “𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑑 𐑖𐑦𐑐.”

“𐑛𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑞𐑰?” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 ·𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑛𐑨𐑛, 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑣𐑪𐑤𐑴 𐑑𐑴𐑯, 𐑯 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑑 𐑥𐑰.

“𐑲 𐑛𐑳𐑕𐑑,” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑲 𐑳𐑯𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑕𐑤𐑦, 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑴 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑕 𐑩 ·𐑒𐑢𐑱𐑒𐑼.

“𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑛𐑵 𐑘𐑰 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑥, ·𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑛𐑨𐑛?” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 ·𐑐𐑰𐑤𐑧𐑜.

“𐑣𐑰'𐑤 𐑛𐑵,” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 ·𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑛𐑨𐑛, 𐑲𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑰, 𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑪𐑯 𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑢𐑱 𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑫𐑒 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑥𐑳𐑥𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑑𐑴𐑯 𐑒𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑷𐑛𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤.

𐑲 𐑔𐑷𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑞 𐑒𐑢𐑽𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑴𐑤𐑛 ·𐑒𐑢𐑱𐑒𐑼 𐑲 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑕𐑷, 𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑨𐑟 ·𐑐𐑰𐑤𐑧𐑜, 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑯 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑥𐑱𐑑, 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩 𐑚𐑤𐑳𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑼. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑲 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑯𐑳𐑔𐑦𐑙, 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑥𐑰 𐑖𐑸𐑐𐑤𐑦. ·𐑐𐑰𐑤𐑧𐑜 𐑯𐑬 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑴𐑐𐑩𐑯 𐑩 𐑗𐑧𐑕𐑑, 𐑯 𐑛𐑮𐑷𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑹𐑔 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐'𐑕 𐑸𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑟, 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕𐑑 𐑐𐑧𐑯 𐑯 𐑦𐑙𐑒 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑯 𐑕𐑰𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑨𐑑 𐑩 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑑𐑱𐑚𐑩𐑤. 𐑲 𐑚𐑦𐑜𐑨𐑯 𐑑 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑣𐑲 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑑 𐑕𐑧𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑥𐑲𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑑𐑻𐑥𐑟 𐑲 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑚𐑰 𐑢𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑜𐑱𐑡 𐑓 𐑞 𐑝𐑶𐑦𐑡. 𐑲 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑷𐑤𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑦 𐑩𐑢𐑺 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑦𐑟𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑞𐑱 𐑐𐑱𐑛 𐑯𐑴 𐑢𐑱𐑡𐑩𐑟; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟, 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑤𐑵𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯, 𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑰𐑝𐑛 𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑖𐑺𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑓𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑛 𐑤𐑱𐑟, 𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑤𐑱𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑐𐑹𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑑 𐑞 𐑛𐑦𐑜𐑮𐑰 𐑝 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑹𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑐𐑼𐑑𐑱𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑞 𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑝 𐑛𐑿𐑑𐑦𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐'𐑕 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑦. 𐑲 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑷𐑤𐑕𐑴 𐑩𐑢𐑺 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙, 𐑥𐑲 𐑴𐑯 𐑤𐑱 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑤𐑸𐑡; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑲 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑿𐑟𐑛 𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑰, 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑕𐑑𐑽 𐑩 𐑖𐑦𐑐, 𐑕𐑐𐑤𐑲𐑕 𐑩 𐑮𐑴𐑐, 𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑨𐑑, 𐑲 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑯𐑴 𐑛𐑬𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑷𐑤 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑣𐑻𐑛 𐑲 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑚𐑰 𐑪𐑓𐑼𐑛 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑰𐑕𐑑 𐑞 275𐑔 𐑤𐑱—𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑟, 𐑞 275𐑔 𐑐𐑸𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑒𐑤𐑽 𐑯𐑧𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑴𐑕𐑰𐑛𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑝𐑶𐑦𐑡, 𐑢𐑪𐑑𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑦𐑝𐑧𐑯𐑗𐑵𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑩𐑥𐑬𐑯𐑑 𐑑. 𐑯 𐑞𐑴 𐑞 275𐑔 𐑤𐑱 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑞𐑱 𐑒𐑷𐑤 𐑩 𐑮𐑭𐑞𐑼 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑤𐑱, 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑚𐑧𐑑𐑼 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑯𐑳𐑔𐑦𐑙; 𐑯 𐑦𐑓 𐑢𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑩 𐑤𐑳𐑒𐑦 𐑝𐑶𐑦𐑡, 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑯𐑽𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑱 𐑓 𐑞 𐑒𐑤𐑴𐑞𐑦𐑙 𐑲 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑢𐑺 𐑬𐑑 𐑪𐑯 𐑦𐑑, 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑑 𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑒 𐑝 𐑥𐑲 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑘𐑽𐑟' 𐑚𐑰𐑓 𐑯 𐑚𐑹𐑛, 𐑓 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑲 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑓 𐑑 𐑐𐑱 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑲𐑝𐑼.

𐑦𐑑 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑔𐑷𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩 𐑐𐑫𐑼 𐑢𐑱 𐑑 𐑩𐑒𐑿𐑥𐑿𐑤𐑱𐑑 𐑩 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑓𐑹𐑗𐑵𐑯—𐑯 𐑕𐑴 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟, 𐑩 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑐𐑫𐑼 𐑢𐑱 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑰𐑛. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑲 𐑨𐑥 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑪𐑯 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑓𐑹𐑗𐑵𐑯𐑟, 𐑯 𐑨𐑥 𐑒𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑦𐑓 𐑞 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛 𐑦𐑟 𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑦 𐑑 𐑚𐑹𐑛 𐑯 𐑤𐑪𐑡 𐑥𐑰, 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑲 𐑨𐑥 𐑐𐑫𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑳𐑐 𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑜𐑮𐑦𐑥 𐑕𐑲𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑔𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 ·𐑒𐑤𐑬𐑛. 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑣𐑴𐑤, 𐑲 𐑔𐑷𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 275𐑔 𐑤𐑱 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑚𐑰 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑞 𐑓𐑺 𐑔𐑦𐑙, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑕𐑼𐑐𐑮𐑲𐑟𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑲 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑪𐑓𐑼𐑛 𐑞 200𐑔, 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑲 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑝 𐑩 𐑚𐑮𐑷𐑛-𐑖𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑼𐑛 𐑥𐑱𐑒.

𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑔𐑦𐑙, 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼𐑞𐑩𐑤𐑧𐑕, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑥𐑰 𐑩 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑕𐑑𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑰𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑕 𐑖𐑺 𐑝 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑓𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞𐑦𐑕: 𐑩𐑖𐑹, 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑣𐑻𐑛 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑚𐑴𐑔 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 ·𐑐𐑰𐑤𐑧𐑜 𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑳𐑯𐑩𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑒𐑮𐑴𐑯𐑦 ·𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑛𐑨𐑛; 𐑣𐑬 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑱 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑐𐑩𐑤 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑐𐑮𐑲𐑩𐑑𐑼𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛, 𐑞𐑺𐑓𐑹 𐑞 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑯 𐑥𐑹 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑼𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑯 𐑕𐑒𐑨𐑑𐑼𐑛 𐑴𐑯𐑼𐑟, 𐑤𐑧𐑓𐑑 𐑯𐑽𐑤𐑦 𐑞 𐑣𐑴𐑤 𐑥𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑡𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐'𐑕 𐑩𐑓𐑺𐑟 𐑑 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑑𐑵. 𐑯 𐑲 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑯𐑴 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑡𐑦 𐑴𐑤𐑛 ·𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑛𐑨𐑛 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑩 𐑥𐑲𐑑𐑦 𐑛𐑰𐑤 𐑑 𐑕𐑱 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟, 𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑨𐑟 𐑲 𐑯𐑬 𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑪𐑯 𐑚𐑹𐑛 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛, 𐑒𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑴𐑥 𐑞𐑺 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑒𐑨𐑚𐑦𐑯, 𐑯 𐑮𐑰𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 ·𐑚𐑲𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑓 𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑴𐑯 𐑓𐑲𐑼𐑕𐑲𐑛. 𐑯𐑬 𐑢𐑲𐑤 ·𐑐𐑰𐑤𐑧𐑜 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑝𐑱𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑩 𐑐𐑧𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑡𐑨𐑒-𐑯𐑲𐑓, 𐑴𐑤𐑛 ·𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑛𐑨𐑛, 𐑑 𐑥𐑲 𐑯𐑴 𐑕𐑥𐑷𐑤 𐑕𐑼𐑐𐑮𐑲𐑟, 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑩𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑐𐑸𐑑𐑦 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑐𐑮𐑴𐑕𐑰𐑛𐑦𐑙𐑟; ·𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑛𐑨𐑛 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑣𐑰𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑳𐑕, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑪𐑯 𐑥𐑳𐑥𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑫𐑒, “𐑤𐑱 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑳𐑐 𐑓 𐑘𐑹𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑝𐑟 𐑑𐑮𐑧𐑠𐑼𐑟 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑻𐑔, 𐑢𐑺 𐑥𐑪𐑔—”

“𐑢𐑧𐑤, ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 ·𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑛𐑨𐑛,” 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑳𐑐𐑑𐑩𐑛 ·𐑐𐑰𐑤𐑧𐑜, “𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑛'𐑘𐑰 𐑕𐑱, 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑤𐑱 𐑖𐑨𐑤 𐑢𐑰 𐑜𐑦𐑝 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑘𐑳𐑙 𐑥𐑨𐑯?”

“𐑞𐑬 𐑯𐑴𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑧𐑕𐑑,” 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞 𐑕𐑧𐑐𐑩𐑤𐑒𐑮𐑩𐑤 𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑤𐑲, “𐑞 𐑕𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑛 𐑯 𐑕𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑦-𐑕𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑯𐑔 𐑢𐑫𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑑𐑵 𐑥𐑳𐑗, 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑦𐑑?—'𐑢𐑺 𐑥𐑪𐑔 𐑯 𐑮𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑛𐑵 𐑒𐑼𐑳𐑐𐑑, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑤𐑱—'”

𐑤𐑱, 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑰𐑛, 𐑔𐑷𐑑 𐑲, 𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩 𐑤𐑱! 𐑞 𐑕𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑛 𐑯 𐑕𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑦-𐑕𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑯𐑔! 𐑢𐑧𐑤, 𐑴𐑤𐑛 ·𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑛𐑨𐑛, 𐑿 𐑸 𐑛𐑦𐑑𐑻𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑲, 𐑓 𐑢𐑳𐑯, 𐑖𐑨𐑤 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑤𐑱 𐑳𐑐 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑤𐑱𐑟 𐑣𐑽 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑴, 𐑢𐑺 𐑥𐑪𐑔 𐑯 𐑮𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑛𐑵 𐑒𐑼𐑳𐑐𐑑. 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑰𐑛𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑤𐑱 𐑞𐑨𐑑, 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑰𐑛; 𐑯 𐑞𐑴 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑥𐑨𐑜𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑿𐑛 𐑝 𐑞 𐑓𐑦𐑜𐑼 𐑦𐑑 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑰𐑝 𐑩 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟𐑥𐑩𐑯, 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑤𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑼𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑖𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑴 𐑕𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑛 𐑯 𐑕𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑦-𐑕𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑟 𐑩 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑤𐑸𐑡 𐑯𐑳𐑥𐑚𐑼, 𐑘𐑧𐑑, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑿 𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑑 𐑥𐑱𐑒 𐑩 𐑑𐑰𐑯𐑔 𐑝 𐑦𐑑, 𐑿 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑕𐑰, 𐑲 𐑕𐑱, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑛 𐑯 𐑕𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑦-𐑕𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑯𐑔 𐑐𐑸𐑑 𐑝 𐑩 𐑓𐑸𐑞𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑟 𐑩 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑛𐑰𐑤 𐑤𐑧𐑕 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑕𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑛 𐑯 𐑕𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑦-𐑕𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑜𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑛𐑳𐑚𐑤𐑵𐑯𐑟; 𐑯 𐑕𐑴 𐑲 𐑔𐑷𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑑𐑲𐑥.

“𐑢𐑲, 𐑚𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑘𐑹 𐑲𐑟, ·𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑛𐑨𐑛,” 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 ·𐑐𐑰𐑤𐑧𐑜, “𐑞𐑬 𐑛𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑯𐑑 𐑑 𐑕𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑤 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑘𐑳𐑙 𐑥𐑨𐑯! 𐑣𐑰 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑥𐑹 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑.”

“𐑕𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑛 𐑯 𐑕𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑦-𐑕𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑯𐑔,” 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯 𐑕𐑧𐑛 ·𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑛𐑨𐑛, 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑 𐑤𐑦𐑓𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑲𐑟; 𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑪𐑯 𐑥𐑳𐑥𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙—“𐑓 𐑢𐑺 𐑘𐑹 𐑑𐑮𐑧𐑠𐑼 𐑦𐑟, 𐑞𐑺 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑘𐑹 𐑣𐑸𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑷𐑤𐑕𐑴.”

“𐑲 𐑨𐑥 𐑜𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑐𐑫𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑓 𐑞 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑛𐑔,” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 ·𐑐𐑰𐑤𐑧𐑜, “𐑛𐑵 𐑘𐑰 𐑣𐑽 𐑞𐑨𐑑, ·𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑛𐑨𐑛! 𐑞 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑛𐑔 𐑤𐑱, 𐑲 𐑕𐑱.”

·𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑛𐑨𐑛 𐑤𐑱𐑛 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑫𐑒, 𐑯 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑪𐑤𐑩𐑥𐑤𐑦 𐑑𐑩𐑢𐑹𐑛𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑕𐑧𐑛, “𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 ·𐑐𐑰𐑤𐑧𐑜, 𐑞𐑬 𐑣𐑨𐑕𐑑 𐑩 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑕 𐑣𐑸𐑑; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞𐑬 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑼 𐑞 𐑛𐑿𐑑𐑦 𐑞𐑬 𐑴𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑑 𐑞 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑴𐑯𐑼𐑟 𐑝 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑖𐑦𐑐—𐑢𐑦𐑛𐑴𐑟 𐑯 𐑹𐑓𐑩𐑯𐑟, 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑝 𐑞𐑧𐑥—𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑓 𐑢𐑰 𐑑𐑵 𐑩𐑚𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑦𐑢𐑹𐑛 𐑞 𐑤𐑱𐑚𐑼𐑟 𐑝 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑘𐑳𐑙 𐑥𐑨𐑯, 𐑢𐑰 𐑥𐑱 𐑚𐑰 𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑚𐑮𐑧𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑛𐑴𐑟 𐑯 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑹𐑓𐑩𐑯𐑟. 𐑞 𐑕𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑛 𐑯 𐑕𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑦-𐑕𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑯𐑔 𐑤𐑱, ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 ·𐑐𐑰𐑤𐑧𐑜.”

“𐑞𐑬 ·𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑛𐑨𐑛!” 𐑮𐑹𐑛 ·𐑐𐑰𐑤𐑧𐑜, 𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑳𐑐 𐑯 𐑒𐑤𐑨𐑑𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑞 𐑒𐑨𐑚𐑦𐑯. “𐑚𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑘𐑰, ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 ·𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑛𐑨𐑛, 𐑦𐑓 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑓𐑪𐑤𐑴𐑛 𐑞𐑲 𐑩𐑛𐑝𐑲𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑥𐑨𐑑𐑼𐑟, 𐑲 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑩𐑓𐑹 𐑯𐑬 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑩 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑑 𐑤𐑳𐑜 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑚𐑰 𐑣𐑧𐑝𐑦 𐑦𐑯𐑳𐑓 𐑑 𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑞 𐑤𐑸𐑡𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑛 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 ·𐑒𐑱𐑐 ·𐑣𐑹𐑯.”

“𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 ·𐑐𐑰𐑤𐑧𐑜,” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 ·𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑛𐑨𐑛 𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑦, “𐑞𐑲 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑥𐑱 𐑚𐑰 𐑛𐑮𐑷𐑦𐑙 𐑑𐑧𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑗𐑩𐑟 𐑝 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼, 𐑹 𐑑𐑧𐑯 𐑓𐑨𐑞𐑩𐑥𐑟, 𐑲 𐑒𐑭𐑯𐑑 𐑑𐑧𐑤; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑞𐑬 𐑸𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑥𐑨𐑯, ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 ·𐑐𐑰𐑤𐑧𐑜, 𐑲 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑓𐑽 𐑤𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑞𐑲 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑚𐑰 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑩 𐑤𐑰𐑒𐑦 𐑢𐑳𐑯; 𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑕𐑦𐑙𐑒 𐑞𐑰 𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑑 𐑞 𐑓𐑲𐑼𐑦 𐑐𐑦𐑑, ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 ·𐑐𐑰𐑤𐑧𐑜.”

“𐑓𐑲𐑼𐑦 𐑐𐑦𐑑! 𐑓𐑲𐑼𐑦 𐑐𐑦𐑑! 𐑘𐑰 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑳𐑤𐑑 𐑥𐑰, 𐑥𐑨𐑯; 𐑐𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑯𐑨𐑗𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑚𐑺𐑦𐑙, 𐑘𐑰 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑳𐑤𐑑 𐑥𐑰. 𐑦𐑑'𐑕 𐑩𐑯 𐑷𐑤-𐑓𐑲𐑼𐑛 𐑬𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑡 𐑑 𐑑𐑧𐑤 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑣𐑿𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑒𐑮𐑰𐑗𐑼 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑰'𐑟 𐑚𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑑 𐑣𐑧𐑤. 𐑓𐑤𐑵𐑒𐑕 𐑯 𐑓𐑤𐑱𐑥𐑟! ·𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑛𐑨𐑛, 𐑕𐑱 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯 𐑑 𐑥𐑰, 𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑑 𐑥𐑲 𐑕𐑴𐑤-𐑚𐑴𐑤𐑑𐑕, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑲'𐑤—𐑲'𐑤—𐑘𐑧𐑕, 𐑲'𐑤 𐑕𐑢𐑪𐑤𐑴 𐑩 𐑤𐑲𐑝 𐑜𐑴𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑷𐑤 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑺 𐑯 𐑣𐑹𐑯𐑟 𐑪𐑯. 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑒𐑨𐑚𐑦𐑯, 𐑘𐑰 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑙, 𐑛𐑮𐑨𐑚-𐑒𐑳𐑤𐑼𐑛 𐑕𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑩 𐑢𐑫𐑛𐑩𐑯 𐑜𐑳𐑯—𐑩 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑒 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑘𐑰!”

𐑨𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑔𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑛 𐑬𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑣𐑰 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑩 𐑮𐑳𐑖 𐑨𐑑 ·𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑛𐑨𐑛, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑥𐑸𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑴𐑚𐑤𐑰𐑒, 𐑕𐑤𐑲𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑩𐑤𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑦, ·𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑛𐑨𐑛 𐑓 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑦𐑤𐑵𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥.

𐑩𐑤𐑸𐑥𐑛 𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑑𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑬𐑑𐑚𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑢𐑰𐑯 𐑞 𐑑𐑵 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑐𐑩𐑤 𐑯 𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑴𐑯𐑼𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐, 𐑯 𐑓𐑰𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑭𐑓 𐑩 𐑥𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑑 𐑜𐑦𐑝 𐑳𐑐 𐑷𐑤 𐑲𐑛𐑾 𐑝 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑝𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑴 𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑕𐑗𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑴𐑯𐑛 𐑯 𐑑𐑧𐑥𐑐𐑼𐑺𐑦𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑭𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛, 𐑲 𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑐𐑑 𐑩𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑛𐑹 𐑑 𐑜𐑦𐑝 𐑰𐑜𐑮𐑧𐑕 𐑑 ·𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑛𐑨𐑛, 𐑣𐑵, 𐑲 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑯𐑴 𐑛𐑬𐑑, 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑷𐑤 𐑰𐑜𐑼𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑑 𐑝𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑖 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑞 𐑩𐑢𐑱𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑮𐑪𐑔 𐑝 ·𐑐𐑰𐑤𐑧𐑜. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑑 𐑥𐑲 𐑩𐑕𐑑𐑪𐑯𐑦𐑖𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑, 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑨𐑑 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑥 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑒𐑢𐑲𐑩𐑑𐑤𐑦, 𐑯 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑤𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑛𐑮𐑷𐑦𐑙. 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑒𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑿𐑟𐑛 𐑑 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑 ·𐑐𐑰𐑤𐑧𐑜 𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑱𐑟. 𐑨𐑟 𐑓 ·𐑐𐑰𐑤𐑧𐑜, 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑤𐑧𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑪𐑓 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑮𐑱𐑡 𐑨𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛, 𐑞𐑺 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑯𐑴 𐑥𐑹 𐑤𐑧𐑓𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑯 𐑣𐑰, 𐑑𐑵, 𐑕𐑨𐑑 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑤𐑨𐑥, 𐑞𐑴 𐑣𐑰 𐑑𐑢𐑦𐑗𐑑 𐑩 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑓 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑯𐑻𐑝𐑩𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑨𐑡𐑦𐑑𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛. “𐑓𐑿!” 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑦𐑕𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑—“𐑞 𐑕𐑒𐑢𐑷𐑤'𐑟 𐑜𐑪𐑯 𐑪𐑓 𐑑 𐑤𐑰𐑢𐑼𐑛, 𐑲 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒. ·𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑛𐑨𐑛, 𐑞𐑬 𐑿𐑟𐑛 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑨𐑑 𐑖𐑸𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑕, 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑐𐑧𐑯, 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑘𐑰. 𐑥𐑲 𐑡𐑨𐑒-𐑯𐑲𐑓 𐑣𐑽 𐑯𐑰𐑛𐑟 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑲𐑯𐑛𐑕𐑑𐑴𐑯. 𐑞𐑨𐑑'𐑕 𐑣𐑰; 𐑔𐑨𐑙𐑒 𐑘𐑰, ·𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑛𐑨𐑛. 𐑯𐑬 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑥𐑲 𐑘𐑳𐑙 𐑥𐑨𐑯, ·𐑦𐑖𐑥𐑱𐑩𐑤'𐑟 𐑞𐑲 𐑯𐑱𐑥, 𐑛𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑘𐑰 𐑕𐑱? 𐑢𐑧𐑤 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑘𐑰 𐑜𐑴 𐑣𐑽, ·𐑦𐑖𐑥𐑱𐑩𐑤, 𐑓 𐑞 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑛𐑔 𐑤𐑱.”

“𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 ·𐑐𐑰𐑤𐑧𐑜,” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑲, “𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑩 𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑥𐑰 𐑣𐑵 𐑢𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑑 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑑𐑵—𐑖𐑨𐑤 𐑲 𐑚𐑮𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑑-𐑥𐑪𐑮𐑴?”

“𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑖𐑫𐑼,” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 ·𐑐𐑰𐑤𐑧𐑜. “𐑓𐑧𐑗 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑙, 𐑯 𐑢𐑰'𐑤 𐑤𐑫𐑒 𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥.”

“𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑤𐑱 𐑛𐑳𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑯𐑑?” 𐑜𐑮𐑴𐑯𐑛 ·𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑛𐑨𐑛, 𐑜𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑳𐑐 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑚𐑫𐑒 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑚𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓.

“𐑴! 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑞𐑰 𐑥𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑, ·𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑛𐑨𐑛,” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 ·𐑐𐑰𐑤𐑧𐑜. “𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑛 𐑦𐑑 𐑧𐑯𐑦?” 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑥𐑰.

“𐑒𐑦𐑤𐑛 𐑥𐑹 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑲 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑, ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 ·𐑐𐑰𐑤𐑧𐑜.”

“𐑢𐑧𐑤, 𐑚𐑮𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑞𐑧𐑯.”

𐑯, 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑕𐑲𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑐𐑱𐑐𐑼𐑟, 𐑪𐑓 𐑲 𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑑; 𐑯𐑳𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑛𐑬𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑛𐑳𐑯 𐑩 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑥𐑹𐑯𐑦𐑙'𐑟 𐑢𐑻𐑒, 𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞 𐑲𐑛𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑞𐑨𐑑 ·𐑘𐑴𐑡𐑴 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑝𐑲𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑑 𐑒𐑨𐑮𐑦 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜 𐑯 𐑥𐑰 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑞 ·𐑒𐑱𐑐.

𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑴𐑕𐑰𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑓𐑸, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑲 𐑚𐑦𐑜𐑨𐑯 𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒 𐑥𐑰 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑵𐑥 𐑲 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑑 𐑕𐑱𐑤 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑱𐑯𐑛 𐑳𐑯𐑕𐑰𐑯 𐑚𐑲 𐑥𐑰; 𐑞𐑴, 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑰𐑛, 𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑒𐑱𐑕𐑩𐑟, 𐑩 𐑢𐑱𐑤-𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑚𐑰 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑰𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑓𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑬𐑑, 𐑯 𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑰𐑝 𐑷𐑤 𐑣𐑻 𐑒𐑮𐑵 𐑪𐑯 𐑚𐑹𐑛, 𐑺 𐑞 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑱𐑒𐑕 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑝𐑦𐑟𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑚𐑲 𐑼𐑲𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑭𐑯𐑛; 𐑓 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑝𐑶𐑦𐑡𐑩𐑟 𐑸 𐑕𐑴 𐑐𐑮𐑴𐑤𐑪𐑙𐑛, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑖𐑹 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑴𐑥 𐑕𐑴 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑰𐑛𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑮𐑰𐑓, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑓 𐑞 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑩 𐑓𐑨𐑥𐑤𐑦, 𐑹 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑩𐑚𐑕𐑹𐑚𐑦𐑙 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑻𐑯𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑹𐑑, 𐑣𐑰 𐑛𐑳𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑦𐑯 𐑐𐑹𐑑, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑤𐑰𐑝𐑟 𐑣𐑻 𐑑 𐑞 𐑴𐑯𐑼𐑟 𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑷𐑤 𐑦𐑟 𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑦 𐑓 𐑕𐑰. 𐑣𐑬𐑧𐑝𐑼, 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑷𐑤𐑢𐑱𐑟 𐑨𐑟 𐑢𐑧𐑤 𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑩 𐑤𐑫𐑒 𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑦𐑮𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑒𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑘𐑹𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟. 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑨𐑒 𐑲 𐑩𐑒𐑪𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 ·𐑐𐑰𐑤𐑧𐑜, 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑢𐑲𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑺 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛.

“𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑛𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑞𐑬 𐑢𐑪𐑯𐑑 𐑝 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚? 𐑦𐑑'𐑕 𐑷𐑤 𐑮𐑲𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑳𐑓; 𐑞𐑬 𐑸𐑑 𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑑.”

“𐑘𐑧𐑕, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑲 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑑 𐑕𐑰 𐑣𐑦𐑥.”

“𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑲 𐑛𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒 𐑞𐑬 𐑢𐑦𐑤𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑱𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑑. 𐑲 𐑛𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑯𐑴 𐑦𐑜𐑟𐑨𐑒𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑢𐑪𐑑'𐑕 𐑞 𐑥𐑨𐑑𐑼 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑥; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑰𐑐𐑕 𐑒𐑤𐑴𐑕 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑞 𐑣𐑬𐑕; 𐑩 𐑕𐑹𐑑 𐑝 𐑕𐑦𐑒, 𐑯 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑛𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑤𐑫𐑒 𐑕𐑴. 𐑦𐑯 𐑓𐑨𐑒𐑑, 𐑣𐑰 𐑱𐑯𐑑 𐑕𐑦𐑒; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑯𐑴, 𐑣𐑰 𐑦𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑢𐑧𐑤 𐑲𐑞𐑼. 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑣𐑬, 𐑘𐑳𐑙 𐑥𐑨𐑯, 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑷𐑤𐑢𐑱𐑟 𐑕𐑰 𐑥𐑰, 𐑕𐑴 𐑲 𐑛𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑕𐑩𐑐𐑴𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑞𐑰. 𐑣𐑰'𐑟 𐑩 𐑒𐑢𐑽 𐑥𐑨𐑯, ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚—𐑕𐑴 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒—𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑩 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑢𐑳𐑯. 𐑴, 𐑞𐑬'𐑤𐑑 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑢𐑧𐑤 𐑦𐑯𐑳𐑓; 𐑯𐑴 𐑓𐑽, 𐑯𐑴 𐑓𐑽. 𐑣𐑰'𐑟 𐑩 𐑜𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑛, 𐑳𐑯𐑜𐑪𐑛𐑤𐑦, 𐑜𐑪𐑛-𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑥𐑨𐑯, ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚; 𐑛𐑳𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑒 𐑥𐑳𐑗; 𐑚𐑳𐑑, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑣𐑰 𐑛𐑳𐑟 𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑒, 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑿 𐑥𐑱 𐑢𐑧𐑤 𐑤𐑦𐑕𐑩𐑯. 𐑥𐑸𐑒 𐑘𐑰, 𐑚𐑰 𐑓𐑹𐑢𐑹𐑯𐑛; ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚'𐑟 𐑩𐑚𐑳𐑝 𐑞 𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑯; ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚'𐑟 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑒𐑪𐑤𐑦𐑡𐑩𐑟, 𐑨𐑟 𐑢𐑧𐑤 𐑨𐑟 '𐑥𐑪𐑙 𐑞 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑟; 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑿𐑟𐑛 𐑑 𐑛𐑰𐑐𐑼 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑝𐑟; 𐑓𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑲𐑼𐑦 𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑲𐑑𐑽, 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑼 𐑓𐑴𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟. 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑕! 𐑲, 𐑞 𐑒𐑰𐑯𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑯 𐑞 𐑖𐑫𐑼𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑷𐑤 𐑬𐑼 𐑲𐑤! 𐑴! 𐑣𐑰 𐑱𐑯𐑑 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 ·𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑛𐑨𐑛; 𐑯𐑴, 𐑯 𐑣𐑰 𐑱𐑯𐑑 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 ·𐑐𐑰𐑤𐑧𐑜; 𐑣𐑰'𐑟 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚, 𐑚𐑶; 𐑯 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑝 𐑴𐑤𐑛, 𐑞𐑬 𐑯𐑴𐑩𐑕𐑑, 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩 𐑒𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑒𐑦𐑙!”

“𐑯 𐑩 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑝𐑲𐑤 𐑢𐑳𐑯. 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑒𐑑 𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑤𐑱𐑯, 𐑞 𐑛𐑪𐑜𐑟, 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑞𐑱 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑤𐑦𐑒 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑤𐑳𐑛?”

“𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑣𐑦𐑞𐑼 𐑑 𐑥𐑰—𐑣𐑦𐑞𐑼, 𐑣𐑦𐑞𐑼,” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 ·𐑐𐑰𐑤𐑧𐑜, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑕𐑦𐑜𐑯𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑲 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑥𐑰. “𐑤𐑫𐑒 𐑘𐑰, 𐑤𐑨𐑛; 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑕𐑱 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑪𐑯 𐑚𐑹𐑛 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛. 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑕𐑱 𐑦𐑑 𐑧𐑯𐑦𐑢𐑺. 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑯𐑱𐑥 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓. '𐑑𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩 𐑓𐑵𐑤𐑦𐑖, 𐑦𐑜𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑥 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑮𐑱𐑟𐑦, 𐑢𐑦𐑛𐑴𐑛 𐑥𐑳𐑞𐑼, 𐑣𐑵 𐑛𐑲𐑛 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑩 𐑑𐑢𐑧𐑤𐑝𐑥𐑳𐑯𐑔 𐑴𐑤𐑛. 𐑯 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑞 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑕𐑒𐑢𐑷 ·𐑑𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑜, 𐑨𐑑 ·𐑜𐑱𐑣𐑧𐑛, 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑯𐑱𐑥 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑣𐑬 𐑐𐑮𐑵𐑝 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑓𐑧𐑑𐑦𐑒. 𐑯, 𐑐𐑼𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑕, 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑓𐑵𐑤𐑟 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑣𐑻 𐑥𐑱 𐑑𐑧𐑤 𐑞𐑰 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥. 𐑲 𐑢𐑦𐑖 𐑑 𐑢𐑹𐑯 𐑞𐑰. 𐑦𐑑'𐑕 𐑩 𐑤𐑲. 𐑲 𐑯𐑴 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑢𐑧𐑤; 𐑲'𐑝 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑨𐑟 𐑥𐑱𐑑 𐑘𐑽𐑟 𐑩𐑜𐑴; 𐑲 𐑯𐑴 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑦𐑟—𐑩 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑥𐑨𐑯—𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑩 𐑐𐑲𐑩𐑕, 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑥𐑨𐑯, 𐑤𐑲𐑒 ·𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑛𐑨𐑛, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑩 𐑕𐑢𐑺𐑦𐑙 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑥𐑨𐑯—𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑥𐑰—𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑞𐑺'𐑟 𐑩 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑛𐑰𐑤 𐑥𐑹 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑥. 𐑲, 𐑲, 𐑲 𐑯𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑡𐑪𐑤𐑦; 𐑯 𐑲 𐑯𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑐𐑨𐑕𐑦𐑡 𐑣𐑴𐑥, 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑓 𐑩 𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑤; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞 𐑖𐑸𐑐 𐑖𐑵𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑐𐑱𐑯𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑤𐑰𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑥𐑐 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑚𐑮𐑷𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑, 𐑨𐑟 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑕𐑰. 𐑲 𐑯𐑴, 𐑑𐑵, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑕𐑦𐑯𐑕 𐑣𐑰 𐑤𐑪𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑤𐑧𐑜 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑝𐑶𐑦𐑡 𐑚𐑲 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑩𐑒𐑻𐑕𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑣𐑰'𐑟 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑩 𐑒𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑝 𐑥𐑵𐑛𐑦—𐑛𐑧𐑕𐑐𐑼𐑩𐑑 𐑥𐑵𐑛𐑦, 𐑯 𐑕𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑡 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑷𐑤 𐑐𐑭𐑕 𐑪𐑓. 𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑕 𐑓 𐑷𐑤, 𐑤𐑧𐑑 𐑥𐑰 𐑑𐑧𐑤 𐑞𐑰 𐑯 𐑩𐑖𐑫𐑼 𐑞𐑰, 𐑘𐑳𐑙 𐑥𐑨𐑯, 𐑦𐑑'𐑕 𐑚𐑧𐑑𐑼 𐑑 𐑕𐑱𐑤 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑥𐑵𐑛𐑦 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑩 𐑤𐑭𐑓𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑨𐑛 𐑢𐑳𐑯. 𐑕𐑴 𐑜𐑫𐑛-𐑚𐑲 𐑑 𐑞𐑰—𐑯 𐑮𐑪𐑙 𐑯𐑪𐑑 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚, 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑪𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑩 𐑢𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑛 𐑯𐑱𐑥. 𐑚𐑦𐑕𐑲𐑛𐑟, 𐑥𐑲 𐑚𐑶, 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑩 𐑢𐑲𐑓—𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑝𐑶𐑦𐑡𐑩𐑟 𐑢𐑧𐑛𐑩𐑛—𐑩 𐑕𐑢𐑰𐑑, 𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑜𐑻𐑤. 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒 𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑; 𐑚𐑲 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑢𐑰𐑑 𐑜𐑻𐑤 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑩 𐑗𐑲𐑤𐑛: 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑘𐑰 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑚𐑰 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑳𐑑𐑼, 𐑣𐑴𐑐𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑣𐑸𐑥 𐑦𐑯 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚? 𐑯𐑴, 𐑯𐑴, 𐑥𐑲 𐑤𐑨𐑛; 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑯, 𐑚𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛, 𐑦𐑓 𐑣𐑰 𐑚𐑰, ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑿𐑥𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑟!”

𐑨𐑟 𐑲 𐑢𐑷𐑒𐑑 𐑩𐑢𐑱, 𐑲 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑓𐑫𐑤 𐑝 𐑔𐑷𐑑𐑓𐑩𐑤𐑯𐑩𐑕; 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑦𐑝𐑰𐑤𐑛 𐑑 𐑥𐑰 𐑝 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚, 𐑓𐑦𐑤𐑛 𐑥𐑰 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑲𐑤𐑛 𐑝𐑱𐑜𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑐𐑱𐑯𐑓𐑩𐑤𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑥. 𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑣𐑬, 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑑𐑲𐑥, 𐑲 𐑓𐑧𐑤𐑑 𐑩 𐑕𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑔𐑦 𐑯 𐑩 𐑕𐑪𐑮𐑴 𐑓 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑓 𐑲 𐑛𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑯𐑴 𐑢𐑪𐑑, 𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑧𐑕 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑵𐑩𐑤 𐑤𐑪𐑕 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑤𐑧𐑜. 𐑯 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑲 𐑷𐑤𐑕𐑴 𐑓𐑧𐑤𐑑 𐑩 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡 𐑷 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑥; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑹𐑑 𐑝 𐑷, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑲 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑚, 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑦𐑜𐑟𐑨𐑒𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑷; 𐑲 𐑛𐑵 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑯𐑴 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑲 𐑓𐑧𐑤𐑑 𐑦𐑑; 𐑯 𐑦𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑤𐑲𐑯 𐑥𐑰 𐑑𐑩𐑢𐑹𐑛𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑥; 𐑞𐑴 𐑲 𐑓𐑧𐑤𐑑 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑦 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑕𐑴 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑻𐑓𐑦𐑒𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑨𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑴𐑯 𐑑 𐑥𐑰 𐑞𐑧𐑯. 𐑣𐑬𐑧𐑝𐑼, 𐑥𐑲 𐑔𐑷𐑑𐑕 𐑢𐑻 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑧𐑙𐑔 𐑒𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑛𐑦𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟, 𐑕𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑓 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑛𐑸𐑒 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑕𐑤𐑦𐑐𐑑 𐑥𐑲 𐑥𐑲𐑯𐑛.

·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 17. 𐑞 ·𐑮𐑭𐑥𐑩𐑛𐑭𐑯.

𐑨𐑟 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜'𐑟 ·𐑮𐑭𐑥𐑩𐑛𐑭𐑯, 𐑹 ·𐑓𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑯 ·𐑣𐑿𐑥𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯, 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑑 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑿 𐑷𐑤 𐑛𐑱, 𐑲 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑗𐑵𐑟 𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑻𐑚 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑑𐑩𐑢𐑹𐑛𐑟 𐑯𐑲𐑑-𐑓𐑷𐑤; 𐑓 𐑲 𐑗𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑖 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑 𐑑𐑩𐑢𐑹𐑛𐑟 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦'𐑟 𐑮𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑡𐑩𐑕 𐑪𐑚𐑤𐑦𐑜𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟, 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑥𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑣𐑬 𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤, 𐑯 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑓𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑲 𐑣𐑸𐑑 𐑑 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑝𐑨𐑤𐑿 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑩 𐑒𐑪𐑙𐑜𐑮𐑦𐑜𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑢𐑻𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑑𐑴𐑛-𐑕𐑑𐑵𐑤; 𐑹 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑒𐑮𐑰𐑗𐑼𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑐𐑸𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑬𐑼 𐑻𐑔, 𐑣𐑵 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑛𐑦𐑜𐑮𐑰 𐑝 𐑓𐑫𐑑𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑟𐑩𐑥 𐑒𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑳𐑯𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑐𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑩𐑑𐑕, 𐑚𐑬 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑞 𐑑𐑹𐑕𐑴 𐑝 𐑩 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑰𐑕𐑑 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑐𐑮𐑲𐑩𐑑𐑼 𐑥𐑽𐑤𐑦 𐑪𐑯 𐑩𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑹𐑛𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑑 𐑐𐑩𐑟𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑴𐑯𐑛 𐑯 𐑮𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑱𐑥.

𐑲 𐑕𐑱, 𐑢𐑰 𐑜𐑫𐑛 ·𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑟𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑽𐑾𐑯 ·𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑗𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑚𐑰 𐑗𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑟, 𐑯 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑓𐑨𐑯𐑕𐑦 𐑬𐑼𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑝𐑟 𐑕𐑴 𐑝𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑵𐑐𐑽𐑽 𐑑 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑥𐑹𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑟, 𐑐𐑱𐑜𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑑, 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑪𐑟 𐑝 𐑞𐑺 𐑣𐑭𐑓-𐑒𐑮𐑱𐑟𐑦 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑰𐑑𐑕 𐑪𐑯 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑕𐑳𐑚𐑡𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑕. 𐑞𐑺 𐑢𐑪𐑟 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜, 𐑯𐑬, 𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑑𐑱𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑩𐑚𐑕𐑻𐑛 𐑯𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 ·𐑘𐑴𐑡𐑴 𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 ·𐑮𐑭𐑥𐑩𐑛𐑭𐑯;—𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑? ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜 𐑔𐑷𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑯𐑿 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑, 𐑲 𐑕𐑩𐑐𐑴𐑟; 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑑; 𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑤𐑧𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑑. 𐑷𐑤 𐑬𐑼 𐑸𐑜𐑿𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑩𐑝𐑱𐑤; 𐑤𐑧𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑚𐑰, 𐑲 𐑕𐑱: 𐑯 ·𐑣𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑥𐑻𐑕𐑦 𐑪𐑯 𐑳𐑕 𐑷𐑤—·𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑟𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑽𐑾𐑯𐑟 𐑯 ·𐑐𐑱𐑜𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑩𐑤𐑲𐑒—𐑓 𐑢𐑰 𐑸 𐑷𐑤 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑣𐑬 𐑛𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑓𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑮𐑨𐑒𐑑 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑞 𐑣𐑧𐑛, 𐑯 𐑕𐑨𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑯𐑰𐑛 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙.

𐑑𐑩𐑢𐑹𐑛𐑟 𐑰𐑝𐑯𐑦𐑙, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑲 𐑓𐑧𐑤𐑑 𐑩𐑖𐑫𐑼𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑼𐑓𐑹𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑯 𐑮𐑦𐑗𐑵𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑴𐑝𐑼, 𐑲 𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑳𐑐 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑮𐑵𐑥 𐑯 𐑯𐑪𐑒𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑛𐑹; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑯𐑴 𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑼. 𐑲 𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑛 𐑑 𐑴𐑐𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑑, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑓𐑭𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑲𐑛. “·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜,” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑲 𐑕𐑪𐑓𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑞 𐑒𐑰-𐑣𐑴𐑤:—𐑷𐑤 𐑕𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑑. “𐑲 𐑕𐑱, ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜! 𐑢𐑲 𐑛𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑿 𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑒? 𐑦𐑑'𐑕 𐑲—·𐑦𐑖𐑥𐑱𐑩𐑤.” 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑱𐑯𐑛 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑨𐑟 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹. 𐑲 𐑚𐑦𐑜𐑨𐑯 𐑑 𐑜𐑮𐑴 𐑩𐑤𐑸𐑥𐑛. 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑩𐑤𐑬𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩𐑚𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑑𐑲𐑥; 𐑲 𐑔𐑷𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑩𐑯 𐑨𐑐𐑩𐑐𐑤𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑓𐑦𐑑. 𐑲 𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑑 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑞 𐑒𐑰-𐑣𐑴𐑤; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞 𐑛𐑹 𐑴𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑩𐑯 𐑪𐑛 𐑒𐑹𐑯𐑼 𐑝 𐑞 𐑮𐑵𐑥, 𐑞 𐑒𐑰-𐑣𐑴𐑤 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑩 𐑒𐑮𐑫𐑒𐑩𐑛 𐑯 𐑕𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑼 𐑢𐑳𐑯. 𐑲 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑰 𐑐𐑸𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑓𐑫𐑑-𐑚𐑹𐑛 𐑝 𐑞 𐑚𐑧𐑛 𐑯 𐑩 𐑤𐑲𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑷𐑤, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑯𐑳𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑹. 𐑲 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑼𐑐𐑮𐑲𐑟𐑛 𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑞 𐑢𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑢𐑫𐑛𐑩𐑯 𐑖𐑭𐑓𐑑 𐑝 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜'𐑟 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑞 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑤𐑱𐑛𐑦 𐑞 𐑰𐑝𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑐𐑮𐑰𐑝𐑾𐑕 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑬𐑼 𐑥𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑞 𐑗𐑱𐑥𐑚𐑼. 𐑞𐑨𐑑'𐑕 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡, 𐑔𐑷𐑑 𐑲; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑮𐑱𐑑, 𐑕𐑦𐑯𐑕 𐑞 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑘𐑪𐑯𐑛𐑼, 𐑯 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑛𐑩𐑥 𐑹 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑜𐑴𐑟 𐑩𐑚𐑮𐑷𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑 𐑦𐑑, 𐑞𐑺𐑓𐑹 𐑣𐑰 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑣𐑽, 𐑯 𐑯𐑴 𐑐𐑪𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑒.

“·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜!—·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜!”—𐑷𐑤 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤. 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑛. 𐑨𐑐𐑩𐑐𐑤𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑦! 𐑲 𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑛 𐑑 𐑚𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑴𐑐𐑩𐑯 𐑞 𐑛𐑹; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚𐑼𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛. 𐑮𐑳𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑺𐑟, 𐑲 𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑥𐑲 𐑕𐑩𐑕𐑐𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑑 𐑞 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑐𐑻𐑕𐑩𐑯 𐑲 𐑥𐑧𐑑—𐑞 𐑗𐑱𐑥𐑚𐑼-𐑥𐑱𐑛. “𐑤𐑭! 𐑤𐑭!” 𐑖𐑰 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛, “𐑲 𐑔𐑷𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑞 𐑥𐑨𐑑𐑼. 𐑲 𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑑 𐑥𐑱𐑒 𐑞 𐑚𐑧𐑛 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑚𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑓𐑩𐑕𐑑, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑛𐑹 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑤𐑪𐑒𐑑; 𐑯 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑩 𐑥𐑬𐑕 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑣𐑻𐑛; 𐑯 𐑦𐑑'𐑕 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑡𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑴 𐑕𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑕𐑦𐑯𐑕. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑲 𐑔𐑷𐑑, 𐑥𐑱 𐑚𐑰, 𐑿 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑴𐑔 𐑜𐑪𐑯 𐑪𐑓 𐑯 𐑤𐑪𐑒𐑑 𐑘𐑹 𐑚𐑨𐑜𐑦𐑡 𐑦𐑯 𐑓 𐑕𐑱𐑓 𐑒𐑰𐑐𐑦𐑙. 𐑤𐑭! 𐑤𐑭, 𐑥𐑨𐑥!—𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑩𐑕! 𐑥𐑻𐑛𐑼! ·𐑥𐑕𐑟 ·𐑣𐑳𐑕𐑦! 𐑨𐑐𐑩𐑐𐑤𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑦!”—𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑟, 𐑖𐑰 𐑮𐑨𐑯 𐑑𐑩𐑢𐑹𐑛𐑟 𐑞 𐑒𐑦𐑗𐑦𐑯, 𐑲 𐑓𐑪𐑤𐑴𐑦𐑙.

·𐑥𐑕𐑟 ·𐑣𐑳𐑕𐑦 𐑕𐑵𐑯 𐑩𐑐𐑽𐑛, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑛-𐑐𐑪𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑯 𐑩 𐑝𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑜𐑼-𐑒𐑮𐑵𐑩𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑳𐑞𐑼, 𐑣𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑡𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑮𐑴𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑩𐑢𐑱 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑪𐑒𐑿𐑐𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑩𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑞 𐑒𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑟, 𐑯 𐑕𐑒𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑻 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑒 𐑚𐑶 𐑥𐑰𐑯𐑑𐑲𐑥.

“𐑢𐑫𐑛-𐑣𐑬𐑕!” 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 𐑲, “𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑢𐑱 𐑑 𐑦𐑑? 𐑮𐑳𐑯 𐑓 ·𐑜𐑪𐑛'𐑟 𐑕𐑱𐑒, 𐑯 𐑓𐑧𐑗 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑲 𐑴𐑐𐑩𐑯 𐑞 𐑛𐑹—𐑞 𐑨𐑒𐑕!—𐑞 𐑨𐑒𐑕! 𐑣𐑰'𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑩 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑴𐑒; 𐑛𐑦𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑦𐑑!”—𐑯 𐑕𐑴 𐑕𐑱𐑦𐑙 𐑲 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑳𐑯𐑥𐑦𐑔𐑪𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑳𐑖𐑦𐑙 𐑳𐑐 𐑕𐑑𐑺𐑟 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯 𐑧𐑥𐑐𐑑𐑦-𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 ·𐑥𐑕𐑟 ·𐑣𐑳𐑕𐑦 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑐𐑴𐑟𐑛 𐑞 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑛-𐑐𐑪𐑑 𐑯 𐑝𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑜𐑼-𐑒𐑮𐑵𐑩𐑑, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑲𐑼 𐑒𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑼 𐑝 𐑣𐑻 𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑯𐑕.

“𐑢𐑪𐑑'𐑕 𐑞 𐑥𐑨𐑑𐑼 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑿, 𐑘𐑳𐑙 𐑥𐑨𐑯?”

“𐑜𐑧𐑑 𐑞 𐑨𐑒𐑕! 𐑓 ·𐑜𐑪𐑛'𐑟 𐑕𐑱𐑒, 𐑮𐑳𐑯 𐑓 𐑞 𐑛𐑪𐑒𐑑𐑼, 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑢𐑳𐑯, 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑲 𐑐𐑮𐑲 𐑦𐑑 𐑴𐑐𐑩𐑯!”

“𐑤𐑫𐑒 𐑣𐑽,” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑞 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑤𐑱𐑛𐑦, 𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑫𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑞 𐑝𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑜𐑼-𐑒𐑮𐑵𐑩𐑑, 𐑕𐑴 𐑨𐑟 𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑰; “𐑤𐑫𐑒 𐑣𐑽; 𐑸 𐑿 𐑑𐑷𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑲𐑦𐑙 𐑴𐑐𐑩𐑯 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑝 𐑥𐑲 𐑛𐑹𐑟?”—𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑖𐑰 𐑕𐑰𐑟𐑛 𐑥𐑲 𐑸𐑥. “𐑢𐑪𐑑'𐑕 𐑞 𐑥𐑨𐑑𐑼 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑿? 𐑢𐑪𐑑'𐑕 𐑞 𐑥𐑨𐑑𐑼 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑿, 𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑥𐑱𐑑?”

𐑦𐑯 𐑨𐑟 𐑒𐑭𐑥, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑮𐑨𐑐𐑦𐑛 𐑩 𐑥𐑨𐑯𐑼 𐑨𐑟 𐑐𐑪𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤, 𐑲 𐑜𐑱𐑝 𐑣𐑻 𐑑 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑞 𐑣𐑴𐑤 𐑒𐑱𐑕. 𐑳𐑯𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑤𐑨𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑝𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑜𐑼-𐑒𐑮𐑵𐑩𐑑 𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑝 𐑣𐑻 𐑯𐑴𐑟, 𐑖𐑰 𐑮𐑵𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑓 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑; 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑒𐑤𐑱𐑥𐑛—“𐑯𐑴! 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑝𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑯 𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑦𐑯𐑕 𐑲 𐑐𐑫𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑞𐑺.” 𐑮𐑳𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑩 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑒𐑤𐑪𐑟𐑩𐑑 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑞 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑺𐑟, 𐑖𐑰 𐑜𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯, 𐑯 𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑙, 𐑑𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑥𐑰 𐑞𐑨𐑑 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜'𐑟 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑦𐑙. “𐑣𐑰'𐑟 𐑒𐑦𐑤𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓,” 𐑖𐑰 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛. “𐑦𐑑'𐑕 𐑳𐑯𐑓𐑹𐑑'𐑯𐑱𐑑 ·𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑜𐑟 𐑛𐑳𐑯 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯—𐑞𐑺 𐑜𐑴𐑟 𐑩𐑯𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑐𐑱𐑯—·𐑜𐑪𐑛 𐑐𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑫𐑼 𐑥𐑳𐑞𐑼!—𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑚𐑰 𐑞 𐑮𐑵𐑦𐑯 𐑝 𐑥𐑲 𐑣𐑬𐑕. 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑐𐑫𐑼 𐑤𐑨𐑛 𐑩 𐑕𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑼? 𐑢𐑺'𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑜𐑻𐑤?—𐑞𐑺, ·𐑚𐑧𐑑𐑦, 𐑜𐑴 𐑑 ·𐑕𐑥𐑸𐑤𐑕 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑱𐑯𐑑𐑼, 𐑯 𐑑𐑧𐑤 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑑 𐑐𐑱𐑯𐑑 𐑥𐑰 𐑩 𐑕𐑲𐑯, 𐑢𐑦𐑞—“𐑯𐑴 𐑕𐑵𐑦𐑕𐑲𐑛𐑟 𐑐𐑼𐑥𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑣𐑽, 𐑯 𐑯𐑴 𐑕𐑥𐑴𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑐𐑸𐑤𐑼;”—𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑢𐑧𐑤 𐑒𐑦𐑤 𐑚𐑴𐑔 𐑚𐑻𐑛𐑟 𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑕. 𐑒𐑦𐑤? 𐑞 ·𐑤𐑹𐑛 𐑚𐑰 𐑥𐑻𐑕𐑦𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑜𐑴𐑕𐑑! 𐑢𐑪𐑑'𐑕 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑯𐑶𐑟 𐑞𐑺? 𐑿, 𐑘𐑳𐑙 𐑥𐑨𐑯, 𐑩𐑝𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑞𐑺!”

𐑯 𐑮𐑳𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑳𐑐 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑥𐑰, 𐑖𐑰 𐑒𐑷𐑑 𐑥𐑰 𐑨𐑟 𐑲 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯 𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑓𐑹𐑕 𐑴𐑐𐑩𐑯 𐑞 𐑛𐑹.

“𐑲 𐑛𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑩𐑤𐑬 𐑦𐑑; 𐑲 𐑢𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑥𐑲 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑕𐑐𐑶𐑤𐑛. 𐑜𐑴 𐑓 𐑞 𐑤𐑪𐑒𐑕𐑥𐑦𐑔, 𐑞𐑺'𐑟 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑩 𐑥𐑲𐑤 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑣𐑽. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑩𐑝𐑭𐑕𐑑!” 𐑐𐑫𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑻 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑻 𐑕𐑲𐑛-𐑐𐑪𐑒𐑩𐑑, “𐑣𐑽'𐑟 𐑩 𐑒𐑰 𐑞𐑨𐑑'𐑤 𐑓𐑦𐑑, 𐑲 𐑜𐑧𐑕; 𐑤𐑧𐑑'𐑕 𐑕𐑰.” 𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞𐑨𐑑, 𐑖𐑰 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑤𐑪𐑒; 𐑚𐑳𐑑, 𐑩𐑤𐑨𐑕! ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜'𐑟 𐑕𐑳𐑐𐑤𐑦𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑚𐑴𐑤𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑱𐑯𐑛 𐑳𐑯𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑛𐑮𐑷𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑦𐑯.

“𐑣𐑨𐑓 𐑑 𐑚𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑴𐑐𐑩𐑯,” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑲, 𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑮𐑳𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑞 𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑦 𐑩 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤, 𐑓 𐑩 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑑, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑞 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑤𐑱𐑛𐑦 𐑒𐑷𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑰, 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯 𐑝𐑬𐑦𐑙 𐑲 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑒 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑣𐑻 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑩𐑟; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑲 𐑑𐑹 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑣𐑻, 𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑕𐑳𐑛𐑩𐑯 𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑳𐑖 𐑛𐑨𐑖𐑑 𐑥𐑲𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑓𐑫𐑤 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑞 𐑥𐑸𐑒.

𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑛𐑦𐑡𐑩𐑕 𐑯𐑶𐑟 𐑞 𐑛𐑹 𐑓𐑤𐑵 𐑴𐑐𐑩𐑯, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑯𐑪𐑚 𐑕𐑤𐑨𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑞 𐑢𐑷𐑤, 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑞 𐑐𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑼 𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑰𐑤𐑦𐑙; 𐑯 𐑞𐑺, 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑣𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑯𐑟! 𐑞𐑺 𐑕𐑨𐑑 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜, 𐑷𐑤𐑑𐑩𐑜𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑒𐑵𐑤 𐑯 𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓-𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑛; 𐑮𐑲𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑥𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑞 𐑮𐑵𐑥; 𐑕𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑥𐑟, 𐑯 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑦𐑙 ·𐑘𐑴𐑡𐑴 𐑪𐑯 𐑑𐑪𐑐 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑧𐑛. 𐑣𐑰 𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑑 𐑯𐑲𐑞𐑼 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑢𐑱 𐑯𐑹 𐑞 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑢𐑱, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑕𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑒𐑸𐑝𐑛 𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑡 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑕𐑒𐑺𐑕 𐑩 𐑕𐑲𐑯 𐑝 𐑨𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑝 𐑤𐑲𐑓.

“·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜,” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑲, 𐑜𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑳𐑐 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥, “·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜, 𐑢𐑪𐑑'𐑕 𐑞 𐑥𐑨𐑑𐑼 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑿?”

“𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑱𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑩 𐑕𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑯' 𐑕𐑴 𐑷𐑤 𐑛𐑱, 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑣𐑰?” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑞 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑤𐑱𐑛𐑦.

𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑢𐑰 𐑕𐑧𐑛, 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑩 𐑢𐑻𐑛 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑢𐑰 𐑛𐑮𐑨𐑜 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑥; 𐑲 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑓𐑧𐑤𐑑 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑐𐑫𐑖𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑴𐑝𐑼, 𐑕𐑴 𐑨𐑟 𐑑 𐑗𐑱𐑯𐑡 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑩𐑟𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯, 𐑓 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑪𐑤𐑼𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤, 𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑕𐑴 𐑐𐑱𐑯𐑓𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑯 𐑳𐑯𐑯𐑨𐑗𐑼𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑛; 𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑤𐑦, 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑚𐑩𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑕𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑴 𐑓 𐑳𐑐𐑢𐑼𐑛𐑟 𐑝 𐑱𐑑 𐑹 𐑑𐑧𐑯 𐑬𐑼𐑟, 𐑜𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑑𐑵 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑮𐑧𐑜𐑿𐑤𐑼 𐑥𐑰𐑤𐑟.

“·𐑥𐑕𐑟 ·𐑣𐑳𐑕𐑦,” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑲, “𐑣𐑰'𐑟 𐑩𐑤𐑲𐑝 𐑨𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑦𐑝𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑕; 𐑕𐑴 𐑤𐑰𐑝 𐑳𐑕, 𐑦𐑓 𐑿 𐑐𐑤𐑰𐑟, 𐑯 𐑲 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑕𐑰 𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡 𐑩𐑓𐑺 𐑥𐑲𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓.”

𐑒𐑤𐑴𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑛𐑹 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑤𐑱𐑛𐑦, 𐑲 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑧𐑝𐑼𐑛 𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑝𐑱𐑤 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜 𐑑 𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑩 𐑗𐑺; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑝𐑱𐑯. 𐑞𐑺 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑨𐑑; 𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑛𐑵—𐑓 𐑷𐑤 𐑥𐑲 𐑐𐑩𐑤𐑲𐑑 𐑸𐑑𐑕 𐑯 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑖𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕—𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑥𐑵𐑝 𐑩 𐑐𐑧𐑜, 𐑯𐑹 𐑕𐑱 𐑩 𐑕𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑻𐑛, 𐑯𐑹 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑤𐑫𐑒 𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑰, 𐑯𐑹 𐑯𐑴𐑑𐑦𐑕 𐑥𐑲 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑤𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑢𐑱.

𐑲 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼, 𐑔𐑷𐑑 𐑲, 𐑦𐑓 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑐𐑪𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑰 𐑩 𐑐𐑸𐑑 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 ·𐑮𐑭𐑥𐑩𐑛𐑭𐑯; 𐑛𐑵 𐑞𐑱 𐑓𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑪𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑣𐑨𐑥𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑱 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑱𐑑𐑦𐑝 𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛. 𐑦𐑑 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑕𐑴; 𐑘𐑧𐑕, 𐑦𐑑'𐑕 𐑐𐑸𐑑 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑮𐑰𐑛, 𐑲 𐑕𐑩𐑐𐑴𐑟; 𐑢𐑧𐑤, 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑤𐑧𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑑; 𐑣𐑰'𐑤 𐑜𐑧𐑑 𐑳𐑐 𐑕𐑵𐑯𐑼 𐑹 𐑤𐑱𐑑𐑼, 𐑯𐑴 𐑛𐑬𐑑. 𐑦𐑑 𐑒𐑭𐑯𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑓 𐑧𐑝𐑼, 𐑔𐑨𐑙𐑒 ·𐑜𐑪𐑛, 𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 ·𐑮𐑭𐑥𐑩𐑛𐑭𐑯 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑟 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑕 𐑩 𐑘𐑽; 𐑯 𐑲 𐑛𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑰𐑝 𐑦𐑑'𐑕 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑐𐑳𐑙𐑒𐑗𐑵𐑩𐑤 𐑞𐑧𐑯.

𐑲 𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑐𐑼. 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑕𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑤𐑦𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑞 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑕𐑑𐑹𐑦𐑟 𐑝 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑼𐑟 𐑣𐑵 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑡𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑩 𐑐𐑤𐑳𐑥-𐑐𐑫𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑝𐑶𐑦𐑡, 𐑨𐑟 𐑞𐑱 𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑛 𐑦𐑑 (𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑟, 𐑩 𐑖𐑹𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙-𐑝𐑶𐑦𐑡 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑕𐑒𐑵𐑯𐑼 𐑹 𐑚𐑮𐑦𐑜, 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑓𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑑 𐑞 𐑯𐑹𐑔 𐑝 𐑞 𐑤𐑲𐑯, 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑩𐑑𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑒 ·𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦); 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑤𐑦𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑐𐑤𐑳𐑥-𐑐𐑫𐑛𐑦𐑙𐑼𐑟 𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑯𐑽𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑤𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑴'𐑒𐑤𐑪𐑒, 𐑲 𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑳𐑐 𐑕𐑑𐑺𐑟 𐑑 𐑜𐑴 𐑑 𐑚𐑧𐑛, 𐑓𐑰𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑒𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑖𐑫𐑼 𐑚𐑲 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑑𐑲𐑥 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑚𐑮𐑷𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 ·𐑮𐑭𐑥𐑩𐑛𐑭𐑯 𐑑 𐑩 𐑑𐑻𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑯𐑴; 𐑞𐑺 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑡𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑢𐑺 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑤𐑧𐑓𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥; 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑻𐑛 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑗. 𐑲 𐑚𐑦𐑜𐑨𐑯 𐑑 𐑜𐑮𐑴 𐑝𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑥; 𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑕𐑴 𐑛𐑬𐑯𐑮𐑲𐑑 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑕𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑱𐑯 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑕𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑺 𐑷𐑤 𐑛𐑱 𐑯 𐑣𐑭𐑓 𐑞 𐑯𐑲𐑑 𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑥𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑒𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑮𐑵𐑥, 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑐𐑰𐑕 𐑝 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑧𐑛.

“𐑓 𐑣𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑯'𐑟 𐑕𐑱𐑒, ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜, 𐑜𐑧𐑑 𐑳𐑐 𐑯 𐑖𐑱𐑒 𐑘𐑹𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓; 𐑜𐑧𐑑 𐑳𐑐 𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑕𐑳𐑐𐑼. 𐑿'𐑤 𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑝; 𐑿'𐑤 𐑒𐑦𐑤 𐑘𐑹𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓, ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜.” 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑩 𐑢𐑻𐑛 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑣𐑰 𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑤𐑲.

𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑺𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑞𐑺𐑓𐑹, 𐑲 𐑛𐑦𐑑𐑻𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑛 𐑑 𐑜𐑴 𐑑 𐑚𐑧𐑛 𐑯 𐑑 𐑕𐑤𐑰𐑐; 𐑯 𐑯𐑴 𐑛𐑬𐑑, 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑩 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑢𐑲𐑤, 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑓𐑪𐑤𐑴 𐑥𐑰. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑰𐑝𐑾𐑕 𐑑 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯, 𐑲 𐑑𐑫𐑒 𐑥𐑲 𐑣𐑧𐑝𐑦 𐑚𐑺𐑕𐑒𐑦𐑯 𐑡𐑨𐑒𐑩𐑑, 𐑯 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑦𐑑 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑑 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑩 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑒𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑯𐑲𐑑; 𐑯 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑯𐑳𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑹𐑛𐑦𐑯𐑼𐑦 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑡𐑨𐑒𐑩𐑑 𐑪𐑯. 𐑓 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑑𐑲𐑥, 𐑛𐑵 𐑷𐑤 𐑲 𐑢𐑫𐑛, 𐑲 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑜𐑧𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑓𐑱𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑛𐑴𐑟. 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑤𐑴𐑯 𐑬𐑑 𐑞 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑤; 𐑯 𐑞 𐑥𐑽 𐑔𐑷𐑑 𐑝 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜—𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑓𐑹 𐑓𐑰𐑑 𐑪𐑓—𐑕𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑺 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑳𐑯𐑰𐑟𐑦 𐑐𐑩𐑟𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯, 𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑒 𐑩𐑤𐑴𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑒𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑯 𐑛𐑸𐑒; 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑥𐑰 𐑮𐑾𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑧𐑗𐑩𐑛. 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒 𐑝 𐑦𐑑; 𐑕𐑤𐑰𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑷𐑤 𐑯𐑲𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑮𐑵𐑥 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑢𐑲𐑛 𐑩𐑢𐑱𐑒 𐑐𐑱𐑜𐑩𐑯 𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑥𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑛𐑮𐑽𐑦, 𐑳𐑯𐑩𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 ·𐑮𐑭𐑥𐑩𐑛𐑭𐑯!

𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑣𐑬 𐑲 𐑛𐑮𐑪𐑐𐑑 𐑪𐑓 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑, 𐑯 𐑯𐑿 𐑯𐑳𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑹 𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑒 𐑝 𐑛𐑱; 𐑢𐑧𐑯, 𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑞 𐑚𐑧𐑛𐑕𐑲𐑛, 𐑞𐑺 𐑕𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑑𐑩𐑛 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜, 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑓 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑵𐑛 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑑 𐑞 𐑓𐑤𐑹. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑕𐑵𐑯 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑜𐑤𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑕 𐑝 𐑕𐑳𐑯 𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑛 𐑞 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑴, 𐑳𐑐 𐑣𐑰 𐑜𐑪𐑑, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑓 𐑯 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑡𐑶𐑯𐑑𐑕, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑗𐑽𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑤𐑫𐑒; 𐑤𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑑 𐑑𐑩𐑢𐑹𐑛𐑟 𐑥𐑰 𐑢𐑺 𐑲 𐑤𐑱; 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑛 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑥𐑲𐑯; 𐑯 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 ·𐑮𐑭𐑥𐑩𐑛𐑭𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑴𐑝𐑼.

𐑯𐑬, 𐑨𐑟 𐑲 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑣𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛, 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑯𐑴 𐑩𐑚𐑡𐑧𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑑 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑐𐑻𐑕𐑩𐑯'𐑟 𐑮𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑡𐑩𐑯, 𐑚𐑰 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑥𐑱, 𐑕𐑴 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑨𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑐𐑻𐑕𐑩𐑯 𐑛𐑳𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑒𐑦𐑤 𐑹 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑳𐑤𐑑 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑐𐑻𐑕𐑩𐑯, 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑪𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑐𐑻𐑕𐑩𐑯 𐑛𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑰𐑝 𐑦𐑑 𐑷𐑤𐑕𐑴. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑩 𐑥𐑨𐑯'𐑟 𐑮𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑡𐑩𐑯 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑟 𐑮𐑾𐑤𐑦 𐑓𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑒; 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑩 𐑐𐑪𐑟𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑝 𐑑𐑹𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥; 𐑯, 𐑦𐑯 𐑓𐑲𐑯, 𐑥𐑱𐑒𐑕 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑻𐑔 𐑝 𐑬𐑼𐑟 𐑩𐑯 𐑳𐑯𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑓𐑼𐑑𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑑 𐑤𐑪𐑡 𐑦𐑯; 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑲 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒 𐑦𐑑 𐑣𐑲 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑑 𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑡𐑵𐑩𐑤 𐑩𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑯 𐑸𐑜𐑿 𐑞 𐑐𐑶𐑯𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑥.

𐑯 𐑡𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑴 𐑲 𐑯𐑬 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜. “·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜,” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑲, “𐑜𐑧𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑚𐑧𐑛 𐑯𐑬, 𐑯 𐑤𐑲 𐑯 𐑤𐑦𐑕𐑩𐑯 𐑑 𐑥𐑰.” 𐑲 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑪𐑯, 𐑚𐑦𐑜𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑮𐑲𐑟 𐑯 𐑐𐑮𐑴𐑜𐑮𐑧𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑝 𐑮𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑡𐑩𐑯𐑟, 𐑯 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑑 𐑞 𐑝𐑺𐑾𐑕 𐑮𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑡𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑑𐑲𐑥, 𐑛𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑲 𐑤𐑱𐑚𐑼𐑛 𐑑 𐑖𐑴 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑰𐑟 ·𐑤𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑕, ·𐑮𐑭𐑥𐑩𐑛𐑭𐑯𐑟, 𐑯 𐑐𐑮𐑴𐑤𐑪𐑙𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑥-𐑕𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑑𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑒𐑴𐑤𐑛, 𐑗𐑽𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑮𐑵𐑥𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑒 𐑯𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑕; 𐑚𐑨𐑛 𐑓 𐑞 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑔; 𐑿𐑕𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑓 𐑞 𐑕𐑴𐑤; 𐑩𐑐𐑴𐑟𐑛, 𐑦𐑯 𐑖𐑹𐑑, 𐑑 𐑞 𐑪𐑚𐑝𐑾𐑕 𐑤𐑷𐑟 𐑝 ·𐑣𐑲𐑡𐑰𐑯 𐑯 𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑕. 𐑲 𐑑𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑑𐑵, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩𐑯 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑰𐑥𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑯 𐑕𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑕 𐑕𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑡, 𐑦𐑑 𐑐𐑱𐑯𐑛 𐑥𐑰, 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑚𐑨𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑱𐑯𐑛 𐑥𐑰, 𐑑 𐑕𐑰 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑯𐑬 𐑕𐑴 𐑛𐑦𐑐𐑤𐑹𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑓𐑵𐑤𐑦𐑖 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑮𐑦𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑩𐑕 ·𐑮𐑭𐑥𐑩𐑛𐑭𐑯 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟. 𐑚𐑦𐑕𐑲𐑛𐑟, 𐑸𐑜𐑿𐑛 𐑲, 𐑓𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑱𐑒𐑕 𐑞 𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦 𐑒𐑱𐑝 𐑦𐑯; 𐑣𐑧𐑯𐑕 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑦𐑮𐑦𐑑 𐑒𐑱𐑝𐑟 𐑦𐑯; 𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑔𐑷𐑑𐑕 𐑚𐑹𐑯 𐑝 𐑩 𐑓𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑯𐑧𐑕𐑦𐑕𐑺𐑦𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑰 𐑣𐑭𐑓-𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑝𐑛. 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑦𐑟 𐑞 𐑮𐑰𐑟𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑲 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑮𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑡𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑕 𐑗𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑖 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑥𐑧𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑒𐑪𐑤𐑦 𐑯𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑣𐑽𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼𐑟. 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑢𐑻𐑛, ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜, 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑲, 𐑮𐑭𐑞𐑼 𐑛𐑲𐑜𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑦𐑝𐑤𐑦; 𐑣𐑧𐑤 𐑦𐑟 𐑩𐑯 𐑲𐑛𐑾 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑹𐑯 𐑪𐑯 𐑩𐑯 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑲𐑡𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑨𐑐𐑩𐑤-𐑛𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑦𐑙; 𐑯 𐑕𐑦𐑯𐑕 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑐𐑼𐑐𐑧𐑗𐑵𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑞 𐑣𐑼𐑧𐑛𐑦𐑑𐑼𐑦 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑐𐑕𐑾𐑟 𐑯𐑻𐑗𐑼𐑛 𐑚𐑲 ·𐑮𐑭𐑥𐑩𐑛𐑭𐑯𐑟.

𐑲 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑭𐑕𐑒𐑑 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜 𐑢𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑐𐑕𐑾; 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑲𐑛𐑾 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑯𐑤𐑦, 𐑕𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑯. 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑯𐑴; 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑥𐑧𐑥𐑼𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑩𐑒𐑱𐑠𐑩𐑯. 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑩 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑓𐑰𐑕𐑑 𐑜𐑦𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑚𐑲 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑭𐑞𐑼 𐑞 𐑒𐑦𐑙, 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑩 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑚𐑨𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑺𐑦𐑯 𐑓𐑦𐑓𐑑𐑦 𐑝 𐑞 𐑧𐑯𐑩𐑥𐑦 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑒𐑦𐑤𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑑𐑵 𐑴'𐑒𐑤𐑪𐑒 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼𐑯𐑵𐑯, 𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑒𐑫𐑒𐑑 𐑯 𐑰𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑰𐑝𐑯𐑦𐑙.

“𐑯𐑴 𐑥𐑹, ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜,” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑲, 𐑖𐑳𐑛𐑼𐑦𐑙; “𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑛𐑵;” 𐑓 𐑲 𐑯𐑿 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑓𐑼𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑻𐑞𐑼 𐑣𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑧𐑥. 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑕𐑰𐑯 𐑩 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑼 𐑣𐑵 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑝𐑦𐑟𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛, 𐑯 𐑣𐑰 𐑑𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑥𐑰 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞 𐑒𐑳𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑥, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑩 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑚𐑨𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑛 𐑞𐑺, 𐑑 𐑚𐑸𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑿 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑕𐑤𐑱𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑘𐑸𐑛 𐑹 𐑜𐑸𐑛𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑝𐑦𐑒𐑑𐑼; 𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑚𐑲 𐑢𐑳𐑯, 𐑞𐑱 𐑢𐑻 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑢𐑫𐑛𐑩𐑯 𐑑𐑮𐑧𐑯𐑗𐑼𐑟, 𐑯 𐑜𐑸𐑯𐑦𐑖𐑑 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑐𐑦𐑤𐑬, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑚𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑓𐑮𐑵𐑑 𐑯 𐑒𐑴𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑳𐑑𐑕; 𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑐𐑸𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑥𐑬𐑞𐑟, 𐑢𐑻 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑝𐑦𐑒𐑑𐑼'𐑟 𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑦𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑟, 𐑡𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑞𐑴 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑢𐑻 𐑕𐑴 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 ·𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑥𐑩𐑕 𐑑𐑻𐑒𐑦𐑟.

𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑷𐑤, 𐑲 𐑛𐑵 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑲 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑸𐑒𐑕 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑡𐑩𐑯 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜. 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑪𐑟, 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕, 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑣𐑬 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑛𐑳𐑤 𐑝 𐑣𐑽𐑦𐑙 𐑪𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑹𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑚𐑡𐑧𐑒𐑑, 𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑧𐑕 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑼𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑴𐑯 𐑐𐑶𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑝𐑿; 𐑯, 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑧𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕, 𐑣𐑰 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑥𐑹 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑔𐑻𐑛 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑥𐑰, 𐑒𐑬𐑗 𐑥𐑲 𐑲𐑛𐑾𐑟 𐑕𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑦 𐑨𐑟 𐑲 𐑢𐑫𐑛; 𐑯, 𐑓𐑲𐑯𐑩𐑤𐑦, 𐑣𐑰 𐑯𐑴 𐑛𐑬𐑑 𐑔𐑷𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑯𐑿 𐑩 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑛𐑰𐑤 𐑥𐑹 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑞 𐑑𐑮𐑵 𐑮𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑡𐑩𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑲 𐑛𐑦𐑛. 𐑣𐑰 𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑰 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑕𐑹𐑑 𐑝 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑻𐑯 𐑯 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑨𐑖𐑩𐑯, 𐑨𐑟 𐑞𐑴 𐑣𐑰 𐑔𐑷𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑩 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑐𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑘𐑳𐑙 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑚𐑰 𐑕𐑴 𐑣𐑴𐑐𐑤𐑩𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑤𐑪𐑕𐑑 𐑑 𐑰𐑝𐑨𐑯𐑡𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑐𐑱𐑜𐑩𐑯 𐑐𐑲𐑩𐑑𐑦.

𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑢𐑰 𐑮𐑴𐑟 𐑯 𐑛𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑑; 𐑯 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜, 𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑛𐑦𐑡𐑩𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑣𐑸𐑑𐑦 𐑚𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑓𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑝 𐑗𐑬𐑛𐑼𐑟 𐑝 𐑷𐑤 𐑕𐑹𐑑𐑕, 𐑕𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑤𐑱𐑛𐑦 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑥𐑱𐑒 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑓𐑦𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑮𐑰𐑟𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 ·𐑮𐑭𐑥𐑩𐑛𐑭𐑯, 𐑢𐑰 𐑕𐑨𐑤𐑦𐑛 𐑬𐑑 𐑑 𐑚𐑹𐑛 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛, 𐑕𐑷𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑙, 𐑯 𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑬𐑼 𐑑𐑰𐑔 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑨𐑤𐑦𐑚𐑩𐑑 𐑚𐑴𐑯𐑟.

·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 18. 𐑣𐑦𐑟 ·𐑥𐑸𐑒.

𐑨𐑟 𐑢𐑰 𐑢𐑻 𐑢𐑷𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑞 𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑹𐑓 𐑑𐑩𐑢𐑹𐑛𐑟 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐, ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜 𐑒𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯, ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 ·𐑐𐑰𐑤𐑧𐑜 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑜𐑮𐑳𐑓 𐑝𐑶𐑕 𐑤𐑬𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑣𐑱𐑤𐑛 𐑳𐑕 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑜𐑢𐑭𐑥, 𐑕𐑱𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑩𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑥𐑲 𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑚𐑩𐑤, 𐑯 𐑓𐑻𐑞𐑼𐑥𐑹 𐑩𐑯𐑬𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑤𐑧𐑑 𐑯𐑴 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑪𐑯 𐑚𐑹𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑒𐑮𐑭𐑓𐑑, 𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑧𐑕 𐑞𐑱 𐑐𐑮𐑰𐑝𐑾𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑛𐑿𐑕𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑐𐑱𐑐𐑼𐑟.

“𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑛𐑵 𐑿 𐑥𐑰𐑯 𐑚𐑲 𐑞𐑨𐑑, ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 ·𐑐𐑰𐑤𐑧𐑜?” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑲, 𐑯𐑬 𐑡𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑫𐑤𐑢𐑼𐑒𐑕, 𐑯 𐑤𐑰𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑲 𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑮𐑱𐑛 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑹𐑓.

“𐑲 𐑥𐑰𐑯,” 𐑣𐑰 𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑤𐑲𐑛, “𐑣𐑰 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑖𐑴 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑱𐑐𐑼𐑟.”

“𐑘𐑧𐑕,” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 ·𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑛𐑨𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑪𐑤𐑴 𐑝𐑶𐑕, 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑚𐑦𐑣𐑲𐑯𐑛 ·𐑐𐑰𐑤𐑧𐑜'𐑟, 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑦𐑜𐑢𐑭𐑥. “𐑣𐑰 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑖𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑰'𐑟 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑝𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑛. 𐑕𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑛𐑸𐑒𐑯𐑩𐑕,” 𐑣𐑰 𐑨𐑛𐑩𐑛, 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑑 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜, “𐑸𐑑 𐑞𐑬 𐑨𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑿𐑯𐑾𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑧𐑯𐑦 ·𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑗𐑩𐑯 𐑗𐑻𐑗?”

“𐑢𐑲,” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑲, “𐑣𐑰'𐑟 𐑩 𐑥𐑧𐑥𐑚𐑼 𐑝 𐑞 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 ·𐑒𐑪𐑙𐑜𐑮𐑦𐑜𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑤 ·𐑗𐑻𐑗.” 𐑣𐑽 𐑚𐑰 𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑧𐑛, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑑𐑩𐑑𐑵𐑛 𐑕𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑡𐑩𐑟 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 ·𐑯𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑑 𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑕 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑝𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑗𐑻𐑗𐑩𐑟.

“𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 ·𐑒𐑪𐑙𐑜𐑮𐑦𐑜𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑤 ·𐑗𐑻𐑗,” 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 ·𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑛𐑨𐑛, “𐑢𐑪𐑑! 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑻𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑕 𐑦𐑯 ·𐑛𐑰𐑒𐑩𐑯 ·𐑛𐑵𐑑𐑼𐑪𐑯𐑩𐑥𐑦 ·𐑒𐑴𐑤𐑥𐑩𐑯'𐑟 𐑥𐑰𐑑𐑦𐑙-𐑣𐑬𐑕?” 𐑯 𐑕𐑴 𐑕𐑱𐑦𐑙, 𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑬𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑟, 𐑣𐑰 𐑮𐑳𐑚𐑛 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑘𐑧𐑤𐑴 𐑚𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑨𐑯𐑩 𐑣𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑼𐑗𐑦𐑓, 𐑯 𐑐𐑫𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑪𐑯 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑒𐑺𐑓𐑩𐑤𐑦, 𐑒𐑱𐑥 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑦𐑜𐑢𐑭𐑥, 𐑯 𐑤𐑰𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑓𐑤𐑦 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑞 𐑚𐑫𐑤𐑢𐑼𐑒𐑕, 𐑑𐑫𐑒 𐑩 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑤𐑫𐑒 𐑨𐑑 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜.

“𐑣𐑬 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑣𐑨𐑔 𐑣𐑰 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑩 𐑥𐑧𐑥𐑚𐑼?” 𐑣𐑰 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑕𐑧𐑛, 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑥𐑰; “𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑤𐑪𐑙, 𐑲 𐑮𐑭𐑞𐑼 𐑜𐑧𐑕, 𐑘𐑳𐑙 𐑥𐑨𐑯.”

“𐑯𐑴,” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 ·𐑐𐑰𐑤𐑧𐑜, “𐑯 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑚𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑲𐑟𐑛 𐑮𐑲𐑑 𐑲𐑞𐑼, 𐑹 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑢𐑪𐑖𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑛𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑤'𐑟 𐑚𐑤𐑵 𐑪𐑓 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑱𐑕.”

“𐑛𐑵 𐑑𐑧𐑤, 𐑯𐑬,” 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 ·𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑛𐑨𐑛, “𐑦𐑟 𐑞𐑦𐑕 ·𐑓𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑲𐑯 𐑩 𐑮𐑧𐑜𐑿𐑤𐑼 𐑥𐑧𐑥𐑚𐑼 𐑝 ·𐑛𐑰𐑒𐑩𐑯 ·𐑛𐑵𐑑𐑼𐑪𐑯𐑩𐑥𐑦'𐑟 𐑥𐑰𐑑𐑦𐑙? 𐑲 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑕𐑷 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑜𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑺, 𐑯 𐑲 𐑐𐑭𐑕 𐑦𐑑 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 ·𐑤𐑹𐑛'𐑟 𐑛𐑱.”

“𐑲 𐑛𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑯𐑴 𐑧𐑯𐑦𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 ·𐑛𐑰𐑒𐑩𐑯 ·𐑛𐑵𐑑𐑼𐑪𐑯𐑩𐑥𐑦 𐑹 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑰𐑑𐑦𐑙,” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑲; “𐑷𐑤 𐑲 𐑯𐑴 𐑦𐑟, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜 𐑣𐑽 𐑦𐑟 𐑩 𐑚𐑹𐑯 𐑥𐑧𐑥𐑚𐑼 𐑝 𐑞 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 ·𐑒𐑪𐑙𐑜𐑮𐑦𐑜𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑤 ·𐑗𐑻𐑗. 𐑣𐑰 𐑦𐑟 𐑩 𐑛𐑰𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓, ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜 𐑦𐑟.”

“𐑘𐑳𐑙 𐑥𐑨𐑯,” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 ·𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑛𐑨𐑛 𐑕𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑤𐑦, “𐑞𐑬 𐑸𐑑 𐑕𐑒𐑲𐑤𐑸𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑥𐑰—𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑯 𐑞𐑲𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓, 𐑞𐑬 𐑘𐑳𐑙 ·𐑣𐑦𐑑𐑲𐑑. 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑗𐑻𐑗 𐑛𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑞𐑰 𐑥𐑰𐑯? 𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑼 𐑥𐑰.”

𐑓𐑲𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑲𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑞𐑳𐑕 𐑣𐑸𐑛 𐑐𐑫𐑖𐑑, 𐑲 𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑤𐑲𐑛. “𐑲 𐑥𐑰𐑯, 𐑕𐑻, 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑱𐑯𐑗𐑩𐑯𐑑 ·𐑒𐑨𐑔𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑒 ·𐑗𐑻𐑗 𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑿 𐑯 𐑲, 𐑯 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 ·𐑐𐑰𐑤𐑧𐑜 𐑞𐑺, 𐑯 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜 𐑣𐑽, 𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑝 𐑳𐑕, 𐑯 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑥𐑳𐑞𐑼'𐑟 𐑕𐑳𐑯 𐑯 𐑕𐑴𐑤 𐑝 𐑳𐑕 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑪𐑙; 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑯 𐑧𐑝𐑼𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 ·𐑒𐑪𐑙𐑜𐑮𐑦𐑜𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑣𐑴𐑤 𐑢𐑻𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛; 𐑢𐑰 𐑷𐑤 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑; 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑝 𐑳𐑕 𐑗𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑖 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑒𐑢𐑽 𐑒𐑮𐑪𐑗𐑩𐑑𐑕 𐑯𐑴 𐑢𐑱𐑟 𐑑𐑳𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑰𐑓; 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑰 𐑷𐑤 𐑡𐑶𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟.”

“𐑕𐑐𐑤𐑲𐑕, 𐑞𐑬 𐑥𐑰𐑯'𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑐𐑤𐑲𐑕 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟,” 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 ·𐑐𐑰𐑤𐑧𐑜, 𐑛𐑮𐑷𐑦𐑙 𐑯𐑽𐑼. “𐑘𐑳𐑙 𐑥𐑨𐑯, 𐑿'𐑛 𐑚𐑧𐑑𐑼 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑓 𐑩 𐑥𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑼𐑦, 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑛 𐑝 𐑩 𐑓𐑹-𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛; 𐑲 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑣𐑻𐑛 𐑩 𐑚𐑧𐑑𐑼 𐑕𐑻𐑥𐑩𐑯. 𐑛𐑰𐑒𐑩𐑯 ·𐑛𐑵𐑑𐑼𐑪𐑯𐑩𐑥𐑦—𐑢𐑲 ·𐑓𐑭𐑞𐑼 ·𐑥𐑱𐑐𐑩𐑤 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑒𐑫𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑚𐑰𐑑 𐑦𐑑, 𐑯 𐑣𐑰'𐑟 𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑔𐑦𐑙. 𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑩𐑚𐑹𐑛, 𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑩𐑚𐑹𐑛; 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑥𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑞 𐑐𐑱𐑐𐑼𐑟. 𐑲 𐑕𐑱, 𐑑𐑧𐑤 ·𐑒𐑢𐑴𐑙𐑪𐑜 𐑞𐑺—𐑢𐑪𐑑'𐑕 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑿 𐑒𐑷𐑤 𐑣𐑦𐑥? 𐑑𐑧𐑤 ·𐑒𐑢𐑴𐑙𐑪𐑜 𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑐 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑙. 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑼, 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑩 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯 𐑣𐑰'𐑟 𐑜𐑪𐑑 𐑞𐑺! 𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑕 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑓 𐑞𐑨𐑑; 𐑯 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑮𐑲𐑑. 𐑲 𐑕𐑱, ·𐑒𐑢𐑴𐑙𐑪𐑜, 𐑹 𐑢𐑪𐑑𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑘𐑹 𐑯𐑱𐑥 𐑦𐑟, 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑿 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑝 𐑩 𐑢𐑱𐑤-𐑚𐑴𐑑? 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑿 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑓𐑦𐑖?”

𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑 𐑕𐑱𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑢𐑻𐑛, ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜, 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑲𐑤𐑛 𐑕𐑹𐑑 𐑝 𐑢𐑱, 𐑡𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑑 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑫𐑤𐑢𐑼𐑒𐑕, 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞𐑧𐑯𐑕 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑚𐑬𐑟 𐑝 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤-𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕 𐑣𐑨𐑙𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑲𐑛; 𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑤𐑧𐑓𐑑 𐑯𐑰, 𐑯 𐑐𐑶𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯, 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 𐑬𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑢𐑱 𐑨𐑟 𐑞𐑦𐑕:—

“𐑒𐑨𐑐'𐑱𐑯, 𐑿 𐑕𐑰 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑕𐑥𐑷𐑤 𐑛𐑮𐑪𐑐 𐑑𐑸 𐑪𐑯 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼 𐑛𐑸? 𐑿 𐑕𐑰 𐑣𐑦𐑥? 𐑢𐑧𐑤, 𐑕𐑐𐑴𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑲, 𐑢𐑧𐑤, 𐑛𐑧𐑯!” 𐑯 𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑖𐑸𐑐 𐑱𐑥 𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑑, 𐑣𐑰 𐑛𐑸𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑞 𐑲𐑼𐑯 𐑮𐑲𐑑 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑴𐑤𐑛 ·𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑛𐑨𐑛'𐑟 𐑚𐑮𐑷𐑛 𐑚𐑮𐑦𐑥, 𐑒𐑤𐑰𐑯 𐑩𐑒𐑮𐑪𐑕 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐'𐑕 𐑛𐑧𐑒𐑕, 𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑒 𐑞 𐑜𐑤𐑦𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑑𐑸 𐑕𐑐𐑪𐑑 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑕𐑲𐑑.

“𐑯𐑬,” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜, 𐑒𐑢𐑲𐑩𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑣𐑷𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑤𐑲𐑯, “𐑕𐑐𐑴𐑟-ee 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑢𐑱𐑤-𐑰 𐑲; 𐑢𐑲, 𐑛𐑨𐑛 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑛𐑧𐑛.”

“𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑒, ·𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑛𐑨𐑛,” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 ·𐑐𐑰𐑤𐑧𐑜, 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑸𐑑𐑯𐑼, 𐑣𐑵, 𐑩𐑜𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑒𐑤𐑴𐑕 𐑝𐑦𐑕𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑝 𐑞 𐑓𐑤𐑲𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯, 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑮𐑰𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑑𐑩𐑢𐑹𐑛𐑟 𐑞 𐑒𐑨𐑚𐑦𐑯 𐑜𐑨𐑙𐑢𐑱. “𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑒, 𐑲 𐑕𐑱, 𐑿 ·𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑛𐑨𐑛, 𐑯 𐑜𐑧𐑑 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐'𐑕 𐑐𐑱𐑐𐑼𐑟. 𐑢𐑰 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 ·𐑣𐑧𐑡𐑣𐑪𐑜 𐑞𐑺, 𐑲 𐑥𐑰𐑯 ·𐑒𐑢𐑴𐑙𐑪𐑜, 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑬𐑼 𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕. 𐑤𐑫𐑒 𐑘𐑰, ·𐑒𐑢𐑴𐑙𐑪𐑜, 𐑢𐑰'𐑤 𐑜𐑦𐑝 𐑘𐑰 𐑞 𐑯𐑲𐑯𐑑𐑾𐑔 𐑤𐑱, 𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑'𐑕 𐑥𐑹 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑜𐑦𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑩 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑽 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 ·𐑯𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑑.”

𐑕𐑴 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑢𐑰 𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑒𐑨𐑚𐑦𐑯, 𐑯 𐑑 𐑥𐑲 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑡𐑶 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑵𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑮𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑖𐑦𐑐'𐑕 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑦 𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑲 𐑥𐑲𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑪𐑙𐑛.

𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑼𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑯 ·𐑐𐑰𐑤𐑧𐑜 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑜𐑪𐑑 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑦 𐑓 𐑕𐑲𐑯𐑦𐑙, 𐑣𐑰 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑛 𐑑 𐑥𐑰 𐑯 𐑕𐑧𐑛, “𐑲 𐑜𐑧𐑕, ·𐑒𐑢𐑴𐑙𐑪𐑜 𐑞𐑺 𐑛𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑯𐑴 𐑣𐑬 𐑑 𐑮𐑲𐑑, 𐑛𐑳𐑟 𐑣𐑰? 𐑲 𐑕𐑱, ·𐑒𐑢𐑴𐑙𐑪𐑜, 𐑚𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑘𐑰! 𐑛𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑞𐑬 𐑕𐑲𐑯 𐑞𐑲 𐑯𐑱𐑥 𐑹 𐑥𐑱𐑒 𐑞𐑲 𐑥𐑸𐑒?”

𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑕𐑗𐑩𐑯, ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜, 𐑣𐑵 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑑𐑢𐑲𐑕 𐑹 𐑔𐑮𐑲𐑕 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑐𐑸𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑤𐑼 𐑕𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑟, 𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑑 𐑯𐑴 𐑢𐑱𐑟 𐑩𐑚𐑨𐑖𐑑; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑪𐑓𐑼𐑛 𐑐𐑧𐑯, 𐑒𐑪𐑐𐑦𐑛 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑐𐑱𐑐𐑼, 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑐𐑼 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕, 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑜𐑟𐑨𐑒𐑑 𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑐𐑸𐑑 𐑝 𐑩 𐑒𐑢𐑽 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑓𐑦𐑜𐑼 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑑𐑩𐑑𐑵𐑛 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑸𐑥; 𐑕𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑔𐑮𐑵 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 ·𐑐𐑰𐑤𐑧𐑜'𐑟 𐑪𐑚𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑑 𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑑𐑳𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑩𐑐𐑧𐑤𐑧𐑑𐑦𐑝, 𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑫𐑛 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑞𐑦𐑕:—

·𐑒𐑢𐑴𐑙𐑪𐑜. 𐑣𐑦𐑟 X 𐑥𐑸𐑒.

𐑥𐑰𐑯𐑢𐑲𐑤 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 ·𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑛𐑨𐑛 𐑕𐑨𐑑 𐑻𐑯𐑩𐑕𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑛𐑓𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑲𐑦𐑙 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜, 𐑯 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑮𐑲𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑪𐑤𐑩𐑥𐑤𐑦 𐑯 𐑓𐑳𐑥𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑣𐑿𐑡 𐑐𐑪𐑒𐑩𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑮𐑷𐑛-𐑕𐑒𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑛𐑮𐑨𐑚 𐑒𐑴𐑑, 𐑑𐑫𐑒 𐑬𐑑 𐑩 𐑚𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑒𐑑𐑕, 𐑯 𐑕𐑦𐑤𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑛 “𐑞 ·𐑤𐑨𐑑𐑼 𐑛𐑱 ·𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑦𐑙; 𐑹 𐑯𐑴 ·𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑑 ·𐑤𐑵𐑟,” 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑯 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜'𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟, 𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑜𐑮𐑭𐑕𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑫𐑒 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑔 𐑣𐑦𐑟, 𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑑 𐑻𐑯𐑩𐑕𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑲𐑟, 𐑯 𐑕𐑧𐑛, “𐑕𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑛𐑸𐑒𐑯𐑩𐑕, 𐑲 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑛𐑵 𐑥𐑲 𐑛𐑿𐑑𐑦 𐑚𐑲 𐑞𐑰; 𐑲 𐑨𐑥 𐑐𐑸𐑑 𐑴𐑯𐑼 𐑝 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑖𐑦𐑐, 𐑯 𐑓𐑰𐑤 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑻𐑯𐑛 𐑓 𐑞 𐑕𐑴𐑤𐑟 𐑝 𐑷𐑤 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑒𐑮𐑵; 𐑦𐑓 𐑞𐑬 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑒𐑤𐑦𐑙𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑑 𐑞𐑲 ·𐑐𐑱𐑜𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑱𐑟, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑲 𐑕𐑨𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑓𐑽, 𐑲 𐑚𐑦𐑕𐑰𐑗 𐑞𐑰, 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑱𐑯 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑓 𐑲 𐑩 ·𐑚𐑧𐑤𐑾𐑤 𐑚𐑪𐑯𐑛𐑟𐑥𐑩𐑯. 𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑯 𐑞 𐑲𐑛𐑩𐑤 ·𐑚𐑧𐑤, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑛𐑾𐑕 𐑛𐑮𐑨𐑜𐑩𐑯; 𐑑𐑻𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑮𐑪𐑔 𐑑 𐑒𐑳𐑥; 𐑥𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑞𐑲𐑯 𐑲, 𐑲 𐑕𐑱; 𐑴! 𐑜𐑫𐑛𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑕! 𐑕𐑑𐑽 𐑒𐑤𐑽 𐑝 𐑞 𐑓𐑲𐑼𐑦 𐑐𐑦𐑑!”

𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑷𐑤𐑑 𐑕𐑰 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑤𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑼𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑴𐑤𐑛 ·𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑛𐑨𐑛'𐑟 𐑤𐑨𐑙𐑜𐑢𐑦𐑡, 𐑣𐑧𐑑𐑼𐑩𐑡𐑰𐑯𐑾𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑥𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 ·𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑗𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑯 𐑛𐑩𐑥𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑓𐑮𐑱𐑟𐑩𐑟.

“𐑩𐑝𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑞𐑺, 𐑩𐑝𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑞𐑺, ·𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑛𐑨𐑛, 𐑩𐑝𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑯𐑬 𐑕𐑐𐑶𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑬𐑼 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑽,” 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 ·𐑐𐑰𐑤𐑧𐑜. “𐑐𐑲𐑩𐑕 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑽𐑟 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑥𐑱𐑒 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑝𐑶𐑦𐑡𐑼𐑟—𐑦𐑑 𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑕 𐑞 𐑖𐑸𐑒 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 '𐑩𐑥; 𐑯𐑴 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑽 𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑻𐑔 𐑩 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑷 𐑣𐑵 𐑱𐑯𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑖𐑸𐑒𐑦𐑖. 𐑞𐑺 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑘𐑳𐑙 ·𐑯𐑨𐑑 ·𐑕𐑢𐑱𐑯, 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑕 𐑞 𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑝𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑴𐑑-𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑼 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑷𐑤 ·𐑯𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑑 𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑝𐑦𐑯𐑘𐑼𐑛; 𐑣𐑰 𐑡𐑶𐑯𐑛 𐑞 𐑥𐑰𐑑𐑦𐑙, 𐑯 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑒𐑱𐑥 𐑑 𐑜𐑫𐑛. 𐑣𐑰 𐑜𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑴 𐑓𐑮𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑜𐑦 𐑕𐑴𐑤, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑖𐑮𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑑 𐑯 𐑖𐑽𐑛 𐑩𐑢𐑱 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟, 𐑓 𐑓𐑽 𐑝 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼-𐑒𐑤𐑨𐑐𐑕, 𐑦𐑯 𐑒𐑱𐑕 𐑣𐑰 𐑜𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑴𐑝 𐑯 𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑑 ·𐑛𐑱𐑝𐑦 ·𐑡𐑴𐑯𐑟.”

“·𐑐𐑰𐑤𐑧𐑜! ·𐑐𐑰𐑤𐑧𐑜!” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 ·𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑛𐑨𐑛, 𐑤𐑦𐑓𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑲𐑟 𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟, “𐑞𐑬 𐑞𐑲𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓, 𐑨𐑟 𐑲 𐑥𐑲𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓, 𐑣𐑨𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑯 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑩 𐑐𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑑𐑲𐑥; 𐑞𐑬 𐑯𐑴𐑩𐑕𐑑, ·𐑐𐑰𐑤𐑧𐑜, 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑞 𐑓𐑽 𐑝 𐑛𐑧𐑔; 𐑣𐑬, 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑒𐑨𐑯'𐑕𐑑 𐑞𐑬 𐑐𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑳𐑯𐑜𐑪𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑜𐑲𐑟. 𐑞𐑬 𐑚𐑧𐑤𐑾𐑕𐑑 𐑞𐑲𐑯 𐑴𐑯 𐑣𐑸𐑑, ·𐑐𐑰𐑤𐑧𐑜. 𐑑𐑧𐑤 𐑥𐑰, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑕𐑱𐑥 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛 𐑣𐑽 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑣𐑻 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑕 𐑴𐑝𐑼𐑚𐑹𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑑𐑲𐑓𐑵𐑯 𐑪𐑯 ·𐑡𐑩𐑐𐑨𐑯, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑝𐑶𐑦𐑡 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑞𐑬 𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑥𐑱𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚, 𐑛𐑲𐑛'𐑕𐑑 𐑞𐑬 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒 𐑝 ·𐑛𐑧𐑔 𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑡𐑳𐑡𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑞𐑧𐑯?”

“𐑣𐑽 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑣𐑽 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑯𐑬,” 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 ·𐑐𐑰𐑤𐑧𐑜, 𐑥𐑸𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑒𐑮𐑪𐑕 𐑞 𐑒𐑨𐑚𐑦𐑯, 𐑯 𐑔𐑮𐑳𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑓𐑸 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑪𐑒𐑩𐑑𐑕,—“𐑣𐑽 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑷𐑤 𐑝 𐑘𐑰. 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒 𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑! 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑥𐑴𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑢𐑰 𐑔𐑷𐑑 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑕𐑦𐑙𐑒! 𐑛𐑧𐑔 𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑡𐑳𐑡𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑞𐑧𐑯? 𐑢𐑪𐑑? 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑷𐑤 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑕 𐑥𐑱𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩𐑯 𐑧𐑝𐑼𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑔𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑲𐑛; 𐑯 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑕𐑰 𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑳𐑕, 𐑓𐑹 𐑯 𐑭𐑓𐑑. 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒 𐑝 ·𐑛𐑧𐑔 𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑡𐑳𐑡𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑞𐑧𐑯? 𐑯𐑴! 𐑯𐑴 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑑 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 ·𐑛𐑧𐑔 𐑞𐑧𐑯. 𐑤𐑲𐑓 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑢𐑪𐑑 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑯 𐑲 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑝; 𐑯 𐑣𐑬 𐑑 𐑕𐑱𐑝 𐑷𐑤 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟—𐑣𐑬 𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑜 𐑡𐑫𐑼𐑦-𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑕—𐑣𐑬 𐑑 𐑜𐑧𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑯𐑽𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑐𐑹𐑑; 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑲 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑝.”

·𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑛𐑨𐑛 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑯𐑴 𐑥𐑹, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑚𐑳𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑳𐑐 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑴𐑑, 𐑕𐑑𐑷𐑒𐑑 𐑪𐑯 𐑛𐑧𐑒, 𐑢𐑺 𐑢𐑰 𐑓𐑪𐑤𐑴𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥. 𐑞𐑺 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑑𐑫𐑛, 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑒𐑢𐑲𐑩𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑴𐑝𐑼𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑥𐑱𐑒𐑼𐑟 𐑣𐑵 𐑢𐑻 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑑𐑪𐑐-𐑕𐑱𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑕𐑑. 𐑯𐑬 𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑑𐑵𐑐𐑑 𐑑 𐑐𐑦𐑒 𐑳𐑐 𐑩 𐑐𐑨𐑗, 𐑹 𐑕𐑱𐑝 𐑩𐑯 𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑝 𐑑𐑸𐑛 𐑑𐑢𐑲𐑯, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑳𐑞𐑼𐑢𐑲𐑟 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑢𐑱𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛.

·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 19. 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑓𐑩𐑑.

“𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑥𐑱𐑑𐑕, 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑘𐑰 𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑖𐑦𐑐?”

·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜 𐑯 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑡𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑤𐑧𐑓𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛, 𐑯 𐑢𐑻 𐑕𐑷𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑢𐑱 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼, 𐑓 𐑞 𐑥𐑴𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑰𐑗 𐑪𐑒𐑿𐑐𐑲𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑴𐑯 𐑔𐑷𐑑𐑕, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑞 𐑩𐑚𐑳𐑝 𐑢𐑻𐑛𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑐𐑫𐑑 𐑑 𐑳𐑕 𐑚𐑲 𐑩 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑼, 𐑣𐑵, 𐑐𐑷𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑳𐑕, 𐑤𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑨𐑕𐑦𐑝 𐑓𐑹𐑓𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑼 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑝𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑕𐑗𐑩𐑯. 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑖𐑨𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑦 𐑩𐑐𐑨𐑮𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑓𐑱𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑡𐑨𐑒𐑩𐑑 𐑯 𐑐𐑨𐑗𐑑 𐑑𐑮𐑴𐑟𐑼𐑟; 𐑩 𐑮𐑨𐑜 𐑝 𐑩 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑒 𐑣𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑼𐑗𐑦𐑓 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑧𐑒. 𐑩 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑓𐑤𐑵𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑕𐑥𐑷𐑤-𐑐𐑪𐑒𐑕 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑛𐑦𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑓𐑤𐑴𐑛 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑱𐑕, 𐑯 𐑤𐑧𐑓𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑞 𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑦𐑒𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑮𐑦𐑚𐑛 𐑚𐑧𐑛 𐑝 𐑩 𐑑𐑪𐑮𐑩𐑯𐑑, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑞 𐑮𐑳𐑖𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑛𐑮𐑲𐑛 𐑳𐑐.

“𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑘𐑰 𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑻?” 𐑣𐑰 𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑰𐑑𐑩𐑛.

“𐑿 𐑥𐑰𐑯 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛, 𐑲 𐑕𐑩𐑐𐑴𐑟,” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑲, 𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑜𐑱𐑯 𐑩 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑥𐑹 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑓 𐑩𐑯 𐑳𐑯𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑳𐑐𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑤𐑫𐑒 𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥.

“𐑲, 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛—𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑞𐑺,” 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑧𐑛, 𐑛𐑮𐑷𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑨𐑒 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑴𐑤 𐑸𐑥, 𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑮𐑨𐑐𐑦𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑖𐑳𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑬𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑓𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑱𐑩𐑯𐑧𐑑 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑶𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑓𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑼 𐑛𐑸𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑓𐑫𐑤 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑪𐑚𐑡𐑧𐑒𐑑.

“𐑘𐑧𐑕,” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑲, “𐑢𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑡𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑞 𐑸𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑟.”

“𐑧𐑯𐑦𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑘𐑹 𐑕𐑴𐑤𐑟?”

“𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑑?”

“𐑴, 𐑐𐑼𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑕 𐑿 𐑙𐑨𐑝'𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑜𐑪𐑑 𐑧𐑯𐑦,” 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑦. “𐑯𐑴 𐑥𐑨𐑑𐑼 𐑞𐑴, 𐑲 𐑯𐑴 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑕 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑙𐑨𐑝'𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑜𐑪𐑑 𐑧𐑯𐑦,—𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑤𐑳𐑒 𐑑 '𐑩𐑥; 𐑯 𐑞𐑱 𐑸 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑚𐑧𐑑𐑼 𐑪𐑓 𐑓 𐑦𐑑. 𐑩 𐑕𐑴𐑤'𐑟 𐑩 𐑕𐑹𐑑 𐑝 𐑩 𐑓𐑦𐑓𐑔 𐑢𐑰𐑤 𐑑 𐑩 𐑢𐑨𐑜𐑩𐑯.”

“𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑸 𐑿 𐑡𐑨𐑚𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑, 𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑥𐑱𐑑?” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑲.

“𐑣𐑰'𐑟 𐑜𐑪𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑳𐑓, 𐑞𐑴, 𐑑 𐑥𐑱𐑒 𐑳𐑐 𐑓 𐑷𐑤 𐑛𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑟 𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑹𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑕,” 𐑩𐑚𐑮𐑳𐑐𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑼, 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑯𐑻𐑝𐑩𐑕 𐑧𐑥𐑓𐑩𐑕𐑦𐑕 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑻𐑛 𐑣𐑰.

“·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜,” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑲, “𐑤𐑧𐑑'𐑕 𐑜𐑴; 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑓𐑧𐑤𐑴 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑚𐑮𐑴𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑤𐑵𐑕 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑢𐑺; 𐑣𐑰'𐑟 𐑑𐑷𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦 𐑢𐑰 𐑛𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑯𐑴.”

“𐑕𐑑𐑪𐑐!” 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑼. “𐑘𐑰 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑑𐑮𐑵—𐑘𐑰 𐑙𐑨𐑝'𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑯 ·𐑴𐑤𐑛 ·𐑔𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑘𐑧𐑑, 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑘𐑰?”

“𐑣𐑵'𐑟 ·𐑴𐑤𐑛 ·𐑔𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼?” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑲, 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯 𐑮𐑦𐑝𐑩𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑱𐑯 𐑻𐑯𐑩𐑕𐑑𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑨𐑯𐑼.

“𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚.”

“𐑢𐑪𐑑! 𐑞 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 𐑝 𐑬𐑼 𐑖𐑦𐑐, 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛?”

“𐑲, 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑝 𐑳𐑕 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑼 𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑕, 𐑣𐑰 𐑜𐑴𐑟 𐑚𐑲 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑯𐑱𐑥. 𐑘𐑰 𐑙𐑨𐑝'𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑘𐑧𐑑, 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑘𐑰?”

“𐑯𐑴, 𐑢𐑰 𐑙𐑨𐑝'𐑩𐑯𐑑. 𐑣𐑰'𐑟 𐑕𐑦𐑒 𐑞𐑱 𐑕𐑱, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑜𐑧𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑧𐑑𐑼, 𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑚𐑰 𐑷𐑤 𐑮𐑲𐑑 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑤𐑪𐑙.”

“𐑷𐑤 𐑮𐑲𐑑 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑤𐑪𐑙!” 𐑤𐑭𐑓𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑼, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑕𐑪𐑤𐑩𐑥𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑦𐑮𐑲𐑕𐑦𐑝 𐑕𐑹𐑑 𐑝 𐑤𐑭𐑓. “𐑤𐑫𐑒 𐑘𐑰; 𐑢𐑧𐑯 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑦𐑟 𐑷𐑤 𐑮𐑲𐑑, 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑤𐑧𐑓𐑑 𐑸𐑥 𐑝 𐑥𐑲𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑚𐑰 𐑷𐑤 𐑮𐑲𐑑; 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹.”

“𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑛𐑵 𐑿 𐑯𐑴 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥?”

“𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑞𐑱 𐑑𐑧𐑤 𐑿 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥? 𐑕𐑱 𐑞𐑨𐑑!”

“𐑞𐑱 𐑛𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑑𐑧𐑤 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑝 𐑧𐑯𐑦𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥; 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑲'𐑝 𐑣𐑻𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑰'𐑟 𐑩 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑢𐑱𐑤-𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑑𐑼, 𐑯 𐑩 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑮𐑵.”

“𐑞𐑨𐑑'𐑕 𐑑𐑮𐑵, 𐑞𐑨𐑑'𐑕 𐑑𐑮𐑵—𐑘𐑧𐑕, 𐑚𐑴𐑔 𐑑𐑮𐑵 𐑦𐑯𐑳𐑓. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑿 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑡𐑳𐑥𐑐 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑣𐑰 𐑜𐑦𐑝𐑟 𐑩𐑯 𐑹𐑛𐑼. 𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑐 𐑯 𐑜𐑮𐑬𐑤; 𐑜𐑮𐑬𐑤 𐑯 𐑜𐑴—𐑞𐑨𐑑'𐑕 𐑞 𐑢𐑻𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑯𐑳𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑪𐑓 ·𐑒𐑱𐑐 ·𐑣𐑹𐑯, 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑩𐑜𐑴, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑣𐑰 𐑤𐑱 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑛𐑧𐑛 𐑓 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑛𐑱𐑟 𐑯 𐑯𐑲𐑑𐑕; 𐑯𐑳𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑛𐑧𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑡 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑐𐑨𐑯𐑘𐑼𐑛 𐑩𐑓𐑹 𐑞 𐑷𐑤𐑑𐑼 𐑦𐑯 ·𐑕𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑩?—𐑣𐑻𐑛 𐑯𐑳𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑, 𐑱? 𐑯𐑳𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑦𐑤𐑝𐑼 𐑒𐑨𐑤𐑩𐑚𐑨𐑖 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑐𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵? 𐑯 𐑯𐑳𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑤𐑵𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑤𐑧𐑜 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑝𐑶𐑦𐑡, 𐑩𐑒𐑹𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑓𐑩𐑕𐑦. 𐑛𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑘𐑰 𐑣𐑽 𐑩 𐑢𐑻𐑛 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑥𐑨𐑑𐑼𐑟 𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑹, 𐑱? 𐑯𐑴, 𐑲 𐑛𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒 𐑘𐑰 𐑛𐑦𐑛; 𐑣𐑬 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑘𐑰? 𐑣𐑵 𐑯𐑴𐑟 𐑦𐑑? 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑷𐑤 ·𐑯𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑑, 𐑲 𐑜𐑧𐑕. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑣𐑬𐑟'𐑧𐑝𐑼, 𐑥𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑐, 𐑘𐑰'𐑝 𐑣𐑻𐑛 𐑑𐑧𐑤 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑞 𐑤𐑧𐑜, 𐑯 𐑣𐑬 𐑣𐑰 𐑤𐑪𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑑; 𐑲, 𐑘𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑣𐑻𐑛 𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑, 𐑲 𐑛𐑺 𐑕𐑱. 𐑴 𐑘𐑧𐑕, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑯𐑴𐑟 𐑩'𐑯𐑴𐑕𐑑—𐑲 𐑥𐑰𐑯 𐑞𐑱 𐑯𐑴 𐑣𐑰'𐑟 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑤𐑧𐑜; 𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑩 ·𐑐𐑸𐑥𐑩𐑕𐑧𐑑𐑦 𐑑𐑫𐑒 𐑞 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑪𐑓.”

“𐑥𐑲 𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑯𐑛,” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑲, “𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑡𐑦𐑚𐑼𐑦𐑖 𐑝 𐑘𐑹𐑟 𐑦𐑟 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑, 𐑲 𐑛𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑯𐑴, 𐑯 𐑲 𐑛𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑒𐑺; 𐑓 𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑟 𐑑 𐑥𐑰 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑿 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑩 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑛𐑨𐑥𐑦𐑡𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑣𐑧𐑛. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑓 𐑿 𐑸 𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑝 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚, 𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑞𐑺, 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛, 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑤𐑧𐑑 𐑥𐑰 𐑑𐑧𐑤 𐑿, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑲 𐑯𐑴 𐑷𐑤 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑞 𐑤𐑪𐑕 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑤𐑧𐑜.”

“𐑷𐑤 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑦𐑑, 𐑱—𐑖𐑫𐑼 𐑿 𐑛𐑵?—𐑷𐑤?”

“𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑖𐑫𐑼.”

𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑓𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑼 𐑐𐑶𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑯 𐑲 𐑤𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛, 𐑞 𐑚𐑧𐑜𐑼-𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑼 𐑕𐑑𐑫𐑛 𐑩 𐑥𐑴𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑, 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑓 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑮𐑧𐑝𐑼𐑦; 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤, 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑛 𐑯 𐑕𐑧𐑛:—“𐑘𐑰'𐑝 𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑑, 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑘𐑰? 𐑯𐑱𐑥𐑟 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑐𐑱𐑐𐑼𐑟? 𐑢𐑧𐑤, 𐑢𐑧𐑤, 𐑢𐑪𐑑'𐑕 𐑕𐑲𐑯𐑛, 𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑲𐑯𐑛; 𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑑'𐑕 𐑑 𐑚𐑰, 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑚𐑰; 𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯, 𐑐𐑼𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑕 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑚𐑰, 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑷𐑤. 𐑧𐑯𐑦𐑣𐑬, 𐑦𐑑'𐑕 𐑷𐑤 𐑓𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑑 𐑯 𐑼𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑛 𐑩'𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑦; 𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑼𐑟 𐑹 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑜𐑴 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑲 𐑕𐑩𐑐𐑴𐑟; 𐑨𐑟 𐑢𐑧𐑤 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑨𐑟 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑥𐑧𐑯, ·𐑜𐑪𐑛 𐑐𐑦𐑑𐑦 '𐑩𐑥! 𐑥𐑹𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑘𐑰, 𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑥𐑱𐑑𐑕, 𐑥𐑹𐑯𐑦𐑙; 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑧𐑓𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑣𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑚𐑤𐑧𐑕 𐑘𐑰; 𐑲'𐑥 𐑕𐑪𐑮𐑦 𐑲 𐑕𐑑𐑪𐑐𐑑 𐑘𐑰.”

“𐑤𐑫𐑒 𐑣𐑽, 𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑯𐑛,” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑲, “𐑦𐑓 𐑿 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑧𐑯𐑦𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑹𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑑 𐑑𐑧𐑤 𐑳𐑕, 𐑬𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑦𐑑; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑓 𐑿 𐑸 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑚𐑨𐑥𐑚𐑵𐑟𐑩𐑤 𐑳𐑕, 𐑿 𐑸 𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑘𐑹 𐑜𐑱𐑥; 𐑞𐑨𐑑'𐑕 𐑷𐑤 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑓 𐑑 𐑕𐑱.”

“𐑯 𐑦𐑑'𐑕 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑢𐑧𐑤, 𐑯 𐑲 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑑 𐑣𐑽 𐑩 𐑗𐑨𐑐 𐑑𐑷𐑒 𐑳𐑐 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑱; 𐑿 𐑸 𐑡𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑞 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑓 𐑣𐑦𐑥—𐑞 𐑤𐑲𐑒𐑕 𐑝 𐑘𐑰. 𐑥𐑹𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑘𐑰, 𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑥𐑱𐑑𐑕, 𐑥𐑹𐑯𐑦𐑙! 𐑴! 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑘𐑰 𐑜𐑧𐑑 𐑞𐑺, 𐑑𐑧𐑤 '𐑩𐑥 𐑲'𐑝 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑒𐑤𐑵𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑑 𐑥𐑱𐑒 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝 '𐑩𐑥.”

“𐑭, 𐑥𐑲 𐑛𐑽 𐑓𐑧𐑤𐑴, 𐑿 𐑒𐑭𐑯𐑑 𐑓𐑵𐑤 𐑳𐑕 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑱—𐑿 𐑒𐑭𐑯𐑑 𐑓𐑵𐑤 𐑳𐑕. 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑞 𐑰𐑟𐑾𐑕𐑑 𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛 𐑓 𐑩 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑑 𐑤𐑫𐑒 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑓 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑩 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑒𐑮𐑩𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥.”

“𐑥𐑹𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑘𐑰, 𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑥𐑱𐑑𐑕, 𐑥𐑹𐑯𐑦𐑙.”

“𐑥𐑹𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟,” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑲. “𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑙, ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜, 𐑤𐑧𐑑'𐑕 𐑤𐑰𐑝 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑒𐑮𐑱𐑟𐑦 𐑥𐑨𐑯. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑪𐑐, 𐑑𐑧𐑤 𐑥𐑰 𐑘𐑹 𐑯𐑱𐑥, 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑿?”

“·𐑦𐑤𐑲𐑡𐑩.”

·𐑦𐑤𐑲𐑡𐑩! 𐑔𐑷𐑑 𐑲, 𐑯 𐑢𐑰 𐑢𐑷𐑒𐑑 𐑩𐑢𐑱, 𐑚𐑴𐑔 𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑙, 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑰𐑗 𐑳𐑞𐑼'𐑟 𐑓𐑨𐑖𐑩𐑯, 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑮𐑨𐑜𐑩𐑛 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑼; 𐑯 𐑩𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑳𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑩 𐑣𐑳𐑥𐑚𐑳𐑜, 𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑩 𐑚𐑳𐑜𐑚𐑺. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑜𐑪𐑯 𐑐𐑼𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑕 𐑩𐑚𐑳𐑝 𐑩 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑛 𐑘𐑸𐑛𐑟, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑗𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑑𐑻𐑯 𐑩 𐑒𐑹𐑯𐑼, 𐑯 𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑨𐑒 𐑨𐑟 𐑲 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑕𐑴, 𐑣𐑵 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑚𐑰 𐑕𐑰𐑯 𐑚𐑳𐑑 ·𐑦𐑤𐑲𐑡𐑩 𐑓𐑪𐑤𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑳𐑕, 𐑞𐑴 𐑨𐑑 𐑩 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕. 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑣𐑬, 𐑞 𐑕𐑲𐑑 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑒 𐑥𐑰 𐑕𐑴, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑲 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑯𐑳𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑑 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑦𐑣𐑲𐑯𐑛, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑐𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑪𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑥𐑲 𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑮𐑱𐑛, 𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑕 𐑑 𐑕𐑰 𐑢𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑼 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑑𐑻𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑒𐑹𐑯𐑼 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑰 𐑛𐑦𐑛. 𐑣𐑰 𐑛𐑦𐑛; 𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑑 𐑥𐑰 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑛𐑪𐑜𐑦𐑙 𐑳𐑕, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑲 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑓 𐑞 𐑤𐑲𐑓 𐑝 𐑥𐑰 𐑦𐑥𐑨𐑡𐑦𐑯. 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑕𐑻𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑕, 𐑒𐑳𐑐𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑨𐑥𐑚𐑦𐑜𐑿𐑩𐑕, 𐑣𐑭𐑓-𐑣𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑙, 𐑣𐑭𐑓-𐑮𐑦𐑝𐑰𐑤𐑦𐑙, 𐑖𐑮𐑬𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑕𐑹𐑑 𐑝 𐑑𐑷𐑒, 𐑯𐑬 𐑚𐑦𐑜𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑰 𐑷𐑤 𐑒𐑲𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑝 𐑝𐑱𐑜 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑯 𐑣𐑭𐑓-𐑨𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑣𐑧𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟, 𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛; 𐑯 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚; 𐑯 𐑞 𐑤𐑧𐑜 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑤𐑪𐑕𐑑; 𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑒𐑱𐑐 ·𐑣𐑹𐑯 𐑓𐑦𐑑; 𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑦𐑤𐑝𐑼 𐑒𐑨𐑤𐑩𐑚𐑨𐑖; 𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑑 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 ·𐑐𐑰𐑤𐑧𐑜 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑲 𐑤𐑧𐑓𐑑 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑞 𐑛𐑱 𐑐𐑮𐑰𐑝𐑾𐑕; 𐑯 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑒𐑢𐑷 ·𐑑𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑜; 𐑯 𐑞 𐑝𐑶𐑦𐑡 𐑢𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑬𐑼𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑝𐑟 𐑑 𐑕𐑱𐑤; 𐑯 𐑩 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑛 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑖𐑨𐑛𐑴𐑦 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑟.

𐑲 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑪𐑤𐑝𐑛 𐑑 𐑕𐑨𐑑𐑦𐑕𐑓𐑲 𐑥𐑲𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑢𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑮𐑨𐑜𐑩𐑛 ·𐑦𐑤𐑲𐑡𐑩 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑮𐑾𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑪𐑜𐑦𐑙 𐑳𐑕 𐑹 𐑯𐑪𐑑, 𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑒𐑮𐑪𐑕𐑑 𐑞 𐑢𐑱 𐑢𐑦𐑞 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜, 𐑯 𐑪𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑝 𐑦𐑑 𐑮𐑰𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑕𐑑 𐑬𐑼 𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑐𐑕. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 ·𐑦𐑤𐑲𐑡𐑩 𐑐𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑪𐑯, 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑯𐑴𐑑𐑦𐑕 𐑳𐑕. 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑮𐑦𐑤𐑰𐑝𐑛 𐑥𐑰; 𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑕 𐑥𐑹, 𐑯 𐑓𐑲𐑯𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑑 𐑥𐑰, 𐑲 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑯𐑬𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑲 𐑣𐑸𐑑, 𐑩 𐑣𐑳𐑥𐑚𐑳𐑜.

·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 20. 𐑷𐑤 ·𐑩𐑕𐑑𐑻.

𐑩 𐑛𐑱 𐑹 𐑑𐑵 𐑐𐑭𐑕𐑑, 𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑨𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑩𐑚𐑹𐑛 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛. 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑢𐑻 𐑞 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑯𐑿 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑪𐑯 𐑚𐑹𐑛, 𐑯 𐑚𐑴𐑤𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑝𐑩𐑕, 𐑯 𐑒𐑶𐑤𐑟 𐑝 𐑮𐑦𐑜𐑦𐑙; 𐑦𐑯 𐑖𐑹𐑑, 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑴𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐'𐑕 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑐𐑼𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑣𐑳𐑮𐑦𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑩 𐑒𐑤𐑴𐑟. 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 ·𐑐𐑰𐑤𐑧𐑜 𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑛𐑩𐑥 𐑹 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑩𐑖𐑹, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑕𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑜𐑢𐑭𐑥 𐑒𐑰𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑖𐑸𐑐 𐑤𐑫𐑒-𐑬𐑑 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟: ·𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑛𐑨𐑛 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑐𐑻𐑗𐑩𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑯 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑝𐑲𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑹𐑟; 𐑯 𐑞 𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑶𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑯 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑮𐑦𐑜𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑻 𐑢𐑻𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑯𐑲𐑑-𐑓𐑷𐑤.

𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑛𐑱 𐑓𐑪𐑤𐑴𐑦𐑙 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜'𐑟 𐑕𐑲𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑸𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑟, 𐑢𐑻𐑛 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑜𐑦𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑨𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑟 𐑢𐑺 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐'𐑕 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑦 𐑢𐑻 𐑕𐑑𐑪𐑐𐑦𐑙, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑗𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑕 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑪𐑯 𐑚𐑹𐑛 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑯𐑲𐑑, 𐑓 𐑞𐑺 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑴 𐑑𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑬 𐑕𐑵𐑯 𐑞 𐑝𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑤 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙. 𐑕𐑴 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜 𐑯 𐑲 𐑜𐑪𐑑 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑬𐑼 𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑐𐑕, 𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑪𐑤𐑝𐑦𐑙, 𐑣𐑬𐑧𐑝𐑼, 𐑑 𐑕𐑤𐑰𐑐 𐑩𐑖𐑹 𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑞 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑟 𐑞𐑱 𐑷𐑤𐑢𐑱𐑟 𐑜𐑦𐑝 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑯𐑴𐑑𐑦𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑒𐑱𐑕𐑩𐑟, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑱𐑤 𐑓 𐑕𐑧𐑝𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑛𐑱𐑟. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑯𐑴 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼; 𐑞𐑺 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑛𐑰𐑤 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑛𐑳𐑯, 𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑴 𐑑𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑬 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑔𐑷𐑑 𐑝, 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑓𐑫𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑐𐑑.

𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑯𐑴𐑟 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑩 𐑥𐑳𐑤𐑑𐑦𐑑𐑿𐑛 𐑝 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑟—𐑚𐑧𐑛𐑟, 𐑕𐑷𐑕-𐑐𐑨𐑯𐑟, 𐑯𐑲𐑝𐑟 𐑯 𐑓𐑹𐑒𐑕, 𐑖𐑳𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑯 𐑑𐑪𐑙𐑟, 𐑯𐑨𐑐𐑒𐑦𐑯𐑟, 𐑯𐑳𐑑-𐑒𐑮𐑨𐑒𐑼𐑟, 𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑑, 𐑸 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑑 𐑞 𐑚𐑦𐑟𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑣𐑬𐑕𐑒𐑰𐑐𐑦𐑙. 𐑡𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑴 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑯𐑦𐑕𐑧𐑕𐑦𐑑𐑱𐑑𐑕 𐑩 𐑔𐑮𐑰-𐑘𐑽𐑟' 𐑣𐑬𐑕𐑒𐑰𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑲𐑛 𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯, 𐑓𐑸 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑷𐑤 𐑜𐑮𐑴𐑕𐑼𐑟, 𐑒𐑪𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑥𐑳𐑙𐑜𐑼𐑟, 𐑛𐑪𐑒𐑑𐑼𐑟, 𐑚𐑱𐑒𐑼𐑟, 𐑯 𐑚𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑼𐑟. 𐑯 𐑞𐑴 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑷𐑤𐑕𐑴 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑟 𐑑𐑮𐑵 𐑝 𐑥𐑻𐑗𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑝𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑤𐑟, 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑥𐑰𐑯𐑟 𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑥𐑧𐑯. 𐑓 𐑚𐑦𐑕𐑲𐑛𐑟 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑤𐑧𐑙𐑔 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑝𐑶𐑦𐑡, 𐑞 𐑯𐑿𐑥𐑼𐑩𐑕 𐑸𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑽 𐑑 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑼𐑦, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑪𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑝 𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑴𐑑 𐑣𐑸𐑚𐑼𐑟 𐑿𐑠𐑵𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑓𐑮𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛, 𐑦𐑑 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑧𐑥𐑚𐑼𐑛, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑝 𐑷𐑤 𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑕, 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑝𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑸 𐑞 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑴𐑟𐑛 𐑑 𐑨𐑒𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑷𐑤 𐑒𐑲𐑯𐑛𐑟, 𐑯 𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑑 𐑞 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑯 𐑤𐑪𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑞 𐑕𐑩𐑒𐑕𐑧𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑝𐑶𐑦𐑡 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑟. 𐑣𐑧𐑯𐑕, 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑺 𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕, 𐑕𐑐𐑺 𐑕𐑐𐑸𐑟, 𐑯 𐑕𐑐𐑺 𐑤𐑲𐑯𐑟 𐑯 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑟, 𐑯 𐑕𐑐𐑺 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑟, 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑩 𐑕𐑐𐑺 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 𐑯 𐑛𐑿𐑐𐑤𐑦𐑒𐑱𐑑 𐑖𐑦𐑐.

𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑐𐑽𐑾𐑛 𐑝 𐑬𐑼 𐑼𐑲𐑝𐑩𐑤 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛, 𐑞 𐑣𐑧𐑝𐑾𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑹𐑦𐑡 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑰𐑑𐑩𐑛; 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑮𐑲𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑻 𐑚𐑰𐑓, 𐑚𐑮𐑧𐑛, 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼, 𐑓𐑿𐑩𐑤, 𐑯 𐑲𐑼𐑯 𐑣𐑵𐑐𐑕 𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑝𐑟. 𐑚𐑳𐑑, 𐑨𐑟 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑣𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛, 𐑓 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑞𐑺 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑿𐑩𐑤 𐑓𐑧𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑯 𐑒𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑦𐑙 𐑪𐑯 𐑚𐑹𐑛 𐑝 𐑛𐑲𐑝𐑼𐑟 𐑪𐑛𐑟 𐑯 𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑝 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑟, 𐑚𐑴𐑔 𐑤𐑸𐑡 𐑯 𐑕𐑥𐑷𐑤.

𐑗𐑰𐑓 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑣𐑵 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑓𐑧𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑯 𐑒𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑪𐑟 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 ·𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑛𐑨𐑛'𐑟 𐑕𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑼, 𐑩 𐑤𐑰𐑯 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑤𐑱𐑛𐑦 𐑝 𐑩 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑑𐑻𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑛 𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑓𐑨𐑑𐑦𐑜𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑐𐑦𐑮𐑦𐑑, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑷𐑤 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑒𐑲𐑯𐑛𐑣𐑸𐑑𐑩𐑛, 𐑣𐑵 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑪𐑤𐑝𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑, 𐑦𐑓 𐑖𐑰 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑐 𐑦𐑑, 𐑯𐑳𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑚𐑰 𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑢𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛, 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑕 𐑓𐑺𐑤𐑦 𐑜𐑧𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑕𐑰. 𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑖𐑰 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑪𐑯 𐑚𐑹𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑡𐑸 𐑝 𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑓 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑿𐑼𐑛'𐑟 𐑐𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑦; 𐑩𐑯𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑚𐑳𐑯𐑗 𐑝 𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑤𐑟 𐑓 𐑞 𐑗𐑰𐑓 𐑥𐑱𐑑'𐑕 𐑛𐑧𐑕𐑒, 𐑢𐑺 𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑧𐑐𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑤𐑪𐑜; 𐑩 𐑔𐑻𐑛 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑮𐑴𐑤 𐑝 𐑓𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑓 𐑞 𐑕𐑥𐑷𐑤 𐑝 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑢𐑳𐑯'𐑟 𐑮𐑵𐑥𐑨𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑚𐑨𐑒. 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑢𐑫𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑚𐑧𐑑𐑼 𐑛𐑦𐑟𐑻𐑝 𐑣𐑻 𐑯𐑱𐑥, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑢𐑪𐑟 ·𐑗𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑦—·𐑭𐑯𐑑 ·𐑗𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑦, 𐑨𐑟 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦 𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑛 𐑣𐑻. 𐑯 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑕𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑼 𐑝 𐑗𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑗𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 ·𐑭𐑯𐑑 ·𐑗𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑚𐑳𐑕𐑩𐑤 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑞𐑼 𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑞𐑼, 𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑦 𐑑 𐑑𐑻𐑯 𐑣𐑻 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑯 𐑣𐑸𐑑 𐑑 𐑧𐑯𐑦𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑑 𐑑 𐑘𐑰𐑤𐑛 𐑕𐑱𐑓𐑑𐑦, 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑓𐑼𐑑, 𐑯 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑤𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑪𐑯 𐑚𐑹𐑛 𐑩 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑣𐑻 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑳𐑝𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑮𐑳𐑞𐑼 ·𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑛𐑨𐑛 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑻𐑯𐑛, 𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑖𐑰 𐑣𐑻𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑴𐑯𐑛 𐑩 𐑕𐑒𐑹 𐑹 𐑑𐑵 𐑝 𐑢𐑧𐑤-𐑕𐑱𐑝𐑛 𐑛𐑪𐑤𐑼𐑟.

𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑕𐑰 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑩𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑣𐑸𐑑𐑩𐑛 ·𐑒𐑢𐑱𐑒𐑼𐑧𐑕 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑪𐑯 𐑚𐑹𐑛, 𐑨𐑟 𐑖𐑰 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑞 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑛𐑱, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑶𐑤-𐑤𐑱𐑛𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛, 𐑯 𐑩 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑤𐑪𐑙𐑜𐑼 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑳𐑞𐑼. 𐑯𐑹 𐑢𐑪𐑟 ·𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑛𐑨𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑯𐑹 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 ·𐑐𐑰𐑤𐑧𐑜 𐑨𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑚𐑨𐑒𐑢𐑼𐑛. 𐑨𐑟 𐑓 ·𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑛𐑨𐑛, 𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑛 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑩 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑤𐑦𐑕𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑸𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑯𐑰𐑛𐑩𐑛, 𐑯 𐑨𐑑 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑖 𐑼𐑲𐑝𐑩𐑤, 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑸𐑒 𐑪𐑐𐑩𐑟𐑦𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑸𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑐𐑱𐑐𐑼. 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑢𐑲𐑤 ·𐑐𐑰𐑤𐑧𐑜 𐑒𐑱𐑥 𐑣𐑪𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑚𐑴𐑯 𐑛𐑧𐑯, 𐑮𐑹𐑦𐑙 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑞 𐑣𐑨𐑗𐑢𐑱𐑟, 𐑮𐑹𐑦𐑙 𐑳𐑐 𐑑 𐑞 𐑮𐑦𐑜𐑼𐑟 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑-𐑣𐑧𐑛, 𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑒𐑤𐑵𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑮𐑹𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑨𐑒 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑜𐑢𐑭𐑥.

𐑛𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑛𐑱𐑟 𐑝 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑐𐑼𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯, ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜 𐑯 𐑲 𐑪𐑓𐑩𐑯 𐑝𐑦𐑟𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑭𐑓𐑑, 𐑯 𐑨𐑟 𐑪𐑓𐑩𐑯 𐑲 𐑭𐑕𐑒𐑑 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚, 𐑯 𐑣𐑬 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟, 𐑯 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑜𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑪𐑯 𐑚𐑹𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑖𐑦𐑐. 𐑑 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑕𐑗𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑞𐑱 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑼, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑜𐑧𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑧𐑑𐑼 𐑯 𐑚𐑧𐑑𐑼, 𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑩𐑚𐑹𐑛 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑛𐑱; 𐑥𐑰𐑯𐑑𐑲𐑥, 𐑞 𐑑𐑵 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑟, ·𐑐𐑰𐑤𐑧𐑜 𐑯 ·𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑛𐑨𐑛, 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑩𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑑 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑯𐑧𐑕𐑦𐑕𐑺𐑦 𐑑 𐑓𐑦𐑑 𐑞 𐑝𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑤 𐑓 𐑞 𐑝𐑶𐑦𐑡. 𐑦𐑓 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑛𐑬𐑯𐑮𐑲𐑑 𐑪𐑯𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑥𐑲𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓, 𐑲 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑕𐑰𐑯 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑲 𐑣𐑸𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑲 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑣𐑭𐑓 𐑓𐑨𐑯𐑕𐑦 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑱 𐑑 𐑕𐑴 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑩 𐑝𐑶𐑦𐑡, 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑕 𐑤𐑱𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑲 𐑲𐑟 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑣𐑵 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑞 𐑨𐑚𐑕𐑩𐑤𐑵𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑑𐑱𐑑𐑼 𐑝 𐑦𐑑, 𐑕𐑴 𐑕𐑵𐑯 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑛 𐑬𐑑 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑴𐑐𐑩𐑯 𐑕𐑰. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑩 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑕𐑩𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑕 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑮𐑪𐑙, 𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑓 𐑣𐑰 𐑚𐑰 𐑷𐑤𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑦 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑪𐑤𐑝𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑥𐑨𐑑𐑼, 𐑣𐑰 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑝𐑟 𐑑 𐑒𐑳𐑝𐑼 𐑳𐑐 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑩𐑕𐑐𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓. 𐑯 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑱 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑥𐑰. 𐑲 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑯𐑳𐑔𐑦𐑙, 𐑯 𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑛 𐑑 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒 𐑯𐑳𐑔𐑦𐑙.

𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑜𐑦𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑬𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑯𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑 𐑛𐑱 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑱𐑤. 𐑕𐑴 𐑯𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑 𐑥𐑹𐑯𐑦𐑙, ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜 𐑯 𐑲 𐑑𐑫𐑒 𐑩 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑻𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑑.

·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 21. 𐑜𐑴𐑦𐑙 ·𐑩𐑚𐑹𐑛.

𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑽𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑕 𐑴'𐑒𐑤𐑪𐑒, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑜𐑮𐑱 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑻𐑓𐑦𐑒𐑑 𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑦 𐑛𐑷𐑯, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑢𐑰 𐑛𐑮𐑵 𐑯𐑲 𐑞 𐑢𐑹𐑓.

“𐑞𐑺 𐑸 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑼𐑟 𐑮𐑳𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑞𐑺, 𐑦𐑓 𐑲 𐑕𐑰 𐑮𐑲𐑑,” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑲 𐑑 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜, “𐑦𐑑 𐑒𐑭𐑯𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑖𐑨𐑛𐑴𐑟; 𐑖𐑰'𐑟 𐑪𐑓 𐑚𐑲 𐑕𐑳𐑯𐑮𐑲𐑟, 𐑲 𐑜𐑧𐑕; 𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑪𐑯!”

“𐑩𐑝𐑭𐑕𐑑!” 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 𐑩 𐑝𐑶𐑕, 𐑣𐑵𐑟 𐑴𐑯𐑼 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑒𐑤𐑴𐑕 𐑚𐑦𐑣𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑳𐑕, 𐑤𐑱𐑛 𐑩 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑚𐑴𐑔 𐑬𐑼 𐑖𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑼𐑟, 𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑯𐑿𐑱𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑢𐑰𐑯 𐑳𐑕, 𐑕𐑑𐑫𐑛 𐑕𐑑𐑵𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑹𐑢𐑼𐑛 𐑩 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤, 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑳𐑯𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑑𐑢𐑲𐑤𐑲𐑑, 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑽𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜 𐑑 𐑥𐑰. 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 ·𐑦𐑤𐑲𐑡𐑩.

“𐑜𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑚𐑹𐑛?”

“𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑪𐑓, 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑿,” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑲.

“𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑰 𐑣𐑽,” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜, 𐑖𐑱𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓, “𐑜𐑴 '𐑢𐑱!”

“𐑱𐑯𐑑 𐑜𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑚𐑹𐑛, 𐑞𐑧𐑯?”

“𐑘𐑧𐑕, 𐑢𐑰 𐑸,” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑲, “𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑟𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑦𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑝 𐑘𐑹𐑟? 𐑛𐑵 𐑿 𐑯𐑴, ·𐑥𐑼 ·𐑦𐑤𐑲𐑡𐑩, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑲 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑼 𐑿 𐑩 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑻𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑯𐑑?”

“𐑯𐑴, 𐑯𐑴, 𐑯𐑴; 𐑲 𐑢𐑪𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑩𐑢𐑺 𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑,” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 ·𐑦𐑤𐑲𐑡𐑩, 𐑕𐑤𐑴𐑤𐑦 𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑥𐑰 𐑑 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑳𐑯𐑩𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑜𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟.

“·𐑦𐑤𐑲𐑡𐑩,” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑲, “𐑿 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑲𐑡 𐑥𐑲 𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑯 𐑥𐑰 𐑚𐑲 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑛𐑮𐑷𐑦𐑙. 𐑢𐑰 𐑸 𐑜𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑾𐑯 𐑯 ·𐑐𐑩𐑕𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑒 ·𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟, 𐑯 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑓𐑻 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑛𐑦𐑑𐑱𐑯𐑛.”

“𐑘𐑰 𐑚𐑰, 𐑚𐑰 𐑘𐑰? 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑨𐑒 𐑩𐑓𐑹 𐑚𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑓𐑩𐑕𐑑?”

“𐑣𐑰'𐑟 𐑒𐑮𐑨𐑒𐑑, ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜,” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑲, “𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑪𐑯.”

“𐑣𐑪𐑤𐑴!” 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑼𐑦 ·𐑦𐑤𐑲𐑡𐑩, 𐑣𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑳𐑕 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑢𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑵𐑝𐑛 𐑩 𐑓𐑿 𐑐𐑱𐑕𐑩𐑟.

“𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑥𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥,” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑲, “·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜, 𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑪𐑯.”

𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑑𐑴𐑤 𐑳𐑐 𐑑 𐑳𐑕 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯, 𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑤𐑨𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑪𐑯 𐑥𐑲 𐑖𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑼, 𐑕𐑧𐑛—“𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑘𐑰 𐑕𐑰 𐑧𐑯𐑦𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑜𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑑𐑩𐑢𐑹𐑛𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑩 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑩𐑜𐑴?”

𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑒 𐑚𐑲 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑯 𐑥𐑨𐑑𐑼-𐑝-𐑓𐑨𐑒𐑑 𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑕𐑗𐑩𐑯, 𐑲 𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑼𐑛, 𐑕𐑱𐑦𐑙, “𐑘𐑧𐑕, 𐑲 𐑔𐑷𐑑 𐑲 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑕𐑰 𐑓𐑹 𐑹 𐑓𐑲𐑝 𐑥𐑧𐑯; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑑𐑵 𐑛𐑦𐑥 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑖𐑫𐑼.”

“𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑛𐑦𐑥, 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑛𐑦𐑥,” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 ·𐑦𐑤𐑲𐑡𐑩. “𐑥𐑹𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑘𐑰.”

𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑕 𐑥𐑹 𐑢𐑰 𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑕 𐑥𐑹 𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑱𐑥 𐑕𐑪𐑓𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑳𐑕; 𐑯 𐑑𐑳𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑲 𐑖𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑼 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯, 𐑕𐑧𐑛, “𐑕𐑰 𐑦𐑓 𐑿 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑓𐑲𐑯𐑛 '𐑩𐑥 𐑯𐑬, 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑘𐑰?

“𐑓𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑣𐑵?”

“𐑥𐑹𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑘𐑰! 𐑥𐑹𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑘𐑰!” 𐑣𐑰 𐑮𐑰𐑡𐑶𐑯𐑛, 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯 𐑥𐑵𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑪𐑓. “𐑴! 𐑲 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑜𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑢𐑹𐑯 𐑘𐑰 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑕𐑑—𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑥𐑲𐑯𐑛, 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑥𐑲𐑯𐑛—𐑦𐑑'𐑕 𐑷𐑤 𐑢𐑳𐑯, 𐑷𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑨𐑥𐑤𐑦 𐑑𐑵;—𐑖𐑸𐑐 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑕𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑥𐑹𐑯𐑦𐑙, 𐑱𐑯𐑑 𐑦𐑑? 𐑜𐑫𐑛-𐑚𐑲 𐑑 𐑘𐑰. 𐑖𐑭𐑯𐑑 𐑕𐑰 𐑘𐑰 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑕𐑵𐑯, 𐑲 𐑜𐑧𐑕; 𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑧𐑕 𐑦𐑑'𐑕 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑞 ·𐑜𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑛 ·𐑡𐑫𐑼𐑦.” 𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑒𐑮𐑨𐑒𐑑 𐑢𐑻𐑛𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑓𐑲𐑯𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑦𐑐𐑸𐑑𐑩𐑛, 𐑤𐑰𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑰, 𐑓 𐑞 𐑥𐑴𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑, 𐑦𐑯 𐑯𐑴 𐑕𐑥𐑷𐑤 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑿𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑕.

𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑, 𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑪𐑯 𐑚𐑹𐑛 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛, 𐑢𐑰 𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑒𐑢𐑲𐑩𐑑, 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑩 𐑕𐑴𐑤 𐑥𐑵𐑝𐑦𐑙. 𐑞 𐑒𐑨𐑚𐑦𐑯 𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑤𐑪𐑒𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑦𐑯; 𐑞 𐑣𐑨𐑗𐑩𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑷𐑤 𐑪𐑯, 𐑯 𐑤𐑳𐑥𐑚𐑼𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑒𐑶𐑤𐑟 𐑝 𐑮𐑦𐑜𐑦𐑙. 𐑜𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑹𐑢𐑼𐑛 𐑑 𐑞 𐑓𐑴𐑒𐑕𐑩𐑤, 𐑢𐑰 𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑞 𐑕𐑤𐑲𐑛 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑒𐑳𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑴𐑐𐑩𐑯. 𐑕𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑤𐑲𐑑, 𐑢𐑰 𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑛𐑬𐑯, 𐑯 𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑩𐑯 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑮𐑦𐑜𐑼 𐑞𐑺, 𐑮𐑨𐑐𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑑𐑨𐑑𐑼𐑛 𐑐𐑰-𐑡𐑨𐑒𐑩𐑑. 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑔𐑮𐑴𐑯 𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑴𐑤 𐑤𐑧𐑙𐑔 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑑𐑵 𐑗𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑕, 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑱𐑕 𐑛𐑬𐑯𐑢𐑼𐑛𐑟 𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑤𐑴𐑟𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑸𐑥𐑟. 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑤𐑳𐑥𐑚𐑼 𐑕𐑤𐑧𐑐𐑑 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥.

“𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑼𐑟 𐑢𐑰 𐑕𐑷, ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜, 𐑢𐑺 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑞𐑱 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑜𐑪𐑯 𐑑?” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑲, 𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑛𐑿𐑚𐑾𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑤𐑰𐑐𐑼. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑹𐑓, ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑯𐑴𐑑𐑦𐑕𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑲 𐑯𐑬 𐑩𐑤𐑵𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑑; 𐑣𐑧𐑯𐑕 𐑲 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑔𐑷𐑑 𐑥𐑲𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑪𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑰𐑝𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑨𐑑𐑼, 𐑢𐑻 𐑦𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑓 ·𐑦𐑤𐑲𐑡𐑩'𐑟 𐑳𐑞𐑼𐑢𐑲𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑤𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑕𐑗𐑩𐑯. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑲 𐑚𐑰𐑑 𐑞 𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑛𐑬𐑯; 𐑯 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯 𐑥𐑸𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑕𐑤𐑰𐑐𐑼, 𐑡𐑪𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑼𐑤𐑦 𐑣𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑑 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑐𐑼𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑕 𐑢𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑦𐑑 𐑳𐑐 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦; 𐑑𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑑 𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑚𐑤𐑦𐑖 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑩𐑒𐑹𐑛𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦. 𐑣𐑰 𐑐𐑫𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑤𐑰𐑐𐑼'𐑟 𐑮𐑽, 𐑨𐑟 𐑞𐑴 𐑓𐑰𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑓 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑪𐑓𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑳𐑓; 𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑 𐑥𐑹 𐑩𐑛𐑵, 𐑕𐑨𐑑 𐑒𐑢𐑲𐑩𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑞𐑺.

“𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑕! ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜, 𐑛𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑕𐑦𐑑 𐑞𐑺,” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑲.

“𐑴! ·𐑐𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑛𐑵𐑛 𐑕𐑰𐑑,” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜, “𐑥𐑲 𐑒𐑳𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑦 𐑢𐑱; 𐑢𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑣𐑻𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑓𐑱𐑕.”

“𐑓𐑱𐑕!” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑲, “𐑒𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑱𐑕? 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑚𐑦𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑞𐑧𐑯; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑣𐑬 𐑣𐑸𐑛 𐑣𐑰 𐑚𐑮𐑰𐑞𐑟, 𐑣𐑰'𐑟 𐑣𐑰𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓; 𐑜𐑧𐑑 𐑪𐑓, ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜, 𐑿 𐑸 𐑣𐑧𐑝𐑦, 𐑦𐑑'𐑕 𐑜𐑮𐑲𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑓𐑱𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑐𐑫𐑼. 𐑜𐑧𐑑 𐑪𐑓, ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜! 𐑤𐑫𐑒, 𐑣𐑰'𐑤 𐑑𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑿 𐑪𐑓 𐑕𐑵𐑯. 𐑲 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑣𐑰 𐑛𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑒.”

·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑵𐑝𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑑 𐑡𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑘𐑪𐑯𐑛 𐑞 𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑤𐑰𐑐𐑼, 𐑯 𐑤𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑑𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑣𐑷𐑒 𐑐𐑲𐑐. 𐑲 𐑕𐑨𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑓𐑰𐑑. 𐑢𐑰 𐑒𐑧𐑐𐑑 𐑞 𐑐𐑲𐑐 𐑐𐑭𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑞 𐑕𐑤𐑰𐑐𐑼, 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑑 𐑞 𐑳𐑞𐑼. 𐑥𐑰𐑯𐑢𐑲𐑤, 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑕𐑗𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑮𐑴𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑓𐑨𐑖𐑩𐑯, ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜 𐑜𐑱𐑝 𐑥𐑰 𐑑 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑, 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛, 𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑞 𐑨𐑚𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑝 𐑕𐑧𐑑𐑰𐑟 𐑯 𐑕𐑴𐑓𐑩𐑟 𐑝 𐑷𐑤 𐑕𐑹𐑑𐑕, 𐑞 𐑒𐑦𐑙, 𐑗𐑰𐑓𐑕, 𐑯 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑐𐑰𐑐𐑩𐑤 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑤𐑦, 𐑢𐑻 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑒𐑳𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑥 𐑝 𐑓𐑨𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑝 𐑞 𐑤𐑴𐑼 𐑹𐑛𐑼𐑟 𐑓 𐑪𐑑𐑩𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑟; 𐑯 𐑑 𐑓𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑖 𐑩 𐑣𐑬𐑕 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑓𐑼𐑑𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑, 𐑿 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑳𐑐 𐑱𐑑 𐑹 𐑑𐑧𐑯 𐑤𐑱𐑟𐑦 𐑓𐑧𐑤𐑴𐑟, 𐑯 𐑤𐑱 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑐𐑽𐑟 𐑯 𐑨𐑤𐑒𐑴𐑝𐑟. 𐑚𐑦𐑕𐑲𐑛𐑟, 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑝𐑰𐑯𐑾𐑯𐑑 𐑪𐑯 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑒𐑻𐑖𐑩𐑯; 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑚𐑧𐑑𐑼 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑜𐑸𐑛𐑩𐑯-𐑗𐑺𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑸 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑝𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑢𐑷𐑒𐑦𐑙-𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑕; 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑩𐑒𐑱𐑠𐑩𐑯, 𐑩 𐑗𐑰𐑓 𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑩𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑑, 𐑯 𐑛𐑦𐑟𐑲𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑑 𐑥𐑱𐑒 𐑩 𐑕𐑧𐑑𐑰 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑩 𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑑𐑮𐑰, 𐑐𐑼𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑛𐑨𐑥𐑐 𐑥𐑸𐑖𐑦 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕.

𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑯𐑼𐑱𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑟, 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑑𐑲𐑥 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜 𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑰𐑝𐑛 𐑞 𐑑𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑣𐑷𐑒 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑥𐑰, 𐑣𐑰 𐑓𐑤𐑳𐑮𐑦𐑖𐑑 𐑞 𐑣𐑨𐑗𐑩𐑑-𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑝 𐑦𐑑 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑞 𐑕𐑤𐑰𐑐𐑼'𐑟 𐑣𐑧𐑛.

“𐑢𐑪𐑑'𐑕 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑓, ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜?”

“·𐑐𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑰𐑟𐑦, 𐑒𐑦𐑤-𐑰; 𐑴! ·𐑐𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑰𐑟𐑦!”

𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑜𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑪𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑢𐑲𐑤𐑛 𐑮𐑧𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑑𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑣𐑷𐑒-𐑐𐑲𐑐, 𐑢𐑦𐑗, 𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛, 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑑𐑵 𐑿𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑚𐑴𐑔 𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑴𐑟 𐑯 𐑕𐑵𐑞𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑴𐑤, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑢𐑰 𐑢𐑻 𐑛𐑦𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑩𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑤𐑰𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑮𐑦𐑜𐑼. 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑪𐑙 𐑝𐑱𐑐𐑼 𐑯𐑬 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑰𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑓𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑣𐑴𐑤, 𐑦𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑜𐑨𐑯 𐑑 𐑑𐑧𐑤 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥. 𐑣𐑰 𐑚𐑮𐑰𐑞𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑕𐑹𐑑 𐑝 𐑥𐑳𐑓𐑩𐑤𐑩𐑛𐑯𐑩𐑕; 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑯𐑴𐑟; 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑮𐑦𐑝𐑪𐑤𐑝𐑛 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑕 𐑹 𐑑𐑢𐑲𐑕; 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑕𐑨𐑑 𐑳𐑐 𐑯 𐑮𐑳𐑚𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑲𐑟.

“𐑣𐑪𐑤𐑴!” 𐑣𐑰 𐑚𐑮𐑰𐑞𐑛 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑, “𐑣𐑵 𐑚𐑰 𐑘𐑰 𐑕𐑥𐑴𐑒𐑼𐑟?”

“𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑑 𐑥𐑧𐑯,” 𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑼𐑛 𐑲, “𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑛𐑳𐑟 𐑖𐑰 𐑕𐑱𐑤?”

“𐑲, 𐑲, 𐑘𐑰 𐑸 𐑜𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑻, 𐑚𐑰 𐑘𐑰? 𐑖𐑰 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑑-𐑛𐑱. 𐑞 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 𐑒𐑱𐑥 𐑩𐑚𐑹𐑛 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑯𐑲𐑑.”

“𐑢𐑪𐑑 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯?—𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚?”

“𐑣𐑵 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑰𐑛?”

𐑲 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑜𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑭𐑕𐑒 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑓𐑻𐑞𐑼 𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑕𐑗𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑙 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑢𐑰 𐑣𐑻𐑛 𐑩 𐑯𐑶𐑟 𐑪𐑯 𐑛𐑧𐑒.

“𐑣𐑪𐑤𐑴! 𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒'𐑕 𐑩𐑕𐑑𐑻,” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑞 𐑮𐑦𐑜𐑼. “𐑣𐑰'𐑟 𐑩 𐑤𐑲𐑝𐑤𐑦 𐑗𐑰𐑓 𐑥𐑱𐑑, 𐑞𐑨𐑑; 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑥𐑨𐑯, 𐑯 𐑩 𐑐𐑲𐑩𐑕; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑩𐑤𐑲𐑝 𐑯𐑬, 𐑲 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑑𐑻𐑯 𐑑.” 𐑯 𐑕𐑴 𐑕𐑱𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑪𐑯 𐑛𐑧𐑒, 𐑯 𐑢𐑰 𐑓𐑪𐑤𐑴𐑛.

𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑬 𐑒𐑤𐑽 𐑕𐑳𐑯𐑮𐑲𐑟. 𐑕𐑵𐑯 𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑵 𐑒𐑱𐑥 𐑪𐑯 𐑚𐑹𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑑𐑵𐑟 𐑯 𐑔𐑮𐑰𐑟; 𐑞 𐑮𐑦𐑜𐑼𐑟 𐑚𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑻𐑛 𐑞𐑧𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑝𐑟; 𐑞 𐑥𐑱𐑑𐑕 𐑢𐑻 𐑨𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑝𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑯𐑜𐑱𐑡𐑛; 𐑯 𐑕𐑧𐑝𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑞 𐑖𐑹 𐑐𐑰𐑐𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑻 𐑚𐑦𐑟𐑦 𐑦𐑯 𐑚𐑮𐑦𐑙𐑦𐑙 𐑝𐑺𐑾𐑕 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑪𐑯 𐑚𐑹𐑛. 𐑥𐑰𐑯𐑢𐑲𐑤 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑱𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑦𐑟𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑯𐑖𐑮𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑨𐑚𐑦𐑯.

·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 22. 𐑥𐑧𐑮𐑦 ·𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑥𐑩𐑕.

𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑧𐑙𐑔, 𐑑𐑩𐑢𐑹𐑛𐑟 𐑯𐑵𐑯, 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑲𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐'𐑕 𐑮𐑦𐑜𐑼𐑟, 𐑯 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑣𐑷𐑤𐑛 𐑬𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑢𐑹𐑓, 𐑯 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑞 𐑧𐑝𐑼-𐑔𐑷𐑑𐑓𐑩𐑤 ·𐑗𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑪𐑓 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑢𐑱𐑤-𐑚𐑴𐑑, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑻 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑜𐑦𐑓𐑑—𐑩 𐑯𐑲𐑑-𐑒𐑨𐑐 𐑓 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚, 𐑞 𐑕𐑧𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑥𐑱𐑑, 𐑣𐑻 𐑚𐑮𐑳𐑞𐑼-𐑦𐑯-𐑤𐑷, 𐑯 𐑩 𐑕𐑐𐑺 ·𐑚𐑲𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑓 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑿𐑼𐑛—𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑦𐑕, 𐑞 𐑑𐑵 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑟, ·𐑐𐑰𐑤𐑧𐑜 𐑯 ·𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑛𐑨𐑛, 𐑦𐑖𐑿𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑒𐑨𐑚𐑦𐑯, 𐑯 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑞 𐑗𐑰𐑓 𐑥𐑱𐑑, ·𐑐𐑰𐑤𐑧𐑜 𐑕𐑧𐑛:

“𐑯𐑬, ·𐑥𐑼 ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒, 𐑸 𐑿 𐑖𐑫𐑼 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑟 𐑮𐑲𐑑? 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑦𐑟 𐑷𐑤 𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑦—𐑡𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑐𐑴𐑒 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥—𐑯𐑳𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑹 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑜𐑪𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑖𐑹, 𐑱? 𐑢𐑧𐑤, 𐑒𐑷𐑤 𐑷𐑤 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟, 𐑞𐑧𐑯. 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑𐑼 '𐑩𐑥 𐑭𐑓𐑑 𐑣𐑽—𐑚𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 '𐑩𐑥!”

“𐑯𐑴 𐑯𐑰𐑛 𐑝 𐑐𐑮𐑴𐑓𐑱𐑯 𐑢𐑻𐑛𐑟, 𐑣𐑬𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑞 𐑣𐑳𐑮𐑦, ·𐑐𐑰𐑤𐑧𐑜,” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 ·𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑛𐑨𐑛, “𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑩𐑢𐑱 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞𐑰, 𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑯𐑛 ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒, 𐑯 𐑛𐑵 𐑬𐑼 𐑚𐑦𐑛𐑦𐑙.”

𐑣𐑬 𐑯𐑬! 𐑣𐑽 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑐𐑶𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑓 𐑞 𐑝𐑶𐑦𐑡, ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 ·𐑐𐑰𐑤𐑧𐑜 𐑯 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 ·𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑛𐑨𐑛 𐑢𐑻 𐑜𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑣𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑒𐑢𐑹𐑑𐑼-𐑛𐑧𐑒, 𐑡𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑓 𐑞𐑱 𐑢𐑻 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑡𐑶𐑯𐑑-𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑭𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑟 𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑰, 𐑨𐑟 𐑢𐑧𐑤 𐑨𐑟 𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑩𐑐𐑽𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑐𐑹𐑑. 𐑯, 𐑨𐑟 𐑓 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚, 𐑯𐑴 𐑕𐑲𐑯 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑕𐑰𐑯; 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦, 𐑞𐑱 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑒𐑨𐑚𐑦𐑯. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑞 𐑲𐑛𐑾 𐑢𐑪𐑟, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑚𐑲 𐑯𐑴 𐑥𐑰𐑯𐑟 𐑯𐑧𐑕𐑦𐑕𐑺𐑦 𐑦𐑯 𐑜𐑧𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑢𐑱, 𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑽𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑻 𐑢𐑧𐑤 𐑬𐑑 𐑑 𐑕𐑰. 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑰𐑛, 𐑨𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑐𐑼 𐑚𐑦𐑟𐑯𐑩𐑕, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞 𐑐𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑑'𐑕; 𐑯 𐑨𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑰𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑳𐑝𐑼𐑛—𐑕𐑴 𐑞𐑱 𐑕𐑧𐑛—𐑞𐑺𐑓𐑹, ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑛 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑴. 𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑯𐑨𐑗𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑯𐑳𐑓; 𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑥𐑻𐑗𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑕𐑻𐑝𐑦𐑕 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑟 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑖𐑴 𐑞𐑧𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑝𐑟 𐑪𐑯 𐑛𐑧𐑒 𐑓 𐑩 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑼𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑣𐑰𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑳𐑐 𐑞 𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑼, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑱𐑯 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑞 𐑒𐑨𐑚𐑦𐑯 𐑑𐑱𐑚𐑩𐑤, 𐑣𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑓𐑺𐑢𐑧𐑤 𐑥𐑧𐑮𐑦-𐑥𐑱𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞𐑺 𐑖𐑹 𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑟, 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑞𐑱 𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑑 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑓 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑐𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑑.

𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑗𐑭𐑯𐑕 𐑑 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑞 𐑥𐑨𐑑𐑼, 𐑓 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 ·𐑐𐑰𐑤𐑧𐑜 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑬 𐑷𐑤 𐑩𐑤𐑲𐑝. 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑑 𐑛𐑵 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑑𐑷𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑯 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑭𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙, 𐑯 𐑯𐑪𐑑 ·𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑛𐑨𐑛.

“𐑭𐑓𐑑 𐑣𐑽, 𐑘𐑰 𐑕𐑳𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑚𐑨𐑗𐑩𐑤𐑼𐑟,” 𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛, 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑼𐑟 𐑤𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑼𐑛 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑥𐑱𐑯-𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑. “·𐑥𐑼 ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒, 𐑛𐑮𐑲𐑝 '𐑩𐑥 𐑭𐑓𐑑.”

“𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑒 𐑞 𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑞𐑺!”—𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞 𐑯𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑 𐑹𐑛𐑼. 𐑨𐑟 𐑲 𐑣𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹, 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑚𐑴𐑯 𐑥𐑸𐑒𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑐𐑦𐑗𐑑 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑧𐑐𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑐𐑹𐑑; 𐑯 𐑪𐑯 𐑚𐑹𐑛 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛, 𐑓 𐑔𐑻𐑑𐑦 𐑘𐑽𐑟, 𐑞 𐑹𐑛𐑼 𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑒 𐑞 𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑢𐑧𐑤 𐑯𐑴𐑯 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑞 𐑯𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑 𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑣𐑰𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑳𐑐 𐑞 𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑼.

“𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑞 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯! 𐑚𐑤𐑳𐑛 𐑯 𐑔𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼!—𐑡𐑳𐑥𐑐!”—𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞 𐑯𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑭𐑯𐑛, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑵 𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑨𐑙 𐑓 𐑞 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑕𐑐𐑲𐑒𐑕.

𐑯𐑬 𐑦𐑯 𐑜𐑧𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑢𐑱, 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑪𐑒𐑿𐑐𐑲𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑐𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑞 𐑓𐑹𐑢𐑼𐑛 𐑐𐑸𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐. 𐑯 𐑣𐑽 ·𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑛𐑨𐑛, 𐑣𐑵, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑤𐑧𐑜, 𐑚𐑰 𐑦𐑑 𐑯𐑴𐑯, 𐑦𐑯 𐑩𐑛𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑪𐑓𐑦𐑕𐑼𐑟, 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑤𐑲𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑐𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑐𐑹𐑑—𐑣𐑰 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑩𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑜𐑪𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑩 𐑐𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑹𐑛𐑼 𐑑 𐑕𐑱𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑯𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑑 𐑐𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑑-𐑓𐑰 𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑕 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑻𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑯, 𐑓 𐑣𐑰 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑐𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑒𐑮𐑭𐑓𐑑—·𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑛𐑨𐑛, 𐑲 𐑕𐑱, 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑯𐑬 𐑚𐑰 𐑕𐑰𐑯 𐑨𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑝𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑯𐑜𐑱𐑡𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑞 𐑚𐑬𐑟 𐑓 𐑞 𐑩𐑐𐑮𐑴𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑼, 𐑯 𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑕𐑦𐑙𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑩 𐑛𐑦𐑟𐑥𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑝 𐑝 𐑕𐑭𐑥𐑩𐑛𐑦, 𐑑 𐑗𐑽 𐑞 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑤𐑩𐑕, 𐑣𐑵 𐑮𐑹𐑛 𐑓𐑹𐑔 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑕𐑹𐑑 𐑝 𐑩 𐑒𐑹𐑩𐑕 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑞 𐑜𐑻𐑤𐑟 𐑦𐑯 ·𐑚𐑵𐑚𐑩𐑤 ·𐑨𐑤𐑦, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑸𐑑𐑦 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑤. 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼𐑞𐑩𐑤𐑧𐑕, 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑛𐑱𐑟 𐑐𐑮𐑰𐑝𐑾𐑕, ·𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑛𐑨𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑑𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑯𐑴 𐑐𐑮𐑴𐑓𐑱𐑯 𐑕𐑪𐑙𐑟 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑚𐑰 𐑩𐑤𐑬𐑛 𐑪𐑯 𐑚𐑹𐑛 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛, 𐑐𐑼𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑼𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑯 𐑜𐑧𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑢𐑱; 𐑯 ·𐑗𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑦, 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑼, 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕𐑑 𐑩 𐑕𐑥𐑷𐑤 𐑗𐑶𐑕 𐑒𐑪𐑐𐑦 𐑝 ·𐑢𐑪𐑑𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑰𐑗 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑩𐑯'𐑟 𐑚𐑻𐑔.

𐑥𐑰𐑯𐑑𐑲𐑥, 𐑴𐑝𐑼𐑕𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑐𐑸𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐, ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 ·𐑐𐑰𐑤𐑧𐑜 𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑑 𐑯 𐑕𐑢𐑹 𐑩𐑕𐑑𐑻𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑲𐑑𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑥𐑨𐑯𐑼. 𐑲 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑔𐑷𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑕𐑦𐑙𐑒 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑞 𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑼 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑚𐑰 𐑜𐑪𐑑 𐑳𐑐; 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑪𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑺𐑦𐑤𐑦 𐑲 𐑐𐑷𐑟𐑛 𐑪𐑯 𐑥𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑕𐑐𐑲𐑒, 𐑯 𐑑𐑴𐑤𐑛 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜 𐑑 𐑛𐑵 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥, 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑞 𐑐𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑤𐑟 𐑢𐑰 𐑚𐑴𐑔 𐑮𐑨𐑯, 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑝𐑶𐑦𐑡 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩 𐑛𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑤 𐑓 𐑩 𐑐𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑑. 𐑲 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑓𐑼𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑲𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓, 𐑣𐑬𐑧𐑝𐑼, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑔𐑷𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑐𐑲𐑩𐑕 ·𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑛𐑨𐑛 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑕𐑨𐑤𐑝𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯, 𐑕𐑐𐑲𐑑 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑛 𐑯 𐑕𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑦-𐑕𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑯𐑔 𐑤𐑱; 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑲 𐑓𐑧𐑤𐑑 𐑩 𐑕𐑳𐑛𐑩𐑯 𐑖𐑸𐑐 𐑐𐑴𐑒 𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑲 𐑮𐑽, 𐑯 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛, 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑣𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑓𐑲𐑛 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑨𐑐𐑼𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 ·𐑐𐑰𐑤𐑧𐑜 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑨𐑒𐑑 𐑝 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑛𐑮𐑷𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑤𐑧𐑜 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑥𐑲 𐑦𐑥𐑰𐑛𐑾𐑑 𐑝𐑦𐑕𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑦. 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑥𐑲 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑒𐑦𐑒.

“𐑦𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑢𐑱 𐑞𐑱 𐑣𐑰𐑝 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑥𐑸𐑗𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑕𐑻𐑝𐑦𐑕?” 𐑣𐑰 𐑮𐑹𐑛. “𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑙, 𐑞𐑬 𐑖𐑰𐑐-𐑣𐑧𐑛; 𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑙, 𐑯 𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑒 𐑞𐑲 𐑚𐑨𐑒𐑚𐑴𐑯! 𐑢𐑲 𐑛𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑘𐑰 𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑙, 𐑲 𐑕𐑱, 𐑷𐑤 𐑝 𐑘𐑰—𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑙! ·𐑒𐑢𐑴𐑙𐑪𐑜! 𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑙, 𐑞𐑬 𐑗𐑨𐑐 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑮𐑧𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑼𐑟; 𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑺, ·𐑕𐑒𐑪𐑗-𐑒𐑨𐑐; 𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑙, 𐑞𐑬 𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑯 𐑐𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑕. 𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑙, 𐑲 𐑕𐑱, 𐑷𐑤 𐑝 𐑘𐑰, 𐑯 𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑙 𐑘𐑹 𐑲𐑟 𐑬𐑑!” 𐑯 𐑕𐑴 𐑕𐑱𐑦𐑙, 𐑣𐑰 𐑥𐑵𐑝𐑛 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑞 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑤𐑩𐑕, 𐑣𐑽 𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑿𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑤𐑧𐑜 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑓𐑮𐑰𐑤𐑦, 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑼𐑑𐑻𐑚𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 ·𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑛𐑨𐑛 𐑒𐑧𐑐𐑑 𐑤𐑰𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑪𐑓 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑭𐑥𐑩𐑛𐑦. 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑕 𐑲, ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 ·𐑐𐑰𐑤𐑧𐑜 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑛𐑮𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑑-𐑛𐑱.

𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑞 𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑼 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑳𐑐, 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑕𐑧𐑑, 𐑯 𐑪𐑓 𐑢𐑰 𐑜𐑤𐑲𐑛𐑩𐑛. 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩 𐑖𐑹𐑑, 𐑒𐑴𐑤𐑛 ·𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑥𐑩𐑕; 𐑯 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑖𐑹𐑑 𐑯𐑹𐑞𐑼𐑯 𐑛𐑱 𐑥𐑻𐑡𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑯𐑲𐑑, 𐑢𐑰 𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑬𐑼𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑝𐑟 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑮𐑷𐑛 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑦 𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯, 𐑣𐑵𐑟 𐑓𐑮𐑰𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑱 𐑒𐑱𐑕𐑑 𐑳𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑲𐑕, 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑐𐑪𐑤𐑦𐑖𐑑 𐑸𐑥𐑼. 𐑞 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑮𐑴𐑟 𐑝 𐑑𐑰𐑔 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑫𐑤𐑢𐑼𐑒𐑕 𐑜𐑤𐑦𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑥𐑵𐑯𐑤𐑲𐑑; 𐑯 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑞 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑲𐑝𐑼𐑦 𐑑𐑳𐑕𐑒𐑕 𐑝 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑣𐑿𐑡 𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑓𐑩𐑯𐑑, 𐑝𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑒𐑻𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑲𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑛𐑦𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑚𐑬𐑟.

·𐑤𐑨𐑙𐑒 ·𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑛𐑨𐑛, 𐑨𐑟 𐑐𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑑, 𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑞 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑗, 𐑯 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑯 𐑩𐑯𐑪𐑯, 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑒𐑮𐑭𐑓𐑑 𐑛𐑰𐑐 𐑛𐑲𐑝𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑯 𐑕𐑰𐑟, 𐑯 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑝𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑕𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑣𐑻, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑣𐑬𐑤𐑛, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑒𐑹𐑛𐑦𐑡 𐑮𐑨𐑙, 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑛𐑦 𐑯𐑴𐑑𐑕 𐑢𐑻 𐑣𐑻𐑛,—

“𐑕𐑢𐑰𐑑 𐑓𐑰𐑤𐑛𐑟 𐑚𐑦𐑘𐑪𐑯𐑛 𐑞 𐑕𐑢𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑤𐑳𐑛,

·𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑛𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑤𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑯.

𐑕𐑴 𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑡𐑵𐑟 𐑴𐑤𐑛 ·𐑒𐑱𐑯𐑩𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑫𐑛,

·𐑢𐑲𐑤 ·𐑡𐑹𐑛𐑩𐑯 𐑮𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑢𐑰𐑯.”

𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑕𐑢𐑰𐑑 𐑢𐑻𐑛𐑟 𐑕𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑥𐑹 𐑕𐑢𐑰𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑑 𐑥𐑰 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯. 𐑞𐑱 𐑢𐑻 𐑓𐑫𐑤 𐑝 𐑣𐑴𐑐 𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑵𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯. 𐑕𐑐𐑲𐑑 𐑝 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑓𐑮𐑦𐑡𐑦𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼 𐑯𐑲𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑶𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑩𐑕 ·𐑩𐑑𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑒, 𐑕𐑐𐑲𐑑 𐑝 𐑥𐑲 𐑢𐑧𐑑 𐑓𐑰𐑑 𐑯 𐑢𐑧𐑑𐑼 𐑡𐑨𐑒𐑩𐑑, 𐑞𐑺 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑘𐑧𐑑, 𐑦𐑑 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑑 𐑥𐑰, 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑩 𐑐𐑤𐑧𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑣𐑱𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑹; 𐑯 𐑥𐑰𐑛𐑟 𐑯 𐑜𐑤𐑱𐑛𐑟 𐑕𐑴 𐑦𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑝𐑻𐑯𐑩𐑤, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑭𐑕 𐑖𐑪𐑑 𐑳𐑐 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑙, 𐑳𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑪𐑛𐑩𐑯, 𐑳𐑯𐑢𐑦𐑤𐑑𐑩𐑛, 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑱𐑯𐑟 𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑦𐑛𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑼.

𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑢𐑰 𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑛 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩𐑯 𐑪𐑓𐑦𐑙, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑑𐑵 𐑐𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑑𐑕 𐑢𐑻 𐑯𐑰𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑯𐑴 𐑤𐑪𐑙𐑜𐑼. 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑬𐑑 𐑕𐑱𐑤-𐑚𐑴𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑩𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑛 𐑳𐑕 𐑚𐑦𐑜𐑨𐑯 𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑙𐑕𐑲𐑛.

𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑒𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑾𐑕 𐑯 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑳𐑯𐑐𐑤𐑰𐑟𐑦𐑙, 𐑣𐑬 ·𐑐𐑰𐑤𐑧𐑜 𐑯 ·𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑛𐑨𐑛 𐑢𐑻 𐑩𐑓𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑡𐑳𐑙𐑒𐑗𐑼, 𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑤𐑦 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 ·𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑛𐑨𐑛. 𐑓 𐑤𐑴𐑞 𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑐𐑸𐑑, 𐑘𐑧𐑑; 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑤𐑴𐑞 𐑑 𐑤𐑰𐑝, 𐑓 𐑜𐑫𐑛, 𐑩 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑚𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑪𐑯 𐑕𐑴 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑯 𐑐𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑩 𐑝𐑶𐑦𐑡—𐑚𐑦𐑘𐑪𐑯𐑛 𐑚𐑴𐑔 𐑕𐑑𐑹𐑥𐑦 ·𐑒𐑱𐑐𐑕; 𐑩 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑔𐑬𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑸𐑛 𐑻𐑯𐑛 𐑛𐑪𐑤𐑼𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛; 𐑩 𐑖𐑦𐑐, 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑩𐑯 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑥𐑱𐑑 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑛 𐑨𐑟 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯; 𐑩 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑨𐑟 𐑣𐑰, 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑕 𐑥𐑹 𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑼 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑑𐑧𐑮𐑼𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑐𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑡𐑷; 𐑤𐑴𐑞 𐑑 𐑕𐑱 𐑜𐑫𐑛-𐑚𐑲 𐑑 𐑩 𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑴 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑢𐑱 𐑚𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑓𐑫𐑤 𐑝 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥,—𐑐𐑫𐑼 𐑴𐑤𐑛 ·𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑛𐑨𐑛 𐑤𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑼𐑛 𐑤𐑪𐑙; 𐑐𐑱𐑕𐑑 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑒 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑕 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑛𐑟; 𐑮𐑨𐑯 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑒𐑨𐑚𐑦𐑯 𐑑 𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑒 𐑩𐑯𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑓𐑺𐑢𐑧𐑤 𐑢𐑻𐑛 𐑞𐑺; 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯 𐑒𐑱𐑥 𐑪𐑯 𐑛𐑧𐑒, 𐑯 𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑑 𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑢𐑼𐑛; 𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑑 𐑑𐑩𐑢𐑹𐑛𐑟 𐑞 𐑢𐑲𐑛 𐑯 𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼𐑟, 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑓𐑸-𐑪𐑓 𐑳𐑯𐑕𐑰𐑯 ·𐑰𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑯 ·𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕; 𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑑 𐑑𐑩𐑢𐑹𐑛𐑟 𐑞 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛; 𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑑 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑓𐑑; 𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑑 𐑮𐑲𐑑 𐑯 𐑤𐑧𐑓𐑑; 𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑑 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦𐑢𐑺 𐑯 𐑯𐑴𐑢𐑺; 𐑯 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑, 𐑥𐑦𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑶𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑮𐑴𐑐 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑐𐑦𐑯, 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑝𐑳𐑤𐑕𐑦𐑝𐑤𐑦 𐑜𐑮𐑭𐑕𐑐𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑬𐑑 ·𐑐𐑰𐑤𐑧𐑜 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛, 𐑯 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑳𐑐 𐑩 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑯, 𐑓 𐑩 𐑥𐑴𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑫𐑛 𐑜𐑱𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑮𐑴𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑱𐑕, 𐑨𐑟 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑨𐑟 𐑑 𐑕𐑱, “𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼𐑞𐑩𐑤𐑧𐑕, 𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑯𐑛 ·𐑐𐑰𐑤𐑧𐑜, 𐑲 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑑; 𐑘𐑧𐑕, 𐑲 𐑒𐑨𐑯.”

𐑨𐑟 𐑓 ·𐑐𐑰𐑤𐑧𐑜 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓, 𐑣𐑰 𐑑𐑫𐑒 𐑦𐑑 𐑥𐑹 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑓𐑦𐑤𐑪𐑕𐑩𐑓𐑼; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑓 𐑷𐑤 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑦𐑤𐑪𐑕𐑩𐑓𐑦, 𐑞𐑺 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩 𐑑𐑺 𐑑𐑢𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑲, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑞 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑯 𐑒𐑱𐑥 𐑑𐑵 𐑯𐑽. 𐑯 𐑣𐑰, 𐑑𐑵, 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑩 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑮𐑳𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑒𐑨𐑚𐑦𐑯 𐑑 𐑛𐑧𐑒—𐑯𐑬 𐑩 𐑢𐑻𐑛 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑴, 𐑯 𐑯𐑬 𐑩 𐑢𐑻𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒, 𐑞 𐑗𐑰𐑓 𐑥𐑱𐑑.

𐑚𐑳𐑑, 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑, 𐑣𐑰 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑛 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑮𐑱𐑛, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑓𐑲𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑹𐑑 𐑝 𐑤𐑫𐑒 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥,—“𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 ·𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑛𐑨𐑛—𐑒𐑳𐑥, 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑥𐑱𐑑, 𐑢𐑰 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑜𐑴. 𐑚𐑨𐑒 𐑞 𐑥𐑱𐑯-𐑘𐑸𐑛 𐑞𐑺! 𐑚𐑴𐑑 𐑩𐑣𐑶! 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑑 𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑒𐑤𐑴𐑕 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑙𐑕𐑲𐑛, 𐑯𐑬! 𐑒𐑺𐑓𐑩𐑤, 𐑒𐑺𐑓𐑩𐑤!—𐑒𐑳𐑥, ·𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑛𐑨𐑛, 𐑚𐑶—𐑕𐑱 𐑘𐑹 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑. 𐑤𐑳𐑒 𐑑 𐑘𐑰, ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒—𐑤𐑳𐑒 𐑑 𐑘𐑰, ·𐑥𐑼 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚—𐑤𐑳𐑒 𐑑 𐑘𐑰, ·𐑥𐑼 ·𐑓𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑒—𐑜𐑫𐑛-𐑚𐑲 𐑯 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑤𐑳𐑒 𐑑 𐑘𐑰 𐑷𐑤—𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑛𐑱 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑘𐑽𐑟 𐑲'𐑤 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑩 𐑣𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑐𐑼 𐑕𐑥𐑴𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑓 𐑘𐑰 𐑦𐑯 𐑴𐑤𐑛 ·𐑯𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑑. 𐑣𐑼𐑭 𐑯 𐑩𐑢𐑱!”

“𐑜𐑪𐑛 𐑚𐑤𐑧𐑕 𐑘𐑰, 𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑘𐑰 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑰𐑐𐑦𐑙, 𐑥𐑧𐑯,” 𐑥𐑻𐑥𐑼𐑛 𐑴𐑤𐑛 ·𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑛𐑨𐑛, 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑴𐑣𐑽𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦. “𐑲 𐑣𐑴𐑐 𐑘𐑰'𐑤 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑓𐑲𐑯 𐑢𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑯𐑬, 𐑕𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑥𐑱 𐑕𐑵𐑯 𐑚𐑰 𐑥𐑵𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑘𐑰—𐑩 𐑐𐑤𐑧𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑯 𐑦𐑟 𐑷𐑤 𐑣𐑰 𐑯𐑰𐑛𐑟, 𐑯 𐑘𐑰'𐑤 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑐𐑤𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑦 𐑝 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑑𐑮𐑪𐑐𐑦𐑒 𐑝𐑶𐑦𐑡 𐑘𐑰 𐑜𐑴. 𐑚𐑰 𐑒𐑺𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑑, 𐑘𐑰 𐑥𐑱𐑑𐑕. 𐑛𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑝 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕 𐑯𐑰𐑛𐑤𐑩𐑕𐑤𐑦, 𐑘𐑰 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑽𐑟; 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑛𐑼 𐑐𐑤𐑨𐑙𐑒 𐑦𐑟 𐑮𐑱𐑟𐑛 𐑓𐑫𐑤 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑐𐑻 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑘𐑽. 𐑛𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑓𐑼𐑜𐑧𐑑 𐑘𐑹 𐑐𐑮𐑱𐑼𐑟, 𐑲𐑞𐑼. ·𐑥𐑼 ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒, 𐑥𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑒𐑵𐑐𐑼 𐑛𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑕𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑺 𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑝𐑟. 𐑴! 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑤-𐑯𐑰𐑛𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑸 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑯 𐑤𐑪𐑒𐑼! 𐑛𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑦𐑑 𐑑𐑵 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑩' ·𐑤𐑹𐑛'𐑟 𐑛𐑱𐑟, 𐑥𐑧𐑯; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑛𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑥𐑦𐑕 𐑩 𐑓𐑺 𐑗𐑭𐑯𐑕 𐑲𐑞𐑼, 𐑞𐑨𐑑'𐑕 𐑮𐑦𐑡𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑙 ·𐑣𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑯'𐑟 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑜𐑦𐑓𐑑𐑕. 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑩𐑯 𐑲 𐑑 𐑞 𐑥𐑩𐑤𐑨𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑑𐑽𐑕, ·𐑥𐑼 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚; 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑤𐑰𐑒𐑦, 𐑲 𐑔𐑷𐑑. 𐑦𐑓 𐑘𐑰 𐑑𐑳𐑗 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛𐑟, ·𐑥𐑼 ·𐑓𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑒, 𐑚𐑦𐑢𐑺 𐑝 𐑓𐑹𐑯𐑦𐑒𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯. 𐑜𐑫𐑛-𐑚𐑲, 𐑜𐑫𐑛-𐑚𐑲! 𐑛𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑒𐑰𐑐 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑗𐑰𐑟 𐑑𐑵 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛, ·𐑥𐑼 ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒; 𐑦𐑑'𐑤 𐑕𐑐𐑶𐑤. 𐑚𐑰 𐑒𐑺𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑚𐑳𐑑𐑼—𐑑𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑦 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑞 𐑐𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟, 𐑯 𐑥𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑘𐑰, 𐑦𐑓—”

“𐑒𐑳𐑥, 𐑒𐑳𐑥, ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 ·𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑛𐑨𐑛; 𐑕𐑑𐑪𐑐 𐑐𐑩𐑤𐑭𐑝𐑼𐑦𐑙,—𐑩𐑢𐑱!” 𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞𐑨𐑑, ·𐑐𐑰𐑤𐑧𐑜 𐑣𐑳𐑮𐑦𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑞 𐑕𐑲𐑛, 𐑯 𐑚𐑴𐑔 𐑛𐑮𐑪𐑐𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑.

𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑯 𐑚𐑴𐑑 𐑛𐑲𐑝𐑻𐑡𐑛; 𐑞 𐑒𐑴𐑤𐑛, 𐑛𐑨𐑥𐑐 𐑯𐑲𐑑 𐑚𐑮𐑰𐑟 𐑚𐑤𐑵 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑢𐑰𐑯; 𐑩 𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑰𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑜𐑳𐑤 𐑓𐑤𐑵 𐑴𐑝𐑼𐑣𐑧𐑛; 𐑞 𐑑𐑵 𐑣𐑳𐑤𐑟 𐑢𐑲𐑤𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑴𐑤𐑛; 𐑢𐑰 𐑜𐑱𐑝 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑣𐑧𐑝𐑦-𐑣𐑸𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑗𐑽𐑟, 𐑯 𐑚𐑤𐑲𐑯𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑤𐑳𐑯𐑡𐑛 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑓𐑱𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑤𐑴𐑯 ·𐑩𐑑𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑒.

·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 23. 𐑞 ·𐑤𐑰 ·𐑖𐑹.

𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼𐑟 𐑚𐑨𐑒, 𐑢𐑳𐑯 ·𐑚𐑳𐑤𐑒𐑦𐑙𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑐𐑴𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑝, 𐑩 𐑑𐑷𐑤, 𐑯𐑿𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑥𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑯𐑼, 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑛 𐑦𐑯 ·𐑯𐑿 ·𐑚𐑧𐑛𐑓𐑼𐑛 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑦𐑯.

𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑪𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑖𐑦𐑝𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼'𐑟 𐑯𐑲𐑑, 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛 𐑔𐑮𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑻 𐑝𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑝 𐑚𐑬𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑒𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑥𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑕 𐑢𐑱𐑝𐑟, 𐑣𐑵 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑲 𐑕𐑰 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑻 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑥 𐑚𐑳𐑑 ·𐑚𐑳𐑤𐑒𐑦𐑙𐑑𐑩𐑯! 𐑲 𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑕𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑔𐑧𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑷 𐑯 𐑓𐑽𐑓𐑩𐑤𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑥𐑨𐑯, 𐑣𐑵 𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑦𐑛-𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼 𐑡𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑩 𐑓𐑹 𐑘𐑽𐑟' 𐑛𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑼𐑩𐑕 𐑝𐑶𐑦𐑡, 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑕𐑴 𐑳𐑯𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑫𐑖 𐑪𐑓 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯 𐑓 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑩𐑯𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑑𐑧𐑥𐑐𐑧𐑕𐑗𐑵𐑩𐑕 𐑑𐑻𐑥. 𐑞 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑕𐑒𐑹𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑰𐑑. 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑓𐑩𐑤𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑸 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑞 𐑳𐑯𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤; 𐑛𐑰𐑐 𐑥𐑧𐑥𐑼𐑦𐑟 𐑘𐑰𐑤𐑛 𐑯𐑴 𐑧𐑐𐑦𐑑𐑭𐑓𐑕; 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑕-𐑦𐑯𐑗 𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 𐑦𐑟 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑝 𐑝 ·𐑚𐑳𐑤𐑒𐑦𐑙𐑑𐑩𐑯. 𐑤𐑧𐑑 𐑥𐑰 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑱 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑓𐑺𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑨𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑹𐑥-𐑑𐑪𐑕𐑑 𐑖𐑦𐑐, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑦𐑟𐑼𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑮𐑲𐑝𐑟 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑞 𐑤𐑰𐑢𐑼𐑛 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛. 𐑞 𐑐𐑹𐑑 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑓𐑱𐑯 𐑜𐑦𐑝 𐑕𐑳𐑒𐑼; 𐑞 𐑐𐑹𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑓𐑩𐑤; 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑐𐑹𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑱𐑓𐑑𐑦, 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑓𐑼𐑑, 𐑣𐑸𐑔𐑕𐑑𐑴𐑯, 𐑕𐑳𐑐𐑼, 𐑢𐑹𐑥 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑩𐑑𐑕, 𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑟, 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑨𐑑'𐑕 𐑒𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑑 𐑬𐑼 𐑥𐑹𐑑𐑨𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑟. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑜𐑱𐑤, 𐑞 𐑐𐑹𐑑, 𐑞 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛, 𐑦𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑖𐑦𐑐'𐑕 𐑛𐑲𐑼𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑡𐑧𐑐𐑼𐑛𐑦; 𐑖𐑰 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑓𐑤𐑲 𐑷𐑤 𐑣𐑪𐑕𐑐𐑦𐑑𐑨𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑦; 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑑𐑳𐑗 𐑝 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛, 𐑞𐑴 𐑦𐑑 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑟 𐑞 𐑒𐑰𐑤, 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑥𐑱𐑒 𐑣𐑻 𐑖𐑳𐑛𐑼 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑯 𐑔𐑮𐑵. 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑷𐑤 𐑣𐑻 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑖𐑰 𐑒𐑮𐑬𐑛𐑟 𐑷𐑤 𐑕𐑱𐑤 𐑪𐑓 𐑖𐑹; 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑴 𐑛𐑵𐑦𐑙, 𐑓𐑲𐑑𐑕 '𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑞 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑢𐑲𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑓𐑱𐑯 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑚𐑤𐑴 𐑣𐑻 𐑣𐑴𐑥𐑢𐑼𐑛; 𐑕𐑰𐑒𐑕 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑤𐑨𐑖𐑑 𐑕𐑰'𐑟 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑤𐑩𐑕𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯; 𐑓 𐑮𐑧𐑓𐑿𐑡'𐑩𐑟 𐑕𐑱𐑒 𐑓𐑼𐑤𐑹𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑳𐑖𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑐𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑤; 𐑣𐑻 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑣𐑻 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑼𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑓𐑴!

𐑯𐑴 𐑘𐑰 𐑯𐑬, ·𐑚𐑳𐑤𐑒𐑦𐑙𐑑𐑩𐑯? 𐑜𐑤𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑛𐑵 𐑘𐑰 𐑕𐑰𐑥 𐑑 𐑕𐑰 𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑹𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑪𐑤𐑼𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑑𐑮𐑵𐑔; 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑛𐑰𐑐, 𐑻𐑯𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑧𐑐𐑦𐑛 𐑧𐑓𐑼𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑴𐑤 𐑑 𐑒𐑰𐑐 𐑞 𐑴𐑐𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑝 𐑣𐑻 𐑕𐑰; 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑞 𐑢𐑲𐑤𐑛𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑝 𐑣𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑯 𐑻𐑔 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑐𐑲𐑼 𐑑 𐑒𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑻 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑑𐑮𐑧𐑗𐑼𐑩𐑕, 𐑕𐑤𐑱𐑝𐑦𐑖 𐑖𐑹?

𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑤𐑩𐑕𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑩𐑤𐑴𐑯 𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑲𐑛𐑟 𐑣𐑲𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑑𐑮𐑵𐑔, 𐑖𐑹𐑤𐑩𐑕, 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑧𐑓𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑑 𐑨𐑟 ·𐑜𐑪𐑛—𐑕𐑴, 𐑚𐑧𐑑𐑼 𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑑 𐑐𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑖 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑬𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯𐑓𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑑, 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑚𐑰 𐑦𐑯𐑜𐑤𐑹𐑾𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑨𐑖𐑑 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑤𐑰, 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑓 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑻 𐑕𐑱𐑓𐑑𐑦! 𐑓 𐑢𐑻𐑥-𐑤𐑲𐑒, 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑴! 𐑣𐑵 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑒𐑮𐑱𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑒𐑮𐑷𐑤 𐑑 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛! 𐑑𐑧𐑮𐑼𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑑𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑚𐑩𐑤! 𐑦𐑟 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑨𐑜𐑩𐑯𐑦 𐑕𐑴 𐑝𐑱𐑯? 𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑣𐑸𐑑, 𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑣𐑸𐑑, 𐑴 ·𐑚𐑳𐑤𐑒𐑦𐑙𐑑𐑩𐑯! 𐑚𐑺 𐑞𐑰 𐑜𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑤𐑦, 𐑛𐑧𐑥𐑦𐑜𐑪𐑛! 𐑳𐑐 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑱 𐑝 𐑞𐑲 𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯-𐑐𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑖𐑦𐑙—𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑳𐑐, 𐑤𐑰𐑐𐑕 𐑞𐑲 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑔𐑦𐑴𐑕𐑦𐑕!

·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 24. 𐑞 ·𐑨𐑛𐑝𐑩𐑒𐑩𐑑.

𐑨𐑟 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜 𐑯 𐑲 𐑸 𐑯𐑬 𐑓𐑺𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑥𐑚𐑸𐑒𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑚𐑦𐑟𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙; 𐑯 𐑨𐑟 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑚𐑦𐑟𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑣𐑬 𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑮𐑦𐑜𐑸𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑨𐑟 𐑩 𐑮𐑭𐑞𐑼 𐑳𐑯𐑐𐑴𐑧𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑯 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑮𐑧𐑐𐑿𐑑𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑐𐑼𐑕𐑿𐑑; 𐑞𐑺𐑓𐑹, 𐑲 𐑨𐑥 𐑷𐑤 𐑨𐑙𐑟𐑲𐑩𐑑𐑦 𐑑 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑝𐑦𐑯𐑕 𐑘𐑰, 𐑘𐑰 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟𐑥𐑧𐑯, 𐑝 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑡𐑳𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑕 𐑣𐑽𐑚𐑲 𐑛𐑳𐑯 𐑑 𐑳𐑕 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑟 𐑝 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟.

𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕, 𐑦𐑑 𐑥𐑱 𐑚𐑰 𐑛𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑵𐑐𐑻𐑓𐑤𐑵𐑩𐑕 𐑑 𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑚𐑤𐑦𐑖 𐑞 𐑓𐑨𐑒𐑑, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑐𐑰𐑐𐑩𐑤 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑸𐑡, 𐑞 𐑚𐑦𐑟𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑩𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑪𐑯 𐑩 𐑤𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑸 𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑛 𐑞 𐑤𐑦𐑚𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑓𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟. 𐑦𐑓 𐑩 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑼 𐑢𐑻 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑩𐑛𐑿𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑩𐑤𐑱𐑯𐑾𐑕 𐑥𐑧𐑑𐑮𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑕𐑩𐑕𐑲𐑩𐑑𐑦, 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑕𐑤𐑲𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑩𐑛𐑝𐑭𐑯𐑕 𐑞 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑩𐑐𐑦𐑯𐑘𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑕, 𐑢𐑻 𐑣𐑰 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑑 𐑞 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑦 𐑨𐑟 𐑩 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑽, 𐑕𐑱; 𐑯 𐑦𐑓 𐑦𐑯 𐑧𐑥𐑿𐑤𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑯𐑱𐑝𐑩𐑤 𐑪𐑓𐑦𐑕𐑼𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑩𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑤𐑟 S.W.F. (·𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤 ·𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑼𐑦) 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑝𐑦𐑟𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑒𐑸𐑛, 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩 𐑐𐑮𐑴𐑕𐑰𐑡𐑼 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑚𐑰 𐑛𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑐𐑮𐑰-𐑧𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑿𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑯 𐑮𐑦𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑩𐑕.

𐑛𐑬𐑑𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑤𐑰𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑮𐑰𐑟𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑲 𐑞 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛 𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑲𐑯𐑟 𐑪𐑯𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑳𐑕 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑥𐑧𐑯, 𐑦𐑟 𐑞𐑦𐑕: 𐑞𐑱 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒 𐑞𐑨𐑑, 𐑨𐑑 𐑚𐑧𐑕𐑑, 𐑬𐑼 𐑝𐑴𐑒𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑩𐑥𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑑 𐑩 𐑚𐑫𐑗𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑹𐑑 𐑝 𐑚𐑦𐑟𐑯𐑩𐑕; 𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑨𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑝𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑯𐑜𐑱𐑡𐑛 𐑞𐑺𐑦𐑯, 𐑢𐑰 𐑸 𐑕𐑼𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑷𐑤 𐑥𐑨𐑯𐑼 𐑝 𐑛𐑦𐑓𐑲𐑤𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕. 𐑚𐑫𐑗𐑼𐑟 𐑢𐑰 𐑸, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑑𐑮𐑵. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑚𐑫𐑗𐑼𐑟, 𐑷𐑤𐑕𐑴, 𐑯 𐑚𐑫𐑗𐑼𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑚𐑤𐑳𐑛𐑾𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑨𐑡 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑷𐑤 ·𐑥𐑸𐑖𐑩𐑤 ·𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑭𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑟 𐑣𐑵𐑥 𐑞 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑺𐑾𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑲𐑑𐑕 𐑑 𐑪𐑯𐑼. 𐑯 𐑨𐑟 𐑓 𐑞 𐑥𐑨𐑑𐑼 𐑝 𐑞 𐑩𐑤𐑧𐑡𐑛 𐑳𐑯𐑒𐑤𐑧𐑯𐑤𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑬𐑼 𐑚𐑦𐑟𐑯𐑩𐑕, 𐑘𐑰 𐑖𐑨𐑤 𐑕𐑵𐑯 𐑚𐑰 𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑖𐑦𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑓𐑨𐑒𐑑𐑕 𐑣𐑦𐑞𐑼𐑑𐑵 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑳𐑯𐑯𐑴𐑯, 𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑗, 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑣𐑴𐑤, 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑳𐑥𐑓𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 𐑢𐑱𐑤-𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑰𐑕𐑑 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑞 𐑒𐑤𐑧𐑯𐑤𐑾𐑕𐑑 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑝 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑑𐑲𐑛𐑦 𐑻𐑔. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑜𐑮𐑭𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑗𐑸𐑡 𐑦𐑯 𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑕𐑗𐑩𐑯 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑑𐑮𐑵; 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑹𐑛𐑼𐑛 𐑕𐑤𐑦𐑐𐑼𐑦 𐑛𐑧𐑒𐑕 𐑝 𐑩 𐑢𐑱𐑤-𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑸 𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑐𐑼𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑑 𐑞 𐑳𐑯𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑒𐑨𐑮𐑾𐑯 𐑝 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑚𐑨𐑑𐑩𐑤-𐑓𐑰𐑤𐑛𐑟 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑕𐑴 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑕𐑴𐑤𐑡𐑼𐑟 𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑻𐑯 𐑑 𐑛𐑮𐑦𐑙𐑒 𐑦𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑤𐑱𐑛𐑦𐑟' 𐑐𐑤𐑷𐑛𐑦𐑑𐑕? 𐑯 𐑦𐑓 𐑞 𐑲𐑛𐑾 𐑝 𐑐𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑤 𐑕𐑴 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑦𐑯𐑣𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑞 𐑐𐑪𐑐𐑿𐑤𐑼 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑰𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑴𐑤𐑡𐑼'𐑟 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑓𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑯; 𐑤𐑧𐑑 𐑥𐑰 𐑩𐑖𐑫𐑼 𐑘𐑰 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑩 𐑝𐑧𐑑𐑼𐑩𐑯 𐑣𐑵 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑓𐑮𐑰𐑤𐑦 𐑥𐑸𐑗𐑑 𐑳𐑐 𐑑 𐑩 𐑚𐑨𐑑𐑼𐑦, 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑶𐑤 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑨𐑐𐑼𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 𐑢𐑱𐑤'𐑟 𐑝𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑑𐑱𐑤, 𐑓𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑧𐑛𐑦𐑟 𐑞 𐑺 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑧𐑛. 𐑓 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑸 𐑞 𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑣𐑧𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑑𐑧𐑮𐑼𐑟 𐑝 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑺𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑤𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑑 𐑑𐑧𐑮𐑼𐑟 𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑟 𐑝 ·𐑜𐑪𐑛!

𐑚𐑳𐑑, 𐑞𐑴 𐑞 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛 𐑕𐑒𐑬𐑑𐑕 𐑨𐑑 𐑳𐑕 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑟, 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑛𐑳𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑳𐑯𐑢𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑱 𐑳𐑕 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑪𐑥𐑦𐑡; 𐑘𐑱, 𐑩𐑯 𐑷𐑤-𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑨𐑛𐑼𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯! 𐑓 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑑𐑱𐑐𐑼𐑟, 𐑤𐑨𐑥𐑐𐑕, 𐑯 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑚𐑻𐑯 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑞 𐑜𐑤𐑴𐑚, 𐑚𐑻𐑯, 𐑨𐑟 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑕𐑴 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑖𐑮𐑲𐑯𐑟, 𐑑 𐑬𐑼 𐑜𐑤𐑹𐑦!

𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑤𐑫𐑒 𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑥𐑨𐑑𐑼 𐑦𐑯 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑤𐑲𐑑𐑕; 𐑢𐑱 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑕𐑹𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑕𐑒𐑱𐑤𐑟; 𐑕𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑢𐑰 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑸, 𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑯.

𐑢𐑲 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑞 ·𐑛𐑳𐑗 𐑦𐑯 ·𐑛𐑦 ·𐑢𐑦𐑑'𐑕 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑨𐑛𐑥𐑼𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑝 𐑞𐑺 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑤𐑰𐑑𐑕? 𐑢𐑲 𐑛𐑦𐑛 ·𐑤𐑵𐑦 XVI. 𐑝 ·𐑓𐑮𐑭𐑯𐑕, 𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑴𐑯 𐑐𐑻𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑕, 𐑓𐑦𐑑 𐑬𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑕 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 ·𐑛𐑳𐑯𐑒𐑼𐑒, 𐑯 𐑐𐑩𐑤𐑲𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑲𐑑 𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑑𐑬𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑕𐑒𐑹 𐑹 𐑑𐑵 𐑝 𐑓𐑨𐑥𐑤𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑬𐑼 𐑴𐑯 𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑝 ·𐑯𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑑? 𐑢𐑲 𐑛𐑦𐑛 ·𐑚𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑢𐑰𐑯 𐑞 𐑘𐑽𐑟 1750 𐑯 1788 𐑐𐑱 𐑑 𐑣𐑻 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑚𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑟 𐑳𐑐𐑢𐑼𐑛𐑟 𐑝 £1,000,000? 𐑯 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑤𐑦, 𐑣𐑬 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑰 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑝 ·𐑩𐑥𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑩 𐑯𐑬 𐑬𐑑𐑯𐑳𐑥𐑚𐑼 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑚𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛; 𐑕𐑱𐑤 𐑩 𐑯𐑱𐑝𐑦 𐑝 𐑳𐑐𐑢𐑼𐑛𐑟 𐑝 𐑕𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑛 𐑝𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑤𐑟; 𐑥𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑱𐑑𐑰𐑯 𐑔𐑬𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑥𐑧𐑯; 𐑘𐑽𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑿𐑥𐑦𐑙 4,000,000 𐑝 𐑛𐑪𐑤𐑼𐑟; 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑕 𐑢𐑻𐑔, 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑝 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙, $20,000,000! 𐑯 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑘𐑽 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑹𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑬𐑼 𐑣𐑸𐑚𐑼𐑟 𐑩 𐑢𐑧𐑤 𐑮𐑰𐑐𐑑 𐑣𐑸𐑝𐑦𐑕𐑑 𐑝 $7,000,000. 𐑣𐑬 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑟 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑦𐑕, 𐑦𐑓 𐑞𐑺 𐑚𐑰 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑐𐑢𐑰𐑕𐑭𐑯𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙?

𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑞 𐑣𐑭𐑓; 𐑤𐑫𐑒 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯.

𐑲 𐑓𐑮𐑰𐑤𐑦 𐑩𐑕𐑻𐑑, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑒𐑪𐑟𐑥𐑴𐑐𐑩𐑤𐑲𐑑 𐑓𐑦𐑤𐑪𐑕𐑩𐑓𐑼 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑪𐑑, 𐑓 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑤𐑲𐑓, 𐑐𐑶𐑯𐑑 𐑬𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑕𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑩𐑤 𐑐𐑰𐑕𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑯𐑓𐑤𐑵𐑩𐑯𐑕, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑦 𐑘𐑽𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑪𐑐𐑼𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑥𐑹 𐑐𐑩𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑣𐑴𐑤 𐑚𐑮𐑷𐑛 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛, 𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑨𐑜𐑮𐑦𐑜𐑩𐑑, 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑞 𐑣𐑲 𐑯 𐑥𐑲𐑑𐑦 𐑚𐑦𐑟𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙. 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑢𐑱 𐑯 𐑩𐑯𐑳𐑞𐑼, 𐑦𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑚𐑦𐑜𐑪𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑝𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑕𐑴 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑸𐑒𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑝𐑟, 𐑯 𐑕𐑴 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑿𐑩𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑥𐑴𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑖𐑿𐑟, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑱 𐑢𐑧𐑤 𐑚𐑰 𐑮𐑦𐑜𐑸𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑨𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 ·𐑦𐑡𐑦𐑐𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑥𐑳𐑞𐑼, 𐑣𐑵 𐑚𐑹 𐑪𐑓𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑧𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑝𐑟 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑜𐑯𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑣𐑻 𐑢𐑵𐑥. 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑚𐑰 𐑩 𐑣𐑴𐑐𐑤𐑩𐑕, 𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑑𐑭𐑕𐑒 𐑑 𐑒𐑨𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑜 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑟. 𐑤𐑧𐑑 𐑩 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑓𐑫𐑤 𐑕𐑩𐑓𐑲𐑕. 𐑓 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑘𐑽𐑟 𐑐𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤-𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑞 𐑐𐑲𐑩𐑯𐑽 𐑦𐑯 𐑓𐑧𐑮𐑩𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑬𐑑 𐑞 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑴𐑑𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑯 𐑤𐑰𐑕𐑑 𐑯𐑴𐑯 𐑐𐑸𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑻𐑔. 𐑖𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑤𐑹𐑛 𐑕𐑰𐑟 𐑯 𐑸𐑒𐑦𐑐𐑧𐑤𐑩𐑜𐑴𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑯𐑴 𐑗𐑸𐑑, 𐑢𐑺 𐑯𐑴 ·𐑒𐑫𐑒 𐑹 ·𐑝𐑨𐑯𐑒𐑵𐑝𐑼 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑛. 𐑦𐑓 ·𐑩𐑥𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑯 ·𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑩𐑐𐑾𐑯 𐑥𐑧𐑯-𐑝-𐑢𐑹 𐑯𐑬 𐑐𐑰𐑕𐑓𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑲𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑕 𐑕𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑡 𐑣𐑸𐑚𐑼𐑟, 𐑤𐑧𐑑 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑓𐑲𐑼 𐑕𐑩𐑤𐑵𐑑𐑕 𐑑 𐑞 𐑪𐑯𐑼 𐑯 𐑜𐑤𐑹𐑦 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤-𐑖𐑦𐑐, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑼𐑦𐑡𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑖𐑴𐑛 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑞 𐑢𐑱, 𐑯 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑻𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑢𐑰𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑡𐑩𐑟. 𐑞𐑱 𐑥𐑱 𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑩𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑞𐑱 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑞 𐑣𐑽𐑴𐑟 𐑝 ·𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑤𐑹𐑦𐑙 ·𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑦𐑛𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟, 𐑘𐑹 ·𐑒𐑫𐑒𐑕, 𐑘𐑹 ·𐑒𐑮𐑵𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑯𐑟; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑲 𐑕𐑱 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑒𐑹𐑟 𐑝 𐑩𐑯𐑪𐑯𐑦𐑥𐑩𐑕 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑛 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 ·𐑯𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑑, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑻 𐑨𐑟 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑, 𐑯 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑𐑼 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑘𐑹 ·𐑒𐑫𐑒 𐑯 𐑘𐑹 ·𐑒𐑮𐑵𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑯. 𐑓 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑕𐑳𐑒𐑼𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑧𐑥𐑐𐑑𐑦-𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛𐑯𐑩𐑕, 𐑞𐑱, 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑣𐑰𐑞𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑖 𐑖𐑸𐑒𐑑 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼𐑟, 𐑯 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑚𐑰𐑗𐑩𐑟 𐑝 𐑳𐑯𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑹𐑛𐑩𐑛, 𐑡𐑨𐑝𐑤𐑦𐑯 𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛𐑟, 𐑚𐑨𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑝𐑻𐑡𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑟 𐑯 𐑑𐑧𐑮𐑼𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 ·𐑒𐑫𐑒 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑷𐑤 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑼𐑰𐑯𐑟 𐑯 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑒𐑩𐑑𐑕 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑛𐑺𐑛. 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩 𐑓𐑤𐑳𐑮𐑦𐑖 𐑝 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑴𐑤𐑛 ·𐑕𐑬𐑔 ·𐑕𐑰 ·𐑝𐑶𐑦𐑡𐑩𐑟, 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞 𐑤𐑲𐑓-𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑝 𐑬𐑼 𐑣𐑦𐑮𐑴𐑦𐑒 ·𐑯𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑑𐑼𐑟. 𐑪𐑓𐑩𐑯, 𐑩𐑛𐑝𐑧𐑯𐑗𐑼𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑗 ·𐑝𐑨𐑯𐑒𐑵𐑝𐑼 𐑛𐑧𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑱𐑑𐑕 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼𐑟 𐑑, 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑩𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑳𐑯𐑢𐑻𐑞𐑦 𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑧𐑑 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐'𐑕 𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑤𐑪𐑜. 𐑭, 𐑞 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛! 𐑴, 𐑞 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛!

𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑼𐑦 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 ·𐑒𐑱𐑐 ·𐑣𐑹𐑯, 𐑯𐑴 𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑻𐑕 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑴𐑯𐑾𐑤, 𐑕𐑒𐑺𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑒𐑹𐑕 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑴𐑯𐑾𐑤, 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑒𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑛 𐑪𐑯 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑢𐑰𐑯 ·𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑩𐑐 𐑯 𐑞 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑤𐑲𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑪𐑐𐑿𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑑 ·𐑕𐑐𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑖 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑝𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑩𐑕𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑒 𐑒𐑴𐑕𐑑. 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑣𐑵 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑮𐑴𐑒 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑞 𐑡𐑧𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑐𐑪𐑤𐑩𐑕𐑦 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑐𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑖 𐑒𐑮𐑬𐑯, 𐑑𐑳𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑒𐑪𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑟; 𐑯, 𐑦𐑓 𐑕𐑐𐑱𐑕 𐑐𐑼𐑥𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑛, 𐑦𐑑 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑖𐑴𐑯 𐑣𐑬 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑝𐑧𐑯𐑗𐑵𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑞 𐑤𐑦𐑚𐑼𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 ·𐑐𐑼𐑵, ·𐑗𐑦𐑤𐑦, 𐑯 ·𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑝𐑾 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑘𐑴𐑒 𐑝 ·𐑴𐑤𐑛 ·𐑕𐑐𐑱𐑯, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑚𐑤𐑦𐑖𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑦𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑛𐑦𐑥𐑪𐑒𐑮𐑩𐑕𐑦 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑐𐑸𐑑𐑕.

𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 ·𐑩𐑥𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑩 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑓𐑽, ·𐑪𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑤𐑾, 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑜𐑦𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑑 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑤𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑥𐑩𐑯. 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑤𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼-𐑚𐑹𐑯 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑳𐑝𐑼𐑦 𐑚𐑲 𐑩 ·𐑛𐑳𐑗𐑥𐑩𐑯, 𐑷𐑤 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑕 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑖𐑳𐑯𐑛 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑖𐑹𐑟 𐑨𐑟 𐑐𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑓𐑼𐑩𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑸𐑚𐑼𐑩𐑕; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤-𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑑𐑳𐑗𐑑 𐑞𐑺. 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤-𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑦𐑟 𐑞 𐑑𐑮𐑵 𐑥𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑯𐑬 𐑥𐑲𐑑𐑦 𐑒𐑪𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑦. 𐑥𐑹𐑴𐑝𐑼, 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑓𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦 𐑝 𐑞 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 ·𐑪𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑤𐑾𐑯 𐑕𐑧𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑, 𐑞 𐑧𐑥𐑦𐑜𐑮𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑢𐑻 𐑕𐑧𐑝𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑕𐑱𐑝𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑝𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑚𐑦𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑦𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤-𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑤𐑳𐑒𐑦𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑮𐑪𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑯 𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑼 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼𐑟. 𐑞 𐑳𐑯𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑲𐑤𐑟 𐑝 𐑷𐑤 ·𐑐𐑪𐑤𐑦𐑯𐑰𐑟𐑾 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑓𐑧𐑕 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑑𐑮𐑵𐑔, 𐑯 𐑛𐑵 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑻𐑖𐑩𐑤 𐑣𐑪𐑥𐑦𐑡 𐑑 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤-𐑖𐑦𐑐, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑒𐑤𐑽𐑛 𐑞 𐑢𐑱 𐑓 𐑞 𐑥𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑼𐑦 𐑯 𐑞 𐑥𐑻𐑗𐑩𐑯𐑑, 𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑒𐑱𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑒𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑛 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑝 𐑥𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑼𐑦𐑟 𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑛𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟. 𐑦𐑓 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑛𐑳𐑚𐑩𐑤-𐑚𐑴𐑤𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛, ·𐑡𐑩𐑐𐑨𐑯, 𐑦𐑟 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑣𐑪𐑕𐑐𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤, 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤-𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑩𐑤𐑴𐑯 𐑑 𐑣𐑵𐑥 𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑚𐑰 𐑛𐑿; 𐑓 𐑷𐑤𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑦 𐑖𐑰 𐑦𐑟 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑔𐑮𐑧𐑖𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛.

𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑓, 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑱𐑕 𐑝 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑦𐑕, 𐑿 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑺 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑯𐑴 𐑧𐑕𐑔𐑧𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑦 𐑯𐑴𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑩𐑕𐑴𐑖𐑦𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑦𐑑, 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑨𐑥 𐑲 𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑦 𐑑 𐑖𐑦𐑝𐑼 𐑓𐑦𐑓𐑑𐑦 𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑿 𐑞𐑺, 𐑯 𐑳𐑯𐑣𐑹𐑕 𐑿 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑕𐑐𐑤𐑦𐑑 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑥𐑩𐑑 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑑𐑲𐑥.

𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑯𐑴 𐑓𐑱𐑥𐑩𐑕 𐑷𐑔𐑼, 𐑯 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑯𐑴 𐑓𐑱𐑥𐑩𐑕 𐑒𐑮𐑪𐑯𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑼, 𐑿 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑕𐑱.

𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑯𐑴 𐑓𐑱𐑥𐑩𐑕 𐑷𐑔𐑼, 𐑯 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑯𐑴 𐑓𐑱𐑥𐑩𐑕 𐑒𐑮𐑪𐑯𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑼? 𐑣𐑵 𐑮𐑴𐑑 𐑞 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑩𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑬𐑼 ·𐑤𐑩𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑔𐑩𐑯? 𐑣𐑵 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑥𐑲𐑑𐑦 ·𐑡𐑴𐑚! 𐑯 𐑣𐑵 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑴𐑟𐑛 𐑞 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑑𐑦𐑝 𐑝 𐑩 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙-𐑝𐑶𐑦𐑡? 𐑣𐑵, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑯𐑴 𐑤𐑧𐑕 𐑩 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑯𐑕 𐑞𐑨𐑯 ·𐑨𐑤𐑓𐑮𐑦𐑛 𐑞 ·𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑, 𐑣𐑵, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑴𐑯 𐑮𐑶𐑩𐑤 𐑐𐑧𐑯, 𐑑𐑫𐑒 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑻𐑛𐑟 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑳𐑞𐑼, 𐑞 ·𐑯𐑹𐑢𐑰𐑡𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑱𐑤-𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑑𐑼 𐑝 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟! 𐑯 𐑣𐑵 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑯𐑬𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑬𐑼 𐑜𐑤𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑿𐑤𐑩𐑡𐑦 𐑦𐑯 ·𐑐𐑸𐑤𐑩𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑? 𐑣𐑵, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 ·𐑧𐑛𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑛 ·𐑚𐑻𐑒!

𐑑𐑮𐑵 𐑦𐑯𐑳𐑓, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑝𐑟 𐑸 𐑐𐑫𐑼 𐑛𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑟; 𐑞𐑱 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑯𐑴 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑚𐑤𐑳𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑝𐑱𐑯𐑟.

𐑯𐑴 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑚𐑤𐑳𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑝𐑱𐑯𐑟? 𐑞𐑱 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑧𐑑𐑼 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑮𐑶𐑩𐑤 𐑚𐑤𐑳𐑛 𐑞𐑺. 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑥𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑝 ·𐑚𐑧𐑯𐑡𐑩𐑥𐑦𐑯 ·𐑓𐑮𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑤𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑟 ·𐑥𐑺𐑦 ·𐑥𐑼𐑧𐑤; 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼𐑢𐑼𐑛𐑟, 𐑚𐑲 𐑥𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑡, ·𐑥𐑺𐑦 ·𐑓𐑴𐑤𐑡𐑼, 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑕𐑧𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑼𐑟 𐑝 ·𐑯𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑑, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑨𐑯𐑕𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑧𐑕 𐑑 𐑩 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑤𐑲𐑯 𐑝 ·𐑓𐑴𐑤𐑡𐑼𐑟 𐑯 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑽𐑟—𐑷𐑤 𐑒𐑦𐑔 𐑯 𐑒𐑦𐑯 𐑑 𐑯𐑴𐑚𐑩𐑤 ·𐑚𐑧𐑯𐑡𐑩𐑥𐑦𐑯—𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑛𐑱 𐑛𐑸𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑚𐑸𐑚𐑛 𐑲𐑼𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛 𐑑 𐑞 𐑳𐑞𐑼.

𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑓𐑧𐑕 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑣𐑬 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤.

𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤? 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑽𐑾𐑤! 𐑚𐑲 𐑴𐑤𐑛 ·𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑤𐑦𐑖 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑗𐑩𐑑𐑼𐑦 𐑤𐑷, 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑦𐑟 𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑺𐑛 “𐑩 𐑮𐑶𐑩𐑤 𐑓𐑦𐑖.” *

𐑴, 𐑞𐑨𐑑'𐑕 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑯𐑪𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑤! 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑓𐑦𐑜𐑼𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑜𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑴𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑱.

𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑓𐑦𐑜𐑼𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑜𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑴𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑱? 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑥𐑲𐑑𐑦 𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑳𐑥𐑓𐑕 𐑜𐑦𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑑 𐑩 ·𐑮𐑴𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛'𐑟 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤, 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑩 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑚𐑮𐑷𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑢𐑱 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑦𐑮𐑾𐑯 𐑒𐑴𐑕𐑑, 𐑢𐑻 𐑞 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑩𐑕 𐑪𐑚𐑡𐑧𐑒𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑦𐑥𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑕𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑯.*

*𐑕𐑰 𐑕𐑳𐑚𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑢𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼𐑟 𐑓 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑹 𐑪𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑣𐑧𐑛.

𐑜𐑮𐑭𐑯𐑑 𐑦𐑑, 𐑕𐑦𐑯𐑕 𐑿 𐑕𐑲𐑑 𐑦𐑑; 𐑚𐑳𐑑, 𐑕𐑱 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑿 𐑢𐑦𐑤, 𐑞𐑺 𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑴 𐑮𐑾𐑤 𐑛𐑦𐑜𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙.

𐑯𐑴 𐑛𐑦𐑜𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙? 𐑞 𐑛𐑦𐑜𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑝 𐑬𐑼 𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑣𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑩𐑑𐑧𐑕𐑑. ·𐑕𐑰𐑑𐑩𐑕 𐑦𐑟 𐑩 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑬𐑔! 𐑯𐑴 𐑥𐑹! 𐑛𐑮𐑲𐑝 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑘𐑹 𐑣𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑑𐑕𐑸, 𐑯 𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑦𐑑 𐑪𐑓 𐑑 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜! 𐑯𐑴 𐑥𐑹! 𐑲 𐑯𐑴 𐑩 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑, 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑤𐑲𐑓𐑑𐑲𐑥, 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑛 𐑯 𐑓𐑦𐑓𐑑𐑦 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟. 𐑲 𐑩𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑥𐑹 𐑪𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 𐑝 𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑣𐑵 𐑚𐑴𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑝 𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑨𐑟 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑢𐑷𐑤𐑛 𐑑𐑬𐑯𐑟.

𐑯, 𐑨𐑟 𐑓 𐑥𐑰, 𐑦𐑓, 𐑚𐑲 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑐𐑪𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑦, 𐑞𐑺 𐑚𐑰 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑨𐑟 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑳𐑝𐑼𐑛 𐑐𐑮𐑲𐑥 𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑰; 𐑦𐑓 𐑲 𐑖𐑨𐑤 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑛𐑦𐑟𐑻𐑝 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑮𐑾𐑤 𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑿𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑥𐑷𐑤 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑣𐑲 𐑣𐑳𐑖𐑑 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑲 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑳𐑯𐑮𐑰𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑨𐑥𐑚𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑕 𐑝; 𐑦𐑓 𐑣𐑽𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑲 𐑖𐑨𐑤 𐑛𐑵 𐑧𐑯𐑦𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑨𐑑, 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑣𐑴𐑤, 𐑩 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑮𐑭𐑞𐑼 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑛𐑳𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑤𐑧𐑓𐑑 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑳𐑯; 𐑦𐑓, 𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑲 𐑛𐑧𐑔, 𐑥𐑲 𐑦𐑜𐑟𐑧𐑒𐑿𐑑𐑼𐑟, 𐑹 𐑥𐑹 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑐𐑼𐑤𐑦 𐑥𐑲 𐑒𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑦𐑑𐑼𐑟, 𐑓𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑕 MSS. 𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑲 𐑛𐑧𐑕𐑒, 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑣𐑽 𐑲 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑝𐑤𐑦 𐑩𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑚 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑪𐑯𐑼 𐑯 𐑞 𐑜𐑤𐑹𐑦 𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙; 𐑓 𐑩 𐑢𐑱𐑤-𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑥𐑲 ·𐑘𐑱𐑤 ·𐑒𐑪𐑤𐑦𐑡 𐑯 𐑥𐑲 ·𐑣𐑸𐑝𐑼𐑛.

·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 25. 𐑐𐑴𐑕𐑑𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑑.

𐑦𐑯 𐑚𐑦𐑣𐑭𐑓 𐑝 𐑞 𐑛𐑦𐑜𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑝 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙, 𐑲 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑓𐑱𐑯 𐑩𐑛𐑝𐑭𐑯𐑕 𐑯𐑷𐑑 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑖𐑦𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑓𐑨𐑒𐑑𐑕. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑦𐑥𐑚𐑨𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑨𐑒𐑑𐑕, 𐑩𐑯 𐑨𐑛𐑝𐑩𐑒𐑩𐑑 𐑣𐑵 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑩𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑕 𐑩 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑳𐑯𐑮𐑰𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑼𐑥𐑲𐑟, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑑𐑧𐑤 𐑧𐑤𐑩𐑒𐑢𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑷𐑟—𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩𐑯 𐑨𐑛𐑝𐑩𐑒𐑩𐑑, 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑣𐑰 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑚𐑤𐑱𐑥𐑢𐑻𐑞𐑦?

𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑧𐑤 𐑯𐑴𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑒𐑪𐑮𐑩𐑯𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑒𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑯 𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑯𐑟, 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑥𐑪𐑛𐑼𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑟, 𐑩 𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑒𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑾𐑕 𐑐𐑮𐑴𐑕𐑧𐑕 𐑝 𐑕𐑰𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑓 𐑞𐑺 𐑓𐑳𐑙𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑦𐑟 𐑜𐑪𐑯 𐑔𐑮𐑵. 𐑞𐑺 𐑦𐑟 𐑩 𐑕𐑷𐑤𐑑𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑼 𐑝 𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑑, 𐑕𐑴 𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑛, 𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑥𐑱 𐑚𐑰 𐑩 𐑒𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑼 𐑝 𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑑. 𐑣𐑬 𐑞𐑱 𐑿𐑟 𐑞 𐑕𐑷𐑤𐑑, 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑲𐑕𐑤𐑦—𐑣𐑵 𐑯𐑴𐑟? 𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑲 𐑨𐑥, 𐑣𐑬𐑧𐑝𐑼, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑩 𐑒𐑦𐑙'𐑟 𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑪𐑤𐑩𐑥𐑤𐑦 𐑶𐑤𐑛 𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑪𐑮𐑩𐑯𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯, 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑨𐑟 𐑩 𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑝 𐑕𐑨𐑤𐑩𐑛. 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑦𐑑 𐑚𐑰, 𐑞𐑴, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑱 𐑩𐑯𐑶𐑯𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑝𐑿 𐑝 𐑥𐑱𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑽𐑽 𐑮𐑳𐑯 𐑢𐑧𐑤, 𐑨𐑟 𐑞𐑱 𐑩𐑯𐑶𐑯𐑑 𐑥𐑩𐑖𐑰𐑯𐑼𐑦? 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑮𐑵𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑣𐑽, 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑦𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑤 𐑛𐑦𐑜𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑝 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑮𐑰𐑜𐑩𐑤 𐑐𐑮𐑴𐑕𐑧𐑕, 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑪𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑤𐑲𐑓 𐑢𐑰 𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑰𐑥 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑥𐑰𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑯 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑥𐑐𐑑𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑩 𐑓𐑧𐑤𐑴 𐑣𐑵 𐑩𐑯𐑶𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑺, 𐑯 𐑐𐑨𐑤𐑐𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑥𐑧𐑤𐑟 𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑩𐑯𐑶𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑙. 𐑦𐑯 𐑑𐑮𐑵𐑔, 𐑩 𐑥𐑩𐑗𐑫𐑼 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑣𐑵 𐑿𐑟𐑩𐑟 𐑣𐑺-𐑶𐑤, 𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑧𐑕 𐑥𐑧𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑤𐑦, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑚𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑜𐑪𐑑 𐑩 𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑜𐑦 𐑕𐑐𐑪𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑢𐑺. 𐑨𐑟 𐑩 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑮𐑵𐑤, 𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑭𐑯𐑑 𐑩𐑥𐑬𐑯𐑑 𐑑 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑑𐑴𐑑𐑨𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑦.

𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑼𐑛 𐑣𐑽, 𐑦𐑟 𐑞𐑦𐑕—𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑒𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑝 𐑶𐑤 𐑦𐑟 𐑿𐑟𐑛 𐑨𐑑 𐑒𐑪𐑮𐑩𐑯𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟? 𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑑 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑪𐑤𐑦𐑝 𐑶𐑤, 𐑯𐑹 𐑥𐑩𐑒𐑨𐑕𐑼 𐑶𐑤, 𐑯𐑹 𐑒𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑼 𐑶𐑤, 𐑯𐑹 𐑚𐑺'𐑟 𐑶𐑤, 𐑯𐑹 𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯 𐑶𐑤, 𐑯𐑹 𐑒𐑪𐑛-𐑤𐑦𐑝𐑼 𐑶𐑤. 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑦𐑑 𐑐𐑪𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑰, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 𐑶𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑳𐑯𐑥𐑨𐑯𐑿𐑓𐑨𐑒𐑗𐑼𐑛, 𐑳𐑯𐑐𐑩𐑤𐑵𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑑, 𐑞 𐑕𐑢𐑰𐑑𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑝 𐑷𐑤 𐑶𐑤𐑟?

𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒 𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑, 𐑘𐑰 𐑤𐑶𐑩𐑤 ·𐑚𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑟! 𐑢𐑰 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑕𐑩𐑐𐑤𐑲 𐑘𐑹 𐑒𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑯 𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑯𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑒𐑪𐑮𐑩𐑯𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑓!

·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 26. 𐑯𐑲𐑑𐑕 𐑯 ·𐑕𐑒𐑢𐑲𐑼𐑟.

𐑞 𐑗𐑰𐑓 𐑥𐑱𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛 𐑢𐑪𐑟 ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒, 𐑩 𐑯𐑱𐑑𐑦𐑝 𐑝 ·𐑯𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑑, 𐑯 𐑩 ·𐑒𐑢𐑱𐑒𐑼 𐑚𐑲 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑑. 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩 𐑤𐑪𐑙, 𐑻𐑯𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑥𐑨𐑯, 𐑯 𐑞𐑴 𐑚𐑹𐑯 𐑪𐑯 𐑩𐑯 𐑲𐑕𐑦 𐑒𐑴𐑕𐑑, 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑢𐑧𐑤 𐑩𐑛𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑻 𐑣𐑪𐑑 𐑤𐑨𐑑𐑦𐑑𐑿𐑛𐑟, 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑤𐑧𐑖 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑸𐑛 𐑨𐑟 𐑑𐑢𐑲𐑕-𐑚𐑱𐑒𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑦𐑑. 𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑕𐑐𐑹𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑟, 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑤𐑲𐑝 𐑚𐑤𐑳𐑛 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑐𐑶𐑤 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑚𐑪𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑱𐑤. 𐑣𐑰 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑚𐑹𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑝 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑛𐑮𐑬𐑑 𐑯 𐑓𐑨𐑥𐑦𐑯, 𐑹 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑓𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑛𐑱𐑟 𐑓 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑱𐑥𐑩𐑕. 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑔𐑻𐑑𐑦 𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑛 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑼𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑰𐑯; 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑼𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑛𐑮𐑲𐑛 𐑳𐑐 𐑷𐑤 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑦𐑟𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑵𐑐𐑻𐑓𐑤𐑵𐑩𐑕𐑯𐑩𐑕. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕, 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑔𐑦𐑯𐑯𐑩𐑕, 𐑕𐑴 𐑑 𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑒, 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑯𐑴 𐑥𐑹 𐑞 𐑑𐑴𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑢𐑱𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑨𐑙𐑟𐑲𐑩𐑑𐑦𐑟 𐑯 𐑒𐑺𐑟, 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑤𐑲𐑑. 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑥𐑽𐑤𐑦 𐑞 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑛𐑧𐑯𐑕𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑥𐑨𐑯. 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑚𐑲 𐑯𐑴 𐑥𐑰𐑯𐑟 𐑦𐑤-𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑦𐑙; 𐑒𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑞 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑺𐑦. 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑘𐑫𐑼 𐑑𐑲𐑑 𐑕𐑒𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩𐑯 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑩𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑓𐑦𐑑; 𐑯 𐑒𐑤𐑴𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑨𐑐𐑑 𐑳𐑐 𐑦𐑯 𐑦𐑑, 𐑯 𐑦𐑥𐑚𐑭𐑥𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑼 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑔 𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑧𐑙𐑔, 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑮𐑰𐑝𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑓𐑲𐑛 ·𐑦𐑡𐑦𐑐𐑖𐑩𐑯, 𐑞𐑦𐑕 ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑺𐑛 𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑻 𐑓 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑱𐑡𐑩𐑟 𐑑 𐑒𐑳𐑥, 𐑯 𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑻 𐑷𐑤𐑢𐑱𐑟, 𐑨𐑟 𐑯𐑬; 𐑓 𐑚𐑰 𐑦𐑑 ·𐑐𐑴𐑤𐑼 𐑕𐑯𐑴 𐑹 𐑑𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑛 𐑕𐑳𐑯, 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑐𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑒𐑮𐑩𐑯𐑪𐑥𐑦𐑑𐑼, 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑽𐑽 𐑝𐑲𐑑𐑨𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑢𐑪𐑮𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑑 𐑛𐑵 𐑢𐑧𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑒𐑤𐑲𐑥𐑩𐑑𐑕. 𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑲𐑟, 𐑿 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑑 𐑕𐑰 𐑞𐑺 𐑞 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑤𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑡𐑩𐑟 𐑝 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑔𐑬𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑛-𐑓𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑐𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑤𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑒𐑭𐑥𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑓𐑮𐑳𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑤𐑲𐑓. 𐑩 𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑛, 𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑛𐑓𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑥𐑨𐑯, 𐑣𐑵𐑟 𐑤𐑲𐑓 𐑓 𐑞 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑐𐑸𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩 𐑑𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑐𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑥𐑲𐑥 𐑝 𐑨𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯, 𐑯 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑩 𐑑𐑱𐑥 𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 𐑝 𐑕𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑟. 𐑘𐑧𐑑, 𐑓 𐑷𐑤 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑸𐑛𐑦 𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑮𐑲𐑩𐑑𐑦 𐑯 𐑓𐑹𐑑𐑦𐑑𐑿𐑛, 𐑞𐑺 𐑢𐑻 𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑨𐑑 𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑩𐑓𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑛, 𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑒𐑱𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑢𐑧𐑤 𐑯𐑲 𐑑 𐑴𐑝𐑼𐑚𐑨𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑑. 𐑳𐑯𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑖𐑦𐑧𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑕 𐑓 𐑩 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑩𐑯, 𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑿𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑛𐑰𐑐 𐑯𐑨𐑗𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑮𐑧𐑝𐑼𐑩𐑯𐑕, 𐑞 𐑢𐑲𐑤𐑛 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼𐑦 𐑤𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑤𐑲𐑓 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑞𐑺𐑓𐑹 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑪𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑤𐑲𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑑 𐑕𐑵𐑐𐑼𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑹𐑑 𐑝 𐑕𐑵𐑐𐑼𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑹𐑜𐑩𐑯𐑲𐑟𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑟 𐑮𐑭𐑞𐑼 𐑑 𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑙, 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑣𐑬, 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑡𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑦𐑜𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑯𐑕. 𐑬𐑑𐑢𐑼𐑛 𐑐𐑹𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑢𐑼𐑛 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑢𐑻 𐑣𐑦𐑟. 𐑯 𐑦𐑓 𐑨𐑑 𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑚𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑞 𐑢𐑧𐑤𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑲𐑼𐑯 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑴𐑤, 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑥𐑹 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑸-𐑩𐑢𐑱 𐑛𐑩𐑥𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑥𐑧𐑥𐑼𐑦𐑟 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑘𐑳𐑙 ·𐑒𐑱𐑐 𐑢𐑲𐑓 𐑯 𐑗𐑲𐑤𐑛, 𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑑 𐑚𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑥𐑹 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑼𐑦𐑡𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑮𐑳𐑜𐑩𐑛𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑱𐑗𐑼, 𐑯 𐑴𐑐𐑩𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑓𐑻𐑞𐑼 𐑑 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑤𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑓𐑤𐑵𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑗, 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑪𐑯𐑩𐑕𐑑-𐑣𐑸𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑥𐑧𐑯, 𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯 𐑞 𐑜𐑳𐑖 𐑝 𐑛𐑺-𐑛𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑤 𐑛𐑺𐑦𐑙, 𐑕𐑴 𐑪𐑓𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑳𐑞𐑼𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑥𐑹 𐑐𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑝𐑦𐑕𐑦𐑕𐑦𐑑𐑿𐑛𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑼𐑦. “𐑲 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑯𐑴 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑲 𐑚𐑴𐑑,” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒, “𐑣𐑵 𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑩𐑓𐑮𐑱𐑛 𐑝 𐑩 𐑢𐑱𐑤.” 𐑚𐑲 𐑞𐑦𐑕, 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑑 𐑥𐑰𐑯, 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑤𐑲𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑯 𐑿𐑕𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑒𐑳𐑮𐑦𐑡 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑼𐑲𐑟𐑩𐑟 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑓𐑺 𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑥𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑛 𐑐𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑤, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑩𐑯 𐑳𐑑𐑼𐑤𐑦 𐑓𐑽𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑦𐑟 𐑩 𐑓𐑸 𐑥𐑹 𐑛𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑼𐑩𐑕 𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑮𐑱𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑩 𐑒𐑬𐑼𐑛.

“𐑲, 𐑲,” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚, 𐑞 𐑕𐑧𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑥𐑱𐑑, “𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒, 𐑞𐑺, 𐑦𐑟 𐑨𐑟 𐑒𐑺𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑩 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑨𐑟 𐑿'𐑤 𐑓𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑧𐑯𐑦𐑢𐑺 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑼𐑦.” 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑰 𐑖𐑨𐑤 𐑺 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑕𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑻𐑛 “𐑒𐑺𐑓𐑩𐑤” 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑲𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑥𐑰𐑯𐑟 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑿𐑟𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑩 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑤𐑲𐑒 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚, 𐑹 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑑𐑼.

𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑴 𐑒𐑮𐑵𐑕𐑱𐑛𐑼 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑐𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑤𐑟; 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑒𐑳𐑮𐑦𐑡 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑩 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑩 𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑦 𐑿𐑕𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑯 𐑷𐑤𐑢𐑱𐑟 𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑥𐑹𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑮𐑨𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑩𐑒𐑱𐑠𐑩𐑯𐑟. 𐑚𐑦𐑕𐑲𐑛𐑟, 𐑣𐑰 𐑔𐑷𐑑, 𐑐𐑼𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑕, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑚𐑦𐑟𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙, 𐑒𐑳𐑮𐑦𐑡 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑐𐑩𐑤 𐑬𐑑𐑓𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐, 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑣𐑻 𐑚𐑰𐑓 𐑯 𐑣𐑻 𐑚𐑮𐑧𐑛, 𐑯 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑓𐑵𐑤𐑦𐑖𐑤𐑦 𐑢𐑱𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛. 𐑢𐑺𐑓𐑹 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑯𐑴 𐑓𐑨𐑯𐑕𐑦 𐑓 𐑤𐑴𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑓 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑕𐑳𐑯-𐑛𐑬𐑯; 𐑯𐑹 𐑓 𐑐𐑼𐑕𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑓𐑲𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑓𐑦𐑖 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑑𐑵 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑐𐑼𐑕𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑓𐑲𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑥. 𐑓, 𐑔𐑷𐑑 ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒, 𐑲 𐑨𐑥 𐑣𐑽 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑑 𐑒𐑦𐑤 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑓 𐑥𐑲 𐑤𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑙, 𐑯 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑒𐑦𐑤𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑓 𐑞𐑺𐑟; 𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑛𐑟 𐑝 𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑕𐑴 𐑒𐑦𐑤𐑛 ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒 𐑢𐑧𐑤 𐑯𐑿. 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑛𐑵𐑥 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑴𐑯 𐑓𐑭𐑞𐑼'𐑟? 𐑢𐑺, 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑪𐑑𐑩𐑥𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑛𐑰𐑐𐑕, 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑣𐑰 𐑓𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑞 𐑑𐑹𐑯 𐑤𐑦𐑥𐑟 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑮𐑳𐑞𐑼?

𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑥𐑧𐑥𐑼𐑦𐑟 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑯, 𐑥𐑹𐑴𐑝𐑼, 𐑜𐑦𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑑 𐑩 𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑕𐑵𐑐𐑼𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑕𐑯𐑩𐑕, 𐑨𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑕𐑧𐑛; 𐑞 𐑒𐑳𐑮𐑦𐑡 𐑝 𐑞𐑦𐑕 ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑒𐑫𐑛, 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼𐑞𐑩𐑤𐑧𐑕, 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑓𐑤𐑳𐑮𐑦𐑖, 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑰𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑰𐑥. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑮𐑰𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑯𐑱𐑗𐑼 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑩 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑕𐑴 𐑹𐑜𐑩𐑯𐑲𐑟𐑛, 𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑑𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑽𐑾𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑯 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑧𐑥𐑚𐑮𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑨𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛; 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑯𐑱𐑗𐑼 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑓𐑱𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑤𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑯𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑯 𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑢𐑦𐑗, 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑕𐑵𐑑𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑻𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟, 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑒 𐑬𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑓𐑲𐑯𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑, 𐑯 𐑚𐑻𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑳𐑮𐑦𐑡 𐑳𐑐. 𐑯 𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑝 𐑨𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑚𐑰, 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑹𐑑 𐑝 𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑝𐑼𐑦 𐑗𐑰𐑓𐑤𐑦, 𐑝𐑦𐑟𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑧𐑐𐑦𐑛 𐑥𐑧𐑯, 𐑢𐑦𐑗, 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑩𐑚𐑲𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑻𐑥 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑓𐑤𐑦𐑒𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑕𐑰𐑟, 𐑹 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑟, 𐑹 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟, 𐑹 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑝 𐑞 𐑹𐑛𐑦𐑯𐑼𐑦 𐑦𐑮𐑨𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑣𐑪𐑮𐑼𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛, 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑥𐑹 𐑑𐑼𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑒, 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑪𐑟 𐑥𐑹 𐑕𐑐𐑦𐑮𐑦𐑗𐑵𐑩𐑤 𐑑𐑧𐑮𐑼𐑟, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑿 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑮𐑬 𐑝 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑮𐑱𐑡𐑛 𐑯 𐑥𐑲𐑑𐑦 𐑥𐑨𐑯.

𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑻 𐑞 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑑𐑦𐑝 𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑝𐑰𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕, 𐑞 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑰𐑑 𐑩𐑚𐑱𐑕𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑐𐑫𐑼 ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒'𐑕 𐑓𐑹𐑑𐑦𐑑𐑿𐑛, 𐑕𐑒𐑺𐑕 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑞 𐑣𐑸𐑑 𐑑 𐑮𐑲𐑑 𐑦𐑑; 𐑓 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑩 𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑪𐑮𐑴𐑓𐑩𐑤, 𐑯𐑱 𐑖𐑪𐑒𐑦𐑙, 𐑑 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑴𐑟 𐑞 𐑓𐑷𐑤 𐑝 𐑝𐑨𐑤𐑼 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑴𐑤. 𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑥𐑱 𐑕𐑰𐑥 𐑛𐑦𐑑𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑨𐑟 𐑡𐑶𐑯𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑪𐑒-𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑟 𐑯 𐑯𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟; 𐑯𐑱𐑝𐑟, 𐑓𐑵𐑤𐑟, 𐑯 𐑥𐑻𐑛𐑼𐑼𐑟 𐑞𐑺 𐑥𐑱 𐑚𐑰; 𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑥𐑱 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑥𐑰𐑯 𐑯 𐑥𐑰𐑜𐑼 𐑓𐑱𐑕𐑩𐑟; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑥𐑨𐑯, 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑲𐑛𐑾𐑤, 𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑴 𐑯𐑴𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑯 𐑕𐑴 𐑕𐑐𐑸𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙, 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩 𐑜𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑯 𐑜𐑤𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑒𐑮𐑰𐑗𐑼, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑦𐑜𐑯𐑩𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑾𐑕 𐑚𐑤𐑧𐑥𐑦𐑖 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑷𐑤 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑧𐑤𐑴𐑟 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑮𐑳𐑯 𐑑 𐑔𐑮𐑴 𐑞𐑺 𐑒𐑪𐑕𐑑𐑤𐑾𐑕𐑑 𐑮𐑴𐑚𐑟. 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑥𐑨𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑩𐑑 𐑥𐑨𐑯𐑤𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑢𐑰 𐑓𐑰𐑤 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑦𐑯 𐑬𐑼𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑝𐑟, 𐑕𐑴 𐑓𐑸 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑦𐑯 𐑳𐑕, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑱𐑯𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑨𐑒𐑑 𐑞𐑴 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑬𐑑𐑼 𐑒𐑨𐑮𐑩𐑒𐑑𐑼 𐑕𐑰𐑥 𐑜𐑪𐑯; 𐑚𐑤𐑰𐑛𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑒𐑰𐑯𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑨𐑙𐑜𐑢𐑦𐑖 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑮𐑱𐑐𐑑 𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑩 𐑝𐑨𐑤𐑼-𐑮𐑵𐑦𐑯𐑛 𐑥𐑨𐑯. 𐑯𐑹 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑐𐑲𐑩𐑑𐑦 𐑦𐑑𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓, 𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩 𐑖𐑱𐑥𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑲𐑑, 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑰𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑑𐑲𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑣𐑻 𐑳𐑐𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑛𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑞 𐑐𐑼𐑥𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑟. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑷𐑜𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑜𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑲 𐑑𐑮𐑰𐑑 𐑝, 𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑞 𐑛𐑦𐑜𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑝 𐑒𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑯 𐑮𐑴𐑚𐑟, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑛𐑦𐑜𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑯𐑴 𐑮𐑴𐑚𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑗𐑼. 𐑞𐑬 𐑖𐑨𐑤𐑑 𐑕𐑰 𐑦𐑑 𐑖𐑲𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑸𐑥 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑰𐑤𐑛𐑟 𐑩 𐑐𐑦𐑒 𐑹 𐑛𐑮𐑲𐑝𐑟 𐑩 𐑕𐑐𐑲𐑒; 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑛𐑧𐑥𐑩𐑒𐑮𐑨𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑛𐑦𐑜𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑢𐑦𐑗, 𐑪𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟, 𐑮𐑱𐑛𐑦𐑱𐑑𐑕 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑 𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 ·𐑜𐑪𐑛; ·𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓! 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 ·𐑜𐑪𐑛 𐑨𐑚𐑕𐑩𐑤𐑵𐑑! 𐑞 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑼 𐑯 𐑕𐑼𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑓𐑼𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑝 𐑷𐑤 𐑛𐑦𐑥𐑪𐑒𐑮𐑩𐑕𐑦! 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑪𐑥𐑯𐑦𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑕, 𐑬𐑼 𐑛𐑦𐑝𐑲𐑯 𐑦𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑦!

𐑦𐑓, 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑑 𐑥𐑰𐑯𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑥𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑯𐑼𐑟, 𐑯 𐑮𐑧𐑯𐑦𐑜𐑱𐑛𐑟 𐑯 𐑒𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑢𐑱𐑟, 𐑲 𐑖𐑨𐑤 𐑣𐑽𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑩𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑚 𐑣𐑲 𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑟, 𐑞𐑴 𐑛𐑸𐑒; 𐑢𐑰𐑝 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑡𐑦𐑒 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑕𐑩𐑟; 𐑦𐑓 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑞 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑥𐑹𐑯𐑓𐑩𐑤, 𐑐𐑼𐑗𐑨𐑯𐑕 𐑞 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑩𐑚𐑱𐑕𐑑, 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑷𐑤, 𐑖𐑨𐑤 𐑨𐑑 𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑤𐑦𐑓𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑑 𐑞 𐑦𐑜𐑟𐑷𐑤𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑥𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑕; 𐑦𐑓 𐑲 𐑖𐑨𐑤 𐑑𐑳𐑗 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑻𐑒𐑥𐑩𐑯'𐑟 𐑸𐑥 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑦𐑔𐑽𐑾𐑤 𐑤𐑲𐑑; 𐑦𐑓 𐑲 𐑖𐑨𐑤 𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑛 𐑩 𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑚𐑴 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑛𐑦𐑟𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑩𐑕 𐑕𐑧𐑑 𐑝 𐑕𐑳𐑯; 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑥𐑹𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑕 𐑚𐑺 𐑥𐑰 𐑬𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑦𐑑, 𐑞𐑬 𐑡𐑳𐑕𐑑 ·𐑕𐑐𐑦𐑮𐑦𐑑 𐑝 ·𐑦𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑦, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑣𐑨𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑛 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑮𐑶𐑩𐑤 𐑥𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑣𐑿𐑥𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑷𐑤 𐑥𐑲 𐑒𐑲𐑯𐑛! 𐑚𐑺 𐑥𐑰 𐑬𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑦𐑑, 𐑞𐑬 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑛𐑧𐑥𐑩𐑒𐑮𐑨𐑑𐑦𐑒 ·𐑜𐑪𐑛! 𐑣𐑵 𐑛𐑦𐑛𐑕𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑓𐑿𐑟 𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑢𐑸𐑑 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑝𐑦𐑒𐑑, ·𐑚𐑳𐑯𐑘𐑩𐑯, 𐑞 𐑐𐑱𐑤, 𐑐𐑴𐑧𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑐𐑻𐑤; ·𐑞𐑬 𐑣𐑵 𐑛𐑦𐑛𐑕𐑑 𐑒𐑤𐑴𐑞 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑛𐑳𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑣𐑨𐑥𐑼𐑛 𐑤𐑰𐑝𐑟 𐑝 𐑓𐑲𐑯𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑜𐑴𐑤𐑛, 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑑 𐑯 𐑐𐑷𐑐𐑼𐑛 𐑸𐑥 𐑝 𐑴𐑤𐑛 ·𐑕𐑧𐑮𐑝𐑭𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑕; ·𐑞𐑬 𐑣𐑵 𐑛𐑦𐑛𐑕𐑑 𐑐𐑦𐑒 𐑳𐑐 ·𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑮𐑵 ·𐑡𐑨𐑒𐑕𐑩𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑐𐑧𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑟; 𐑣𐑵 𐑛𐑦𐑛𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑻𐑤 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑩 𐑢𐑹-𐑣𐑹𐑕; 𐑣𐑵 𐑛𐑦𐑛𐑕𐑑 𐑔𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑣𐑲𐑼 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑩 𐑔𐑮𐑴𐑯! 𐑞𐑬 𐑣𐑵, 𐑦𐑯 𐑷𐑤 ·𐑞𐑲 𐑥𐑲𐑑𐑦, 𐑻𐑔𐑤𐑦 𐑥𐑸𐑗𐑦𐑙𐑟, 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑒𐑳𐑤𐑩𐑕𐑑 ·𐑞𐑲 𐑕𐑦𐑤𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑗𐑨𐑥𐑐𐑾𐑯𐑟 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑒𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑟; 𐑚𐑺 𐑥𐑰 𐑬𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑦𐑑, 𐑴 ·𐑜𐑪𐑛!

·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 27. 𐑯𐑲𐑑𐑕 𐑯 ·𐑕𐑒𐑢𐑲𐑼𐑟.

𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞 𐑕𐑧𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑥𐑱𐑑. 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩 𐑯𐑱𐑑𐑦𐑝 𐑝 ·𐑒𐑱𐑐 ·𐑒𐑪𐑛; 𐑯 𐑣𐑧𐑯𐑕, 𐑩𐑒𐑹𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑤𐑴𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑿𐑕𐑦𐑡, 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑛 𐑩 ·𐑒𐑱𐑐-·𐑒𐑪𐑛-𐑥𐑨𐑯. 𐑩 𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑦-𐑜𐑴-𐑤𐑳𐑒𐑦; 𐑯𐑲𐑞𐑼 𐑒𐑮𐑱𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑯𐑹 𐑝𐑨𐑤𐑾𐑯𐑑; 𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑐𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑤𐑟 𐑨𐑟 𐑞𐑱 𐑒𐑱𐑥 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑓𐑼𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑺; 𐑯 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑦𐑯𐑜𐑱𐑡𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑕𐑦𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑗𐑱𐑕, 𐑑𐑶𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑢𐑱, 𐑒𐑭𐑥 𐑯 𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑨𐑟 𐑩 𐑡𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑡𐑶𐑯𐑼 𐑦𐑯𐑜𐑱𐑡𐑛 𐑓 𐑞 𐑘𐑽. 𐑜𐑫𐑛-𐑣𐑿𐑥𐑼𐑛, 𐑰𐑟𐑦, 𐑯 𐑒𐑺𐑤𐑩𐑕, 𐑣𐑰 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑲𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑱𐑤-𐑚𐑴𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑓 𐑞 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑛𐑧𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑼 𐑢𐑻 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑩 𐑛𐑦𐑯𐑼, 𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑮𐑵 𐑷𐑤 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑜𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑕. 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑨𐑟 𐑐𐑼𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑼 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑞 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑓𐑼𐑑𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑼𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑸𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑, 𐑨𐑟 𐑩𐑯 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑡-𐑛𐑮𐑲𐑝𐑼 𐑦𐑟 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑯𐑳𐑜𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑪𐑒𐑕. 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑒𐑤𐑴𐑟 𐑑 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑛𐑧𐑔-𐑤𐑪𐑒 𐑝 𐑞 𐑓𐑲𐑑, 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑳𐑯𐑐𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑦𐑙 𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑕 𐑒𐑵𐑤𐑦 𐑯 𐑪𐑓-𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛𐑤𐑦, 𐑨𐑟 𐑩 𐑢𐑦𐑕𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑑𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑼 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑥𐑼. 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑣𐑳𐑥 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑴𐑤𐑛 ·𐑮𐑰𐑜𐑩𐑛𐑦𐑜 𐑑𐑿𐑯𐑟 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑓𐑤𐑨𐑙𐑒 𐑯 𐑓𐑤𐑨𐑙𐑒 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑜𐑟𐑨𐑕𐑐𐑼𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑥𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑼. 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑿𐑕𐑦𐑡 𐑣𐑨𐑛, 𐑓 𐑞𐑦𐑕 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚, 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑝𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑞 𐑡𐑷𐑟 𐑝 𐑛𐑧𐑔 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑩𐑯 𐑰𐑟𐑦 𐑗𐑺. 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑔𐑷𐑑 𐑝 𐑛𐑧𐑔 𐑦𐑑𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓, 𐑞𐑺 𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑴 𐑑𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑙. 𐑢𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑣𐑰 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑔𐑷𐑑 𐑝 𐑦𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑷𐑤, 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑩 𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑕𐑗𐑩𐑯; 𐑚𐑳𐑑, 𐑦𐑓 𐑣𐑰 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑗𐑭𐑯𐑕 𐑑 𐑒𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑱 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑩 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑓𐑼𐑑𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑛𐑦𐑯𐑼, 𐑯𐑴 𐑛𐑬𐑑, 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑼, 𐑣𐑰 𐑑𐑫𐑒 𐑦𐑑 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑩 𐑕𐑹𐑑 𐑝 𐑒𐑷𐑤 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑪𐑗 𐑑 𐑑𐑳𐑥𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑓𐑑, 𐑯 𐑚𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑻 𐑞𐑧𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑝𐑟 𐑞𐑺, 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑓𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑬𐑑 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑣𐑰 𐑴𐑚𐑱𐑛 𐑞 𐑹𐑛𐑼, 𐑯 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑵𐑯𐑼.

𐑢𐑪𐑑, 𐑐𐑼𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑕, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑟, 𐑥𐑱𐑛 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩𐑯 𐑰𐑟𐑦-𐑜𐑴𐑦𐑙, 𐑳𐑯𐑓𐑽𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑨𐑯, 𐑕𐑴 𐑗𐑽𐑦𐑤𐑦 𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑡𐑦𐑙 𐑪𐑓 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑚𐑻𐑛𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑤𐑲𐑓 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛 𐑓𐑫𐑤 𐑝 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑝 𐑐𐑧𐑛𐑤𐑼𐑟, 𐑷𐑤 𐑚𐑬𐑛 𐑑 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞𐑺 𐑐𐑨𐑒𐑕; 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑐𐑑 𐑑 𐑚𐑮𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑲𐑩𐑕 𐑜𐑫𐑛-𐑣𐑿𐑥𐑼 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟; 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑲𐑐. 𐑓, 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑴𐑟, 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑖𐑹𐑑, 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑒 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑐𐑲𐑐 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑮𐑧𐑜𐑿𐑤𐑼 𐑓𐑰𐑗𐑼𐑟 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑱𐑕. 𐑿 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑕𐑵𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑑 𐑑𐑻𐑯 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑳𐑙𐑒 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑴𐑟 𐑨𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑲𐑐. 𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑧𐑐𐑑 𐑩 𐑣𐑴𐑤 𐑮𐑴 𐑝 𐑐𐑲𐑐𐑕 𐑞𐑺 𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑦 𐑤𐑴𐑛𐑩𐑛, 𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑒 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑮𐑨𐑒, 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑦𐑯 𐑰𐑟𐑦 𐑮𐑰𐑗 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛; 𐑯, 𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑣𐑰 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑯, 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑥𐑴𐑒𐑑 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑷𐑤 𐑬𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑩𐑒𐑕𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑯, 𐑤𐑲𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑑 𐑞 𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑝 𐑞 𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼; 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑤𐑴𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑦𐑯 𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑩𐑯𐑿. 𐑓, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚 𐑛𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑑, 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑛 𐑝 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑐𐑫𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑤𐑧𐑜𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑑𐑮𐑴𐑟𐑼𐑟, 𐑣𐑰 𐑐𐑫𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑲𐑐 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑬𐑔.

𐑲 𐑕𐑱 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑿𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑥𐑴𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑒𐑷𐑟, 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑰𐑕𐑑, 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑽 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑩𐑟𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯; 𐑓 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑯𐑴𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑻𐑔𐑤𐑦 𐑺, 𐑢𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑩𐑖𐑹 𐑹 𐑩𐑓𐑤𐑴𐑑, 𐑦𐑟 𐑑𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑯𐑓𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑯𐑱𐑥𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑥𐑦𐑟𐑼𐑦𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑯𐑳𐑥𐑚𐑼𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑥𐑹𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑣𐑵 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑛𐑲𐑛 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑣𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑑; 𐑯 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑝 𐑞 𐑒𐑪𐑤𐑼𐑩, 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑐𐑰𐑐𐑩𐑤 𐑜𐑴 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑒𐑨𐑥𐑓𐑼𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑼𐑗𐑦𐑓 𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑥𐑬𐑞𐑟; 𐑕𐑴, 𐑤𐑲𐑒𐑢𐑲𐑟, 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑥𐑹𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑚𐑿𐑤𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟, ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚'𐑟 𐑑𐑩𐑚𐑨𐑒𐑴 𐑕𐑥𐑴𐑒 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑪𐑐𐑼𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑨𐑟 𐑩 𐑕𐑹𐑑 𐑝 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑦𐑯𐑓𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑱𐑡𐑩𐑯𐑑.

𐑞 𐑔𐑻𐑛 𐑥𐑱𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 ·𐑓𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑒, 𐑩 𐑯𐑱𐑑𐑦𐑝 𐑝 ·𐑑𐑦𐑟𐑚𐑼𐑦, 𐑦𐑯 ·𐑥𐑸𐑔𐑩'𐑟 ·𐑝𐑦𐑯𐑘𐑼𐑛. 𐑩 𐑖𐑹𐑑, 𐑕𐑑𐑬𐑑, 𐑮𐑳𐑛𐑦 𐑘𐑳𐑙 𐑓𐑧𐑤𐑴, 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑐𐑳𐑜𐑯𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑕 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟, 𐑣𐑵 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑣𐑬 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑑 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑤𐑩𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑔𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑐𐑻𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑯 𐑣𐑼𐑧𐑛𐑦𐑑𐑺𐑦𐑤𐑦 𐑩𐑓𐑮𐑳𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥; 𐑯 𐑞𐑺𐑓𐑹 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩 𐑕𐑹𐑑 𐑝 𐑐𐑶𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑪𐑯𐑼 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑶 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑛. 𐑕𐑴 𐑳𐑑𐑼𐑤𐑦 𐑤𐑪𐑕𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑕 𐑝 𐑮𐑧𐑝𐑼𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑓 𐑞 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑥𐑸𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑝 𐑞𐑺 𐑥𐑩𐑡𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑚𐑳𐑤𐑒 𐑯 𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑢𐑱𐑟; 𐑯 𐑕𐑴 𐑛𐑧𐑛 𐑑 𐑧𐑯𐑦𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩𐑯 𐑨𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑣𐑧𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑐𐑪𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑛𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑼 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑧𐑥; 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑫𐑼 𐑩𐑐𐑦𐑯𐑘𐑩𐑯, 𐑞 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑕 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑩 𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑖𐑰𐑟 𐑝 𐑥𐑨𐑜𐑯𐑦𐑓𐑲𐑛 𐑥𐑬𐑕, 𐑹 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑰𐑕𐑑 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼-𐑮𐑨𐑑, 𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑢𐑲𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑩 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑻𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑝𐑧𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑕𐑥𐑷𐑤 𐑨𐑐𐑤𐑦𐑒𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑯 𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑹𐑛𐑼 𐑑 𐑒𐑦𐑤 𐑯 𐑚𐑶𐑤. 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑦𐑜𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑯𐑑, 𐑳𐑯𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑕 𐑓𐑽𐑤𐑩𐑕𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑩 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑨𐑜𐑦𐑖 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑥𐑨𐑑𐑼 𐑝 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟; 𐑣𐑰 𐑓𐑪𐑤𐑴𐑛 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑓𐑦𐑖 𐑓 𐑞 𐑓𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑦𐑑; 𐑯 𐑩 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑘𐑽𐑟' 𐑝𐑶𐑦𐑡 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 ·𐑒𐑱𐑐 ·𐑣𐑹𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑩 𐑡𐑪𐑤𐑦 𐑡𐑴𐑒 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑧𐑙𐑔 𐑝 𐑑𐑲𐑥. 𐑨𐑟 𐑩 𐑒𐑸𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑼'𐑟 𐑯𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑸 𐑛𐑦𐑝𐑲𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑮𐑷𐑑 𐑯𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑯 𐑒𐑳𐑑 𐑯𐑱𐑤𐑟; 𐑕𐑴 𐑥𐑨𐑯𐑒𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑥𐑱 𐑚𐑰 𐑕𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑤𐑼𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑦𐑝𐑲𐑛𐑩𐑛. 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 ·𐑓𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑒 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑮𐑷𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑟; 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑑 𐑒𐑤𐑦𐑯𐑗 𐑑𐑲𐑑 𐑯 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑤𐑪𐑙. 𐑞𐑱 𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥 ·𐑒𐑦𐑙-·𐑐𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑪𐑯 𐑚𐑹𐑛 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛; 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑪𐑟, 𐑦𐑯 𐑓𐑹𐑥, 𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑚𐑰 𐑢𐑧𐑤 𐑤𐑲𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑑 𐑞 𐑖𐑹𐑑, 𐑕𐑒𐑢𐑺 𐑑𐑦𐑥𐑚𐑼 𐑯𐑴𐑯 𐑚𐑲 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑯𐑱𐑥 𐑦𐑯 ·𐑸𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑼𐑟; 𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑥𐑰𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑮𐑱𐑛𐑦𐑱𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑑𐑦𐑥𐑚𐑼𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑦𐑑, 𐑕𐑻𐑝𐑟 𐑑 𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑕 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑞 𐑲𐑕𐑦 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑒𐑳𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑚𐑨𐑑𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑰𐑟.

𐑯𐑬 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑥𐑱𐑑𐑕—·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒, ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚, 𐑯 ·𐑓𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑒, 𐑢𐑻 𐑥𐑴𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑕 𐑥𐑧𐑯. 𐑞𐑱 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑣𐑵 𐑚𐑲 𐑿𐑯𐑦𐑝𐑻𐑕𐑩𐑤 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑭𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛'𐑟 𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕 𐑨𐑟 𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑟𐑥𐑧𐑯. 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑜𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑹𐑛𐑼 𐑝 𐑚𐑨𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑗 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑚𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑥𐑸𐑖𐑩𐑤 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑹𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟, 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑟𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑢𐑻 𐑨𐑟 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑟. 𐑹, 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑸𐑥𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞𐑺 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑒𐑰𐑯 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑐𐑽𐑟, 𐑞𐑱 𐑢𐑻 𐑨𐑟 𐑩 𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑑 𐑑𐑮𐑰𐑴 𐑝 𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑼𐑟; 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑽𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑓𐑤𐑦𐑙𐑼𐑟 𐑝 𐑡𐑨𐑝𐑤𐑦𐑯𐑟.

𐑯 𐑕𐑦𐑯𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑓𐑱𐑥𐑩𐑕 𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑼𐑦, 𐑰𐑗 𐑥𐑱𐑑 𐑹 𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑟𐑥𐑩𐑯, 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 ·𐑜𐑪𐑔𐑦𐑒 ·𐑯𐑲𐑑 𐑝 𐑴𐑤𐑛, 𐑦𐑟 𐑷𐑤𐑢𐑱𐑟 𐑩𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑴𐑑-𐑕𐑑𐑽𐑼 𐑹 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑽, 𐑣𐑵 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑡𐑳𐑙𐑒𐑗𐑼𐑟 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑝𐑲𐑛𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑖 𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑕, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑹𐑥𐑼 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑚𐑨𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑑𐑢𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛, 𐑹 𐑧𐑤𐑚𐑴𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑩𐑕𐑷𐑤𐑑; 𐑯 𐑥𐑹𐑴𐑝𐑼, 𐑨𐑟 𐑞𐑺 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑕𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑕 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑢𐑰𐑯 𐑞 𐑑𐑵, 𐑩 𐑒𐑤𐑴𐑕 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑥𐑩𐑕𐑦 𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑤𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑕; 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑞𐑺𐑓𐑹 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑥𐑰𐑑, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕 𐑢𐑰 𐑕𐑧𐑑 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑣𐑵 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛'𐑟 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑽𐑟 𐑢𐑻, 𐑯 𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑟𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑰𐑗 𐑝 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑪𐑙𐑛.

𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑝 𐑷𐑤 𐑢𐑪𐑟 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜, 𐑣𐑵𐑥 ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒, 𐑞 𐑗𐑰𐑓 𐑥𐑱𐑑, 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑕𐑦𐑤𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑓 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑒𐑢𐑲𐑼. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜 𐑦𐑟 𐑷𐑤𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑦 𐑯𐑴𐑯.

𐑯𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 ·𐑑𐑨𐑖𐑑𐑱𐑜𐑴, 𐑩𐑯 𐑳𐑯𐑥𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑑 ·𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑾𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 ·𐑜𐑱 ·𐑣𐑧𐑛, 𐑞 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑢𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑦 𐑝 ·𐑥𐑸𐑔𐑩'𐑟 ·𐑝𐑦𐑯𐑘𐑼𐑛, 𐑢𐑺 𐑞𐑺 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑦𐑜𐑟𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑕 𐑞 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑮𐑧𐑥𐑯𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑩 𐑝𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑡 𐑝 𐑮𐑧𐑛 𐑥𐑧𐑯, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑕𐑩𐑐𐑤𐑲𐑛 𐑞 𐑯𐑱𐑚𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑝 ·𐑯𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑝 𐑣𐑻 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑛𐑺𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑽𐑟. 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑼𐑦, 𐑞𐑱 𐑿𐑠𐑵𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑜𐑴 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑡𐑦𐑯𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑒 𐑯𐑱𐑥 𐑝 ·𐑜𐑱-·𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑼𐑟. ·𐑑𐑨𐑖𐑑𐑱𐑜𐑴'𐑟 𐑤𐑪𐑙, 𐑤𐑰𐑯, 𐑕𐑱𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑣𐑺, 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑲 𐑗𐑰𐑒 𐑚𐑴𐑯𐑟, 𐑯 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑒 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑲𐑟—𐑓 𐑩𐑯 ·𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑾𐑯, ·𐑹𐑦𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑤𐑸𐑡𐑯𐑩𐑕, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 ·𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑸𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑜𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑯—𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑕𐑩𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑮𐑴𐑒𐑤𐑱𐑥𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑣𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑼 𐑝 𐑞 𐑳𐑯𐑝𐑦𐑖𐑦𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑤𐑳𐑛 𐑝 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑐𐑮𐑬𐑛 𐑢𐑹𐑽 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑟, 𐑣𐑵, 𐑦𐑯 𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 ·𐑯𐑿 ·𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑥𐑵𐑕, 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑕𐑒𐑬𐑼𐑛, 𐑚𐑴 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛, 𐑞 𐑨𐑚𐑼𐑦𐑡𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑓𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑥𐑱𐑯. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑯𐑴 𐑤𐑪𐑙𐑜𐑼 𐑕𐑯𐑳𐑓𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑤 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑲𐑤𐑛 𐑚𐑰𐑕𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑫𐑛𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛, ·𐑑𐑨𐑖𐑑𐑱𐑜𐑴 𐑯𐑬 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑒 𐑝 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑰; 𐑞 𐑳𐑯𐑻𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑯 𐑓𐑦𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑓𐑨𐑤𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑨𐑮𐑴 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑲𐑼𐑟. 𐑑 𐑤𐑫𐑒 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑑𐑷𐑯𐑦 𐑚𐑮𐑷𐑯 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑤𐑲𐑞 𐑕𐑯𐑱𐑒𐑦 𐑤𐑦𐑥𐑟, 𐑿 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑒𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑞 𐑕𐑵𐑐𐑼𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑝 𐑞 𐑻𐑤𐑽 ·𐑐𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑟, 𐑯 𐑣𐑭𐑓-𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑰𐑝𐑛 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑲𐑤𐑛 ·𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑾𐑯 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑩 𐑕𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑯𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑬𐑼𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑺. ·𐑑𐑨𐑖𐑑𐑱𐑜𐑴 𐑢𐑪𐑟 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚 𐑞 𐑕𐑧𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑥𐑱𐑑'𐑕 𐑕𐑒𐑢𐑲𐑼.

𐑔𐑻𐑛 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑞 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑽𐑟 𐑢𐑪𐑟 ·𐑛𐑨𐑜𐑵, 𐑩 𐑡𐑲𐑜𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑒, 𐑒𐑴𐑤-𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑒 𐑯𐑰𐑜𐑮𐑴-𐑕𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑡, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑤𐑲𐑩𐑯-𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑑𐑮𐑧𐑛—𐑩𐑯 ·𐑩𐑙𐑨𐑕𐑻𐑩𐑕 𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛. 𐑕𐑩𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑽𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑑𐑵 𐑜𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑩𐑯 𐑣𐑵𐑐𐑕, 𐑕𐑴 𐑤𐑸𐑡 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑼𐑟 𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑛 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑮𐑦𐑙-𐑚𐑴𐑤𐑑𐑕, 𐑯 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑑𐑷𐑒 𐑝 𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑑𐑪𐑐-𐑕𐑱𐑤 𐑣𐑨𐑤𐑘𐑼𐑛𐑟 𐑑 𐑞𐑧𐑥. 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑿𐑔 ·𐑛𐑨𐑜𐑵 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑝𐑪𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑺𐑦𐑤𐑦 𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑑 𐑪𐑯 𐑚𐑹𐑛 𐑝 𐑩 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑼, 𐑤𐑲𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑤𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑱 𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑱𐑑𐑦𐑝 𐑒𐑴𐑕𐑑. 𐑯 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑣𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑧𐑯𐑦𐑢𐑺 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑯 ·𐑨𐑓𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑩, ·𐑯𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑑, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑐𐑱𐑜𐑩𐑯 𐑣𐑸𐑚𐑼𐑟 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑥𐑧𐑯; 𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑯𐑬 𐑤𐑧𐑛 𐑓 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑘𐑽𐑟 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑤𐑲𐑓 𐑝 𐑞 𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑼𐑦 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑕 𐑝 𐑴𐑯𐑼𐑟 𐑳𐑯𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑣𐑰𐑛𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑥𐑨𐑯𐑼 𐑝 𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑞𐑱 𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑑; ·𐑛𐑨𐑜𐑵 𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑱𐑯𐑛 𐑷𐑤 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑸𐑚𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑒 𐑝𐑻𐑗𐑵𐑟, 𐑯 𐑦𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑩 𐑡𐑦𐑮𐑭𐑓, 𐑥𐑵𐑝𐑛 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑒𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑐𐑪𐑥𐑐 𐑝 𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑕 𐑓𐑰𐑑 𐑓𐑲𐑝 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑪𐑒𐑕. 𐑞𐑺 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩 𐑒𐑹𐑐𐑹𐑾𐑤 𐑣𐑿𐑥𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑦𐑯 𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑳𐑐 𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥; 𐑯 𐑩 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑩 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑓𐑤𐑨𐑜 𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑑 𐑚𐑧𐑜 𐑑𐑮𐑵𐑕 𐑝 𐑩 𐑓𐑹𐑑𐑮𐑩𐑕. 𐑒𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑾𐑕 𐑑 𐑑𐑧𐑤, 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑽𐑾𐑤 𐑯𐑰𐑜𐑮𐑴, ·𐑩𐑙𐑨𐑕𐑻𐑩𐑕 ·𐑛𐑨𐑜𐑵, 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑒𐑢𐑲𐑼 𐑝 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 ·𐑓𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑒, 𐑣𐑵 𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑑 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑗𐑧𐑕-𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑚𐑦𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥. 𐑨𐑟 𐑓 𐑞 𐑮𐑧𐑟𐑦𐑛𐑿 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛'𐑟 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑦, 𐑚𐑰 𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑧𐑛, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑛𐑱 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑑𐑵 𐑝 𐑞 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑔𐑬𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑞 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑶𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑩𐑥𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑼𐑦, 𐑸 ·𐑩𐑥𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑚𐑹𐑯, 𐑞𐑴 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑯𐑽𐑤𐑦 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑪𐑓𐑦𐑕𐑼𐑟 𐑸. 𐑣𐑽𐑦𐑯 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 ·𐑩𐑥𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑼𐑦 𐑨𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 ·𐑩𐑥𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑸𐑥𐑦 𐑯 𐑥𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑺𐑦 𐑯 𐑥𐑻𐑗𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑯𐑱𐑝𐑦𐑟, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑧𐑯𐑡𐑦𐑯𐑽𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑹𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑶𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑩𐑥𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑯 ·𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑨𐑤𐑟 𐑯 ·𐑮𐑱𐑤𐑮𐑴𐑛𐑟. 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥, 𐑲 𐑕𐑱, 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑪𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑒𐑱𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑞 𐑯𐑱𐑑𐑦𐑝 ·𐑩𐑥𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑤𐑦𐑚𐑼𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑝𐑲𐑛𐑟 𐑞 𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑟, 𐑞 𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛 𐑨𐑟 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑩𐑐𐑤𐑲𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑩𐑤𐑟. 𐑯𐑴 𐑕𐑥𐑷𐑤 𐑯𐑳𐑥𐑚𐑼 𐑝 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑩𐑟𐑹𐑟, 𐑢𐑺 𐑞 𐑬𐑑𐑢𐑼𐑛 𐑚𐑬𐑯𐑛 ·𐑯𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑼𐑟 𐑓𐑮𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑑𐑳𐑗 𐑑 𐑷𐑜𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑒𐑮𐑵𐑟 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑣𐑸𐑛𐑦 𐑐𐑧𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑮𐑪𐑒𐑦 𐑖𐑹𐑟. 𐑦𐑯 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑥𐑨𐑯𐑼, 𐑞 ·𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑯𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑼𐑟 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 ·𐑣𐑳𐑤 𐑹 ·𐑤𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑯, 𐑐𐑫𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑖𐑧𐑑𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛 ·𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛𐑟, 𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑰𐑝 𐑞 𐑓𐑫𐑤 𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑦𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑞𐑺 𐑒𐑮𐑵. 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑐𐑨𐑕𐑦𐑡 𐑣𐑴𐑥𐑢𐑼𐑛𐑟, 𐑞𐑱 𐑛𐑮𐑪𐑐 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑞𐑺 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯. 𐑣𐑬 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟, 𐑞𐑺 𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑴 𐑑𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑙, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 ·𐑲𐑕𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑟 𐑕𐑰𐑥 𐑑 𐑥𐑱𐑒 𐑞 𐑚𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑥𐑧𐑯. 𐑞𐑱 𐑢𐑻 𐑯𐑽𐑤𐑦 𐑷𐑤 ·𐑲𐑕𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛, ·𐑲𐑕𐑩𐑤𐑱𐑑𐑴𐑟 𐑑𐑵, 𐑲 𐑒𐑷𐑤 𐑕𐑳𐑗, 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑩𐑒𐑯𐑪𐑤𐑦𐑡𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑥𐑧𐑯, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑰𐑗 ·𐑲𐑕𐑩𐑤𐑱𐑑𐑴 𐑤𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑪𐑯 𐑩 𐑕𐑧𐑐𐑼𐑩𐑑 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑴𐑯. 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑯𐑬, 𐑓𐑧𐑛𐑼𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑒𐑰𐑤, 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑩 𐑕𐑧𐑑 𐑞𐑰𐑟 ·𐑲𐑕𐑩𐑤𐑱𐑑𐑴𐑟 𐑢𐑻! 𐑩𐑯 ·𐑨𐑯𐑩𐑗𐑸𐑟𐑦𐑕 ·𐑒𐑤𐑴𐑪𐑑𐑕 𐑛𐑧𐑐𐑿𐑑𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑲𐑤𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑰, 𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑻𐑔, 𐑩𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑦𐑙 ·𐑴𐑤𐑛 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛 𐑑 𐑤𐑱 𐑞 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛'𐑟 𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑚𐑸 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑝 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑚𐑨𐑒. 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑒 ·𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 ·𐑐𐑦𐑐—𐑣𐑰 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑛𐑦𐑛—𐑴, 𐑯𐑴! 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹. 𐑐𐑫𐑼 ·𐑨𐑤𐑩𐑚𐑨𐑥𐑩 𐑚𐑶! 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑦𐑥 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛'𐑟 𐑓𐑴𐑒𐑕𐑩𐑤, 𐑘𐑰 𐑖𐑨𐑤 𐑺 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑕𐑰 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑚𐑰𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑑𐑨𐑥𐑚𐑼𐑰𐑯; 𐑐𐑮𐑰𐑤𐑿𐑟𐑦𐑝 𐑝 𐑞 𐑦𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑑𐑲𐑥, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑓, 𐑑 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑒𐑢𐑹𐑑𐑼-𐑛𐑧𐑒 𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑲, 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑚𐑦𐑛 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑒 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑩𐑤𐑟, 𐑯 𐑚𐑰𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑑𐑨𐑥𐑚𐑼𐑰𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑜𐑤𐑹𐑦; 𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑛 𐑩 𐑒𐑬𐑼𐑛 𐑣𐑽, 𐑣𐑱𐑤𐑛 𐑩 𐑣𐑽𐑴 𐑞𐑺!

·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 28. 𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚.

𐑓 𐑕𐑧𐑝𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑛𐑱𐑟 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑤𐑰𐑝𐑦𐑙 ·𐑯𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑑, 𐑯𐑳𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑚𐑳𐑝 𐑣𐑨𐑗𐑩𐑟 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑰𐑯 𐑝 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚. 𐑞 𐑥𐑱𐑑𐑕 𐑮𐑧𐑜𐑿𐑤𐑼𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑦𐑤𐑰𐑝𐑛 𐑰𐑗 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑢𐑪𐑗𐑩𐑟, 𐑯 𐑓 𐑷𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑚𐑰 𐑕𐑰𐑯 𐑑 𐑞 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑺𐑦, 𐑞𐑱 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑞 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑭𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐; 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑞𐑱 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑦𐑖𐑿𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑒𐑨𐑚𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑹𐑛𐑼𐑟 𐑕𐑴 𐑕𐑳𐑛𐑩𐑯 𐑯 𐑐𐑼𐑧𐑥𐑐𐑑𐑼𐑦, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑷𐑤 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑯 𐑞𐑱 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑭𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑝𐑦𐑒𐑺𐑾𐑕𐑤𐑦. 𐑘𐑧𐑕, 𐑞𐑺 𐑕𐑵𐑐𐑮𐑰𐑥 𐑤𐑹𐑛 𐑯 𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑑𐑱𐑑𐑼 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞𐑺, 𐑞𐑴 𐑣𐑦𐑞𐑼𐑑𐑵 𐑳𐑯𐑕𐑰𐑯 𐑚𐑲 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑲𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑐𐑼𐑥𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑑 𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑯𐑬 𐑕𐑱𐑒𐑮𐑩𐑛 𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑮𐑰𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑒𐑨𐑚𐑦𐑯.

𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑲 𐑩𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑑 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑒 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑥𐑲 𐑢𐑪𐑗𐑩𐑟 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑴, 𐑲 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑜𐑱𐑟𐑛 𐑭𐑓𐑑 𐑑 𐑥𐑸𐑒 𐑦𐑓 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡 𐑓𐑱𐑕 𐑢𐑻 𐑝𐑦𐑟𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤; 𐑓 𐑥𐑲 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑝𐑱𐑜 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑢𐑲𐑩𐑑𐑵𐑛 𐑑𐑳𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑳𐑯𐑯𐑴𐑯 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯, 𐑯𐑬 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑵𐑠𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑰, 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑱𐑥 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑩 𐑐𐑻𐑑𐑼𐑚𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯. 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑤𐑦 𐑣𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑨𐑑 𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑮𐑨𐑜𐑩𐑛 ·𐑦𐑤𐑲𐑡𐑩'𐑟 𐑛𐑲𐑩𐑚𐑪𐑤𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑴𐑣𐑽𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑳𐑯𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑳𐑮𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑥𐑰, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑕𐑳𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑧𐑯𐑼𐑡𐑦 𐑲 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑰𐑝𐑛 𐑝. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑐𐑫𐑼𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑲 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑞𐑧𐑥, 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑥𐑵𐑛𐑟 𐑲 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑦 𐑑 𐑕𐑥𐑲𐑤 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑪𐑤𐑩𐑥 𐑢𐑦𐑥𐑟𐑦𐑒𐑨𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑟 𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑬𐑑𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑖 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑓𐑩𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑹𐑝𐑟. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑑𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑝 𐑨𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑣𐑧𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑝𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑹 𐑳𐑯𐑰𐑟𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑕—𐑑 𐑒𐑷𐑤 𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑴—𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑲 𐑓𐑧𐑤𐑑, 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑲 𐑒𐑱𐑥 𐑑 𐑤𐑫𐑒 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑥𐑰 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐, 𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑢𐑪𐑮𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑦 𐑑 𐑗𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑖 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑦𐑥𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟. 𐑓 𐑞𐑴 𐑞 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑽𐑟, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦 𐑝 𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑵, 𐑢𐑻 𐑩 𐑓𐑸 𐑥𐑹 𐑚𐑸𐑚𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑒, 𐑣𐑰𐑞𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑖, 𐑯 𐑥𐑪𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑧𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑝 𐑞 𐑑𐑱𐑥 𐑥𐑻𐑗𐑩𐑯𐑑-𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑥𐑲 𐑐𐑮𐑰𐑝𐑾𐑕 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑽𐑾𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑥𐑰 𐑩𐑒𐑢𐑱𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞, 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑲 𐑩𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑚𐑛 𐑞𐑦𐑕—𐑯 𐑮𐑲𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑩𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑚𐑛 𐑦𐑑—𐑑 𐑞 𐑓𐑽𐑕 𐑿𐑯𐑰𐑒𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑯𐑱𐑗𐑼 𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑲𐑤𐑛 ·𐑕𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑯𐑱𐑝𐑾𐑯 𐑝𐑴𐑒𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑕𐑴 𐑩𐑚𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑥𐑚𐑸𐑒𐑑. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑞 𐑨𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑗𐑰𐑓 𐑪𐑓𐑦𐑕𐑼𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐, 𐑞 𐑥𐑱𐑑𐑕, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑓𐑹𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑨𐑤𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑑 𐑩𐑤𐑱 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑒𐑳𐑤𐑼𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑜𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑙𐑟, 𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑿𐑕 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑓𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑯 𐑗𐑽𐑓𐑩𐑤𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑟𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑝𐑶𐑦𐑡. 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑚𐑧𐑑𐑼, 𐑥𐑹 𐑤𐑲𐑒𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑰-𐑪𐑓𐑦𐑕𐑼𐑟 𐑯 𐑥𐑧𐑯, 𐑰𐑗 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑴𐑯 𐑛𐑦𐑓𐑼𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑢𐑱, 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑰 𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛, 𐑯 𐑞𐑱 𐑢𐑻 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑞𐑧𐑥 ·𐑩𐑥𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑟; 𐑩 ·𐑯𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑑𐑼, 𐑩 ·𐑝𐑦𐑯𐑘𐑼𐑛𐑼, 𐑩 ·𐑒𐑱𐑐 𐑥𐑨𐑯. 𐑯𐑬, 𐑦𐑑 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 ·𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑥𐑩𐑕 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑖𐑪𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑬𐑑 𐑣𐑻 𐑣𐑸𐑚𐑼, 𐑓 𐑩 𐑕𐑐𐑱𐑕 𐑢𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑲𐑑𐑦𐑙 ·𐑐𐑴𐑤𐑼 𐑢𐑧𐑞𐑼, 𐑞𐑴 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑮𐑳𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑢𐑱 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑦𐑑 𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑬𐑔𐑢𐑼𐑛; 𐑯 𐑚𐑲 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑛𐑦𐑜𐑮𐑰 𐑯 𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑑 𐑝 𐑤𐑨𐑑𐑦𐑑𐑿𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑢𐑰 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑛, 𐑜𐑮𐑨𐑡𐑵𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑤𐑰𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑻𐑕𐑦𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼, 𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑪𐑤𐑼𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑚𐑦𐑣𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑳𐑕. 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑤𐑧𐑕 𐑤𐑴𐑼𐑦𐑙, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑜𐑮𐑱 𐑯 𐑜𐑤𐑵𐑥𐑦 𐑦𐑯𐑳𐑓 𐑥𐑹𐑯𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑟𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑓𐑺 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑮𐑳𐑖𐑦𐑙 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑞 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑝𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑝 𐑕𐑹𐑑 𐑝 𐑤𐑰𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑯 𐑥𐑧𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑒𐑪𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑩𐑐𐑦𐑛𐑦𐑑𐑦, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑲 𐑥𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑑 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑒 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑒𐑷𐑤 𐑝 𐑞 𐑓𐑹𐑯𐑵𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑗, 𐑕𐑴 𐑕𐑵𐑯 𐑨𐑟 𐑲 𐑤𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑥𐑲 𐑜𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑕 𐑑𐑩𐑢𐑹𐑛𐑟 𐑞 𐑑𐑨𐑓𐑮𐑱𐑤, 𐑓𐑹𐑚𐑴𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑖𐑦𐑝𐑼𐑟 𐑮𐑨𐑯 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑥𐑰. 𐑮𐑦𐑨𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑬𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑯 𐑨𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑣𐑧𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑯; ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑕𐑑𐑫𐑛 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑢𐑹𐑑𐑼-𐑛𐑧𐑒.

𐑞𐑺 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑯𐑴 𐑕𐑲𐑯 𐑝 𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑤𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑯𐑹 𐑝 𐑞 𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑳𐑝𐑼𐑦 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑧𐑯𐑦. 𐑣𐑰 𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑑 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑒𐑳𐑑 𐑩𐑢𐑱 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑒, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑲𐑼 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑴𐑝𐑼𐑮𐑳𐑯𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑢𐑱𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑤𐑦𐑥𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑿𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑧𐑥, 𐑹 𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑢𐑱 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑐𐑸𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞𐑺 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑨𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑱𐑡𐑛 𐑮𐑴𐑚𐑳𐑕𐑑𐑯𐑩𐑕. 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑴𐑤 𐑣𐑲, 𐑚𐑮𐑷𐑛 𐑓𐑹𐑥, 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑝 𐑕𐑪𐑤𐑦𐑛 𐑚𐑮𐑪𐑯𐑟, 𐑯 𐑖𐑱𐑐𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑩𐑯 𐑳𐑯𐑷𐑤𐑑𐑼𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑥𐑴𐑤𐑛, 𐑤𐑲𐑒 ·𐑗𐑧𐑤𐑰𐑯𐑦'𐑟 𐑒𐑭𐑕𐑑 ·𐑐𐑻𐑕𐑾𐑕. 𐑔𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑢𐑱 𐑬𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑜𐑮𐑱 𐑣𐑺𐑟, 𐑯 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑿𐑦𐑙 𐑮𐑲𐑑 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑑𐑷𐑯𐑦 𐑕𐑒𐑹𐑗𐑑 𐑓𐑱𐑕 𐑯 𐑯𐑧𐑒, 𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑦𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑩𐑐𐑽𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑤𐑴𐑞𐑦𐑙, 𐑿 𐑕𐑷 𐑩 𐑕𐑤𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑮𐑪𐑛-𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑥𐑸𐑒, 𐑤𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑢𐑲𐑑𐑦𐑖. 𐑦𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑧𐑥𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑐𐑻𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑼 𐑕𐑰𐑥 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑑, 𐑤𐑪𐑓𐑑𐑦 𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑙𐑒 𐑝 𐑩 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑑𐑮𐑰, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑞 𐑳𐑐𐑼 𐑤𐑲𐑑𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑑𐑺𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑸𐑑𐑕 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑦𐑑, 𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑 𐑮𐑧𐑯𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑕𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑩𐑤 𐑑𐑢𐑦𐑜, 𐑐𐑰𐑤𐑟 𐑯 𐑜𐑮𐑵𐑝𐑟 𐑬𐑑 𐑞 𐑚𐑸𐑒 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑑𐑪𐑐 𐑑 𐑚𐑪𐑑𐑩𐑥, 𐑺 𐑮𐑳𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑪𐑓 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑕𐑶𐑤, 𐑤𐑰𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑑𐑮𐑰 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑩𐑤𐑲𐑝, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑚𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛. 𐑢𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑸𐑒 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑚𐑹𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑹 𐑢𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞 𐑕𐑒𐑸 𐑤𐑧𐑓𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑛𐑧𐑕𐑐𐑼𐑩𐑑 𐑢𐑵𐑯𐑛, 𐑯𐑴 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑱. 𐑚𐑲 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑑𐑨𐑕𐑦𐑑 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑑, 𐑔𐑮𐑵𐑬𐑑 𐑞 𐑝𐑶𐑦𐑡 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑹 𐑯𐑴 𐑩𐑤𐑵𐑠𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑑 𐑦𐑑, 𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑥𐑱𐑑𐑕. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑕 ·𐑑𐑨𐑖𐑑𐑱𐑜𐑴'𐑟 𐑕𐑰𐑯𐑽, 𐑩𐑯 𐑴𐑤𐑛 ·𐑜𐑱-·𐑣𐑧𐑛 ·𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑾𐑯 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑵, 𐑕𐑵𐑐𐑼𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑩𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑓𐑫𐑤 𐑓𐑹𐑑𐑦 𐑘𐑽𐑟 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑛𐑦𐑛 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑱 𐑚𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛, 𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑦𐑑 𐑒𐑱𐑥 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑦 𐑝 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑥𐑹𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑓𐑮𐑱, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑩𐑯 𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑓 𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑰. 𐑘𐑧𐑑, 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑲𐑤𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑯𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑓𐑼𐑧𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑯𐑧𐑜𐑩𐑑𐑦𐑝𐑛, 𐑚𐑲 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑩 𐑜𐑮𐑱 ·𐑥𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑕𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑯𐑿𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛, 𐑩𐑯 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑕𐑧𐑐𐑩𐑤𐑒𐑮𐑩𐑤 𐑥𐑨𐑯, 𐑣𐑵, 𐑣𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑛 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 ·𐑯𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑑, 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑺 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑤𐑱𐑛 𐑲 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑢𐑲𐑤𐑛 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚. 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼𐑞𐑩𐑤𐑧𐑕, 𐑞 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑕𐑰-𐑑𐑮𐑩𐑛𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟, 𐑞 𐑦𐑥𐑩𐑥𐑹𐑾𐑤 𐑒𐑮𐑧𐑡𐑵𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑟, 𐑐𐑪𐑐𐑿𐑤𐑼𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑴𐑤𐑛 ·𐑥𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑕𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑰𐑑𐑼𐑯𐑨𐑗𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑐𐑬𐑼𐑟 𐑝 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑻𐑯𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑. 𐑕𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑯𐑴 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑼 𐑕𐑽𐑾𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑩𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑓 𐑧𐑝𐑼 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑚𐑰 𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑤𐑦 𐑤𐑱𐑛 𐑬𐑑—𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑣𐑸𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑑 𐑐𐑭𐑕, 𐑕𐑴 𐑣𐑰 𐑥𐑳𐑑𐑼𐑛—𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑣𐑵𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑛𐑵 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑪𐑓𐑦𐑕 𐑓 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑛, 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑓𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑩 𐑚𐑻𐑔-𐑥𐑸𐑒 𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑒𐑮𐑬𐑯 𐑑 𐑕𐑴𐑤.

𐑕𐑴 𐑐𐑬𐑼𐑓𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑞 𐑣𐑴𐑤 𐑜𐑮𐑦𐑥 𐑨𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑 𐑝 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑩𐑓𐑧𐑒𐑑 𐑥𐑰, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑤𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑛 𐑚𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑰𐑒𐑑 𐑦𐑑, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑓 𐑞 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑓𐑿 𐑥𐑴𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑲 𐑣𐑸𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑯𐑴𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑩 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑴𐑝𐑼𐑚𐑺𐑦𐑙 𐑜𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑞 𐑚𐑸𐑚𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑒 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑤𐑧𐑜 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑣𐑰 𐑐𐑸𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑑𐑫𐑛. 𐑦𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑐𐑮𐑰𐑝𐑾𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑑 𐑥𐑰 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑲𐑝𐑼𐑦 𐑤𐑧𐑜 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑰 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑓𐑨𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑐𐑪𐑤𐑦𐑖𐑑 𐑚𐑴𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 𐑢𐑱𐑤'𐑟 𐑡𐑷. “𐑲, 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑪𐑓 ·𐑡𐑩𐑐𐑨𐑯,” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑞 𐑴𐑤𐑛 ·𐑜𐑱-·𐑣𐑧𐑛 ·𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑾𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑕; “𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑒𐑮𐑭𐑓𐑑, 𐑣𐑰 𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑑 𐑩𐑯𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑴𐑥 𐑓 𐑦𐑑. 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑩 𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑝𐑼 𐑝 '𐑩𐑥.”

𐑲 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑒 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑕𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑿𐑤𐑼 𐑐𐑪𐑕𐑗𐑼 𐑣𐑰 𐑥𐑱𐑯𐑑𐑱𐑯𐑛. 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑰𐑗 𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛'𐑟 𐑒𐑢𐑹𐑑𐑼 𐑛𐑧𐑒, 𐑯 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑒𐑤𐑴𐑕 𐑑 𐑞 𐑥𐑦𐑟𐑩𐑯 𐑖𐑮𐑬𐑛𐑟, 𐑞𐑺 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩𐑯 𐑷𐑜𐑼 𐑣𐑴𐑤, 𐑚𐑹𐑛 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑣𐑭𐑓 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑗 𐑹 𐑕𐑴, 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑐𐑤𐑨𐑙𐑒. 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑴𐑯 𐑤𐑧𐑜 𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑴𐑤; 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑸𐑥 𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑝𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛, 𐑯 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑲 𐑩 𐑖𐑮𐑬𐑛; ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑕𐑑𐑫𐑛 𐑦𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑑, 𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑬𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑘𐑪𐑯𐑛 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐'𐑕 𐑧𐑝𐑼-𐑐𐑦𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑐𐑮𐑬. 𐑞𐑺 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑓𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑝 𐑓𐑻𐑥𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑓𐑹𐑑𐑦𐑑𐑿𐑛, 𐑩 𐑛𐑦𐑑𐑻𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑑, 𐑳𐑯𐑕𐑼𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑦𐑤𐑓𐑩𐑤𐑯𐑩𐑕, 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑑 𐑯 𐑓𐑽𐑤𐑩𐑕, 𐑓𐑹𐑢𐑼𐑛 𐑛𐑧𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑜𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑕. 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑩 𐑢𐑻𐑛 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑐𐑴𐑒; 𐑯𐑹 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑪𐑓𐑦𐑕𐑼𐑟 𐑕𐑱 𐑷𐑑 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥; 𐑞𐑴 𐑚𐑲 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑺 𐑥𐑲𐑯𐑿𐑑𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑡𐑧𐑕𐑗𐑼𐑟 𐑯 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟, 𐑞𐑱 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑖𐑴𐑛 𐑞 𐑳𐑯𐑰𐑟𐑦, 𐑦𐑓 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑐𐑱𐑯𐑓𐑩𐑤, 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑕𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑩 𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑼-𐑲. 𐑯 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑞𐑨𐑑, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑥𐑵𐑛𐑦 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑯 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑕𐑑𐑫𐑛 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑒𐑮𐑵𐑕𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑱𐑕; 𐑦𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑯𐑱𐑥𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑮𐑰𐑜𐑩𐑤 𐑴𐑝𐑼𐑚𐑺𐑦𐑙 𐑛𐑦𐑜𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑝 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑥𐑲𐑑𐑦 𐑢𐑴.

𐑺 𐑤𐑪𐑙, 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑝𐑦𐑟𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑺, 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑛𐑮𐑵 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑨𐑚𐑦𐑯. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑹𐑯𐑦𐑙, 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑛𐑱 𐑝𐑦𐑟𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑑 𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑵; 𐑲𐑞𐑼 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑦𐑝𐑩𐑑-𐑣𐑴𐑤, 𐑹 𐑕𐑰𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑩𐑯 𐑲𐑝𐑼𐑦 𐑕𐑑𐑵𐑤 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛; 𐑹 𐑣𐑧𐑝𐑦𐑤𐑦 𐑢𐑷𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑒. 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑕𐑒𐑲 𐑜𐑮𐑵 𐑤𐑧𐑕 𐑜𐑤𐑵𐑥𐑦; 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑰𐑛, 𐑚𐑦𐑜𐑨𐑯 𐑑 𐑜𐑮𐑴 𐑩 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑡𐑰𐑯𐑾𐑤, 𐑣𐑰 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑱𐑥 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑤𐑧𐑕 𐑯 𐑤𐑧𐑕 𐑩 𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑵𐑕; 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑓, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑣𐑴𐑥, 𐑯𐑳𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑦 𐑚𐑤𐑰𐑒𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑒𐑧𐑐𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑕𐑴 𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑵𐑛𐑩𐑛. 𐑯, 𐑚𐑲 𐑯 𐑚𐑲, 𐑦𐑑 𐑒𐑱𐑥 𐑑 𐑐𐑭𐑕, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑿𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑺; 𐑚𐑳𐑑, 𐑨𐑟 𐑘𐑧𐑑, 𐑓 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑧𐑛, 𐑹 𐑐𐑼𐑕𐑧𐑐𐑑𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑦𐑛, 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑯𐑦 𐑛𐑧𐑒, 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑨𐑟 𐑳𐑯𐑯𐑧𐑕𐑦𐑕𐑺𐑦 𐑞𐑺 𐑨𐑟 𐑩𐑯𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑥𐑱𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑐𐑨𐑕𐑦𐑡 𐑯𐑬; 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑮𐑧𐑜𐑿𐑤𐑼𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑮𐑵𐑟𐑦𐑙; 𐑯𐑽𐑤𐑦 𐑷𐑤 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑐𐑼𐑱𐑑𐑦𐑝𐑟 𐑯𐑰𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑵𐑐𐑼𐑝𐑦𐑠𐑩𐑯 𐑞 𐑥𐑱𐑑𐑕 𐑢𐑻 𐑓𐑫𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑐𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑑, 𐑕𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑹 𐑯𐑳𐑔𐑦𐑙, 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓, 𐑑 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑶 𐑹 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑲𐑑 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚, 𐑯𐑬; 𐑯 𐑞𐑳𐑕 𐑗𐑱𐑕 𐑩𐑢𐑱, 𐑓 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑝𐑩𐑤, 𐑞 𐑒𐑤𐑬𐑛𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑱𐑼 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑤𐑱𐑼 𐑢𐑻 𐑐𐑲𐑤𐑛 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑮𐑬, 𐑨𐑟 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑷𐑤 𐑒𐑤𐑬𐑛𐑟 𐑗𐑵𐑟 𐑞 𐑤𐑪𐑓𐑑𐑾𐑕𐑑 𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑕 𐑑 𐑐𐑲𐑤 𐑞𐑧𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑝𐑟 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯.

𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼𐑞𐑩𐑤𐑧𐑕, 𐑺 𐑤𐑪𐑙, 𐑞 𐑢𐑹𐑥, 𐑢𐑹𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑐𐑼𐑕𐑢𐑱𐑕𐑦𐑝𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑐𐑤𐑧𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑑, 𐑣𐑪𐑤𐑦𐑛𐑱 𐑢𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑢𐑰 𐑒𐑱𐑥 𐑑, 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑜𐑮𐑨𐑡𐑵𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑑 𐑗𐑸𐑥 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑵𐑛. 𐑓, 𐑨𐑟 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑞 𐑮𐑧𐑛-𐑗𐑰𐑒𐑑, 𐑛𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑜𐑻𐑤𐑟, 𐑱𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑤 𐑯 𐑥𐑱, 𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑐 𐑣𐑴𐑥 𐑑 𐑞 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑦, 𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑔𐑮𐑪𐑐𐑦𐑒 𐑢𐑫𐑛𐑟; 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑺𐑩𐑕𐑑, 𐑮𐑳𐑜𐑩𐑛𐑩𐑕𐑑, 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑔𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼-𐑒𐑤𐑴𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑴𐑒 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑰𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑓𐑹𐑔 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑓𐑿 𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑯 𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑬𐑑𐑕, 𐑑 𐑢𐑧𐑤𐑒𐑩𐑥 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑜𐑤𐑨𐑛-𐑣𐑸𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑝𐑦𐑟𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕; 𐑕𐑴 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑛𐑦𐑛, 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑧𐑯𐑛, 𐑩 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑪𐑯𐑛 𐑑 𐑞 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑩𐑤𐑫𐑼𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑜𐑻𐑤𐑦𐑖 𐑺. 𐑥𐑹 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑕 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑣𐑰 𐑐𐑫𐑑 𐑓𐑹𐑔 𐑞 𐑓𐑱𐑯𐑑 𐑚𐑤𐑪𐑕𐑩𐑥 𐑝 𐑩 𐑤𐑫𐑒, 𐑢𐑦𐑗, 𐑦𐑯 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑥𐑨𐑯, 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑕𐑵𐑯 𐑓𐑤𐑬𐑼𐑛 𐑬𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑕𐑥𐑲𐑤.

·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 29. 𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑼 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚; 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥, ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚.

𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑛𐑱𐑟 𐑦𐑤𐑨𐑐𐑕𐑑, 𐑯 𐑲𐑕 𐑯 𐑲𐑕𐑚𐑻𐑜𐑟 𐑷𐑤 𐑩𐑕𐑑𐑻𐑯, 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛 𐑯𐑬 𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑮𐑴𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑞 𐑚𐑮𐑲𐑑 ·𐑒𐑰𐑑𐑴 𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑙, 𐑢𐑦𐑗, 𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑰, 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑐𐑼𐑐𐑧𐑗𐑵𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑟 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑔𐑮𐑧𐑖𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑝 𐑞 𐑦𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑷𐑜𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑑𐑮𐑪𐑐𐑦𐑒. 𐑞 𐑢𐑹𐑥𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑵𐑤, 𐑒𐑤𐑽, 𐑮𐑦𐑙𐑦𐑙, 𐑐𐑼𐑓𐑿𐑥𐑛, 𐑴𐑝𐑼𐑓𐑤𐑴𐑦𐑙, 𐑮𐑦𐑛𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑛𐑱𐑟, 𐑢𐑻 𐑨𐑟 𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑜𐑪𐑚𐑤𐑩𐑑𐑕 𐑝 ·𐑐𐑻𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑖𐑻𐑚𐑩𐑑, 𐑣𐑰𐑐𐑑 𐑳𐑐—𐑓𐑤𐑱𐑒𐑑 𐑳𐑐, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑮𐑴𐑟-𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼 𐑕𐑯𐑴. 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑛 𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑯𐑲𐑑𐑕 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑣𐑷𐑑𐑦 𐑛𐑱𐑥𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑡𐑵𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑝𐑧𐑤𐑝𐑩𐑑𐑕, 𐑯𐑻𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑴𐑥 𐑦𐑯 𐑤𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑮𐑲𐑛, 𐑞 𐑥𐑧𐑥𐑼𐑦 𐑝 𐑞𐑺 𐑨𐑚𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑒𐑪𐑙𐑒𐑼𐑦𐑙 ·𐑻𐑤𐑟, 𐑞 𐑜𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑩𐑯 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑥𐑩𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑕𐑳𐑯𐑟! 𐑓 𐑕𐑤𐑰𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑨𐑯, '𐑑𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑣𐑸𐑛 𐑑 𐑗𐑵𐑟 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑢𐑰𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑥 𐑛𐑱𐑟 𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑿𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑯𐑲𐑑𐑕. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑢𐑦𐑗𐑼𐑦𐑟 𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑳𐑯𐑢𐑱𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑥𐑽𐑤𐑦 𐑤𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑯𐑿 𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑤𐑟 𐑯 𐑐𐑴𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑟 𐑑 𐑞 𐑬𐑑𐑢𐑼𐑛 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛. 𐑦𐑯𐑢𐑼𐑛 𐑞𐑱 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑛 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑴𐑤, 𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑥𐑲𐑤𐑛 𐑬𐑼𐑟 𐑝 𐑰𐑝 𐑒𐑱𐑥 𐑪𐑯; 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑥𐑧𐑥𐑼𐑦 𐑖𐑪𐑑 𐑣𐑻 𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑒𐑤𐑽 𐑲𐑕 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑓𐑹𐑥𐑟 𐑝 𐑯𐑶𐑟𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑑𐑢𐑲𐑤𐑲𐑑𐑕. 𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑕𐑳𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑱𐑡𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑟, 𐑥𐑹 𐑯 𐑥𐑹 𐑞𐑱 𐑮𐑷𐑑 𐑪𐑯 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚'𐑟 𐑑𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑗𐑼.

𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑱𐑡 𐑦𐑟 𐑷𐑤𐑢𐑱𐑟 𐑢𐑱𐑒𐑓𐑩𐑤; 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑓, 𐑞 𐑤𐑪𐑙𐑜𐑼 𐑤𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑤𐑲𐑓, 𐑞 𐑤𐑧𐑕 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑕 𐑑 𐑛𐑵 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑷𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑕 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑛𐑧𐑔. 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑕𐑰-𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑭𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑟, 𐑞 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑚𐑽𐑛𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑪𐑓𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑤𐑰𐑝 𐑞𐑺 𐑚𐑻𐑔𐑕 𐑑 𐑝𐑦𐑟𐑦𐑑 𐑞 𐑯𐑲𐑑-𐑒𐑤𐑴𐑒𐑑 𐑛𐑧𐑒. 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑴 𐑢𐑦𐑞 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚; 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑯𐑬, 𐑝 𐑤𐑱𐑑, 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑕𐑴 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑑 𐑤𐑦𐑝 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑴𐑐𐑩𐑯 𐑺, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑑𐑮𐑵𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑦𐑙, 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑝𐑦𐑟𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑢𐑻 𐑥𐑹 𐑑 𐑞 𐑒𐑨𐑚𐑦𐑯, 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑒𐑨𐑚𐑦𐑯 𐑑 𐑞 𐑐𐑤𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑕. “𐑦𐑑 𐑓𐑰𐑤𐑟 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑜𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑢𐑳𐑯'𐑟 𐑑𐑵𐑥,”—𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑥𐑳𐑑𐑼 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓—“𐑓 𐑩𐑯 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑥𐑰 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑯𐑼𐑴 𐑕𐑒𐑳𐑑𐑩𐑤, 𐑑 𐑜𐑴 𐑑 𐑥𐑲 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑝-𐑛𐑳𐑜 𐑚𐑻𐑔.”

𐑕𐑴, 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑑𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑦-𐑓𐑹 𐑬𐑼𐑟, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑪𐑗𐑩𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑯𐑲𐑑 𐑢𐑻 𐑕𐑧𐑑, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑪𐑯 𐑛𐑧𐑒 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑞 𐑕𐑤𐑳𐑥𐑚𐑼𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑚𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑴; 𐑯 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑦𐑓 𐑩 𐑮𐑴𐑐 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑣𐑷𐑤𐑛 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑴𐑒𐑕𐑩𐑤, 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑼𐑟 𐑓𐑤𐑳𐑙 𐑦𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑮𐑵𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑬𐑯, 𐑨𐑟 𐑚𐑲 𐑛𐑱, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑒𐑷𐑖𐑩𐑕𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑛𐑮𐑪𐑐𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑑 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕 𐑓 𐑓𐑽 𐑝 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑻𐑚𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑺 𐑕𐑤𐑳𐑥𐑚𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑥𐑱𐑑𐑕; 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑕𐑹𐑑 𐑝 𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑛𐑦 𐑒𐑢𐑲𐑩𐑑𐑵𐑛 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑚𐑦𐑜𐑦𐑯 𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑝𐑱𐑤, 𐑣𐑩𐑚𐑦𐑗𐑵𐑩𐑤𐑦, 𐑞 𐑕𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑽𐑟𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑢𐑪𐑗 𐑞 𐑒𐑨𐑚𐑦𐑯-𐑕𐑒𐑳𐑑𐑩𐑤; 𐑯 𐑺 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑞 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑦𐑥𐑻𐑡, 𐑜𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑲𐑼𐑯 𐑚𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑼, 𐑑 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑐 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑢𐑱. 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑑𐑳𐑗 𐑝 𐑣𐑿𐑥𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥; 𐑓 𐑨𐑑 𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑞𐑰𐑟, 𐑣𐑰 𐑿𐑠𐑵𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑩𐑚𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑯𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑐𐑩𐑑𐑮𐑴𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑒𐑢𐑹𐑑𐑼-𐑛𐑧𐑒; 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑪𐑟 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑽𐑦𐑛 𐑥𐑱𐑑𐑕, 𐑕𐑰𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑴𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑕 𐑦𐑯𐑗𐑩𐑟 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑲𐑝𐑼𐑦 𐑣𐑰𐑤, 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑞 𐑮𐑦𐑝𐑻𐑚𐑼𐑱𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑒𐑮𐑨𐑒 𐑯 𐑛𐑦𐑯 𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑚𐑴𐑯𐑦 𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑐, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑛𐑮𐑰𐑥𐑟 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑳𐑯𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑑𐑰𐑔 𐑝 𐑖𐑸𐑒𐑕. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑕, 𐑞 𐑥𐑵𐑛 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑑𐑵 𐑛𐑰𐑐 𐑓 𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑮𐑦𐑜𐑸𐑛𐑦𐑙𐑟; 𐑯 𐑨𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑧𐑝𐑦, 𐑤𐑳𐑥𐑚𐑼-𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑐𐑱𐑕 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑥𐑧𐑠𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑑𐑨𐑓𐑮𐑱𐑤 𐑑 𐑥𐑱𐑯𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑, ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚, 𐑞 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑕𐑧𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑥𐑱𐑑, 𐑒𐑱𐑥 𐑳𐑐 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑴, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑳𐑯𐑩𐑖𐑫𐑼𐑛, 𐑛𐑧𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑒𐑱𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑿𐑥𐑼𐑩𐑕𐑯𐑩𐑕, 𐑣𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑓 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑐𐑤𐑰𐑟𐑛 𐑑 𐑢𐑷𐑒 𐑞 𐑐𐑤𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑕, 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑯𐑴 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑕𐑱 𐑯𐑱; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑢𐑱 𐑝 𐑥𐑳𐑓𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑯𐑶𐑟; 𐑣𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑯 𐑣𐑧𐑟𐑦𐑑𐑱𐑑𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑩 𐑜𐑤𐑴𐑚 𐑝 𐑑𐑴, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑻𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑦𐑑, 𐑝 𐑞 𐑲𐑝𐑼𐑦 𐑣𐑰𐑤. 𐑭! 𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚, 𐑞𐑬 𐑛𐑦𐑛𐑕𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑯𐑴 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑞𐑧𐑯.

“𐑨𐑥 𐑲 𐑩 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑩𐑯-𐑚𐑷𐑤, ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚,” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚, “𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑬 𐑢𐑫𐑛𐑕𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑛 𐑥𐑰 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑓𐑨𐑖𐑩𐑯? 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑜𐑴 𐑞𐑲 𐑢𐑱𐑟; 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑓𐑼𐑜𐑪𐑑. 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑴 𐑑 𐑞𐑲 𐑯𐑲𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑝; 𐑢𐑺 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑨𐑟 𐑘𐑰 𐑕𐑤𐑰𐑐 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑢𐑰𐑯 𐑖𐑮𐑬𐑛𐑟, 𐑑 𐑿𐑟 𐑘𐑰 𐑑 𐑞 𐑓𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑.—𐑛𐑬𐑯, 𐑛𐑪𐑜, 𐑯 𐑒𐑧𐑯𐑩𐑤!”

𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑳𐑯𐑓𐑹𐑕𐑰𐑯 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑒𐑤𐑵𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑒𐑤𐑩𐑥𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑴 𐑕𐑳𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑒𐑹𐑯𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑥𐑨𐑯, ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑗𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑩 𐑥𐑴𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑; 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑛𐑤𐑦, “𐑲 𐑨𐑥 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑿𐑟𐑛 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑕𐑐𐑴𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑱, 𐑕𐑻; 𐑲 𐑛𐑵 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑤𐑧𐑕 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑣𐑭𐑓 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑦𐑑, 𐑕𐑻.”

“𐑩𐑝𐑭𐑕𐑑! 𐑜𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑛 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑢𐑰𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑧𐑑 𐑑𐑰𐑔, 𐑯 𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑥𐑵𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑢𐑱, 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑓 𐑑 𐑩𐑝𐑶𐑛 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑐𐑨𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑑 𐑑𐑧𐑥𐑐𐑑𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯.

“𐑯𐑴, 𐑕𐑻; 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑘𐑧𐑑,” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚, 𐑦𐑥𐑚𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑛, “𐑲 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑑𐑱𐑥𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑰 𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑛 𐑩 𐑛𐑪𐑜, 𐑕𐑻.”

“𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑚𐑰 𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑛 𐑑𐑧𐑯 𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑩 𐑛𐑪𐑙𐑒𐑦, 𐑯 𐑩 𐑥𐑿𐑤, 𐑯 𐑩𐑯 𐑨𐑕, 𐑯 𐑚𐑦𐑜𐑪𐑯, 𐑹 𐑲'𐑤 𐑒𐑤𐑽 𐑞 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛 𐑝 𐑞𐑰!”

𐑨𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑞𐑦𐑕, ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑩𐑛𐑝𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑴𐑝𐑼𐑚𐑺𐑦𐑙 𐑑𐑧𐑮𐑼𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑨𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑪𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑺𐑦𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑮𐑰𐑑𐑩𐑛.

“𐑲 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑕𐑻𐑝𐑛 𐑕𐑴 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑 𐑜𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑣𐑸𐑛 𐑚𐑤𐑴 𐑓 𐑦𐑑,” 𐑥𐑳𐑑𐑼𐑛 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚, 𐑨𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑒𐑨𐑚𐑦𐑯-𐑕𐑒𐑳𐑑𐑩𐑤. “𐑦𐑑'𐑕 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑒𐑢𐑽. 𐑕𐑑𐑪𐑐, ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚; 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑣𐑬, 𐑯𐑬, 𐑲 𐑛𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑢𐑧𐑤 𐑯𐑴 𐑢𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑑 𐑜𐑴 𐑚𐑨𐑒 𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑒 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑹—𐑢𐑪𐑑'𐑕 𐑞𐑨𐑑?—𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑣𐑽 𐑪𐑯 𐑥𐑲 𐑯𐑰𐑟 𐑯 𐑐𐑮𐑱 𐑓 𐑣𐑦𐑥? 𐑘𐑧𐑕, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞 𐑔𐑷𐑑 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑳𐑐 𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑰; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑚𐑰 𐑞 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑲 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑐𐑮𐑱. 𐑦𐑑'𐑕 𐑒𐑢𐑽; 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑒𐑢𐑽; 𐑯 𐑣𐑰'𐑟 𐑒𐑢𐑽 𐑑𐑵; 𐑲, 𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑓𐑹 𐑯 𐑭𐑓𐑑, 𐑣𐑰'𐑟 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑞 𐑒𐑢𐑽𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑥𐑨𐑯 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞. 𐑣𐑬 𐑣𐑰 𐑓𐑤𐑨𐑖𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑰!—𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑲𐑟 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑐𐑬𐑛𐑼-𐑐𐑨𐑯𐑟! 𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑥𐑨𐑛? 𐑧𐑯𐑦𐑢𐑱 𐑞𐑺'𐑟 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑲𐑯𐑛, 𐑨𐑟 𐑖𐑫𐑼 𐑨𐑟 𐑞𐑺 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑪𐑯 𐑩 𐑛𐑧𐑒 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑦𐑑 𐑒𐑮𐑨𐑒𐑕. 𐑣𐑰 𐑱𐑯𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑧𐑛 𐑯𐑬, 𐑲𐑞𐑼, 𐑥𐑹 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑬𐑼𐑟 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑑𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑦-𐑓𐑹; 𐑯 𐑣𐑰 𐑛𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑕𐑤𐑰𐑐 𐑞𐑧𐑯. 𐑛𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 ·𐑛𐑴-·𐑚𐑶, 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑿𐑼𐑛, 𐑑𐑧𐑤 𐑥𐑰 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑝 𐑩 𐑥𐑹𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑰 𐑷𐑤𐑢𐑱𐑟 𐑓𐑲𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑞 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑥𐑨𐑯'𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑥𐑩𐑒 𐑒𐑤𐑴𐑞𐑟 𐑷𐑤 𐑮𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑯 𐑑𐑳𐑥𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑛, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑖𐑰𐑑𐑕 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑓𐑫𐑑, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑒𐑳𐑝𐑼𐑤𐑦𐑛 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑑𐑲𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑯𐑪𐑑𐑕, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑐𐑦𐑤𐑴 𐑩 𐑕𐑹𐑑 𐑝 𐑓𐑮𐑲𐑑𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑣𐑪𐑑, 𐑨𐑟 𐑞𐑴 𐑩 𐑚𐑱𐑒𐑑 𐑚𐑮𐑦𐑒 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑪𐑯 𐑦𐑑? 𐑩 𐑣𐑪𐑑 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑥𐑨𐑯! 𐑲 𐑜𐑧𐑕 𐑣𐑰'𐑟 𐑜𐑪𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑓𐑴𐑒𐑕 𐑩𐑖𐑹 𐑒𐑷𐑤 𐑩 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑕; 𐑦𐑑'𐑕 𐑩 𐑒𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑝 ·𐑑𐑦𐑒-·𐑛𐑪𐑤𐑦-𐑮𐑴 𐑞𐑱 𐑕𐑱—𐑢𐑻𐑕 𐑯𐑹 𐑩 𐑑𐑵𐑔𐑱𐑒. 𐑢𐑧𐑤, 𐑢𐑧𐑤; 𐑲 𐑛𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑯𐑴 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑤𐑹𐑛 𐑒𐑰𐑐 𐑥𐑰 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑒𐑨𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑑. 𐑣𐑰'𐑟 𐑓𐑫𐑤 𐑝 𐑮𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑤𐑟; 𐑲 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑜𐑴𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑓, 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑯𐑲𐑑, 𐑨𐑟 ·𐑛𐑴-·𐑚𐑶 𐑑𐑧𐑤𐑟 𐑥𐑰 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑩𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑕; 𐑢𐑪𐑑'𐑕 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑓, 𐑲 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑑 𐑯𐑴? 𐑣𐑵'𐑟 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑩𐑐𐑶𐑯𐑑𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛? 𐑱𐑯𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑒𐑢𐑽, 𐑯𐑬? 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞𐑺'𐑟 𐑯𐑴 𐑑𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑙, 𐑦𐑑'𐑕 𐑞 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑜𐑱𐑥—·𐑣𐑽 𐑜𐑴𐑟 𐑓 𐑩 𐑕𐑯𐑵𐑟. 𐑛𐑨𐑥 𐑥𐑰, 𐑦𐑑'𐑕 𐑢𐑻𐑔 𐑩 𐑓𐑧𐑤𐑴'𐑟 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑚𐑹𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛, 𐑦𐑓 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑑 𐑓𐑷𐑤 𐑮𐑲𐑑 𐑩𐑕𐑤𐑰𐑐. 𐑯 𐑯𐑬 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑲 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒 𐑝 𐑦𐑑, 𐑞𐑨𐑑'𐑕 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑞 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑱𐑚𐑦𐑟 𐑛𐑵, 𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑'𐑕 𐑩 𐑕𐑹𐑑 𐑝 𐑒𐑢𐑽, 𐑑𐑵. 𐑛𐑨𐑥 𐑥𐑰, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑸 𐑒𐑢𐑽, 𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑑 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒 𐑝 '𐑩𐑥. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑'𐑕 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑥𐑲 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑐𐑩𐑤𐑟. 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒 𐑯𐑪𐑑, 𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑲 𐑦𐑤𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑯𐑔 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑭𐑯𐑛𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑; 𐑯 𐑕𐑤𐑰𐑐 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑿 𐑒𐑨𐑯, 𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑲 𐑑𐑢𐑧𐑤𐑓𐑔—𐑕𐑴 𐑣𐑽 𐑜𐑴𐑟 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑣𐑬'𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑? 𐑛𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑷𐑤 𐑥𐑰 𐑩 𐑛𐑪𐑜? 𐑚𐑤𐑱𐑟𐑩𐑟! 𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑛 𐑥𐑰 𐑑𐑧𐑯 𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑩 𐑛𐑪𐑙𐑒𐑦, 𐑯 𐑐𐑲𐑤𐑛 𐑩 𐑤𐑪𐑑 𐑝 𐑡𐑨𐑒𐑨𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑪𐑯 𐑑𐑪𐑐 𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑! 𐑣𐑰 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑢𐑧𐑤 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑒𐑦𐑒𐑑 𐑥𐑰, 𐑯 𐑛𐑳𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑦𐑑. 𐑥𐑱𐑚𐑰 𐑣𐑰 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑒𐑦𐑒 𐑥𐑰, 𐑯 𐑲 𐑛𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑩𐑚𐑟𐑻𐑝 𐑦𐑑, 𐑲 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑴 𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑩𐑚𐑨𐑒 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑮𐑬, 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑣𐑬. 𐑦𐑑 𐑓𐑤𐑨𐑖𐑑 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑚𐑤𐑰𐑗𐑑 𐑚𐑴𐑯. 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑤'𐑟 𐑞 𐑥𐑨𐑑𐑼 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑥𐑰? 𐑲 𐑛𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑮𐑲𐑑 𐑪𐑯 𐑥𐑲 𐑤𐑧𐑜𐑟. 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑓𐑬𐑤 𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑩 𐑕𐑹𐑑 𐑝 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑛 𐑥𐑰 𐑮𐑪𐑙 𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑬𐑑. 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 ·𐑤𐑹𐑛, 𐑲 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑛𐑮𐑰𐑥𐑦𐑙, 𐑞𐑴—𐑣𐑬? 𐑣𐑬? 𐑣𐑬?—𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑢𐑱'𐑟 𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑖 𐑦𐑑; 𐑕𐑴 𐑣𐑽 𐑜𐑴𐑟 𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑥𐑩𐑒 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯; 𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑥𐑹𐑯𐑦𐑙, 𐑲'𐑤 𐑕𐑰 𐑣𐑬 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑜𐑦 𐑡𐑳𐑜𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑕 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑚𐑲 𐑛𐑱𐑤𐑲𐑑.”

·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 30. 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑲𐑐.

𐑢𐑧𐑯 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑛𐑦𐑐𐑸𐑑𐑩𐑛, ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑕𐑑𐑫𐑛 𐑓 𐑩 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑤𐑰𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑞 𐑚𐑫𐑤𐑢𐑼𐑒𐑕; 𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑨𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑿𐑠𐑵𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑝 𐑤𐑱𐑑, 𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑼 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑪𐑗, 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑴 𐑓 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑲𐑝𐑼𐑦 𐑕𐑑𐑵𐑤, 𐑯 𐑷𐑤𐑕𐑴 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑲𐑐. 𐑤𐑲𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑐𐑲𐑐 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑚𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑤𐑨𐑥𐑐 𐑯 𐑐𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑵𐑤 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑝 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑒, 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑨𐑑 𐑯 𐑕𐑥𐑴𐑒𐑑.

𐑦𐑯 𐑴𐑤𐑛 ·𐑯𐑹𐑕 𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟, 𐑞 𐑔𐑮𐑴𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑰-𐑤𐑳𐑝𐑦𐑙 ·𐑛𐑱𐑯𐑦𐑖 𐑒𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑓𐑨𐑚𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛, 𐑕𐑧𐑔 𐑑𐑮𐑩𐑛𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯, 𐑝 𐑞 𐑑𐑳𐑕𐑒𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑯𐑸𐑢𐑪𐑤. 𐑣𐑬 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑤𐑫𐑒 𐑨𐑑 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑕𐑰𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑪𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑐𐑪𐑛 𐑝 𐑚𐑴𐑯𐑟, 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑝 𐑞 𐑮𐑶𐑩𐑤𐑑𐑦 𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑦𐑥𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑲𐑟𐑛? 𐑓 𐑩 ·𐑒𐑭𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑐𐑤𐑨𐑙𐑒, 𐑯 𐑩 𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑰, 𐑯 𐑩 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑤𐑹𐑛 𐑝 ·𐑤𐑩𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑔𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑢𐑪𐑟 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚.

𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑥𐑴𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑐𐑭𐑕𐑑, 𐑛𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑞 𐑔𐑦𐑒 𐑝𐑱𐑐𐑼 𐑒𐑱𐑥 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑬𐑔 𐑦𐑯 𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑒 𐑯 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑐𐑳𐑓𐑕, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑚𐑤𐑵 𐑚𐑨𐑒 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑱𐑕. “𐑣𐑬 𐑯𐑬,” 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑤𐑩𐑒𐑢𐑲𐑟𐑛 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑, 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑛𐑮𐑷𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑑𐑿𐑚, “𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑕𐑥𐑴𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑯𐑴 𐑤𐑪𐑙𐑜𐑼 𐑕𐑵𐑞𐑟. 𐑴, 𐑥𐑲 𐑐𐑲𐑐! 𐑣𐑸𐑛 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑜𐑴 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑥𐑰 𐑦𐑓 𐑞𐑲 𐑗𐑸𐑥 𐑚𐑰 𐑜𐑪𐑯! 𐑣𐑽 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑲 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑳𐑯𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑑𐑶𐑤𐑦𐑙, 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑐𐑤𐑧𐑠𐑼𐑦𐑙—𐑲, 𐑯 𐑦𐑜𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑥𐑴𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑢𐑼𐑛 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑢𐑲𐑤; 𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑢𐑼𐑛, 𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑯𐑻𐑝𐑩𐑕 𐑢𐑦𐑓𐑕, 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑓, 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑞 𐑛𐑲𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑥𐑲 𐑓𐑲𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑡𐑧𐑑𐑕 𐑢𐑻 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑪𐑙𐑜𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑯 𐑓𐑫𐑤𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑝 𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑚𐑩𐑤. 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑟𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑲 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑐𐑲𐑐? 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑓 𐑕𐑼𐑰𐑯𐑯𐑩𐑕, 𐑑 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑳𐑐 𐑥𐑲𐑤𐑛 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑝𐑱𐑐𐑼𐑟 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑥𐑲𐑤𐑛 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑣𐑺𐑟, 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑑𐑹𐑯 𐑲𐑼𐑯-𐑜𐑮𐑱 𐑤𐑪𐑒𐑕 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑥𐑲𐑯. 𐑲'𐑤 𐑕𐑥𐑴𐑒 𐑯𐑴 𐑥𐑹—”

𐑣𐑰 𐑑𐑪𐑕𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑤𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑐𐑲𐑐 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑕𐑰. 𐑞 𐑓𐑲𐑼 𐑣𐑦𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑝𐑟; 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑖𐑪𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑚𐑳𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑞 𐑕𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑐𐑲𐑐 𐑥𐑱𐑛. 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑕𐑤𐑬𐑗𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑑, ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑤𐑻𐑗𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑱𐑕𐑑 𐑞 𐑐𐑤𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑕.

·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 31. 𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑯 ·𐑥𐑨𐑚.

𐑯𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑 𐑥𐑹𐑯𐑦𐑙 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚 𐑩𐑒𐑪𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛 ·𐑓𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑒.

“𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩 𐑒𐑢𐑽 𐑛𐑮𐑰𐑥, ·𐑒𐑦𐑙-·𐑐𐑴𐑕𐑑, 𐑲 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑣𐑨𐑛. 𐑿 𐑯𐑴 𐑞 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑥𐑨𐑯'𐑟 𐑲𐑝𐑼𐑦 𐑤𐑧𐑜, 𐑢𐑧𐑤 𐑲 𐑛𐑮𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑦𐑒𐑑 𐑥𐑰 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑦𐑑; 𐑯 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑲 𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑛 𐑑 𐑒𐑦𐑒 𐑚𐑨𐑒, 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑥𐑲 𐑕𐑴𐑤, 𐑥𐑲 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑥𐑨𐑯, 𐑲 𐑒𐑦𐑒𐑑 𐑥𐑲 𐑤𐑧𐑜 𐑮𐑲𐑑 𐑪𐑓! 𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑴! 𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑩 𐑐𐑦𐑮𐑩𐑥𐑦𐑛, 𐑯 𐑲, 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑚𐑤𐑱𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑵𐑤, 𐑒𐑧𐑐𐑑 𐑒𐑦𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑑. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑥𐑹 𐑒𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑾𐑕, ·𐑓𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑒—𐑿 𐑯𐑴 𐑣𐑬 𐑒𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑾𐑕 𐑷𐑤 𐑛𐑮𐑰𐑥𐑟 𐑸—𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑮𐑱𐑡 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑲 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑦𐑯, 𐑲 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑣𐑬 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑥𐑲𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑷𐑤, 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑝 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑳𐑤𐑑, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑒𐑦𐑒 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚. '𐑢𐑲,' 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑕 𐑲, '𐑢𐑪𐑑'𐑕 𐑞 𐑮𐑴? 𐑦𐑑'𐑕 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑩 𐑮𐑾𐑤 𐑤𐑧𐑜, 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑩 𐑓𐑷𐑤𐑕 𐑤𐑧𐑜.' 𐑯 𐑞𐑺'𐑟 𐑩 𐑥𐑲𐑑𐑦 𐑛𐑦𐑓𐑼𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑢𐑰𐑯 𐑩 𐑤𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑔𐑳𐑥𐑐 𐑯 𐑩 𐑛𐑧𐑛 𐑔𐑳𐑥𐑐. 𐑞𐑨𐑑'𐑕 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑥𐑱𐑒𐑕 𐑩 𐑚𐑤𐑴 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛, ·𐑓𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑒, 𐑓𐑦𐑓𐑑𐑦 𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑥𐑹 𐑕𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑡 𐑑 𐑚𐑺 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑩 𐑚𐑤𐑴 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑩 𐑒𐑱𐑯. 𐑞 𐑤𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑧𐑥𐑚𐑼—𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑱𐑒𐑕 𐑞 𐑤𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑳𐑤𐑑, 𐑥𐑲 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑥𐑨𐑯. 𐑯 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑕 𐑲 𐑑 𐑥𐑲𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑢𐑲𐑤, 𐑥𐑲𐑯𐑛, 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑲 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑲 𐑕𐑦𐑤𐑦 𐑑𐑴𐑟 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑒𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑐𐑦𐑮𐑩𐑥𐑦𐑛—𐑕𐑴 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑩𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑑𐑼𐑦 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑷𐑤, 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑢𐑲𐑤, 𐑲 𐑕𐑱, 𐑲 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑥𐑲𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓, '𐑢𐑪𐑑'𐑕 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑤𐑧𐑜 𐑯𐑬, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑩 𐑒𐑱𐑯—𐑩 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑚𐑴𐑯 𐑒𐑱𐑯. 𐑘𐑧𐑕,' 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑕 𐑲, '𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑩 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑒𐑳𐑡𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙—𐑦𐑯 𐑓𐑨𐑒𐑑, 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑩 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑚𐑴𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑜𐑱𐑝 𐑥𐑰—𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑩 𐑚𐑱𐑕 𐑒𐑦𐑒. 𐑚𐑦𐑕𐑲𐑛𐑟,' 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑕 𐑲, '𐑤𐑫𐑒 𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑕; 𐑢𐑲, 𐑞 𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑝 𐑦𐑑—𐑞 𐑓𐑫𐑑 𐑐𐑸𐑑—𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑩 𐑕𐑥𐑷𐑤 𐑕𐑹𐑑 𐑝 𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟; 𐑢𐑺𐑨𐑟, 𐑦𐑓 𐑩 𐑚𐑮𐑷𐑛 𐑓𐑫𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑓𐑸𐑥𐑼 𐑒𐑦𐑒𐑑 𐑥𐑰, 𐑞𐑺'𐑟 𐑩 𐑛𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑖 𐑚𐑮𐑷𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑳𐑤𐑑. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑳𐑤𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑑 𐑩 𐑐𐑶𐑯𐑑 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦.' 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑯𐑬 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑟 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑡𐑴𐑒 𐑝 𐑞 𐑛𐑮𐑰𐑥, ·𐑓𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑒. 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑲 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑚𐑨𐑑𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑢𐑱 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑐𐑦𐑮𐑩𐑥𐑦𐑛, 𐑩 𐑕𐑹𐑑 𐑝 𐑚𐑨𐑡𐑼-𐑣𐑺𐑛 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑥𐑻𐑥𐑩𐑯, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑣𐑳𐑥𐑐 𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑨𐑒, 𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑕 𐑥𐑰 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑖𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑼𐑟, 𐑯 𐑕𐑤𐑵𐑟 𐑥𐑰 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛. '𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑸 𐑿 '𐑚𐑬𐑑?' 𐑕𐑧𐑟 𐑣𐑰. 𐑕𐑤𐑦𐑛! 𐑥𐑨𐑯, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑲 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑓𐑮𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑛. 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩 𐑓𐑦𐑟! 𐑚𐑳𐑑, 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑣𐑬, 𐑯𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑 𐑥𐑴𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑲 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑞 𐑓𐑮𐑲𐑑. '𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑨𐑥 𐑲 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑?' 𐑕𐑧𐑟 𐑲 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑. '𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑟𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑦𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑝 𐑘𐑹𐑟, 𐑲 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑑 𐑯𐑴, ·𐑥𐑼 ·𐑣𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑚𐑨𐑒? 𐑛𐑵 𐑿 𐑢𐑪𐑯𐑑 𐑩 𐑒𐑦𐑒?' 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑤𐑹𐑛, ·𐑓𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑒, 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑯𐑴 𐑕𐑵𐑯𐑼 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑, 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑣𐑰 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑛 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑻𐑯 𐑑 𐑥𐑰, 𐑚𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑴𐑝𐑼, 𐑯 𐑛𐑮𐑨𐑜𐑦𐑙 𐑳𐑐 𐑩 𐑤𐑪𐑑 𐑝 𐑕𐑰𐑢𐑰𐑛 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑓 𐑩 𐑒𐑤𐑬𐑑—𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑛𐑵 𐑿 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒, 𐑲 𐑕𐑷?—𐑢𐑲 𐑔𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑩𐑤𐑲𐑝, 𐑥𐑨𐑯, 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑻𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑒 𐑓𐑫𐑤 𐑝 𐑯𐑸𐑤𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑐𐑲𐑒𐑕, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑐𐑶𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑬𐑑. 𐑕𐑧𐑟 𐑲, 𐑪𐑯 𐑕𐑧𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑔𐑷𐑑𐑕, '𐑲 𐑜𐑧𐑕 𐑲 𐑢𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑒𐑦𐑒 𐑿, 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑓𐑧𐑤𐑴.' '𐑢𐑲𐑟 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚,' 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑣𐑰, '𐑢𐑲𐑟 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚;' 𐑯 𐑒𐑧𐑐𐑑 𐑥𐑳𐑑𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑑𐑲𐑥, 𐑩 𐑕𐑹𐑑 𐑝 𐑰𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑴𐑯 𐑜𐑳𐑥𐑟 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑗𐑦𐑥𐑯𐑦 𐑣𐑨𐑜. 𐑕𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑜𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑪𐑐 𐑕𐑱𐑦𐑙 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑣𐑦𐑟 '𐑢𐑲𐑟 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚, 𐑢𐑲𐑟 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚,' 𐑲 𐑔𐑷𐑑 𐑲 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑢𐑧𐑤 𐑓𐑷𐑤 𐑑 𐑒𐑦𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑐𐑦𐑮𐑩𐑥𐑦𐑛 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑡𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑤𐑦𐑓𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑥𐑲 𐑓𐑫𐑑 𐑓 𐑦𐑑, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑣𐑰 𐑮𐑹𐑛 𐑬𐑑, '·𐑕𐑑𐑪𐑐 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑒𐑦𐑒𐑦𐑙!' '𐑣𐑩𐑤𐑴,' 𐑕𐑧𐑟 𐑲, '𐑢𐑪𐑑'𐑕 𐑞 𐑥𐑨𐑑𐑼 𐑯𐑬, 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑓𐑧𐑤𐑴?' '𐑤𐑫𐑒 𐑘𐑰 𐑣𐑽,' 𐑕𐑧𐑟 𐑣𐑰; '𐑤𐑧𐑑'𐑕 𐑸𐑜𐑿 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑳𐑤𐑑. 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑒𐑦𐑒𐑑 𐑘𐑰, 𐑛𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑣𐑰?' '𐑘𐑧𐑕, 𐑣𐑰 𐑛𐑦𐑛,' 𐑕𐑧𐑟 𐑲—'𐑮𐑲𐑑 𐑣𐑽 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟.' '𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑜𐑫𐑛,' 𐑕𐑧𐑟 𐑣𐑰—'𐑣𐑰 𐑿𐑟𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑲𐑝𐑼𐑦 𐑤𐑧𐑜, 𐑛𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑣𐑰?' '𐑘𐑧𐑕, 𐑣𐑰 𐑛𐑦𐑛,' 𐑕𐑧𐑟 𐑲. '𐑢𐑧𐑤 𐑞𐑧𐑯,' 𐑕𐑧𐑟 𐑣𐑰, '𐑢𐑲𐑟 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚, 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑿 𐑑 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑯 𐑝? 𐑛𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑦𐑒 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑮𐑲𐑑 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑤? 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑩 𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑐𐑦𐑗 𐑐𐑲𐑯 𐑤𐑧𐑜 𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑦𐑒𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞, 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑦𐑑? 𐑯𐑴, 𐑿 𐑢𐑻 𐑒𐑦𐑒𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑩 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑥𐑨𐑯, 𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑚𐑿𐑑𐑦𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑲𐑝𐑼𐑦 𐑤𐑧𐑜, ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚. 𐑦𐑑'𐑕 𐑩𐑯 𐑪𐑯𐑼; 𐑲 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑼 𐑦𐑑 𐑩𐑯 𐑪𐑯𐑼. 𐑤𐑦𐑕𐑩𐑯, 𐑢𐑲𐑟 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚. 𐑦𐑯 𐑴𐑤𐑛 ·𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑤𐑹𐑛𐑟 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒 𐑦𐑑 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑜𐑤𐑹𐑦 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑕𐑤𐑨𐑐𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑩 𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑯, 𐑯 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑜𐑸𐑑𐑼-𐑯𐑲𐑑𐑕 𐑝; 𐑚𐑳𐑑, 𐑚𐑰 𐑘𐑹 𐑚𐑴𐑕𐑑, ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑘𐑰 𐑢𐑻 𐑒𐑦𐑒𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑴𐑤𐑛 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚, 𐑯 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑩 𐑢𐑲𐑟 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑝. 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑧𐑥𐑚𐑼 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑲 𐑕𐑱; 𐑚𐑰 𐑒𐑦𐑒𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑣𐑦𐑥; 𐑩𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑦𐑒𐑕 𐑪𐑯𐑼𐑟; 𐑯 𐑪𐑯 𐑯𐑴 𐑩𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑 𐑒𐑦𐑒 𐑚𐑨𐑒; 𐑓 𐑿 𐑒𐑭𐑯𐑑 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑐 𐑘𐑹𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓, 𐑢𐑲𐑟 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚. 𐑛𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑿 𐑕𐑰 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑐𐑦𐑮𐑩𐑥𐑦𐑛?' 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞𐑨𐑑, 𐑣𐑰 𐑷𐑤 𐑝 𐑩 𐑕𐑳𐑛𐑩𐑯 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑣𐑬, 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑒𐑢𐑽 𐑓𐑨𐑖𐑩𐑯, 𐑑 𐑕𐑢𐑦𐑥 𐑪𐑓 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑺. 𐑲 𐑕𐑯𐑹𐑛; 𐑮𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑴𐑝𐑼; 𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑲 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑥𐑩𐑒! 𐑯𐑬, 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑛𐑵 𐑿 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒 𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑛𐑮𐑰𐑥, ·𐑓𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑒?”

“𐑲 𐑛𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑯𐑴; 𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑟 𐑩 𐑕𐑹𐑑 𐑝 𐑓𐑵𐑤𐑦𐑖 𐑑 𐑥𐑰, 𐑞𐑴.'”

“𐑥𐑱 𐑚𐑰; 𐑥𐑱 𐑚𐑰. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑑'𐑕 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑩 𐑢𐑲𐑟 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑝 𐑥𐑰, ·𐑓𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑒. ·𐑛'𐑘𐑰 𐑕𐑰 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑺, 𐑕𐑲𐑛𐑢𐑱𐑟 𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑻𐑯? 𐑢𐑧𐑤, 𐑞 𐑚𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑿 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑛𐑵, ·𐑓𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑒, 𐑦𐑟 𐑑 𐑤𐑧𐑑 𐑞 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑩𐑤𐑴𐑯; 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑒 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑢𐑪𐑑𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑧𐑟. 𐑣𐑩𐑤𐑴! 𐑢𐑪𐑑'𐑕 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑖𐑬𐑑𐑕? 𐑣𐑸𐑒!”

“𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑-𐑣𐑧𐑛, 𐑞𐑺! 𐑤𐑫𐑒 𐑖𐑸𐑐, 𐑷𐑤 𐑝 𐑘𐑰! 𐑞𐑺 𐑸 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑣𐑽𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑𐑕!

“𐑦𐑓 𐑘𐑰 𐑕𐑰 𐑩 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯, 𐑕𐑐𐑤𐑦𐑑 𐑘𐑹 𐑤𐑳𐑙𐑟 𐑓 𐑣𐑦𐑥!

“𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑛𐑵 𐑿 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒 𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑯𐑬, ·𐑓𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑒? 𐑱𐑯𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑩 𐑕𐑥𐑷𐑤 𐑛𐑮𐑪𐑐 𐑝 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑒𐑢𐑽 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑, 𐑱? 𐑩 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑤—𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑘𐑰 𐑥𐑸𐑒 𐑞𐑨𐑑, 𐑥𐑨𐑯? 𐑤𐑫𐑒 𐑘𐑰—𐑞𐑺'𐑟 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛. 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑓 𐑦𐑑, ·𐑓𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑒. 𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑'𐑕 𐑚𐑤𐑳𐑛𐑦 𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑲𐑯𐑛. 𐑚𐑳𐑑, 𐑥𐑳𐑥; 𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑟 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑱.”

·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 32. ·𐑕𐑧𐑑𐑪𐑤𐑩𐑡𐑦.

𐑷𐑤𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑦 𐑢𐑰 𐑸 𐑚𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑤𐑷𐑯𐑗𐑑 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑛𐑰𐑐; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑕𐑵𐑯 𐑢𐑰 𐑖𐑨𐑤 𐑚𐑰 𐑤𐑪𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑳𐑯𐑖𐑹𐑛, 𐑣𐑸𐑚𐑼𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑦𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑟. 𐑺 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑑 𐑐𐑭𐑕; 𐑺 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛'𐑟 𐑢𐑰𐑛𐑦 𐑣𐑳𐑤 𐑮𐑴𐑤𐑟 𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑚𐑸𐑯𐑩𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑣𐑳𐑤𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑤𐑩𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑔𐑩𐑯; 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑬𐑑𐑕𐑧𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑧𐑤 𐑑 𐑩𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑑 𐑩 𐑥𐑨𐑑𐑼 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑑 𐑩 𐑔𐑳𐑮𐑴 𐑩𐑐𐑮𐑰𐑖𐑩𐑑𐑦𐑝 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑞 𐑥𐑹 𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑤 𐑤𐑩𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑔𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑒 𐑮𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑯 𐑩𐑤𐑵𐑠𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑷𐑤 𐑕𐑹𐑑𐑕 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑸 𐑑 𐑓𐑪𐑤𐑴.

𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑕𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑥𐑩𐑑𐑲𐑟𐑛 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑦𐑚𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑮𐑷𐑛 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑼𐑩, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑲 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑯𐑬 𐑓𐑱𐑯 𐑐𐑫𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑿. 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑯𐑴 𐑰𐑟𐑦 𐑑𐑭𐑕𐑒. 𐑞 𐑒𐑤𐑨𐑕𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑒𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑗𐑵𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑩 𐑒𐑱𐑪𐑕, 𐑯𐑳𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑤𐑧𐑕 𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑽 𐑧𐑕𐑱𐑛. 𐑤𐑦𐑕𐑩𐑯 𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑞 𐑚𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑯 𐑤𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑷𐑔𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑤𐑱𐑛 𐑛𐑬𐑯.

“𐑯𐑴 𐑚𐑮𐑭𐑯𐑗 𐑝 ·𐑟𐑴𐑪𐑤𐑩𐑡𐑦 𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑴 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑪𐑤𐑝𐑛 𐑨𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑛 ·𐑕𐑧𐑑𐑪𐑤𐑩𐑡𐑦,” 𐑕𐑧𐑟 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 ·𐑕𐑒𐑹𐑟𐑚𐑦, ⸰𐑱𐑛 1820.

“𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑥𐑲 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑯, 𐑢𐑻 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑲 𐑐𐑬𐑼, 𐑑 𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑼 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑢𐑲𐑼𐑦 𐑨𐑟 𐑑 𐑞 𐑑𐑮𐑵 𐑥𐑧𐑔𐑩𐑛 𐑝 𐑛𐑦𐑝𐑲𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑧𐑑𐑱𐑖𐑩 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑜𐑮𐑵𐑐𐑕 𐑯 𐑓𐑨𐑥𐑤𐑦𐑟. * * * 𐑳𐑑𐑼 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑓𐑿𐑠𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑜𐑟𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑕 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑹𐑾𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑥𐑩𐑤” (𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 𐑢𐑱𐑤), 𐑕𐑧𐑟 ·𐑕𐑻𐑡𐑩𐑯 ·𐑚𐑦𐑱𐑤, ⸰𐑱𐑛 1839.

“𐑳𐑯𐑓𐑦𐑑𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑑 𐑐𐑼𐑕𐑿 𐑬𐑼 𐑮𐑰𐑕𐑻𐑗 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑳𐑯𐑓𐑨𐑞𐑩𐑥𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼𐑟.” “𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑮𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑝𐑱𐑤 𐑒𐑳𐑝𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑬𐑼 𐑯𐑪𐑤𐑦𐑡 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑧𐑑𐑱𐑖𐑩.” “𐑩 𐑓𐑰𐑤𐑛 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑵𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑔𐑹𐑯𐑟.” “𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑰𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑕𐑻𐑝 𐑑 𐑑𐑹𐑗𐑼 𐑳𐑕 𐑯𐑨𐑗𐑼𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑕.”

𐑞𐑳𐑕 𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑒 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 ·𐑒𐑿𐑝𐑽, 𐑯 ·𐑡𐑪𐑯 ·𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑑𐑼, 𐑯 ·𐑤𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑯, 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑤𐑲𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑟𐑴𐑪𐑤𐑩𐑡𐑦 𐑯 𐑩𐑯𐑨𐑑𐑩𐑥𐑦. 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼𐑞𐑩𐑤𐑧𐑕, 𐑞𐑴 𐑝 𐑮𐑾𐑤 𐑯𐑪𐑤𐑦𐑡 𐑞𐑺 𐑚𐑰 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤, 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑝 𐑚𐑫𐑒𐑕 𐑞𐑺 𐑸 𐑩 𐑐𐑤𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑦; 𐑯 𐑕𐑴 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑕𐑥𐑷𐑤 𐑛𐑦𐑜𐑮𐑰, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 ·𐑕𐑧𐑑𐑪𐑤𐑩𐑡𐑦, 𐑹 𐑞 𐑕𐑲𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑝 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟. 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑸 𐑞 𐑥𐑧𐑯, 𐑕𐑥𐑷𐑤 𐑯 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑, 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑯 𐑯𐑿, 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑯 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑧𐑯, 𐑣𐑵 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑸𐑡 𐑹 𐑦𐑯 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤, 𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤. 𐑮𐑳𐑯 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑩 𐑓𐑿:—𐑞 ·𐑷𐑔𐑼𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑚𐑲𐑚𐑩𐑤; ·𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑪𐑑𐑩𐑤; ·𐑐𐑤𐑲𐑯𐑦; ·𐑷𐑤𐑛𐑮𐑴𐑝𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑦; ·𐑕𐑻 ·𐑑𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑕 ·𐑚𐑮𐑬𐑯; ·𐑡𐑦𐑟𐑯𐑼; ·𐑮𐑱; ·𐑤𐑦𐑯𐑾𐑕; ·𐑮𐑪𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑤𐑩𐑖𐑩𐑕; ·𐑢𐑦𐑤𐑴𐑚𐑦; ·𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑯; ·𐑸𐑑𐑩𐑛𐑦; ·𐑕𐑦𐑚𐑨𐑤𐑑; ·𐑚𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑩𐑯; ·𐑥𐑸𐑑𐑦𐑯; ·𐑤𐑱𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑛; Bonneterre; ·𐑛𐑧𐑥𐑸𐑱; ·𐑚𐑨𐑮𐑩𐑯 ·𐑒𐑿𐑝𐑽; ·𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑼𐑦𐑒 ·𐑒𐑿𐑝𐑽; ·𐑡𐑪𐑯 ·𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑑𐑼; ·𐑴𐑢𐑧𐑯; ·𐑕𐑒𐑹𐑟𐑚𐑦; ·𐑚𐑦𐑱𐑤; ·𐑚𐑧𐑯𐑩𐑑; J. ·𐑮𐑪𐑕 ·𐑚𐑮𐑬𐑯; 𐑞 ·𐑷𐑔𐑼 𐑝 ·𐑥𐑦𐑮𐑾𐑥 ·𐑒𐑪𐑓𐑦𐑯; ·𐑴𐑤𐑥𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑛; 𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑮𐑧𐑝 T. ·𐑗𐑰𐑝𐑼. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑳𐑤𐑑𐑦𐑥𐑩𐑑 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑤𐑲𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑐𐑻𐑐𐑩𐑕 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑯, 𐑞 𐑩𐑚𐑳𐑝 𐑕𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑒𐑑𐑕 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑖𐑴.

𐑝 𐑞 𐑯𐑱𐑥𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑤𐑦𐑕𐑑 𐑝 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑷𐑔𐑼𐑟, 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑓𐑪𐑤𐑴𐑦𐑙 ·𐑴𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑕𐑷 𐑤𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟; 𐑯 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩 𐑮𐑾𐑤 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑓𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑽 𐑯 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑥𐑩𐑯. 𐑲 𐑥𐑰𐑯 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 ·𐑕𐑒𐑹𐑟𐑚𐑦. 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑧𐑐𐑼𐑩𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑚𐑡𐑧𐑒𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑯𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑹 𐑮𐑲𐑑-𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑣𐑰 𐑦𐑟 𐑞 𐑚𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑜𐑟𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑷𐑔𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑦. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 ·𐑕𐑒𐑹𐑟𐑚𐑦 𐑯𐑿 𐑯𐑳𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑯 𐑕𐑧𐑟 𐑯𐑳𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑺𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑞 ·𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑯𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑦𐑟 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑳𐑯𐑢𐑻𐑞𐑦 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑙. 𐑯 𐑣𐑽 𐑚𐑰 𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑧𐑛, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑯𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑦𐑟 𐑩𐑯 𐑿𐑟𐑻𐑐𐑼 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑔𐑮𐑴𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑰𐑟. 𐑣𐑰 𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑚𐑲 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑥𐑰𐑯𐑟 𐑞 𐑤𐑸𐑡𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟. 𐑘𐑧𐑑, 𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑞 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑐𐑮𐑲𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑤𐑱𐑥𐑟, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑜𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑢𐑦𐑗, 𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑕𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑦 𐑘𐑽𐑟 𐑚𐑨𐑒, 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑞 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑓𐑨𐑚𐑿𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑹 𐑳𐑑𐑼𐑤𐑦 𐑳𐑯𐑯𐑴𐑯 𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥-𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑦𐑜𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑛𐑱 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑓𐑿 𐑕𐑲𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑒 𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑮𐑰𐑑𐑕 𐑯 𐑢𐑱𐑤-𐑐𐑹𐑑𐑕; 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑿𐑟𐑻𐑐𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑢𐑱 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑰𐑑. 𐑮𐑧𐑓𐑼𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑑 𐑯𐑽𐑤𐑦 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑤𐑩𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑔𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑒 𐑩𐑤𐑵𐑠𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑐𐑴𐑩𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑐𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑛𐑱𐑟, 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑕𐑨𐑑𐑦𐑕𐑓𐑲 𐑿 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑯𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑮𐑲𐑝𐑩𐑤, 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑑 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑞 𐑥𐑪𐑯𐑸𐑒 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑰𐑟. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑓 𐑩 𐑯𐑿 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑒𐑤𐑩𐑥𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯. 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑦𐑟 ·𐑗𐑸𐑦𐑙 ·𐑒𐑮𐑪𐑕; 𐑣𐑽 𐑘𐑰! 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑐𐑰𐑐𐑩𐑤 𐑷𐑤,—𐑞 ·𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑯𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑦𐑟 𐑛𐑦𐑐𐑴𐑟𐑛,—𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑯𐑬 𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑩𐑔!

𐑞𐑺 𐑸 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑑𐑵 𐑚𐑫𐑒𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑨𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑑 𐑐𐑫𐑑 𐑞 𐑤𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑿, 𐑯 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑑𐑲𐑥, 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑴𐑑𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑜𐑮𐑰 𐑕𐑩𐑒𐑕𐑰𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑩𐑑𐑧𐑥𐑐𐑑. 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑚𐑫𐑒𐑕 𐑸 ·𐑚𐑦𐑱𐑤'𐑟 𐑯 ·𐑚𐑧𐑯𐑩𐑑'𐑕; 𐑚𐑴𐑔 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑕𐑻𐑡𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑑 ·𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑤𐑦𐑖 ·𐑕𐑬𐑔-·𐑕𐑰 𐑢𐑱𐑤-𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑕, 𐑯 𐑚𐑴𐑔 𐑦𐑜𐑟𐑨𐑒𐑑 𐑯 𐑮𐑦𐑤𐑲𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑥𐑧𐑯. 𐑞 𐑼𐑦𐑡𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑥𐑨𐑑𐑼 𐑑𐑳𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑝𐑪𐑤𐑿𐑥𐑟 𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑧𐑕𐑦𐑕𐑺𐑦𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑥𐑷𐑤; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑕𐑴 𐑓𐑸 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑜𐑴𐑟, 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑝 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑩𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑦, 𐑞𐑴 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑓𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑑 𐑕𐑲𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑒 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑖𐑩𐑯. 𐑨𐑟 𐑘𐑧𐑑, 𐑣𐑬𐑧𐑝𐑼, 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑕𐑲𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑒 𐑹 𐑐𐑴𐑧𐑑𐑦𐑒, 𐑤𐑦𐑝𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑰𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑼𐑩𐑗𐑼. 𐑓𐑸 𐑩𐑚𐑳𐑝 𐑷𐑤 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟, 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑟 𐑩𐑯 𐑳𐑯𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑤𐑲𐑓.

𐑯𐑬 𐑞 𐑝𐑺𐑾𐑕 𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑖𐑰𐑟 𐑝 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑯𐑰𐑛 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑕𐑹𐑑 𐑝 𐑐𐑪𐑐𐑿𐑤𐑼 𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑣𐑧𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑝 𐑒𐑤𐑨𐑕𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑒𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯, 𐑦𐑓 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑩𐑯 𐑰𐑟𐑦 𐑬𐑑𐑤𐑲𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑓 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑑, 𐑣𐑽𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑓𐑦𐑤𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑛𐑦𐑐𐑸𐑑𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑚𐑲 𐑕𐑳𐑚𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑢𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑤𐑱𐑚𐑼𐑼𐑟. 𐑨𐑟 𐑯𐑴 𐑚𐑧𐑑𐑼 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑩𐑛𐑝𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑑 𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑥𐑨𐑑𐑼 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛, 𐑲 𐑣𐑽𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑪𐑓𐑼 𐑥𐑲 𐑴𐑯 𐑐𐑫𐑼 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑧𐑝𐑼𐑟. 𐑲 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑥𐑦𐑕 𐑯𐑳𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑰𐑑; 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑪𐑟 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑣𐑿𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑩𐑐𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑰𐑑, 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑓 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑮𐑰𐑟𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑓𐑨𐑤𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑰 𐑓𐑷𐑤𐑑𐑦. 𐑲 𐑖𐑨𐑤 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑑 𐑩 𐑥𐑲𐑯𐑿𐑑 𐑨𐑯𐑩𐑑𐑪𐑥𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑝𐑺𐑾𐑕 𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑖𐑰𐑟, 𐑹—𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑰𐑕𐑑—𐑑 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑝 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑖𐑩𐑯. 𐑥𐑲 𐑪𐑚𐑡𐑧𐑒𐑑 𐑣𐑽 𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑦 𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑡𐑧𐑒𐑑 𐑞 𐑛𐑮𐑭𐑓𐑑 𐑝 𐑩 𐑕𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑥𐑩𐑑𐑲𐑟𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 ·𐑕𐑧𐑑𐑪𐑤𐑩𐑡𐑦. 𐑲 𐑨𐑥 𐑞 𐑸𐑒𐑦𐑑𐑧𐑒𐑑, 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑞 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑛𐑼.

𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑩 𐑐𐑪𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑩𐑕 𐑑𐑭𐑕𐑒; 𐑯𐑴 𐑹𐑛𐑦𐑯𐑼𐑦 𐑤𐑧𐑑𐑼-𐑕𐑹𐑑𐑼 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑴𐑕𐑑-·𐑪𐑓𐑦𐑕 𐑦𐑟 𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑩𐑤 𐑑 𐑦𐑑. 𐑑 𐑜𐑮𐑴𐑐 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑚𐑪𐑑𐑩𐑥 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑰 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑞𐑧𐑥; 𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑢𐑳𐑯'𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑞 𐑳𐑯𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟, 𐑮𐑦𐑚𐑟, 𐑯 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑐𐑧𐑤𐑝𐑦𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛; 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑦𐑟 𐑩 𐑓𐑽𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑔𐑦𐑙. 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑨𐑥 𐑲 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑲 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑧𐑕𐑱 𐑑 𐑣𐑫𐑒 𐑞 𐑯𐑴𐑟 𐑝 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑤𐑩𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑔𐑩𐑯! 𐑞 𐑷𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑑𐑷𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑦𐑯 ·𐑡𐑴𐑚 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑢𐑧𐑤 𐑩𐑐𐑷𐑤 𐑥𐑰. 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑣𐑰 (𐑞 𐑤𐑩𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑔𐑩𐑯) 𐑥𐑱𐑒 𐑩 𐑒𐑳𐑝𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞𐑰? 𐑚𐑦𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑞 𐑣𐑴𐑐 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑦𐑟 𐑝𐑱𐑯! 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑕𐑢𐑨𐑥 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑤𐑲𐑚𐑮𐑺𐑦𐑟 𐑯 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑛 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟; 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑑 𐑛𐑵 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑝𐑦𐑟𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟; 𐑲 𐑨𐑥 𐑦𐑯 𐑻𐑯𐑩𐑕𐑑; 𐑯 𐑲 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑑𐑮𐑲. 𐑞𐑺 𐑸 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑼𐑦𐑟 𐑑 𐑕𐑧𐑑𐑩𐑤.

𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑: 𐑞 𐑳𐑯𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑯, 𐑳𐑯𐑕𐑧𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑕𐑲𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑝 ·𐑕𐑧𐑑𐑪𐑤𐑩𐑡𐑦 𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑝𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑚𐑿𐑤 𐑩𐑑𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑓𐑨𐑒𐑑, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑒𐑢𐑹𐑑𐑼𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑱𐑯𐑟 𐑩 𐑥𐑵𐑑 𐑐𐑶𐑯𐑑 𐑢𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑩 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑚𐑰 𐑩 𐑓𐑦𐑖. 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 ·𐑕𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑥 𐑝 ·𐑯𐑱𐑗𐑼, ⸰𐑱𐑛 1776, ·𐑤𐑦𐑯𐑾𐑕 𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑺𐑟, “𐑲 𐑣𐑽𐑚𐑲 𐑕𐑧𐑐𐑼𐑩𐑑 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑓𐑦𐑖.” 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑝 𐑥𐑲 𐑴𐑯 𐑯𐑪𐑤𐑦𐑡, 𐑲 𐑯𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑑 𐑞 𐑘𐑽 1850, 𐑖𐑸𐑒𐑕 𐑯 𐑖𐑨𐑛, ·𐑱𐑤𐑵𐑦𐑝𐑟 𐑯 𐑣𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑙, 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑕𐑑 ·𐑤𐑦𐑯𐑾𐑕'𐑩𐑟 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑕 𐑰𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑑, 𐑢𐑻 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑛𐑦𐑝𐑲𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑐𐑩𐑟𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑕𐑰𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 ·𐑤𐑩𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑔𐑩𐑯.

𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑗 ·𐑤𐑦𐑯𐑾𐑕 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑓𐑱𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑚𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑖𐑑 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼𐑟, 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑑𐑕 𐑨𐑟 𐑓𐑪𐑤𐑴𐑟: “𐑪𐑯 𐑩𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑞𐑺 𐑢𐑹𐑥 𐑚𐑲𐑤𐑴𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑼 𐑣𐑸𐑑, 𐑞𐑺 𐑤𐑳𐑙𐑟, 𐑞𐑺 𐑥𐑵𐑝𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑲𐑤𐑦𐑛𐑟, 𐑞𐑺 𐑣𐑪𐑤𐑴 𐑽𐑟, 𐑐𐑰𐑯𐑩𐑥 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑥 𐑓𐑧𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑭𐑥 𐑥𐑨𐑥𐑦𐑕 𐑤𐑨𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑥,” 𐑯 𐑓𐑲𐑯𐑩𐑤𐑦, “𐑧𐑒𐑕 𐑤𐑧𐑡 𐑯𐑱𐑗𐑼𐑦 𐑡𐑻𐑦 meritoque.” 𐑲 𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑥𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑑 𐑥𐑲 𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑟 ·𐑕𐑦𐑥𐑾𐑯 ·𐑥𐑱𐑕𐑦 𐑯 ·𐑗𐑸𐑤𐑦 ·𐑒𐑪𐑓𐑦𐑯, 𐑝 ·𐑯𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑑, 𐑚𐑴𐑔 𐑥𐑧𐑕𐑥𐑱𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑥𐑲𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑝𐑶𐑦𐑡, 𐑯 𐑞𐑱 𐑿𐑯𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑩𐑐𐑦𐑯𐑘𐑩𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑮𐑰𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑕𐑧𐑑 𐑓𐑹𐑔 𐑢𐑻 𐑷𐑤𐑑𐑩𐑜𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑑. ·𐑗𐑸𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑮𐑴𐑓𐑱𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑣𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑞𐑱 𐑢𐑻 𐑣𐑳𐑥𐑚𐑳𐑜.

𐑚𐑰 𐑦𐑑 𐑯𐑴𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑, 𐑢𐑱𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑷𐑤 𐑸𐑜𐑿𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑, 𐑲 𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑞 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑓𐑨𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑜𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑦𐑟 𐑩 𐑓𐑦𐑖, 𐑯 𐑒𐑷𐑤 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑦 ·𐑡𐑴𐑯𐑩 𐑑 𐑚𐑨𐑒 𐑥𐑰. 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑓𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑧𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑛, 𐑞 𐑯𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑 𐑐𐑶𐑯𐑑 𐑦𐑟, 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑 𐑛𐑳𐑟 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑛𐑦𐑓𐑼 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑓𐑦𐑖. 𐑩𐑚𐑳𐑝, ·𐑤𐑦𐑯𐑾𐑕 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑜𐑦𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑿 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑥𐑟. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑚𐑮𐑰𐑓, 𐑞𐑱 𐑸 𐑞𐑰𐑟: 𐑤𐑳𐑙𐑟 𐑯 𐑢𐑹𐑥 𐑚𐑤𐑳𐑛; 𐑢𐑺𐑨𐑟, 𐑷𐑤 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑓𐑦𐑖 𐑸 𐑤𐑳𐑙𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑯 𐑒𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑚𐑤𐑳𐑛𐑩𐑛.

𐑯𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑: 𐑣𐑬 𐑖𐑨𐑤 𐑢𐑰 𐑛𐑦𐑓𐑲𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑚𐑲 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑪𐑚𐑝𐑾𐑕 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑯𐑩𐑤𐑟, 𐑕𐑴 𐑨𐑟 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑩𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑑 𐑤𐑱𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑓 𐑷𐑤 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑑 𐑒𐑳𐑥? 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑖𐑹𐑑, 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑩 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑦𐑟 𐑩 𐑕𐑐𐑬𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑦𐑖 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑣𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑑𐑱𐑤. 𐑞𐑺 𐑿 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑥. 𐑣𐑬𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑛, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑛𐑧𐑓𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑟 𐑞 𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑳𐑤𐑑 𐑝 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑥𐑧𐑛𐑦𐑑𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯. 𐑩 𐑢𐑷𐑤𐑮𐑩𐑕 𐑕𐑐𐑬𐑑𐑕 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞 𐑢𐑷𐑤𐑮𐑩𐑕 𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑩 𐑓𐑦𐑖, 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑪𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑦𐑟 𐑨𐑥𐑓𐑦𐑚𐑾𐑕. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑑𐑻𐑥 𐑝 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑓𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑥𐑹 𐑒𐑴𐑡𐑩𐑯𐑑, 𐑨𐑟 𐑒𐑳𐑐𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑. 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑯𐑴𐑑𐑦𐑕𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑓𐑦𐑖 𐑓𐑩𐑥𐑦𐑤𐑽 𐑑 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑩 𐑓𐑤𐑨𐑑, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑩 𐑝𐑻𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤, 𐑹 𐑳𐑐-𐑯-𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑑𐑱𐑤. 𐑢𐑺𐑨𐑟, 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑕𐑐𐑬𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑦𐑖 𐑞 𐑑𐑱𐑤, 𐑞𐑴 𐑦𐑑 𐑥𐑱 𐑚𐑰 𐑕𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑤𐑼𐑤𐑦 𐑖𐑱𐑐𐑑, 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑺𐑾𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑩𐑕𐑿𐑥𐑟 𐑩 𐑣𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑐𐑩𐑟𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯.

𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑩𐑚𐑳𐑝 𐑛𐑧𐑓𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑩 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑦𐑟, 𐑲 𐑛𐑵 𐑚𐑲 𐑯𐑴 𐑥𐑰𐑯𐑟 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑒𐑤𐑵𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑤𐑩𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑔𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑒 𐑚𐑮𐑳𐑞𐑼𐑣𐑫𐑛 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑕𐑰 𐑒𐑮𐑰𐑗𐑼 𐑣𐑦𐑞𐑼𐑑𐑵 𐑲𐑛𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑓𐑲𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑚𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑓𐑹𐑥𐑛 ·𐑯𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑑𐑼𐑟; 𐑯𐑹, 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛, 𐑤𐑦𐑙𐑒 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑦𐑑 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑓𐑦𐑖 𐑣𐑦𐑞𐑼𐑑𐑵 𐑷𐑔𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑑𐑦𐑝𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑦𐑜𐑸𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑨𐑟 𐑱𐑤𐑾𐑯.* 𐑣𐑧𐑯𐑕, 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑕𐑥𐑷𐑤𐑼, 𐑕𐑐𐑬𐑑𐑦𐑙, 𐑯 𐑣𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑑𐑱𐑤𐑛 𐑓𐑦𐑖 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑤𐑵𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑜𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛-𐑐𐑤𐑨𐑯 𐑝 ·𐑕𐑧𐑑𐑪𐑤𐑩𐑡𐑦. 𐑯𐑬, 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑛𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑠𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑲𐑼 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑣𐑴𐑕𐑑.

*𐑲 𐑨𐑥 𐑩𐑢𐑺 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑑 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑑𐑲𐑥, 𐑞 𐑓𐑦𐑖 𐑕𐑑𐑲𐑤𐑛 ·𐑤𐑭𐑥𐑱𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑟 𐑯 ·𐑛𐑵𐑜𐑪𐑙𐑟 (·𐑐𐑦𐑜-𐑓𐑦𐑖 𐑯 ·𐑕𐑬-𐑓𐑦𐑖 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑒𐑪𐑓𐑦𐑯𐑟 𐑝 ·𐑯𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑑) 𐑸 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑤𐑵𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑯𐑨𐑗𐑼𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑕 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑐𐑦𐑜-𐑓𐑦𐑖 𐑸 𐑩 𐑯𐑶𐑟𐑦, 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑥𐑐𐑑𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑧𐑑, 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑤𐑻𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑥𐑬𐑞𐑟 𐑝 𐑮𐑦𐑝𐑼𐑟, 𐑯 𐑓𐑰𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑪𐑯 𐑢𐑧𐑑 𐑣𐑱, 𐑯 𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑨𐑟 𐑞𐑱 𐑛𐑵 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑐𐑬𐑑, 𐑲 𐑛𐑦𐑯𐑲 𐑞𐑺 𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑛𐑧𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑨𐑟 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟; 𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞𐑺 𐑐𐑭𐑕𐑐𐑹𐑑𐑕 𐑑 𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑒𐑦𐑙𐑛𐑩𐑥 𐑝 ·𐑕𐑧𐑑𐑪𐑤𐑩𐑡𐑦.

𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑: 𐑩𐑒𐑹𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑥𐑨𐑜𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑿𐑛 𐑲 𐑛𐑦𐑝𐑲𐑛 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑐𐑮𐑲𐑥𐑼𐑦 ·𐑚𐑫𐑒𐑕 (𐑕𐑳𐑚𐑛𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑟𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 ·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼𐑟), 𐑯 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑖𐑨𐑤 𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑣𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑷𐑤, 𐑚𐑴𐑔 𐑕𐑥𐑷𐑤 𐑯 𐑤𐑸𐑡.

𐑲. 𐑞 ·𐑓𐑴𐑤𐑦𐑴 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤; II. 𐑞 ·𐑪𐑒𐑑𐑱𐑝𐑴 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤; III. 𐑞 ·𐑛𐑘𐑵𐑴𐑛𐑧𐑕𐑦𐑥𐑩𐑤 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤.

𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑑𐑲𐑐 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑓𐑴𐑤𐑦𐑴 𐑲 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤; 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑪𐑒𐑑𐑱𐑝𐑴, 𐑞 ·𐑜𐑮𐑨𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑕; 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑛𐑘𐑵𐑴𐑛𐑧𐑕𐑦𐑥𐑩𐑤, 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑹𐑐𐑩𐑕.

·𐑓𐑴𐑤𐑦𐑴𐑟. 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑲 𐑣𐑽 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑤𐑵𐑛 𐑞 𐑓𐑪𐑤𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼𐑟:—𐑲. 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤; II. 𐑞 ·𐑮𐑲𐑑 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤; III. 𐑞 ·𐑓𐑦𐑯-𐑚𐑨𐑒 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤; IV. 𐑞 ·𐑣𐑳𐑥𐑐-𐑚𐑨𐑒𐑑 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤; V. 𐑞 ·𐑮𐑱𐑟𐑼 𐑚𐑨𐑒 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤; VI. 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑳𐑤𐑓𐑼 ·𐑚𐑪𐑑𐑩𐑥 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤.

·𐑚𐑫𐑒 𐑲. (𐑓𐑴𐑤𐑦𐑴), ·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 𐑲. (𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤).—𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑞 ·𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑤𐑦𐑖 𐑝 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑝𐑱𐑜𐑤𐑦 𐑯𐑴𐑯 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 ·𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑩 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑓𐑦𐑟𐑩𐑑𐑼 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑨𐑯𐑝𐑦𐑤 ·𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑦𐑟 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑑 ·𐑒𐑨𐑖𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑯𐑗, 𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑪𐑑𐑕𐑓𐑦𐑖 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑡𐑻𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑟, 𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑥𐑨𐑒𐑮𐑴𐑕𐑧𐑓𐑩𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑤𐑪𐑙 ·𐑢𐑻𐑛𐑟. 𐑣𐑰 𐑦𐑟, 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑 𐑛𐑬𐑑, 𐑞 𐑤𐑸𐑡𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑣𐑨𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑜𐑤𐑴𐑚; 𐑞 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑓𐑹𐑥𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑷𐑤 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑼; 𐑞 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑥𐑩𐑡𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑦𐑯 𐑨𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑; 𐑯 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑤𐑦, 𐑚𐑲 𐑓𐑸 𐑞 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑝𐑨𐑤𐑿𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑻𐑕; 𐑣𐑰 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑮𐑰𐑗𐑼 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑝𐑨𐑤𐑿𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑳𐑚𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕, 𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥𐑩𐑕𐑧𐑑𐑦, 𐑦𐑟 𐑩𐑚𐑑𐑱𐑯𐑛. 𐑷𐑤 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑦𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑤, 𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕𐑩𐑟, 𐑚𐑰 𐑦𐑯𐑤𐑸𐑡𐑛 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯. 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑗𐑰𐑓𐑤𐑦 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑱𐑥 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑲 𐑯𐑬 𐑣𐑨𐑓 𐑑 𐑛𐑵. 𐑓𐑦𐑤𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑡𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑼𐑛, 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑩𐑚𐑕𐑻𐑛. 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑗𐑼𐑦𐑟 𐑩𐑜𐑴, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑦 𐑳𐑯𐑯𐑴𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑴𐑯 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑐𐑼 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑡𐑵𐑨𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑦, 𐑯 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑶𐑤 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑨𐑒𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑩𐑚𐑑𐑱𐑯𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑓𐑦𐑖; 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑛𐑱𐑟 𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥𐑩𐑕𐑧𐑑𐑦, 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑕𐑰𐑥, 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑐𐑪𐑐𐑿𐑤𐑼𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑩𐑐𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑛𐑦𐑮𐑲𐑝𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑩 𐑒𐑮𐑰𐑗𐑼 𐑲𐑛𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑯𐑴𐑯 𐑦𐑯 ·𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 ·𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑯𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑹 ·𐑮𐑲𐑑 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤. 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞 𐑲𐑛𐑾 𐑷𐑤𐑕𐑴, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥𐑩𐑕𐑧𐑑𐑦 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑿𐑥𐑼 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑯𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑞 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑦𐑤𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑻𐑛 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑼𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑟. 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟, 𐑷𐑤𐑕𐑴, 𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥𐑩𐑕𐑧𐑑𐑦 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑰𐑛𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑒𐑺𐑕, 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑿𐑟𐑛 𐑓 𐑤𐑲𐑑, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑨𐑟 𐑩𐑯 𐑶𐑯𐑑𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑯 𐑥𐑧𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑. 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑛𐑮𐑳𐑜𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑕 𐑨𐑟 𐑿 𐑯𐑬𐑩𐑛𐑱𐑟 𐑚𐑲 𐑩𐑯 𐑬𐑯𐑕 𐑝 𐑮𐑵𐑚𐑸𐑚. 𐑢𐑧𐑯, 𐑨𐑟 𐑲 𐑩𐑐𐑲𐑯, 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑒𐑹𐑕 𐑝 𐑑𐑲𐑥, 𐑞 𐑑𐑮𐑵 𐑯𐑱𐑗𐑼 𐑝 𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥𐑩𐑕𐑧𐑑𐑦 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑱𐑥 𐑯𐑴𐑯, 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑼𐑦𐑡𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑯𐑱𐑥 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑱𐑯𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑛𐑰𐑤𐑼𐑟; 𐑯𐑴 𐑛𐑬𐑑 𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑣𐑭𐑯𐑕 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑝𐑨𐑤𐑿 𐑚𐑲 𐑩 𐑯𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑕𐑴 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑦𐑜𐑯𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑕𐑒𐑺𐑕𐑦𐑑𐑦. 𐑯 𐑕𐑴 𐑞 𐑨𐑐𐑩𐑤𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑚𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑴𐑛 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥𐑩𐑕𐑧𐑑𐑦 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑮𐑾𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑦𐑮𐑲𐑝𐑛.

·𐑚𐑫𐑒 𐑲. (𐑓𐑴𐑤𐑦𐑴), ·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 II. (𐑮𐑲𐑑 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤).—𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑦𐑟 𐑞 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑝𐑧𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑞 𐑤𐑩𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑔𐑩𐑯𐑟, 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑮𐑧𐑜𐑿𐑤𐑼𐑤𐑦 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑥𐑨𐑯. 𐑦𐑑 𐑘𐑰𐑤𐑛𐑟 𐑞 𐑸𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑯𐑴𐑯 𐑨𐑟 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑚𐑴𐑯 𐑹 𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑰𐑯; 𐑯 𐑞 𐑶𐑤 𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑯𐑴𐑯 𐑨𐑟 “𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑶𐑤,” 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑓𐑽𐑽 𐑸𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑻𐑕. 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑞 𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑼𐑥𐑧𐑯, 𐑣𐑰 𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑧𐑟𐑦𐑜𐑯𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑓𐑪𐑤𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑑𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑟: 𐑞 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤; 𐑞 ·𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑯𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤; 𐑞 ·𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑒 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤; 𐑞 ·𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤; 𐑞 ·𐑑𐑮𐑵 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤; 𐑞 ·𐑮𐑲𐑑 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤. 𐑞𐑺 𐑦𐑟 𐑩 𐑛𐑰𐑤 𐑝 𐑩𐑚𐑕𐑒𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑲𐑛𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑖𐑰𐑟 𐑞𐑳𐑕 𐑥𐑳𐑤𐑑𐑦𐑑𐑿𐑛𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑲𐑟𐑛. 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑦𐑟 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑲 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑤𐑵𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑧𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑖𐑰𐑟 𐑝 𐑥𐑲 ·𐑓𐑴𐑤𐑦𐑴𐑟? 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑞 ·𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 ·𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑕𐑰𐑑𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑤𐑦𐑖 𐑯𐑨𐑗𐑼𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑕; 𐑞 ·𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑯𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑤𐑦𐑖 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑥𐑧𐑯; 𐑞 ·𐑚𐑱𐑤𐑰𐑯 ·𐑹𐑛𐑦𐑯𐑺 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑯𐑗 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑥𐑧𐑯; 𐑞 ·𐑜𐑮𐑬𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟 ·𐑢𐑷𐑤𐑓𐑦𐑖 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑢𐑰𐑛𐑟. 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑓 𐑥𐑹 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑑𐑵 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑗𐑼𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 ·𐑛𐑳𐑗 𐑯 ·𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑤𐑦𐑖 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑸𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑕𐑰𐑟; 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑞 ·𐑩𐑥𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑼𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑐𐑼𐑕𐑿𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑾𐑯 𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯, 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑚𐑮𐑩𐑟𐑦𐑤 ·𐑚𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑕, 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑯𐑹' ·𐑢𐑧𐑕𐑑 ·𐑒𐑴𐑕𐑑, 𐑯 𐑝𐑺𐑾𐑕 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑐𐑸𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛, 𐑛𐑧𐑟𐑦𐑜𐑯𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑞𐑧𐑥 ·𐑮𐑲𐑑 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤 ·𐑒𐑮𐑵𐑟𐑦𐑙 ·𐑜𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑟.

𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑑 𐑕𐑰 𐑩 𐑛𐑦𐑓𐑼𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑢𐑰𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑯𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑤𐑦𐑖 𐑯 𐑞 𐑮𐑲𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑩𐑥𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑟. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞𐑱 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑲𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑩𐑜𐑮𐑰 𐑦𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑺 𐑜𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑓𐑰𐑗𐑼𐑟; 𐑯𐑹 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑞𐑺 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑩 𐑕𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑩𐑤 𐑛𐑦𐑑𐑻𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑑 𐑓𐑨𐑒𐑑 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑑 𐑜𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑩 𐑮𐑨𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯. 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑲 𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑕𐑳𐑚𐑛𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑠𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑚𐑱𐑕𐑑 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑒𐑤𐑵𐑕𐑦𐑝 𐑛𐑦𐑓𐑼𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑛𐑦𐑐𐑸𐑑𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑯𐑨𐑗𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑣𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑦 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑕𐑴 𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑑. 𐑞 𐑮𐑲𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑚𐑰 𐑧𐑤𐑕𐑢𐑺 𐑑𐑮𐑰𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑝 𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑤𐑧𐑙𐑔, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑮𐑧𐑓𐑼𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑑 𐑦𐑤𐑵𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑱𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 𐑢𐑱𐑤.

·𐑚𐑫𐑒 𐑲. (𐑓𐑴𐑤𐑦𐑴), ·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 III. (𐑓𐑦𐑯-𐑚𐑨𐑒).—𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑲 𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑩 𐑥𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑼 𐑢𐑦𐑗, 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑝𐑺𐑾𐑕 𐑯𐑱𐑥𐑟 𐑝 ·𐑓𐑦𐑯-𐑚𐑨𐑒, ·𐑑𐑷𐑤-·𐑕𐑐𐑬𐑑, 𐑯 ·𐑤𐑪𐑙-·𐑡𐑪𐑯, 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑕𐑰𐑯 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑕𐑰 𐑯 𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑣𐑵𐑟 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑡𐑧𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑴 𐑪𐑓𐑩𐑯 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑐𐑨𐑕𐑦𐑯𐑡𐑼𐑟 𐑒𐑮𐑪𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑞 ·𐑩𐑑𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑒, 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑯𐑿 ·𐑘𐑹𐑒 𐑐𐑨𐑒𐑩𐑑-𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑒𐑕. 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑤𐑧𐑙𐑔 𐑣𐑰 𐑩𐑑𐑱𐑯𐑟, 𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑰𐑯, 𐑞 ·𐑓𐑦𐑯-𐑚𐑨𐑒 𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑧𐑥𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑞 𐑮𐑲𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑝 𐑩 𐑤𐑧𐑕 𐑐𐑹𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑜𐑻𐑔, 𐑯 𐑩 𐑤𐑲𐑑𐑼 𐑒𐑳𐑤𐑼, 𐑩𐑐𐑮𐑴𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑪𐑤𐑦𐑝. 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑤𐑦𐑐𐑕 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑩 𐑒𐑱𐑚𐑩𐑤-𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑨𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑, 𐑓𐑹𐑥𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑑𐑢𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙, 𐑕𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑟 𐑝 𐑤𐑸𐑡 𐑮𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑟. 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑜𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑢𐑦𐑖𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑰𐑗𐑼, 𐑞 𐑓𐑦𐑯, 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑣𐑰 𐑛𐑦𐑮𐑲𐑝𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑱𐑥, 𐑦𐑟 𐑪𐑓𐑩𐑯 𐑩 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑩𐑕 𐑪𐑚𐑡𐑧𐑒𐑑. 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑓𐑦𐑯 𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑹 𐑓𐑹 𐑓𐑰𐑑 𐑤𐑪𐑙, 𐑜𐑮𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑝𐑻𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑦 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑐𐑸𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑚𐑨𐑒, 𐑝 𐑩𐑯 𐑨𐑙𐑜𐑿𐑤𐑼 𐑖𐑱𐑐, 𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑖𐑸𐑐 𐑐𐑶𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑧𐑯𐑛. 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑓 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑤𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑐𐑸𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑰𐑗𐑼 𐑚𐑰 𐑝𐑦𐑟𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤, 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑲𐑕𐑩𐑤𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑓𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑤, 𐑨𐑑 𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟, 𐑚𐑰 𐑕𐑰𐑯 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑡𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑕𐑻𐑓𐑦𐑕. 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑰 𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑪𐑛𐑼𐑩𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑭𐑥, 𐑯 𐑕𐑤𐑲𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑥𐑸𐑒𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑕𐑓𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑩𐑤𐑟, 𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑯𐑴𐑥𐑩𐑯-𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑓𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑳𐑐 𐑯 𐑒𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑕 𐑖𐑨𐑛𐑴𐑟 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑮𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑕𐑻𐑓𐑦𐑕, 𐑦𐑑 𐑥𐑱 𐑢𐑧𐑤 𐑚𐑰 𐑕𐑩𐑐𐑴𐑟𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼𐑦 𐑕𐑻𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑼𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑧𐑥𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑩 𐑛𐑲𐑩𐑤, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑕𐑑𐑲𐑤 𐑯 𐑢𐑱𐑝𐑦 𐑬𐑼-𐑤𐑲𐑯𐑟 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑝𐑛 𐑪𐑯 𐑦𐑑. 𐑪𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑟-𐑛𐑲𐑩𐑤 𐑞 𐑖𐑨𐑛𐑴 𐑪𐑓𐑩𐑯 𐑜𐑴𐑟 𐑚𐑨𐑒. 𐑞 ·𐑓𐑦𐑯-𐑚𐑨𐑒 𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑜𐑮𐑦𐑜𐑺𐑾𐑕. 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑟 𐑩 𐑢𐑱𐑤-𐑣𐑱𐑑𐑼, 𐑨𐑟 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑸 𐑥𐑨𐑯-𐑣𐑱𐑑𐑼𐑟. 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑖𐑲; 𐑷𐑤𐑢𐑱𐑟 𐑜𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑪𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑼𐑦; 𐑳𐑯𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑲𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑻𐑓𐑦𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑴𐑑𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑯 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑤𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼𐑟; 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑯 𐑕𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑩𐑤 𐑤𐑪𐑓𐑑𐑦 𐑡𐑧𐑑 𐑮𐑲𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑑𐑷𐑤 𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑔𐑮𐑪𐑐𐑦𐑒 𐑕𐑐𐑽 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑩 𐑚𐑨𐑮𐑩𐑯 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑯; 𐑜𐑦𐑓𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑕 𐑐𐑬𐑼 𐑯 𐑝𐑦𐑤𐑪𐑕𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑢𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑙, 𐑨𐑟 𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑓𐑲 𐑷𐑤 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑐𐑼𐑕𐑿𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑥𐑨𐑯; 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑤𐑩𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑔𐑩𐑯 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑟 𐑞 𐑚𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑖𐑑 𐑯 𐑳𐑯𐑒𐑪𐑙𐑒𐑼𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 ·𐑒𐑱𐑯 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑮𐑱𐑕, 𐑚𐑺𐑦𐑙 𐑓 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑸𐑒 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑲𐑤 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑨𐑒. 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑣𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑰𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑬𐑔, 𐑞 ·𐑓𐑦𐑯-𐑚𐑨𐑒 𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑤𐑵𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑮𐑲𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑩 𐑔𐑽𐑧𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑖𐑰𐑟 𐑛𐑦𐑯𐑪𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑚𐑴𐑯 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑟, 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑰𐑯. 𐑝 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑕𐑴 𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑛 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑚𐑴𐑯 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟, 𐑞𐑺 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑕𐑰𐑥 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑕𐑧𐑝𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑝𐑼𐑲𐑩𐑑𐑦𐑟, 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑝 𐑢𐑦𐑗, 𐑣𐑬𐑧𐑝𐑼, 𐑸 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑯𐑴𐑯. 𐑚𐑮𐑷𐑛-𐑯𐑴𐑟𐑛 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑯 𐑚𐑰𐑒𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟; 𐑐𐑲𐑒-𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟; 𐑚𐑳𐑯𐑗𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟; 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼-𐑡𐑷𐑛 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑯 𐑮𐑪𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟, 𐑸 𐑞 𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑼𐑥𐑧𐑯'𐑟 𐑯𐑱𐑥𐑟 𐑓 𐑩 𐑓𐑿 𐑕𐑹𐑑𐑕.

𐑦𐑯 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑧𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑩𐑐𐑧𐑤𐑧𐑑𐑦𐑝 𐑝 “𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑚𐑴𐑯 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟,” 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑝 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑹𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑑 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑯, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑬𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩 𐑯𐑴𐑥𐑧𐑙𐑒𐑤𐑩𐑗𐑼 𐑥𐑱 𐑚𐑰 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑝𐑰𐑯𐑾𐑯𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑓𐑩𐑕𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑱𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑤𐑵𐑠𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑒𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑝 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟, 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑝𐑱𐑯 𐑑 𐑩𐑑𐑧𐑥𐑐𐑑 𐑩 𐑒𐑤𐑽 𐑒𐑤𐑨𐑕𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑒𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑤𐑩𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑔𐑩𐑯, 𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑲𐑞𐑼 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑰𐑯, 𐑹 𐑣𐑳𐑥𐑐, 𐑹 𐑓𐑦𐑯, 𐑹 𐑑𐑰𐑔; 𐑯𐑪𐑑𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑥𐑸𐑒𐑑 𐑐𐑸𐑑𐑕 𐑹 𐑓𐑰𐑗𐑼𐑟 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑪𐑚𐑝𐑾𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑰𐑥 𐑚𐑧𐑑𐑼 𐑩𐑛𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑑 𐑩𐑓𐑹𐑛 𐑞 𐑚𐑱𐑕𐑦𐑕 𐑓 𐑩 𐑮𐑧𐑜𐑿𐑤𐑼 𐑕𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑥 𐑝 ·𐑕𐑧𐑑𐑪𐑤𐑩𐑡𐑦 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑛𐑦𐑑𐑨𐑗𐑑 𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑲𐑯𐑛𐑟, 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕. 𐑣𐑬 𐑞𐑧𐑯? 𐑞 𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑰𐑯, 𐑣𐑳𐑥𐑐, 𐑚𐑨𐑒-𐑓𐑦𐑯, 𐑯 𐑑𐑰𐑔; 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑸 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑣𐑵𐑟 𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑦𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑟 𐑸 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑷𐑤 𐑕𐑹𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟, 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑮𐑦𐑜𐑸𐑛 𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑥𐑱 𐑚𐑰 𐑞 𐑯𐑱𐑗𐑼 𐑝 𐑞𐑺 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑒𐑗𐑼 𐑦𐑯 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑯 𐑥𐑹 𐑦𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑤 𐑐𐑼𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑼𐑟. 𐑞𐑳𐑕, 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑯 𐑞 𐑣𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑚𐑨𐑒𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑰𐑗 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑩 𐑣𐑳𐑥𐑐; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑞 𐑕𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑿𐑛 𐑕𐑰𐑕𐑩𐑟. 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑣𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑚𐑨𐑒𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑯𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑰𐑗 𐑝 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑰𐑯; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑿𐑛 𐑕𐑰𐑕𐑩𐑟. 𐑯 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑡𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑐𐑸𐑑𐑕 𐑩𐑚𐑳𐑝 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑛. 𐑦𐑯 𐑝𐑺𐑾𐑕 𐑕𐑹𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟, 𐑞𐑱 𐑓𐑹𐑥 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑦𐑮𐑧𐑜𐑿𐑤𐑼 𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑚𐑦𐑯𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟; 𐑹, 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑒𐑱𐑕 𐑝 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑛𐑦𐑑𐑨𐑗𐑑, 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑮𐑧𐑜𐑿𐑤𐑼 𐑲𐑕𐑩𐑤𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯; 𐑨𐑟 𐑳𐑑𐑼𐑤𐑦 𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑓𐑲 𐑷𐑤 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑥𐑧𐑔𐑩𐑛𐑲𐑟𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑓𐑹𐑥𐑛 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩 𐑚𐑱𐑕𐑦𐑕. 𐑪𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑮𐑪𐑒 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤-𐑯𐑨𐑗𐑼𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑕 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑕𐑐𐑤𐑦𐑑.

𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑥𐑱 𐑐𐑪𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑰 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑰𐑝𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑, 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑐𐑸𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑩𐑯𐑨𐑑𐑩𐑥𐑦—𐑞𐑺, 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑰𐑕𐑑, 𐑢𐑰 𐑖𐑨𐑤 𐑚𐑰 𐑱𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑑 𐑞 𐑮𐑲𐑑 𐑒𐑤𐑨𐑕𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑒𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯. 𐑯𐑱; 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑔𐑦𐑙, 𐑓 𐑦𐑜𐑟𐑭𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑤, 𐑦𐑟 𐑞𐑺 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑯𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑢𐑱𐑤'𐑟 𐑩𐑯𐑨𐑑𐑩𐑥𐑦 𐑥𐑹 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑰𐑯? 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑢𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑕𐑰𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑰𐑯 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑪𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑒𐑼𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑑 𐑒𐑤𐑨𐑕𐑦𐑓𐑲 𐑞 ·𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑯𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑢𐑱𐑤. 𐑯 𐑦𐑓 𐑿 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑚𐑬𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑝𐑺𐑾𐑕 𐑤𐑩𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑔𐑩𐑯𐑟, 𐑢𐑲 𐑞𐑺 𐑿 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑓𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑩 𐑓𐑦𐑓𐑑𐑾𐑔 𐑐𐑸𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑩𐑝𐑱𐑤𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑥𐑩𐑑𐑲𐑟𐑼 𐑨𐑟 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑟 𐑷𐑤𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑦 𐑦𐑯𐑿𐑥𐑼𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛. 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑱𐑯𐑟? 𐑯𐑳𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑑 𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑦, 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑲𐑼 𐑤𐑦𐑚𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑝𐑪𐑤𐑿𐑥, 𐑯 𐑚𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑹𐑑 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑱. 𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑦𐑟 𐑞 ·𐑚𐑦𐑚𐑤𐑾𐑜𐑮𐑨𐑓𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑥 𐑣𐑽 𐑩𐑛𐑪𐑐𐑑𐑩𐑛; 𐑯 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑞 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑐𐑪𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑩𐑒𐑕𐑰𐑛, 𐑓 𐑦𐑑 𐑩𐑤𐑴𐑯 𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑮𐑨𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤. 𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑴𐑕𐑰𐑛.

·𐑚𐑫𐑒 𐑲. (𐑓𐑴𐑤𐑦𐑴) ·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 IV. (𐑣𐑳𐑥𐑐 𐑚𐑨𐑒).—𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑦𐑟 𐑪𐑓𐑩𐑯 𐑕𐑰𐑯 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑯𐑹𐑞𐑼𐑯 ·𐑩𐑥𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑒𐑴𐑕𐑑. 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑗𐑼𐑛 𐑞𐑺, 𐑯 𐑑𐑴𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑣𐑸𐑚𐑼. 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑩 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑐𐑨𐑒 𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑐𐑧𐑛𐑩𐑤𐑼; 𐑹 𐑿 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑒𐑷𐑤 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑞 ·𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑓𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑯 ·𐑒𐑭𐑕𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑱𐑤. 𐑨𐑑 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑮𐑱𐑑, 𐑞 𐑐𐑪𐑐𐑿𐑤𐑼 𐑯𐑱𐑥 𐑓 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑛𐑳𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑩𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑢𐑦𐑖 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑕𐑦𐑯𐑕 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑷𐑤𐑕𐑴 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑩 𐑣𐑳𐑥𐑐 𐑞𐑴 𐑩 𐑕𐑥𐑷𐑤𐑼 𐑢𐑳𐑯. 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑶𐑤 𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑝𐑨𐑤𐑿𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤. 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑰𐑯. 𐑣𐑰 𐑦𐑟 𐑞 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑜𐑱𐑥𐑕𐑩𐑥 𐑯 𐑤𐑲𐑑-𐑣𐑸𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑝 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟, 𐑥𐑱𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑹 𐑜𐑱 𐑓𐑴𐑥 𐑯 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑝 𐑞𐑧𐑥.

·𐑚𐑫𐑒 𐑲. (𐑓𐑴𐑤𐑦𐑴), ·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 V. (𐑮𐑱𐑟𐑼 𐑚𐑨𐑒).—𐑝 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑴𐑯 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑱𐑥. 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑕𐑰𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑨𐑑 𐑩 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑪𐑓 ·𐑒𐑱𐑐 ·𐑣𐑹𐑯. 𐑝 𐑩 𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑲𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑯𐑱𐑗𐑼, 𐑣𐑰 𐑦𐑤𐑵𐑛𐑟 𐑚𐑴𐑔 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑟 𐑯 𐑓𐑦𐑤𐑪𐑕𐑩𐑓𐑼𐑟. 𐑞𐑴 𐑯𐑴 𐑒𐑬𐑼𐑛, 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑖𐑴𐑯 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑐𐑸𐑑 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑨𐑒, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑮𐑲𐑟𐑩𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑖𐑸𐑐 𐑮𐑦𐑡. 𐑤𐑧𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑜𐑴. 𐑲 𐑯𐑴 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑥𐑹 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑯𐑹 𐑛𐑳𐑟 𐑧𐑯𐑦𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦 𐑧𐑤𐑕.

·𐑚𐑫𐑒 𐑲. (𐑓𐑴𐑤𐑦𐑴), ·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 VI. (𐑕𐑳𐑤𐑓𐑼 ·𐑚𐑪𐑑𐑩𐑥).—𐑩𐑯𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑲𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑥𐑩𐑯, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑚𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑑𐑴𐑯 𐑚𐑧𐑤𐑦, 𐑛𐑬𐑑𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑜𐑪𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑱𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑞 ·𐑑𐑸𐑑𐑼𐑾𐑯 𐑑𐑲𐑤𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑛𐑲𐑝𐑦𐑙𐑟. 𐑣𐑰 𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑛𐑩𐑥 𐑕𐑰𐑯; 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑰𐑕𐑑 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑕𐑰𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑧𐑐𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑴𐑑𐑼 𐑕𐑳𐑞𐑼𐑯 𐑕𐑰𐑟, 𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑷𐑤𐑢𐑱𐑟 𐑨𐑑 𐑑𐑵 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑩 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑛𐑦 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑯𐑕. 𐑣𐑰 𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑗𐑱𐑕𐑑; 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑮𐑳𐑯 𐑩𐑢𐑱 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑮𐑴𐑐-𐑢𐑷𐑒𐑕 𐑝 𐑤𐑲𐑯. 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑛𐑦𐑡𐑦𐑟 𐑸 𐑑𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑥. 𐑩𐑛𐑿, ·𐑕𐑳𐑤𐑓𐑼 ·𐑚𐑪𐑑𐑩𐑥! 𐑲 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑕𐑱 𐑯𐑳𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑹 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑑𐑮𐑵 𐑝 𐑘𐑰, 𐑯𐑹 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑞 𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑩𐑕𐑑 ·𐑯𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑑𐑼.

𐑞𐑳𐑕 𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑟 ·𐑚𐑫𐑒 𐑲. (𐑓𐑴𐑤𐑦𐑴), 𐑯 𐑯𐑬 𐑚𐑦𐑜𐑦𐑯𐑟 ·𐑚𐑫𐑒 II. (𐑪𐑒𐑑𐑱𐑝𐑴).

·𐑪𐑒𐑑𐑱𐑝𐑴𐑟.*—𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑦𐑥𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑕 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑝 𐑥𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑨𐑜𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑿𐑛, 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑥𐑱 𐑚𐑰 𐑯𐑳𐑥𐑚𐑼𐑛:—𐑲., 𐑞 ·𐑜𐑮𐑨𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑕; II., 𐑞 ·𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑒 ·𐑓𐑦𐑖; III., 𐑞 ·𐑯𐑸𐑢𐑪𐑤; IV., 𐑞 ·𐑔𐑮𐑨𐑖𐑼; V., 𐑞 ·𐑒𐑦𐑤𐑼.

*𐑢𐑲 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑚𐑫𐑒 𐑝 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑯𐑪𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑞 ·𐑒𐑢𐑹𐑑𐑴 𐑦𐑟 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑯. 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑪𐑟, 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑝 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑹𐑛𐑼, 𐑞𐑴 𐑕𐑥𐑷𐑤𐑼 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑓𐑹𐑥𐑼 𐑹𐑛𐑼, 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼𐑞𐑩𐑤𐑧𐑕 𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑱𐑯 𐑩 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑐𐑹𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑑 𐑤𐑲𐑒𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑑 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑦𐑯 𐑓𐑦𐑜𐑼, 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑞 𐑚𐑫𐑒𐑚𐑲𐑯𐑛𐑼'𐑟 ·𐑒𐑢𐑹𐑑𐑴 𐑝𐑪𐑤𐑿𐑥 𐑦𐑯 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑛𐑦𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑓𐑹𐑥 𐑛𐑳𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑻𐑝 𐑞 𐑖𐑱𐑐 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑓𐑴𐑤𐑦𐑴 𐑝𐑪𐑤𐑿𐑥, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑪𐑒𐑑𐑱𐑝𐑴 𐑝𐑪𐑤𐑿𐑥 𐑛𐑳𐑟.

·𐑚𐑫𐑒 II. (𐑪𐑒𐑑𐑱𐑝𐑴), ·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 𐑲. (𐑜𐑮𐑨𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑕).—𐑞𐑴 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑓𐑦𐑖, 𐑣𐑵𐑟 𐑤𐑬𐑛 𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑹𐑩𐑕 𐑚𐑮𐑰𐑞𐑦𐑙, 𐑹 𐑮𐑭𐑞𐑼 𐑚𐑤𐑴𐑦𐑙, 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑓𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑖𐑑 𐑩 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑝𐑻𐑚 𐑑 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟𐑥𐑧𐑯, 𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑴 𐑢𐑧𐑤 𐑯𐑴𐑯 𐑩 𐑛𐑧𐑯𐑦𐑟𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑛𐑰𐑐, 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑐𐑪𐑐𐑿𐑤𐑼𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑐𐑩𐑟𐑧𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑝 𐑓𐑰𐑗𐑼𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑤𐑩𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑔𐑩𐑯, 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑯𐑨𐑗𐑼𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑕 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑩𐑜𐑯𐑲𐑟𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑓 𐑢𐑳𐑯. 𐑣𐑰 𐑦𐑟 𐑝 𐑥𐑪𐑛𐑼𐑩𐑑 𐑪𐑒𐑑𐑱𐑝𐑴 𐑕𐑲𐑟, 𐑝𐑺𐑦𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑓𐑦𐑓𐑑𐑰𐑯 𐑑 𐑑𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑦-𐑓𐑲𐑝 𐑓𐑰𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑤𐑧𐑙𐑔, 𐑯 𐑝 𐑒𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑪𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑛𐑦𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑕𐑑. 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑢𐑦𐑥𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑻𐑛𐑟; 𐑣𐑰 𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑮𐑧𐑜𐑿𐑤𐑼𐑤𐑦 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛, 𐑞𐑴 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑶𐑤 𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑼𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑑𐑦, 𐑯 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑓 𐑤𐑲𐑑. 𐑚𐑲 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑼𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑩𐑐𐑮𐑴𐑗 𐑦𐑟 𐑮𐑦𐑜𐑸𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑨𐑟 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑪𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑼𐑦 𐑝 𐑞 𐑩𐑛𐑝𐑭𐑯𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 𐑢𐑱𐑤.

·𐑚𐑫𐑒 II. (𐑪𐑒𐑑𐑱𐑝𐑴), ·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 II. (𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑒 ·𐑓𐑦𐑖).—𐑲 𐑜𐑦𐑝 𐑞 𐑐𐑪𐑐𐑿𐑤𐑼 𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑼𐑥𐑧𐑯'𐑟 𐑯𐑱𐑥𐑟 𐑓 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑓𐑦𐑖, 𐑓 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑞𐑱 𐑸 𐑞 𐑚𐑧𐑕𐑑. 𐑢𐑺 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑯𐑱𐑥 𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑝𐑱𐑜 𐑹 𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑦𐑝, 𐑲 𐑖𐑨𐑤 𐑕𐑱 𐑕𐑴, 𐑯 𐑕𐑩𐑡𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑩𐑯𐑳𐑞𐑼. 𐑲 𐑛𐑵 𐑕𐑴 𐑯𐑬, 𐑑𐑳𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑞 ·𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑒 ·𐑓𐑦𐑖, 𐑕𐑴-𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑛, 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑪𐑟 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑒𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑦𐑟 𐑞 𐑮𐑵𐑤 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟. 𐑕𐑴, 𐑒𐑷𐑤 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑞 ·𐑣𐑲𐑰𐑯𐑩 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑦𐑓 𐑿 𐑐𐑤𐑰𐑟. 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑝𐑼𐑨𐑕𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑧𐑤 𐑯𐑴𐑯, 𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑕𐑻𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑕 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑼 𐑨𐑙𐑜𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑤𐑦𐑐𐑕 𐑸 𐑒𐑻𐑝𐑛 𐑳𐑐𐑢𐑼𐑛𐑟, 𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑟 𐑩𐑯 𐑧𐑝𐑼𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙 ·𐑥𐑧𐑓𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑓𐑰𐑤𐑾𐑯 𐑜𐑮𐑦𐑯 𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑱𐑕. 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑨𐑝𐑼𐑦𐑡𐑩𐑟 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑰𐑯 𐑹 𐑱𐑑𐑰𐑯 𐑓𐑰𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑤𐑧𐑙𐑔. 𐑣𐑰 𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑤𐑨𐑑𐑦𐑑𐑿𐑛𐑟. 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑩 𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑽 𐑢𐑱 𐑝 𐑖𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑛𐑹𐑕𐑩𐑤 𐑣𐑫𐑒𐑑 𐑓𐑦𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑢𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑙, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑕 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 ·𐑮𐑴𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑯𐑴𐑟. 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑥𐑹 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑓𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑶𐑛, 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑟 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑗𐑼 𐑞 ·𐑣𐑲𐑰𐑯𐑩 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑑 𐑒𐑰𐑐 𐑳𐑐 𐑞 𐑕𐑩𐑐𐑤𐑲 𐑝 𐑗𐑰𐑐 𐑶𐑤 𐑓 𐑛𐑩𐑥𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑶𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑—𐑨𐑟 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑓𐑮𐑵𐑜𐑩𐑤 𐑣𐑬𐑕𐑒𐑰𐑐𐑼𐑟, 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑨𐑚𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑝 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑦, 𐑯 𐑒𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑩𐑤𐑴𐑯 𐑚𐑲 𐑞𐑧𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑝𐑟, 𐑚𐑻𐑯 𐑳𐑯𐑕𐑱𐑝𐑼𐑦 𐑑𐑨𐑤𐑴 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑛 𐑝 𐑴𐑛𐑼𐑩𐑕 𐑢𐑨𐑒𐑕. 𐑞𐑴 𐑞𐑺 𐑚𐑤𐑳𐑚𐑼 𐑦𐑟 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑔𐑦𐑯, 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑝 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑘𐑰𐑤𐑛 𐑿 𐑳𐑐𐑢𐑼𐑛𐑟 𐑝 𐑔𐑻𐑑𐑦 𐑜𐑨𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑶𐑤.

·𐑚𐑫𐑒 II. (𐑪𐑒𐑑𐑱𐑝𐑴), ·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 III. (𐑯𐑸𐑢𐑪𐑤), 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑟, ·𐑯𐑪𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑱𐑤.—𐑩𐑯𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑝 𐑩 𐑒𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑾𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑯𐑱𐑥𐑛 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑕𐑴 𐑯𐑱𐑥𐑛 𐑲 𐑕𐑩𐑐𐑴𐑟 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑽 𐑣𐑹𐑯 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑼𐑦𐑡𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑓 𐑩 𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑑 𐑯𐑴𐑟. 𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑰𐑗𐑼 𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑰𐑯 𐑓𐑰𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑤𐑧𐑙𐑔, 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑣𐑹𐑯 𐑨𐑝𐑼𐑦𐑡𐑩𐑟 𐑓𐑲𐑝 𐑓𐑰𐑑, 𐑞𐑴 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑰𐑛 𐑑𐑧𐑯, 𐑯 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑩𐑑𐑱𐑯 𐑑 𐑓𐑦𐑓𐑑𐑰𐑯 𐑓𐑰𐑑. 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑦𐑙, 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑣𐑹𐑯 𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑩 𐑤𐑧𐑙𐑔𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑑𐑳𐑕𐑒, 𐑜𐑮𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑬𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑡𐑷 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑤𐑲𐑯 𐑩 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑛𐑦𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑣𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑼 𐑕𐑲𐑛, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑤 𐑦𐑓𐑧𐑒𐑑, 𐑜𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑴𐑯𐑼 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑯𐑨𐑤𐑩𐑜𐑩𐑕 𐑑 𐑞 𐑨𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑 𐑝 𐑩 𐑒𐑤𐑳𐑥𐑟𐑦 𐑤𐑧𐑓𐑑-𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑥𐑨𐑯. 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑲𐑕 𐑐𐑻𐑐𐑩𐑕 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑲𐑝𐑼𐑦 𐑣𐑹𐑯 𐑹 𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑕 𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑼𐑟, 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑚𐑰 𐑣𐑸𐑛 𐑑 𐑕𐑱. 𐑦𐑑 𐑛𐑳𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑥 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑿𐑟𐑛 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑞 𐑚𐑤𐑱𐑛 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑹𐑛-𐑓𐑦𐑖 𐑯 𐑚𐑦𐑤-𐑓𐑦𐑖; 𐑞𐑴 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑼𐑟 𐑑𐑧𐑤 𐑥𐑰 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑯𐑸𐑢𐑪𐑤 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑶𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑓 𐑩 𐑮𐑱𐑒 𐑦𐑯 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑞 𐑚𐑪𐑑𐑩𐑥 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑰 𐑓 𐑓𐑵𐑛. ·𐑗𐑸𐑤𐑦 ·𐑒𐑪𐑓𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑿𐑟𐑛 𐑓 𐑩𐑯 𐑲𐑕-𐑐𐑽𐑕𐑼; 𐑓 𐑞 ·𐑯𐑸𐑢𐑪𐑤, 𐑮𐑲𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑻𐑓𐑦𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑴𐑤𐑼 ·𐑕𐑰, 𐑯 𐑓𐑲𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑑 𐑖𐑰𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑲𐑕, 𐑔𐑮𐑳𐑕𐑑𐑕 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑹𐑯 𐑳𐑐, 𐑯 𐑕𐑴 𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑒𐑕 𐑔𐑮𐑵. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑿 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑵𐑝 𐑲𐑞𐑼 𐑝 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑕𐑼𐑥𐑲𐑟𐑩𐑟 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑒𐑼𐑧𐑒𐑑. 𐑥𐑲 𐑴𐑯 𐑩𐑐𐑦𐑯𐑘𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑟, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑬𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑳𐑯-𐑕𐑲𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑣𐑹𐑯 𐑥𐑱 𐑮𐑾𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑰 𐑿𐑟𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 ·𐑯𐑸𐑢𐑪𐑤—𐑣𐑬𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑱 𐑚𐑰—𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑰 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑝𐑰𐑯𐑾𐑯𐑑 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑓 𐑩 𐑓𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑼 𐑦𐑯 𐑮𐑰𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑐𐑨𐑥𐑓𐑤𐑩𐑑𐑕. 𐑞 ·𐑯𐑸𐑢𐑪𐑤 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑣𐑻𐑛 𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑛 𐑞 ·𐑑𐑳𐑕𐑒𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑞 ·𐑣𐑹𐑯𐑛 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑿𐑯𐑦𐑒𐑹𐑯 𐑢𐑱𐑤. 𐑣𐑰 𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑩 𐑒𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑾𐑕 𐑦𐑜𐑟𐑭𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑿𐑯𐑦𐑒𐑹𐑯𐑦𐑟𐑩𐑥 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑒𐑦𐑙𐑛𐑩𐑥 𐑝 𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑥𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑯𐑱𐑗𐑼. 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑒𐑤𐑶𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑛 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑷𐑔𐑼𐑟 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑜𐑨𐑞𐑼𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑕𐑰-𐑿𐑯𐑦𐑒𐑹𐑯'𐑟 𐑣𐑹𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑱𐑯𐑗𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑛𐑱𐑟 𐑮𐑦𐑜𐑸𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑛𐑴𐑑 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑐𐑶𐑟𐑩𐑯, 𐑯 𐑨𐑟 𐑕𐑳𐑗, 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑐𐑼𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑦𐑑 𐑚𐑮𐑷𐑑 𐑦𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑕 𐑐𐑮𐑲𐑕𐑩𐑟. 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑷𐑤𐑕𐑴 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤𐑛 𐑑 𐑩 𐑝𐑪𐑤𐑩𐑑𐑲𐑤 𐑕𐑷𐑤𐑑𐑕 𐑓 𐑓𐑱𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑤𐑱𐑛𐑦𐑟, 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑢𐑱 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑣𐑹𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑥𐑱𐑤 𐑛𐑽 𐑸 𐑥𐑨𐑯𐑿𐑓𐑨𐑒𐑗𐑼𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑣𐑸𐑑𐑕𐑣𐑹𐑯. 𐑼𐑦𐑡𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑦𐑑𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑩𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑩𐑯 𐑪𐑚𐑡𐑧𐑒𐑑 𐑝 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑒𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑦𐑪𐑕𐑦𐑑𐑦. 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑒 ·𐑤𐑧𐑑𐑼 𐑑𐑧𐑤𐑟 𐑥𐑰 𐑞𐑨𐑑 ·𐑕𐑻 ·𐑥𐑸𐑑𐑦𐑯 ·𐑓𐑮𐑴𐑚𐑦𐑖𐑼 𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑻𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑝𐑶𐑦𐑡, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑯 ·𐑚𐑧𐑕 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑜𐑨𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑢𐑱𐑝 𐑣𐑻 𐑡𐑵𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑩 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑴 𐑝 ·𐑜𐑮𐑧𐑯𐑦𐑗 ·𐑐𐑨𐑤𐑩𐑕, 𐑨𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑛 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑑𐑧𐑥𐑟; “𐑢𐑧𐑯 ·𐑕𐑻 ·𐑥𐑸𐑑𐑦𐑯 𐑮𐑩𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑝𐑶𐑦𐑡,” 𐑕𐑧𐑔 ·𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑒 ·𐑤𐑧𐑑𐑼, “𐑪𐑯 𐑚𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑯𐑰𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑑 𐑣𐑻 𐑣𐑲𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑩 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑛𐑦𐑡𐑩𐑕 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑣𐑹𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑯𐑸𐑢𐑪𐑤, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑓 𐑩 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑐𐑽𐑾𐑛 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑣𐑳𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑒𐑭𐑕𐑩𐑤 𐑨𐑑 ·𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑟𐑼.” 𐑩𐑯 ·𐑲𐑮𐑦𐑖 𐑷𐑔𐑼 𐑩𐑝𐑻𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑻𐑤 𐑝 ·𐑤𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑼, 𐑪𐑯 𐑚𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑯𐑰𐑟, 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑤𐑲𐑒𐑢𐑲𐑟 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑑 𐑣𐑻 𐑣𐑲𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑩𐑯𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑣𐑹𐑯, 𐑐𐑼𐑑𐑱𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑩 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑚𐑰𐑕𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑿𐑯𐑦𐑒𐑹𐑯 𐑯𐑱𐑗𐑼.

𐑞 ·𐑯𐑸𐑢𐑪𐑤 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑩 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑗𐑼𐑧𐑕𐑒, 𐑤𐑧𐑐𐑼𐑛-𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑤𐑫𐑒, 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑩 𐑥𐑦𐑤𐑒-𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑜𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑒𐑳𐑤𐑼, 𐑛𐑪𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑯 𐑪𐑚𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑕𐑐𐑪𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑒. 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑶𐑤 𐑦𐑟 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑕𐑵𐑐𐑽𐑽, 𐑒𐑤𐑽 𐑯 𐑓𐑲𐑯; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑦𐑟 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑦𐑑, 𐑯 𐑣𐑰 𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑛𐑩𐑥 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛. 𐑣𐑰 𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑼𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑴𐑤𐑼 𐑕𐑰𐑟.

·𐑚𐑫𐑒 II. (𐑪𐑒𐑑𐑱𐑝𐑴), ·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 IV. (𐑒𐑦𐑤𐑼).—𐑝 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑲𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑯𐑴𐑯 𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑯𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑑𐑼, 𐑯 𐑯𐑳𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑨𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑑 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑓𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑯𐑨𐑗𐑼𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑕𐑑. 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑕𐑰𐑯 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑨𐑑 𐑩 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕, 𐑲 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑕𐑱 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑞 𐑚𐑦𐑜𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑩 𐑜𐑮𐑨𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑕. 𐑣𐑰 𐑦𐑟 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑕𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑡—𐑩 𐑕𐑹𐑑 𐑝 ·𐑝𐑰𐑡𐑰 𐑓𐑦𐑖. 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑕 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 ·𐑓𐑴𐑤𐑦𐑴 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑤𐑦𐑐, 𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑙𐑟 𐑞𐑺 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑤𐑰𐑗, 𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑞 𐑥𐑲𐑑𐑦 𐑚𐑮𐑵𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑳𐑮𐑦𐑛 𐑑 𐑛𐑧𐑔. 𐑞 ·𐑒𐑦𐑤𐑼 𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛. 𐑲 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑣𐑻𐑛 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑹𐑑 𐑝 𐑶𐑤 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑟. 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑧𐑐𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑑 𐑞 𐑯𐑱𐑥 𐑚𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑴𐑛 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑝 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑑𐑯𐑩𐑕. 𐑓 𐑢𐑰 𐑸 𐑷𐑤 𐑒𐑦𐑤𐑼𐑟, 𐑪𐑯 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑯 𐑪𐑯 𐑕𐑰; ·𐑚𐑴𐑯𐑩𐑐𐑸𐑑𐑕 𐑯 ·𐑖𐑸𐑒𐑕 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑤𐑵𐑛𐑩𐑛.

·𐑚𐑫𐑒 II. (𐑪𐑒𐑑𐑱𐑝𐑴), ·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 V. (𐑔𐑮𐑨𐑖𐑼).—𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑱𐑥𐑩𐑕 𐑓 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑑𐑱𐑤, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑣𐑰 𐑿𐑟𐑩𐑟 𐑓 𐑩 𐑓𐑧𐑮𐑵𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑔𐑮𐑨𐑖𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑴𐑟. 𐑣𐑰 𐑥𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑞 ·𐑓𐑴𐑤𐑦𐑴 𐑢𐑱𐑤'𐑟 𐑚𐑨𐑒, 𐑯 𐑨𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑢𐑦𐑥𐑟, 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑻𐑒𐑕 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑨𐑕𐑦𐑡 𐑚𐑲 𐑓𐑤𐑪𐑜𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑥; 𐑨𐑟 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑕𐑒𐑵𐑤𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑟 𐑜𐑧𐑑 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑩 𐑕𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑤𐑼 𐑐𐑮𐑴𐑕𐑧𐑕. 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑤𐑧𐑕 𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑴𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑔𐑮𐑨𐑖𐑼 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑒𐑦𐑤𐑼. 𐑚𐑴𐑔 𐑸 𐑬𐑑𐑤𐑷𐑟, 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑤𐑷𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑕𐑰𐑟.

𐑞𐑳𐑕 𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑟 ·𐑚𐑫𐑒 II. (𐑪𐑒𐑑𐑱𐑝𐑴), 𐑯 𐑚𐑦𐑜𐑦𐑯𐑟 ·𐑚𐑫𐑒 III. (·𐑛𐑘𐑵𐑴𐑛𐑧𐑕𐑦𐑥𐑩𐑤).

·𐑛𐑘𐑵𐑴𐑛𐑧𐑕𐑦𐑥𐑴𐑟.—𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑤𐑵𐑛 𐑞 𐑕𐑥𐑷𐑤𐑼 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟. 𐑲. 𐑞 ·𐑣𐑩𐑟𐑭 ·𐑐𐑹𐑐𐑩𐑕. II. 𐑞 ·𐑨𐑤𐑜𐑩𐑮𐑲𐑯 ·𐑐𐑹𐑐𐑩𐑕. III. 𐑞 ·𐑥𐑰𐑤𐑦-𐑥𐑬𐑞𐑛 ·𐑐𐑹𐑐𐑩𐑕.

𐑑 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑣𐑵 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑗𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑛𐑦 𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑚𐑡𐑧𐑒𐑑, 𐑦𐑑 𐑥𐑱 𐑐𐑪𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑰𐑥 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑰𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑹 𐑹 𐑓𐑲𐑝 𐑓𐑰𐑑 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑚𐑰 𐑥𐑸𐑖𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟—𐑩 𐑢𐑻𐑛, 𐑢𐑦𐑗, 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑐𐑪𐑐𐑿𐑤𐑼 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑕, 𐑷𐑤𐑢𐑱𐑟 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑝𐑱𐑟 𐑩𐑯 𐑲𐑛𐑾 𐑝 𐑣𐑿𐑡𐑯𐑩𐑕. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑰𐑗𐑼𐑟 𐑕𐑧𐑑 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑩𐑚𐑳𐑝 𐑨𐑟 ·𐑛𐑘𐑵𐑴𐑛𐑧𐑕𐑦𐑥𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑸 𐑦𐑯𐑓𐑨𐑤𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟, 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑑𐑻𐑥𐑟 𐑝 𐑥𐑲 𐑛𐑧𐑓𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑩 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑦𐑟—𐑲𐑰 𐑩 𐑕𐑐𐑬𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑦𐑖, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑣𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑑𐑱𐑤.

·𐑚𐑫𐑒 III. (·𐑛𐑘𐑵𐑴𐑛𐑧𐑕𐑦𐑥𐑩𐑤), ·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 1. (𐑣𐑩𐑟𐑭 ·𐑐𐑹𐑐𐑩𐑕).—𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑦𐑟 𐑞 𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑐𐑹𐑐𐑩𐑕 𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑞 𐑜𐑤𐑴𐑚. 𐑞 𐑯𐑱𐑥 𐑦𐑟 𐑝 𐑥𐑲 𐑴𐑯 𐑚𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑴𐑩𐑤; 𐑓 𐑞𐑺 𐑸 𐑥𐑹 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑕𐑹𐑑 𐑝 𐑐𐑹𐑐𐑩𐑕𐑩𐑟, 𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑛𐑳𐑯 𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑢𐑦𐑖 𐑞𐑧𐑥. 𐑲 𐑒𐑷𐑤 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑞𐑳𐑕, 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑪𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑷𐑤𐑢𐑱𐑟 𐑕𐑢𐑦𐑥𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑤𐑺𐑾𐑕 𐑖𐑴𐑤𐑟, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑮𐑷𐑛 𐑕𐑰 𐑒𐑰𐑐 𐑑𐑪𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑧𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑝𐑟 𐑑 𐑣𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 ·𐑓𐑹𐑔-𐑝-𐑡𐑩𐑤𐑲 𐑒𐑮𐑬𐑛. 𐑞𐑺 𐑩𐑐𐑽𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑦𐑟 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑣𐑱𐑤𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑲𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑥𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑯𐑼. 𐑓𐑫𐑤 𐑝 𐑓𐑲𐑯 𐑕𐑐𐑦𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑕, 𐑞𐑱 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑺𐑾𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑚𐑮𐑰𐑟𐑦 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑴𐑟 𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑢𐑼𐑛. 𐑞𐑱 𐑸 𐑞 𐑤𐑨𐑛𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑷𐑤𐑢𐑱𐑟 𐑤𐑦𐑝 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑞 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛. 𐑞𐑱 𐑸 𐑩𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑩 𐑤𐑳𐑒𐑦 𐑴𐑥𐑩𐑯. 𐑦𐑓 𐑿 𐑘𐑹𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑗𐑽𐑟 𐑨𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑝𐑦𐑝𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑕 𐑓𐑦𐑖, 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑣𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑐 𐑘𐑰; 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑦𐑮𐑦𐑑 𐑝 𐑜𐑪𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑜𐑱𐑥𐑕𐑩𐑥𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑘𐑰. 𐑩 𐑢𐑧𐑤-𐑓𐑧𐑛, 𐑐𐑤𐑳𐑥𐑐 ·𐑣𐑩𐑟𐑭 ·𐑐𐑹𐑐𐑩𐑕 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑘𐑰𐑤𐑛 𐑿 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑜𐑨𐑤𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑶𐑤. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞 𐑓𐑲𐑯 𐑯 𐑛𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑑 𐑓𐑤𐑵𐑦𐑛 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑡𐑷𐑟 𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑰𐑛𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑝𐑨𐑤𐑿𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤. 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑡𐑵𐑩𐑤𐑼𐑟 𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑗𐑥𐑱𐑒𐑼𐑟. 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑼𐑟 𐑐𐑫𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑪𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑣𐑴𐑯𐑟. 𐑐𐑹𐑐𐑩𐑕 𐑥𐑰𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑰𐑑𐑦𐑙, 𐑿 𐑯𐑴. 𐑦𐑑 𐑥𐑱 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑩𐑒𐑻𐑛 𐑑 𐑿 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑩 𐑐𐑹𐑐𐑩𐑕 𐑕𐑐𐑬𐑑𐑕. 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑰𐑛, 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑐𐑬𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑴 𐑕𐑥𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑻𐑯𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞 𐑯𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑿 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑩 𐑗𐑭𐑯𐑕, 𐑢𐑪𐑗 𐑣𐑦𐑥; 𐑯 𐑿 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑕𐑰 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 ·𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑗𐑼.

·𐑚𐑫𐑒 III. (·𐑛𐑘𐑵𐑴𐑛𐑧𐑕𐑦𐑥𐑩𐑤), ·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 II. (·𐑨𐑤𐑜𐑩𐑮𐑲𐑯 ·𐑐𐑹𐑐𐑩𐑕).—𐑩 𐑐𐑲𐑮𐑩𐑑. 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑕𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑡. 𐑣𐑰 𐑦𐑟 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛, 𐑲 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒, 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑩𐑕𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑒. 𐑣𐑰 𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑤𐑸𐑡𐑼 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑣𐑩𐑟𐑭 ·𐑐𐑹𐑐𐑩𐑕, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑥𐑱𐑒. 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑝𐑴𐑒 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑯 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑚𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑑 𐑩 𐑖𐑸𐑒. 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑤𐑴𐑼𐑛 𐑓 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑕𐑷 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑗𐑼𐑛.

·𐑚𐑫𐑒 III. (·𐑛𐑘𐑵𐑴𐑛𐑧𐑕𐑦𐑥𐑩𐑤), ·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 III. (𐑥𐑰𐑤𐑦-𐑥𐑬𐑞𐑛 ·𐑐𐑹𐑐𐑩𐑕).—𐑞 𐑤𐑸𐑡𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑒𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑝 ·𐑐𐑹𐑐𐑩𐑕; 𐑯 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑩𐑕𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑒, 𐑕𐑴 𐑓𐑸 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑴𐑯. 𐑞 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 ·𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑤𐑦𐑖 𐑯𐑱𐑥, 𐑚𐑲 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑞𐑼𐑑𐑵 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑛𐑧𐑟𐑦𐑜𐑯𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛, 𐑦𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑼𐑟—·𐑮𐑲𐑑-·𐑢𐑱𐑤 ·𐑐𐑹𐑐𐑩𐑕, 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑕𐑻𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑕 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑦𐑟 𐑗𐑰𐑓𐑤𐑦 𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑝𐑦𐑕𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑 ·𐑓𐑴𐑤𐑦𐑴. 𐑦𐑯 𐑖𐑱𐑐, 𐑣𐑰 𐑛𐑦𐑓𐑼𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑛𐑦𐑜𐑮𐑰 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 ·𐑣𐑩𐑟𐑭 ·𐑐𐑹𐑐𐑩𐑕, 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑩 𐑤𐑧𐑕 𐑮𐑴𐑑𐑳𐑯𐑛 𐑯 𐑡𐑪𐑤𐑦 𐑜𐑻𐑔; 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑰𐑛, 𐑣𐑰 𐑦𐑟 𐑝 𐑒𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑩 𐑯𐑰𐑑 𐑯 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑥𐑩𐑯-𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑓𐑦𐑜𐑼. 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑯𐑴 𐑓𐑦𐑯𐑟 𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑨𐑒 (𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑐𐑹𐑐𐑩𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑝), 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑩 𐑤𐑳𐑝𐑤𐑦 𐑑𐑱𐑤, 𐑯 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤 ·𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑾𐑯 𐑲𐑟 𐑝 𐑩 𐑣𐑱𐑟𐑩𐑤 𐑣𐑿. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑰𐑤𐑦-𐑥𐑬𐑔 𐑕𐑐𐑶𐑤𐑟 𐑷𐑤. 𐑞𐑴 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑲𐑼 𐑚𐑨𐑒 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑓𐑦𐑯𐑟 𐑦𐑟 𐑝 𐑩 𐑛𐑰𐑐 𐑕𐑱𐑚𐑩𐑤, 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑩 𐑚𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑮𐑦 𐑤𐑲𐑯, 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑥𐑸𐑒 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑖𐑦𐑐'𐑕 𐑣𐑳𐑤, 𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑛 𐑞 “𐑚𐑮𐑲𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑕𐑑,” 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑲𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑰𐑒𐑕 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑥 𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑻𐑯, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑑𐑵 𐑕𐑧𐑐𐑼𐑩𐑑 𐑒𐑳𐑤𐑼𐑟, 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑒 𐑩𐑚𐑳𐑝 𐑯 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑴. 𐑞 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑮𐑲𐑟𐑩𐑟 𐑐𐑸𐑑 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑧𐑛, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑣𐑴𐑤 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑬𐑔, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑥𐑱𐑒𐑕 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑤𐑫𐑒 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑓 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑡𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑱𐑐𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑩 𐑓𐑦𐑤𐑴𐑯𐑾𐑕 𐑝𐑦𐑟𐑦𐑑 𐑑 𐑩 𐑥𐑰𐑤-𐑚𐑨𐑜. 𐑩 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑥𐑰𐑯 𐑯 𐑥𐑰𐑤𐑦 𐑨𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑! 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑶𐑤 𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑐𐑹𐑐𐑩𐑕.

* * * * * *

𐑚𐑦𐑘𐑪𐑯𐑛 𐑞 ·𐑛𐑘𐑵𐑴𐑛𐑧𐑕𐑦𐑥𐑩𐑤, 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑕𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑥 𐑛𐑳𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑴𐑕𐑰𐑛, 𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑟𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑹𐑐𐑩𐑕 𐑦𐑟 𐑞 𐑕𐑥𐑷𐑤𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟. 𐑩𐑚𐑳𐑝, 𐑿 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 ·𐑤𐑩𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑔𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑯𐑴𐑑. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑸 𐑩 𐑮𐑨𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑳𐑯𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑯, 𐑓𐑿𐑡𐑩𐑑𐑦𐑝, 𐑣𐑭𐑓-𐑓𐑨𐑚𐑿𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟, 𐑢𐑦𐑗, 𐑨𐑟 𐑩𐑯 ·𐑩𐑥𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑥𐑩𐑯, 𐑲 𐑯𐑴 𐑚𐑲 𐑮𐑧𐑐𐑿𐑑𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑐𐑻𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑤𐑦. 𐑲 𐑖𐑨𐑤 𐑦𐑯𐑿𐑥𐑼𐑱𐑑 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑚𐑲 𐑞𐑺 𐑓𐑹-𐑒𐑭𐑕𐑩𐑤 𐑨𐑐𐑩𐑤𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟; 𐑓 𐑐𐑪𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩 𐑤𐑦𐑕𐑑 𐑥𐑱 𐑚𐑰 𐑝𐑨𐑤𐑿𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑑 𐑓𐑿𐑗𐑼 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑜𐑱𐑑𐑼𐑟, 𐑣𐑵 𐑥𐑱 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑰𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑣𐑽 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑜𐑳𐑯. 𐑦𐑓 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑝 𐑞 𐑓𐑪𐑤𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟, 𐑖𐑨𐑤 𐑣𐑽𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑚𐑰 𐑒𐑷𐑑 𐑯 𐑥𐑸𐑒𐑑, 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑰 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑹𐑐𐑼𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞𐑦𐑕 ·𐑕𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑥, 𐑩𐑒𐑹𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 ·𐑓𐑴𐑤𐑦𐑴, ·𐑪𐑒𐑑𐑱𐑝𐑴, 𐑹 ·𐑛𐑘𐑵𐑴𐑛𐑧𐑕𐑦𐑥𐑩𐑤 𐑥𐑨𐑜𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑿𐑛:—𐑞 ·𐑚𐑪𐑑𐑩𐑤-·𐑯𐑴𐑟 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤; 𐑞 ·𐑡𐑳𐑙𐑒 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤; 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑫𐑛𐑦𐑙-·𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑩𐑛 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤; 𐑞 ·𐑒𐑱𐑐 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤; 𐑞 ·𐑤𐑰𐑛𐑦𐑙 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤; 𐑞 ·𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑩𐑯 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤; 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑨𐑜 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤; 𐑞 ·𐑒𐑪𐑐𐑼𐑛 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤; 𐑞 ·𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑓𐑩𐑯𐑑 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤; 𐑞 ·𐑲𐑕𐑚𐑻𐑜 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤; 𐑞 ·𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑜 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤; 𐑞 ·𐑚𐑤𐑵 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤; 𐑧𐑑𐑕 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 ·𐑲𐑕𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑒, ·𐑛𐑳𐑗, 𐑯 𐑴𐑤𐑛 ·𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑤𐑦𐑖 𐑷𐑔𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑟, 𐑞𐑺 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑒𐑢𐑴𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑤𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑳𐑯𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟, 𐑚𐑤𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑷𐑤 𐑥𐑨𐑯𐑼 𐑝 𐑳𐑯𐑒𐑵𐑔 𐑯𐑱𐑥𐑟. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑲 𐑴𐑥𐑦𐑑 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑨𐑟 𐑷𐑤𐑑𐑩𐑜𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑪𐑚𐑕𐑩𐑤𐑰𐑑; 𐑯 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑣𐑸𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑐 𐑕𐑩𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑓 𐑥𐑽 𐑕𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑟, 𐑓𐑫𐑤 𐑝 ·𐑤𐑩𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑔𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑟𐑩𐑥, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑕𐑦𐑜𐑯𐑦𐑓𐑲𐑦𐑙 𐑯𐑳𐑔𐑦𐑙.

𐑓𐑲𐑯𐑩𐑤𐑦: 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑬𐑑𐑕𐑧𐑑, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑕𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑥 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑣𐑽, 𐑯 𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑕, 𐑐𐑼𐑓𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑛. 𐑿 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑰 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑒𐑧𐑐𐑑 𐑥𐑲 𐑢𐑻𐑛. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑲 𐑯𐑬 𐑤𐑰𐑝 𐑥𐑲 𐑕𐑧𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑡𐑦𐑒𐑨𐑤 ·𐑕𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑥 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑳𐑕 𐑳𐑯𐑓𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑖𐑑, 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 ·𐑒𐑩𐑔𐑰𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑤 𐑝 ·𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑴𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑤𐑧𐑓𐑑, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑱𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑑𐑪𐑐 𐑝 𐑞 𐑳𐑯𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑰𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑑𐑬𐑼. 𐑓 𐑕𐑥𐑷𐑤 𐑦𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑥𐑱 𐑚𐑰 𐑓𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑖𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑞𐑺 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑸𐑒𐑦𐑑𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑕; 𐑜𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑟, 𐑑𐑮𐑵 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑟, 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑤𐑰𐑝 𐑞 𐑒𐑴𐑐𐑕𐑑𐑴𐑯 𐑑 𐑐𐑪𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑦. 𐑜𐑪𐑛 𐑒𐑰𐑐 𐑥𐑰 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑰𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑧𐑯𐑦𐑔𐑦𐑙. 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑣𐑴𐑤 𐑚𐑫𐑒 𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑩 𐑛𐑮𐑭𐑓𐑑—𐑯𐑱, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞 𐑛𐑮𐑭𐑓𐑑 𐑝 𐑩 𐑛𐑮𐑭𐑓𐑑. 𐑴, ·𐑑𐑲𐑥, ·𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑧𐑙𐑔, ·𐑒𐑨𐑖, 𐑯 ·𐑐𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑕!

·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 33. 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑯𐑲𐑛𐑼.

𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑪𐑓𐑦𐑕𐑼𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤-𐑒𐑮𐑭𐑓𐑑, 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑟 𐑨𐑟 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑩 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕 𐑨𐑟 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑑 𐑕𐑧𐑑 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑩 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑛𐑩𐑥𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑦𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑪𐑯 𐑖𐑦𐑐-𐑚𐑹𐑛, 𐑼𐑲𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑦𐑜𐑟𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑽 𐑒𐑤𐑭𐑕 𐑝 𐑪𐑓𐑦𐑕𐑼𐑟, 𐑩 𐑒𐑤𐑭𐑕 𐑳𐑯𐑯𐑴𐑯 𐑝 𐑒𐑹𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑥𐑼𐑰𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤-𐑓𐑤𐑰𐑑.

𐑞 𐑤𐑸𐑡 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑹𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑩𐑑𐑨𐑗𐑑 𐑑 𐑞 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑽'𐑟 𐑝𐑴𐑒𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑓𐑨𐑒𐑑, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑼𐑦𐑡𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑴𐑤𐑛 ·𐑛𐑳𐑗 ·𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑼𐑦, 𐑑𐑵 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑗𐑼𐑦𐑟 𐑯 𐑥𐑹 𐑩𐑜𐑴, 𐑞 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑭𐑯𐑛 𐑝 𐑩 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑦 𐑤𐑪𐑡𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑐𐑻𐑕𐑩𐑯 𐑯𐑬 𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑛 𐑞 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑛𐑦𐑝𐑲𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑢𐑰𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑯 𐑩𐑯 𐑪𐑓𐑦𐑕𐑼 𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑛 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑯𐑲𐑛𐑼. 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑼𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑻𐑛 𐑥𐑰𐑯𐑟 ·𐑓𐑨𐑑-·𐑒𐑳𐑑𐑼; 𐑿𐑕𐑦𐑡, 𐑣𐑬𐑧𐑝𐑼, 𐑦𐑯 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑑 ·𐑗𐑰𐑓 ·𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑽. 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑛𐑱𐑟, 𐑞 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯'𐑟 𐑷𐑔𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑑 𐑞 𐑯𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑜𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑯 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑥𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑡𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑝𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑤; 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤-𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑛𐑦𐑐𐑸𐑑𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑻𐑯𐑟, 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑯𐑲𐑛𐑼 𐑹 ·𐑗𐑰𐑓 ·𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑽 𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑛 𐑕𐑵𐑐𐑮𐑰𐑥. 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑚𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑖 ·𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑯𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛 ·𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑼𐑦, 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑞 𐑒𐑼𐑳𐑐𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑑𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑝 ·𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑾𐑯𐑽, 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑴𐑤𐑛 ·𐑛𐑳𐑗 𐑩𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑱𐑯𐑛, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑹𐑥𐑼 𐑛𐑦𐑜𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑨𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑩𐑚𐑮𐑦𐑡𐑛. 𐑨𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑮𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑕 𐑕𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑦 𐑨𐑟 𐑕𐑰𐑯𐑽 ·𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑽; 𐑯 𐑨𐑟 𐑕𐑳𐑗, 𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯'𐑟 𐑥𐑹 𐑦𐑯𐑓𐑽𐑽 𐑕𐑳𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑑𐑼𐑯𐑟. 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼𐑞𐑩𐑤𐑧𐑕, 𐑨𐑟 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑛𐑳𐑒𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑽𐑟 𐑞 𐑕𐑩𐑒𐑕𐑧𐑕 𐑝 𐑩 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑝𐑶𐑦𐑡 𐑤𐑸𐑡𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑦𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑟, 𐑯 𐑕𐑦𐑯𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑩𐑥𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑯 ·𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑼𐑦 𐑣𐑰 𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑹𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑪𐑓𐑦𐑕𐑼 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑕𐑻𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟 (𐑯𐑲𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑗𐑩𐑟 𐑪𐑯 𐑩 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑜𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛) 𐑞 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑭𐑯𐑛 𐑝 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐'𐑕 𐑛𐑧𐑒 𐑦𐑟 𐑷𐑤𐑕𐑴 𐑣𐑦𐑟; 𐑞𐑺𐑓𐑹 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑐𐑪𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑥𐑨𐑒𐑕𐑦𐑥 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑰 𐑛𐑦𐑥𐑭𐑯𐑛𐑟, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑤𐑦𐑝 𐑩𐑐𐑸𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑞 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑, 𐑯 𐑚𐑰 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑢𐑱 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑢𐑦𐑖𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑞𐑺 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑓𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑵𐑐𐑽𐑽; 𐑞𐑴 𐑷𐑤𐑢𐑱𐑟, 𐑚𐑲 𐑞𐑧𐑥, 𐑓𐑩𐑥𐑦𐑤𐑽𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑦𐑜𐑸𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑨𐑟 𐑞𐑺 𐑕𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑤 𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑩𐑤.

𐑯𐑬, 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑛𐑮𐑷𐑯 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑢𐑰𐑯 𐑪𐑓𐑦𐑕𐑼 𐑯 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑰, 𐑦𐑟 𐑞𐑦𐑕—𐑞 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑤𐑦𐑝𐑟 𐑭𐑓𐑑, 𐑞 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑓𐑹𐑢𐑼𐑛. 𐑣𐑧𐑯𐑕, 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑱𐑤-𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑕 𐑯 𐑥𐑻𐑗𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑩𐑤𐑲𐑒, 𐑞 𐑥𐑱𐑑𐑕 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑞𐑺 𐑒𐑢𐑹𐑑𐑼𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯; 𐑯 𐑕𐑴, 𐑑𐑵, 𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑩𐑥𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑼𐑟 𐑞 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑽𐑟 𐑸 𐑤𐑪𐑡𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑐𐑸𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐. 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑑 𐑕𐑱, 𐑞𐑱 𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑞𐑺 𐑥𐑰𐑤𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯'𐑟 𐑒𐑨𐑚𐑦𐑯, 𐑯 𐑕𐑤𐑰𐑐 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑿𐑯𐑦𐑒𐑱𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑦𐑑.

𐑞𐑴 𐑞 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑐𐑽𐑾𐑛 𐑝 𐑩 ·𐑕𐑳𐑞𐑼𐑯 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑝𐑶𐑦𐑡 (𐑚𐑲 𐑓𐑸 𐑞 𐑤𐑪𐑙𐑜𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑝 𐑷𐑤 𐑝𐑶𐑦𐑡𐑩𐑟 𐑯𐑬 𐑹 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑥𐑨𐑯), 𐑞 𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑽 𐑐𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑤𐑟 𐑝 𐑦𐑑, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑿𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑝 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑝𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑩 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑦, 𐑷𐑤 𐑝 𐑣𐑵𐑥, 𐑣𐑲 𐑹 𐑤𐑴, 𐑛𐑦𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑓 𐑞𐑺 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑓𐑦𐑑𐑕, 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑓𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑡𐑩𐑟, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑤𐑳𐑒, 𐑑𐑩𐑜𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞𐑺 𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑝𐑦𐑡𐑦𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑕, 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑦𐑛𐑦𐑑𐑦, 𐑯 𐑣𐑸𐑛 𐑢𐑻𐑒; 𐑞𐑴 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑛𐑵 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑒𐑱𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑜𐑧𐑑 𐑩 𐑤𐑧𐑕 𐑮𐑦𐑜𐑼𐑩𐑕 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑦𐑐𐑤𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑻𐑗𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑤𐑦; 𐑘𐑧𐑑, 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑥𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑣𐑬 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩𐑯 𐑴𐑤𐑛 ·𐑥𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑐𐑩𐑑𐑱𐑥𐑾𐑯 𐑓𐑨𐑥𐑤𐑦 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑥𐑱, 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑝 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟, 𐑤𐑦𐑝 𐑑𐑩𐑜𐑧𐑞𐑼; 𐑓 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑨𐑑, 𐑞 𐑐𐑳𐑙𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑤𐑾𐑕 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑯𐑩𐑤𐑟, 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑰𐑕𐑑, 𐑝 𐑞 𐑒𐑢𐑹𐑑𐑼-𐑛𐑧𐑒 𐑸 𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑛𐑩𐑥 𐑥𐑩𐑑𐑽𐑾𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑦𐑤𐑨𐑒𐑕𐑑, 𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑯𐑴 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑛𐑳𐑯 𐑩𐑢𐑱. 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑰𐑛, 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑸 𐑞 ·𐑯𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑑 𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑿 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑕𐑰 𐑞 𐑕𐑒𐑦𐑐𐑼 𐑐𐑼𐑱𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑢𐑹𐑑𐑼-𐑛𐑧𐑒 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑤𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑜𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑡𐑼 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑼𐑐𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑥𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑺𐑦 𐑯𐑱𐑝𐑦; 𐑯𐑱, 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑹𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑬𐑑𐑢𐑼𐑛 𐑣𐑪𐑥𐑦𐑡 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑓 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑹 𐑞 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑽𐑾𐑤 𐑐𐑻𐑐𐑩𐑤, 𐑯 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑞 𐑖𐑨𐑚𐑾𐑕𐑑 𐑝 𐑐𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑑-𐑒𐑤𐑪𐑔.

𐑯 𐑞𐑴 𐑝 𐑷𐑤 𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑞 𐑥𐑵𐑛𐑦 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞 𐑤𐑰𐑕𐑑 𐑜𐑦𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑹𐑑 𐑝 𐑖𐑨𐑤𐑴𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑩𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑖𐑩𐑯; 𐑯 𐑞𐑴 𐑞 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑣𐑪𐑥𐑦𐑡 𐑣𐑰 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑦𐑜𐑟𐑨𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑛, 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑦𐑕𐑦𐑑, 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑱𐑯𐑾𐑕 𐑴𐑚𐑰𐑛𐑾𐑯𐑕; 𐑞𐑴 𐑣𐑰 𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑢𐑲𐑼𐑛 𐑯𐑴 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑵𐑝 𐑞 𐑖𐑵𐑟 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑰𐑑 𐑺 𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑒𐑢𐑹𐑑𐑼-𐑛𐑧𐑒; 𐑯 𐑞𐑴 𐑞𐑺 𐑢𐑻 𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑢𐑧𐑯, 𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑽 𐑕𐑻𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑦𐑝𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑣𐑽𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑛𐑰𐑑𐑱𐑤𐑛, 𐑣𐑰 𐑩𐑛𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑦𐑯 𐑳𐑯𐑿𐑠𐑵𐑩𐑤 𐑑𐑻𐑥𐑟, 𐑢𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑝 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑹 𐑦𐑯 𐑑𐑧𐑮𐑼𐑩𐑥, 𐑹 𐑳𐑞𐑼𐑢𐑲𐑟; 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑚𐑲 𐑯𐑴 𐑥𐑰𐑯𐑟 𐑳𐑯𐑩𐑚𐑟𐑻𐑝𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑐𐑨𐑮𐑩𐑥𐑬𐑯𐑑 𐑓𐑹𐑥𐑟 𐑯 𐑿𐑕𐑦𐑡𐑩𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑰.

𐑯𐑹, 𐑐𐑼𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑕, 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑦𐑑 𐑓𐑱𐑤 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑦𐑝𐑧𐑯𐑗𐑵𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑼𐑕𐑰𐑝𐑛, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑣𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑓𐑹𐑥𐑟 𐑯 𐑿𐑕𐑦𐑡𐑩𐑟, 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑻, 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑒𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓; 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑥𐑱𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑿𐑕 𐑝 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑓 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑯 𐑥𐑹 𐑐𐑮𐑲𐑝𐑩𐑑 𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑞𐑱 𐑢𐑻 𐑤𐑦𐑡𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑥𐑩𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑑 𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑕𐑻𐑝. 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑤𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑟𐑩𐑥 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑯, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑳𐑞𐑼𐑢𐑲𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑛𐑦𐑜𐑮𐑰 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑱𐑯𐑛 𐑳𐑯𐑥𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑓𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛; 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑓𐑹𐑥𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑕𐑳𐑤𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑟𐑩𐑥 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑱𐑥 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑸𐑯𐑩𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑑𐑱𐑑𐑼𐑖𐑦𐑐. 𐑓 𐑚𐑰 𐑩 𐑥𐑨𐑯'𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑧𐑒𐑗𐑵𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑵𐑐𐑽𐑦𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑤, 𐑦𐑑 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑩𐑕𐑿𐑥 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑨𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤, 𐑩𐑝𐑱𐑤𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑵𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑥𐑩𐑕𐑦 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑥𐑧𐑯, 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑 𐑞 𐑱𐑛 𐑝 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑕𐑹𐑑 𐑝 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑸𐑑𐑕 𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑧𐑯𐑗𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕, 𐑷𐑤𐑢𐑱𐑟, 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑝𐑟, 𐑥𐑹 𐑹 𐑤𐑧𐑕 𐑐𐑷𐑤𐑑𐑮𐑦 𐑯 𐑚𐑱𐑕. 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑓 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑒𐑰𐑐𐑕 ·𐑜𐑪𐑛'𐑟 𐑑𐑮𐑵 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑧𐑥𐑐𐑲𐑼 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛'𐑟 𐑣𐑳𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙𐑟; 𐑯 𐑤𐑰𐑝𐑟 𐑞 𐑣𐑲𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑪𐑯𐑼𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑺 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑜𐑦𐑝, 𐑑 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑣𐑵 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑓𐑱𐑥𐑩𐑕 𐑥𐑹 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑞𐑺 𐑦𐑯𐑓𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑓𐑽𐑦𐑹𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑑 𐑞 𐑗𐑶𐑕 𐑣𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑓𐑫𐑤 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑛𐑦𐑝𐑲𐑯 ·𐑦𐑯𐑻𐑑, 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑞𐑺 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑬𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑕𐑵𐑐𐑽𐑦𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑛 𐑤𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑞 𐑥𐑨𐑕. 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑤𐑸𐑡 𐑝𐑻𐑗𐑵 𐑤𐑻𐑒𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑕𐑥𐑷𐑤 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑰𐑥 𐑐𐑪𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑵𐑐𐑼𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑞𐑧𐑥, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑮𐑶𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑑 𐑦𐑛𐑾𐑑 𐑦𐑥𐑚𐑩𐑕𐑰𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑞𐑱 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑸𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑐𐑴𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑧𐑯, 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑒𐑱𐑕 𐑝 ·𐑯𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑞 ·𐑑𐑕𐑸, 𐑞 𐑮𐑦𐑙𐑛 𐑒𐑮𐑬𐑯 𐑝 𐑡𐑾𐑜𐑮𐑨𐑓𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑧𐑥𐑐𐑲𐑼 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑻𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑽𐑾𐑤 𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑯; 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑞 𐑐𐑤𐑦𐑚𐑾𐑯 𐑣𐑻𐑛𐑟 𐑒𐑮𐑬𐑗 𐑩𐑚𐑱𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑞 𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑕 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑩𐑤𐑲𐑟𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯. 𐑯𐑹, 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑞 𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑡𐑦𐑒 𐑛𐑮𐑨𐑥𐑩𐑑𐑦𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑵 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑛𐑦𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑑 𐑥𐑹𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑪𐑥𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑓𐑫𐑤𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑢𐑰𐑐 𐑯 𐑛𐑦𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑑 𐑕𐑢𐑦𐑙, 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑓𐑼𐑜𐑧𐑑 𐑩 𐑣𐑦𐑯𐑑, 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑴 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑹𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑸𐑑, 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑯𐑬 𐑩𐑤𐑵𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑑.

𐑚𐑳𐑑 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚, 𐑥𐑲 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯, 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑥𐑵𐑝𐑟 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑥𐑰 𐑦𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑣𐑦𐑟 ·𐑯𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑑 𐑜𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑯 𐑖𐑨𐑜𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑕; 𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑧𐑐𐑦𐑕𐑴𐑛 𐑑𐑳𐑗𐑦𐑙 ·𐑧𐑥𐑐𐑼𐑼𐑟 𐑯 ·𐑒𐑦𐑙𐑟, 𐑲 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑰𐑤 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑑 𐑛𐑵 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑐𐑫𐑼 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑢𐑱𐑤-𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑑𐑼 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑣𐑦𐑥; 𐑯, 𐑞𐑺𐑓𐑹, 𐑷𐑤 𐑬𐑑𐑢𐑼𐑛 𐑥𐑩𐑡𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑐𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑯 𐑣𐑬𐑟𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑸 𐑛𐑦𐑯𐑲𐑛 𐑥𐑰. 𐑴, ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚! 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑖𐑨𐑤 𐑚𐑰 𐑜𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑰, 𐑦𐑑 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑯𐑰𐑛𐑟 𐑚𐑰 𐑐𐑤𐑳𐑒𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑕𐑒𐑲𐑟, 𐑯 𐑛𐑲𐑝𐑛 𐑓 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑛𐑰𐑐, 𐑯 𐑓𐑰𐑗𐑼𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑳𐑯𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑺!

·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 34. 𐑞 ·𐑒𐑨𐑚𐑦𐑯-·𐑑𐑱𐑚𐑩𐑤.

𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑵𐑯; 𐑯 ·𐑛𐑴-·𐑚𐑶, 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑿𐑼𐑛, 𐑔𐑮𐑳𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑱𐑤 𐑤𐑴𐑓-𐑝-𐑚𐑮𐑧𐑛 𐑓𐑱𐑕 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑒𐑨𐑚𐑦𐑯-𐑕𐑒𐑳𐑑𐑩𐑤, 𐑩𐑯𐑬𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑛𐑦𐑯𐑼 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑤𐑹𐑛 𐑯 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑼; 𐑣𐑵, 𐑕𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑤𐑰 𐑒𐑢𐑹𐑑𐑼-𐑚𐑴𐑑, 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑡𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑯 𐑪𐑚𐑟𐑼𐑝𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑯; 𐑯 𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑬 𐑥𐑿𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑤𐑨𐑑𐑦𐑑𐑿𐑛 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑥𐑵𐑞, 𐑥𐑦𐑛𐑨𐑤𐑾𐑯-𐑖𐑱𐑐𐑑 𐑑𐑨𐑚𐑤𐑩𐑑, 𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑻𐑝𐑛 𐑓 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑛𐑱𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑻𐑐𐑩𐑕 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑳𐑐𐑼 𐑐𐑸𐑑 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑲𐑝𐑼𐑦 𐑤𐑧𐑜. 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑰𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑑 𐑞 𐑑𐑲𐑛𐑦𐑙𐑟, 𐑿 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑵𐑛𐑦 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑣𐑻𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑰𐑯𐑾𐑤. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦, 𐑒𐑨𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑝 𐑞 𐑥𐑦𐑟𐑩𐑯 𐑖𐑮𐑬𐑛𐑟, 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑢𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑑 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑒, 𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑩𐑯 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯, 𐑳𐑯𐑦𐑜𐑟𐑦𐑤𐑼𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑝𐑶𐑕, 𐑕𐑱𐑦𐑙, “𐑛𐑦𐑯𐑼, ·𐑥𐑼 ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒,” 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑩𐑐𐑽𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑒𐑨𐑚𐑦𐑯.

𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑞 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑧𐑒𐑴 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑳𐑤𐑑𐑩𐑯'𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑐 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑛𐑲𐑛 𐑩𐑢𐑱, 𐑯 ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒, 𐑞 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 ·𐑧𐑥𐑽, 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑮𐑰𐑟𐑩𐑯 𐑑 𐑕𐑩𐑐𐑴𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑰𐑑𐑩𐑛, 𐑞𐑧𐑯 ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒 𐑮𐑬𐑟𐑩𐑟 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑢𐑲𐑩𐑑𐑵𐑛, 𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑕 𐑩 𐑓𐑿 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑟 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑞 𐑐𐑤𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑕, 𐑯, 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑩 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑝 𐑐𐑰𐑐 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑚𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑒𐑩𐑤, 𐑕𐑧𐑟, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑑𐑳𐑗 𐑝 𐑐𐑤𐑧𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑯𐑩𐑕, “𐑛𐑦𐑯𐑼, ·𐑥𐑼 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚,” 𐑯 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑞 𐑕𐑒𐑳𐑑𐑩𐑤. 𐑞 𐑕𐑧𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑛 ·𐑧𐑥𐑽 𐑤𐑬𐑯𐑡𐑩𐑟 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑞 𐑮𐑦𐑜𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑢𐑲𐑤, 𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑕𐑤𐑲𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑖𐑱𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑥𐑱𐑯 𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑕, 𐑑 𐑕𐑰 𐑢𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑚𐑰 𐑷𐑤 𐑮𐑲𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑹𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑮𐑴𐑐, 𐑣𐑰 𐑤𐑲𐑒𐑢𐑲𐑟 𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑕 𐑳𐑐 𐑞 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑚𐑻𐑛𐑩𐑯, 𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑮𐑨𐑐𐑦𐑛 “𐑛𐑦𐑯𐑼, ·𐑥𐑼 ·𐑓𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑒,” 𐑓𐑪𐑤𐑴𐑟 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑮𐑰𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑧𐑕𐑼𐑟.

𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞 𐑔𐑻𐑛 ·𐑧𐑥𐑽, 𐑯𐑬 𐑕𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑷𐑤 𐑩𐑤𐑴𐑯 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑒𐑢𐑹𐑑𐑼-𐑛𐑧𐑒, 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑟 𐑑 𐑓𐑰𐑤 𐑮𐑦𐑤𐑰𐑝𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑒𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑾𐑕 𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑑; 𐑓, 𐑑𐑦𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑷𐑤 𐑕𐑹𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑯𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑕𐑹𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑛𐑦𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟, 𐑯 𐑒𐑦𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑪𐑓 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑖𐑵𐑟, 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑒𐑕 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑩 𐑖𐑸𐑐 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑯𐑶𐑟𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑕𐑒𐑢𐑷𐑤 𐑝 𐑩 𐑣𐑹𐑯𐑐𐑲𐑐 𐑮𐑲𐑑 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑞 ·𐑜𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑛 ·𐑑𐑻𐑒'𐑕 𐑣𐑧𐑛; 𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑚𐑲 𐑩 𐑛𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑩𐑕 𐑕𐑤𐑲𐑑, 𐑐𐑦𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑨𐑐 𐑳𐑐 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑥𐑦𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑪𐑐 𐑓 𐑩 𐑖𐑧𐑤𐑓, 𐑣𐑰 𐑜𐑴𐑟 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑮𐑪𐑤𐑦𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑴 𐑓𐑸 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑰𐑕𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑱𐑯𐑟 𐑝𐑦𐑟𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑒, 𐑮𐑦𐑝𐑻𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑷𐑤 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑕𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟, 𐑚𐑲 𐑚𐑮𐑦𐑙𐑦𐑙 𐑳𐑐 𐑞 𐑮𐑽 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑥𐑿𐑟𐑦𐑒. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑺 𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑒𐑨𐑚𐑦𐑯 𐑛𐑹𐑢𐑱 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑴, 𐑣𐑰 𐑐𐑷𐑟𐑩𐑟, 𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑕 𐑩 𐑯𐑿 𐑓𐑱𐑕 𐑷𐑤𐑑𐑩𐑜𐑧𐑞𐑼, 𐑯, 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑑, 𐑣𐑦𐑤𐑺𐑾𐑕 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 ·𐑓𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑒 𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑟 ·𐑒𐑦𐑙 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚'𐑟 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑕, 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑒𐑨𐑮𐑩𐑒𐑑𐑼 𐑝 ·𐑨𐑚𐑡𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑕, 𐑹 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑤𐑱𐑝.

𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑞 𐑤𐑰𐑕𐑑 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑚𐑮𐑧𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑕 𐑸𐑑𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑤𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑕𐑰-𐑿𐑕𐑦𐑡𐑩𐑟, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑴𐑐𐑩𐑯 𐑺 𐑝 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑒 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑪𐑓𐑦𐑕𐑼𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑤, 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑝𐑩𐑒𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯, 𐑚𐑺 𐑞𐑧𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑝𐑟 𐑚𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑯 𐑛𐑦𐑓𐑲𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑯𐑳𐑓 𐑑𐑩𐑢𐑹𐑛𐑟 𐑞𐑺 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑭𐑯𐑛𐑼; 𐑘𐑧𐑑, 𐑑𐑧𐑯 𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯, 𐑤𐑧𐑑 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑪𐑓𐑦𐑕𐑼𐑟 𐑞 𐑯𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑 𐑥𐑴𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑜𐑴 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑒𐑳𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑥𐑼𐑦 𐑛𐑦𐑯𐑼 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑭𐑯𐑛𐑼'𐑟 𐑒𐑨𐑚𐑦𐑯, 𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑑𐑢𐑱 𐑞𐑺 𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑓𐑧𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑝, 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑑 𐑕𐑱 𐑛𐑧𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑒𐑩𐑑𐑼𐑦 𐑯 𐑣𐑳𐑥𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑺 𐑑𐑩𐑢𐑹𐑛𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑨𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑝 𐑞 𐑑𐑱𐑚𐑩𐑤; 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑸𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑩𐑕, 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤. 𐑢𐑺𐑓𐑹 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑛𐑦𐑓𐑼𐑩𐑯𐑕? 𐑩 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑚𐑤𐑩𐑥? 𐑐𐑼𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑕 𐑯𐑪𐑑. 𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑯 ·𐑚𐑧𐑤𐑖𐑩𐑟𐑸, ·𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑝 ·𐑚𐑨𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑪𐑯; 𐑯 𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑯 ·𐑚𐑧𐑤𐑖𐑩𐑟𐑸, 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑣𐑷𐑑𐑦𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑒𐑻𐑑𐑾𐑕𐑤𐑦, 𐑞𐑺𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑑𐑳𐑗 𐑝 𐑥𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑱𐑯 𐑜𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑡𐑼. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑵 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑮𐑲𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑰𐑜𐑩𐑤 𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑡𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑕𐑐𐑦𐑮𐑦𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑲𐑛𐑟 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑴𐑯 𐑐𐑮𐑲𐑝𐑩𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑯𐑼-𐑑𐑱𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑜𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑕, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑨𐑯'𐑟 𐑳𐑯𐑗𐑨𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑡𐑛 𐑐𐑬𐑼 𐑯 𐑛𐑩𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑾𐑯 𐑝 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑡𐑵𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑯𐑓𐑤𐑵𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑓 𐑞 𐑑𐑲𐑥; 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑨𐑯'𐑟 𐑮𐑶𐑩𐑤𐑑𐑦 𐑝 𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑑 𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑟 ·𐑚𐑧𐑤𐑖𐑩𐑟𐑸'𐑟, 𐑓 ·𐑚𐑧𐑤𐑖𐑩𐑟𐑸 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑕𐑑. 𐑣𐑵 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑕 𐑛𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑟, 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑑𐑱𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 ·𐑕𐑰𐑟𐑼. 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑩 𐑢𐑦𐑗𐑼𐑦 𐑝 𐑕𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑤 𐑑𐑕𐑸𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑞𐑺 𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑴 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙. 𐑯𐑬, 𐑦𐑓 𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑼𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑿 𐑕𐑵𐑐𐑼𐑨𐑛 𐑞 𐑩𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑵𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑥𐑩𐑕𐑦 𐑝 𐑩 𐑖𐑦𐑐-𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑼, 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑚𐑲 𐑦𐑯𐑓𐑼𐑩𐑯𐑕, 𐑿 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑛𐑦𐑮𐑲𐑝 𐑞 𐑒𐑷𐑟 𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑦𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑝 𐑕𐑰-𐑤𐑲𐑓 𐑡𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑛.

𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑲𐑝𐑼𐑦-𐑦𐑯𐑤𐑱𐑛 𐑑𐑱𐑚𐑩𐑤, ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑲𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑥𐑿𐑑, 𐑥𐑱𐑯𐑛 𐑕𐑰-𐑤𐑲𐑩𐑯 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑒𐑪𐑮𐑩𐑤 𐑚𐑰𐑗, 𐑕𐑼𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑹𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑛𐑧𐑓𐑼𐑧𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑤 𐑒𐑳𐑚𐑟. 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑴𐑯 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑐𐑼 𐑑𐑻𐑯, 𐑰𐑗 𐑪𐑓𐑦𐑕𐑼 𐑢𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑕𐑻𐑝𐑛. 𐑞𐑱 𐑢𐑻 𐑨𐑟 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑗𐑦𐑤𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑯 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚; 𐑯 𐑘𐑧𐑑, 𐑦𐑯 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚, 𐑞𐑺 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑑 𐑤𐑻𐑒 𐑞 𐑕𐑥𐑷𐑤𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑤 𐑨𐑮𐑩𐑜𐑩𐑯𐑕. 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑥𐑲𐑯𐑛, 𐑞𐑺 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑲𐑟 𐑷𐑤 𐑓𐑭𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑥𐑨𐑯'𐑟 𐑯𐑲𐑓, 𐑨𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑸𐑝𐑛 𐑞 𐑗𐑰𐑓 𐑛𐑦𐑖 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑣𐑦𐑥. 𐑲 𐑛𐑵 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑩𐑐𐑴𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑓 𐑞 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛 𐑞𐑱 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑐𐑮𐑴𐑓𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑴𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑕𐑤𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑪𐑚𐑟𐑼𐑝𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯, 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑕𐑴 𐑯𐑿𐑑𐑮𐑩𐑤 𐑩 𐑑𐑪𐑐𐑦𐑒 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑢𐑧𐑞𐑼. 𐑯𐑴! 𐑯 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑮𐑰𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑬𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑲𐑓 𐑯 𐑓𐑹𐑒, 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑢𐑰𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑞 𐑕𐑤𐑲𐑕 𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑓 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑤𐑪𐑒𐑑, ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑞𐑺𐑚𐑲 𐑥𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑛 ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒'𐑕 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑑 𐑑𐑩𐑢𐑹𐑛𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑞 𐑥𐑱𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑰𐑝𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑰𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑞𐑴 𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑰𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑭𐑥𐑟; 𐑯 𐑒𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑤𐑦; 𐑯 𐑩 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑓, 𐑐𐑼𐑗𐑨𐑯𐑕, 𐑞 𐑯𐑲𐑓 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑟𐑛 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑞 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑑; 𐑯 𐑗𐑵𐑛 𐑦𐑑 𐑯𐑶𐑟𐑤𐑩𐑕𐑤𐑦; 𐑯 𐑕𐑢𐑪𐑤𐑴𐑛 𐑦𐑑, 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑 𐑕𐑻𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯. 𐑓, 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑞 ·𐑒𐑪𐑮𐑩𐑯𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑚𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑢𐑩𐑑 𐑨𐑑 ·𐑓𐑮𐑭𐑙𐑒𐑓𐑼𐑑, 𐑢𐑺 𐑞 ·𐑡𐑻𐑥𐑩𐑯 ·𐑧𐑥𐑐𐑼𐑼 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑲𐑯𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑕𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑯 ·𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑽𐑾𐑤 ·𐑦𐑤𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑼𐑟, 𐑕𐑴 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑒𐑨𐑚𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑰𐑤𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑣𐑬 𐑕𐑪𐑤𐑩𐑥 𐑥𐑰𐑤𐑟, 𐑰𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑷𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑕; 𐑯 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑑𐑱𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑴𐑤𐑛 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑓𐑼𐑚𐑨𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑝𐑼𐑕𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯; 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑛𐑳𐑥. 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑩 𐑮𐑦𐑤𐑰𐑓 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑑 𐑗𐑴𐑒𐑦𐑙 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑩 𐑮𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑩 𐑕𐑳𐑛𐑩𐑯 𐑮𐑨𐑒𐑩𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑴. 𐑯 𐑐𐑫𐑼 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 ·𐑓𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑒, 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞 𐑘𐑳𐑙𐑜𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑯, 𐑯 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑚𐑶 𐑝 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑽𐑦 𐑓𐑨𐑥𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑸𐑑𐑦. 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑯𐑚𐑴𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑲𐑯 𐑚𐑰𐑓; 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑞 𐑛𐑮𐑳𐑥𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑕. 𐑓 ·𐑓𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑒 𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑿𐑥𐑛 𐑑 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑐 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓, 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑥𐑬𐑯𐑑 𐑑 𐑤𐑸𐑕𐑦𐑯𐑦 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑜𐑮𐑰. 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑐𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑑𐑱𐑚𐑩𐑤, 𐑛𐑬𐑑𐑤𐑩𐑕, 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑥𐑹 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑱𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑑 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑳𐑐 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑪𐑯𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛; 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼𐑞𐑩𐑤𐑧𐑕, 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡 𐑑 𐑕𐑱, ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑓𐑼𐑚𐑨𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥. 𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑛 ·𐑓𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑒 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑐𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓, 𐑞 𐑗𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑢𐑻 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑕𐑴 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑨𐑟 𐑯𐑴𐑑𐑦𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑑. 𐑤𐑰𐑕𐑑 𐑝 𐑷𐑤, 𐑛𐑦𐑛 ·𐑓𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑒 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑿𐑥 𐑑 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑐 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑑 𐑚𐑳𐑑𐑼. 𐑢𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑣𐑰 𐑔𐑷𐑑 𐑞 𐑴𐑯𐑼𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑛𐑦𐑯𐑲𐑛 𐑦𐑑 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑪𐑯 𐑩𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑒𐑤𐑪𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑤𐑽, 𐑕𐑳𐑯𐑦 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑧𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯; 𐑹 𐑢𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑣𐑰 𐑛𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑, 𐑪𐑯 𐑕𐑴 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑩 𐑝𐑶𐑦𐑡 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑥𐑸𐑒𐑩𐑑𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼𐑟, 𐑚𐑳𐑑𐑼 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑨𐑑 𐑩 𐑐𐑮𐑰𐑥𐑾𐑥, 𐑯 𐑞𐑺𐑓𐑹 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑓 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑩 𐑕𐑳𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑑𐑼𐑯; 𐑣𐑬𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟, ·𐑓𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑒, 𐑩𐑤𐑨𐑕! 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩 𐑚𐑳𐑑𐑼𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑥𐑨𐑯!

𐑩𐑯𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑔𐑦𐑙. 𐑓𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑒 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑐𐑻𐑕𐑩𐑯 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑛𐑦𐑯𐑼, 𐑯 ·𐑓𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑒 𐑦𐑟 𐑞 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑳𐑐. 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑼! 𐑓 𐑣𐑽𐑚𐑲 ·𐑓𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑒'𐑕 𐑛𐑦𐑯𐑼 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑚𐑨𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑡𐑨𐑥𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑐𐑶𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑑𐑲𐑥. 𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒 𐑯 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚 𐑚𐑴𐑔 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑑 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑥; 𐑯 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑞𐑱 𐑷𐑤𐑕𐑴 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑡 𐑝 𐑤𐑬𐑯𐑡𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑮𐑽. 𐑦𐑓 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯, 𐑣𐑵 𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑩 𐑐𐑧𐑜 𐑣𐑲𐑼 𐑞𐑨𐑯 ·𐑓𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑒, 𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑩 𐑕𐑥𐑷𐑤 𐑨𐑐𐑩𐑑𐑲𐑑, 𐑯 𐑕𐑵𐑯 𐑖𐑴𐑟 𐑕𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑑𐑩𐑥𐑟 𐑝 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑒𐑤𐑵𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑭𐑕𐑑, 𐑞𐑧𐑯 ·𐑓𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑒 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑻 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓, 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑜𐑧𐑑 𐑥𐑹 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑥𐑬𐑔𐑓𐑫𐑤𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑛𐑱; 𐑓 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑦 𐑿𐑕𐑦𐑡 𐑓 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚 𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑰𐑛 ·𐑓𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑒 𐑑 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑒. 𐑞𐑺𐑓𐑹 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 ·𐑓𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑒 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑕 𐑩𐑛𐑥𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑐𐑮𐑲𐑝𐑩𐑑, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑕𐑦𐑯𐑕 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑼𐑦𐑟𐑩𐑯 𐑑 𐑞 𐑛𐑦𐑜𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑝 𐑩𐑯 𐑪𐑓𐑦𐑕𐑼, 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑴𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑯𐑴𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑳𐑞𐑼𐑢𐑲𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑣𐑳𐑙𐑜𐑮𐑦, 𐑥𐑹 𐑹 𐑤𐑧𐑕. 𐑓 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑱𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑴 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑮𐑦𐑤𐑰𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑳𐑙𐑜𐑼, 𐑨𐑟 𐑒𐑰𐑐 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑥𐑹𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥. 𐑐𐑰𐑕 𐑯 𐑕𐑨𐑑𐑦𐑕𐑓𐑨𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯, 𐑔𐑷𐑑 ·𐑓𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑒, 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑓 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑛𐑦𐑐𐑸𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑥𐑲 𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑥𐑩𐑒. 𐑲 𐑨𐑥 𐑩𐑯 𐑪𐑓𐑦𐑕𐑼; 𐑚𐑳𐑑, 𐑣𐑬 𐑲 𐑢𐑦𐑖 𐑲 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑓𐑦𐑖 𐑩 𐑚𐑦𐑑 𐑝 𐑴𐑤𐑛-𐑓𐑨𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑚𐑰𐑓 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑴𐑒𐑕𐑩𐑤, 𐑨𐑟 𐑲 𐑿𐑕𐑑 𐑑 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑲 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑞 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑. 𐑞𐑺'𐑟 𐑞 𐑓𐑮𐑵𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑥𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑯𐑬; 𐑞𐑺'𐑟 𐑞 𐑝𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑝 𐑜𐑤𐑹𐑦: 𐑞𐑺'𐑟 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑝 𐑤𐑲𐑓! 𐑚𐑦𐑕𐑲𐑛𐑟, 𐑦𐑓 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑻 𐑕𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑥𐑽 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑼 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑩 𐑜𐑮𐑳𐑡 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑕𐑑 ·𐑓𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑒 𐑦𐑯 ·𐑓𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑒'𐑕 𐑩𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑤 𐑒𐑩𐑐𐑨𐑕𐑦𐑑𐑦, 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑼 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑑 𐑛𐑵, 𐑦𐑯 𐑹𐑛𐑼 𐑑 𐑩𐑚𐑑𐑱𐑯 𐑨𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑤 𐑝𐑧𐑯𐑡𐑩𐑯𐑕, 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑑 𐑜𐑴 𐑭𐑓𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑯𐑼-𐑑𐑲𐑥, 𐑯 𐑜𐑧𐑑 𐑩 𐑐𐑰𐑐 𐑨𐑑 ·𐑓𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑒 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑞 𐑒𐑨𐑚𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑒𐑲-𐑤𐑲𐑑, 𐑕𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑦𐑤𐑦 𐑯 𐑛𐑳𐑥𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑛 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑷𐑓𐑩𐑤 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚.

𐑯𐑬, ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑥𐑱𐑑𐑕 𐑓𐑹𐑥𐑛 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑥𐑱 𐑚𐑰 𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑛 𐑞 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑑𐑱𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛'𐑟 𐑒𐑨𐑚𐑦𐑯. 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑞𐑺 𐑛𐑦𐑐𐑸𐑗𐑼, 𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑹𐑛𐑼 𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑼𐑲𐑝𐑩𐑤, 𐑞 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑝𐑩𐑕 𐑒𐑤𐑪𐑔 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑒𐑤𐑽𐑛, 𐑹 𐑮𐑭𐑞𐑼 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑹𐑛 𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑣𐑳𐑮𐑦𐑛 𐑹𐑛𐑼 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑐𐑨𐑤𐑦𐑛 𐑕𐑑𐑿𐑼𐑛. 𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑞 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑽𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑚𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑯 𐑑 𐑞 𐑓𐑰𐑕𐑑, 𐑞𐑱 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑦𐑡𐑫𐑼𐑦 𐑤𐑧𐑜𐑩𐑑𐑰𐑟. 𐑞𐑱 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑩 𐑕𐑹𐑑 𐑝 𐑑𐑧𐑥𐑐𐑼𐑼𐑦 𐑕𐑻𐑝𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕' 𐑣𐑷𐑤 𐑝 𐑞 𐑣𐑲 𐑯 𐑥𐑲𐑑𐑦 𐑒𐑨𐑚𐑦𐑯.

𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑑 𐑞 𐑣𐑸𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑑𐑪𐑤𐑼𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑑 𐑯 𐑯𐑱𐑥𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑦𐑟𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑛𐑪𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑽𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯'𐑟 𐑑𐑱𐑚𐑩𐑤, 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑲𐑼 𐑒𐑺-𐑓𐑮𐑰 𐑤𐑲𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑯 𐑰𐑟, 𐑞 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑛𐑦𐑥𐑪𐑒𐑮𐑩𐑕𐑦 𐑝 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑓𐑽𐑽 𐑓𐑧𐑤𐑴𐑟 𐑞 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑽𐑟. 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑞𐑺 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑟, 𐑞 𐑥𐑱𐑑𐑕, 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑩𐑓𐑮𐑱𐑛 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑝 𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑯𐑡𐑩𐑟 𐑝 𐑞𐑺 𐑴𐑯 𐑡𐑷𐑟, 𐑞 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑽𐑟 𐑗𐑵𐑛 𐑞𐑺 𐑓𐑵𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩 𐑮𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑖 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩 𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑹𐑑 𐑑 𐑦𐑑. 𐑞𐑱 𐑛𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑤𐑹𐑛𐑟; 𐑞𐑱 𐑓𐑦𐑤𐑛 𐑞𐑺 𐑚𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑟 𐑤𐑲𐑒 ·𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑾𐑯 𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑕 𐑷𐑤 𐑛𐑱 𐑤𐑴𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑲𐑕𐑩𐑟. 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑐𐑹𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑕 𐑨𐑐𐑩𐑑𐑲𐑑𐑕 𐑣𐑨𐑛 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜 𐑯 ·𐑑𐑨𐑖𐑑𐑱𐑜𐑴, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑑 𐑓𐑦𐑤 𐑬𐑑 𐑞 𐑝𐑱𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑰𐑝𐑾𐑕 𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑭𐑕𐑑, 𐑪𐑓𐑩𐑯 𐑞 𐑐𐑱𐑤 ·𐑛𐑴-·𐑚𐑶 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑓𐑱𐑯 𐑑 𐑚𐑮𐑦𐑙 𐑪𐑯 𐑩 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑚𐑨𐑮𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑕𐑷𐑤𐑑-𐑡𐑳𐑙𐑒, 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑛 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑪𐑤𐑦𐑛 𐑪𐑒𐑕. 𐑯 𐑦𐑓 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑻 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑤𐑲𐑝𐑤𐑦 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑦𐑑, 𐑦𐑓 𐑣𐑰 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑜𐑴 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑯𐑦𐑥𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑣𐑪𐑐-𐑕𐑒𐑦𐑐-𐑯-𐑡𐑳𐑥𐑐, 𐑞𐑧𐑯 ·𐑑𐑨𐑖𐑑𐑱𐑜𐑴 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑩𐑯 𐑳𐑯𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑢𐑱 𐑝 𐑩𐑒𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑼𐑱𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑚𐑲 𐑛𐑸𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑓𐑹𐑒 𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑨𐑒, 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯-𐑢𐑲𐑟. 𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑕 ·𐑛𐑨𐑜𐑵, 𐑕𐑰𐑟𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑕𐑳𐑛𐑩𐑯 𐑣𐑿𐑥𐑼, 𐑩𐑕𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛 ·𐑛𐑴-·𐑚𐑶'𐑟 𐑥𐑧𐑥𐑼𐑦 𐑚𐑲 𐑕𐑯𐑨𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑳𐑐 𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑦, 𐑯 𐑔𐑮𐑳𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑩 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑧𐑥𐑐𐑑𐑦 𐑢𐑫𐑛𐑩𐑯 𐑑𐑮𐑧𐑯𐑗𐑼, 𐑢𐑲𐑤 ·𐑑𐑨𐑖𐑑𐑱𐑜𐑴, 𐑯𐑲𐑓 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛, 𐑚𐑦𐑜𐑨𐑯 𐑤𐑱𐑦𐑙 𐑬𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑻𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑼𐑦 𐑑 𐑕𐑒𐑨𐑤𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑥. 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑨𐑗𐑼𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑩 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑯𐑻𐑝𐑩𐑕, 𐑖𐑳𐑛𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑹𐑑 𐑝 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑓𐑧𐑤𐑴, 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑚𐑮𐑧𐑛-𐑓𐑱𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑿𐑼𐑛; 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑡𐑩𐑯𐑦 𐑝 𐑩 𐑚𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑮𐑳𐑐𐑑 𐑚𐑱𐑒𐑼 𐑯 𐑩 𐑣𐑪𐑕𐑐𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑯𐑻𐑕. 𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑞 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑒 𐑑𐑼𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑒 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑐𐑽𐑦𐑪𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑑𐑿𐑥𐑳𐑤𐑗𐑵𐑩𐑕 𐑝𐑦𐑟𐑦𐑑𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑕𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑡𐑩𐑟, ·𐑛𐑴-·𐑚𐑶'𐑟 𐑣𐑴𐑤 𐑤𐑲𐑓 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑿𐑩𐑤 𐑤𐑦𐑐-𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑝𐑼. 𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑦, 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑕𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑽𐑟 𐑓𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑖𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑷𐑤 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑞𐑱 𐑛𐑦𐑥𐑭𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛, 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑱𐑐 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞𐑺 𐑒𐑤𐑳𐑗𐑩𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑐𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑦 𐑩𐑡𐑶𐑯𐑦𐑙, 𐑯 𐑓𐑽𐑓𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑰𐑐 𐑬𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑞 𐑚𐑤𐑲𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑝 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑛𐑹, 𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑷𐑤 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑴𐑝𐑼.

𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩 𐑕𐑲𐑑 𐑑 𐑕𐑰 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜 𐑕𐑰𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑕𐑑 ·𐑑𐑨𐑖𐑑𐑱𐑜𐑴, 𐑩𐑐𐑴𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑲𐑤𐑛 𐑑𐑰𐑔 𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑾𐑯'𐑟: 𐑒𐑮𐑪𐑕𐑢𐑲𐑟 𐑑 𐑞𐑧𐑥, ·𐑛𐑨𐑜𐑵 𐑕𐑰𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑤𐑹, 𐑓 𐑩 𐑚𐑧𐑯𐑗 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑚𐑮𐑷𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑻𐑕-𐑐𐑤𐑵𐑥𐑛 𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑑 𐑞 𐑤𐑴 𐑒𐑸𐑤𐑲𐑯𐑟; 𐑨𐑑 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑥𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑕𐑩𐑤 𐑤𐑦𐑥𐑟, 𐑥𐑱𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑤𐑴 𐑒𐑨𐑚𐑦𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑱𐑥𐑢𐑻𐑒 𐑑 𐑖𐑱𐑒, 𐑨𐑟 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑩𐑯 ·𐑨𐑓𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑓𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑜𐑴𐑟 𐑐𐑨𐑕𐑦𐑯𐑡𐑼 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑖𐑦𐑐. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑓 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑦𐑕, 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑯𐑰𐑜𐑮𐑴 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑓𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑩𐑚𐑕𐑑𐑰𐑥𐑾𐑕, 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑑 𐑕𐑱 𐑛𐑱𐑯𐑑𐑦. 𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑣𐑸𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑪𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑨𐑮𐑩𐑑𐑦𐑝𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑥𐑷𐑤 𐑥𐑬𐑔𐑓𐑫𐑤𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑒𐑰𐑐 𐑳𐑐 𐑞 𐑝𐑲𐑑𐑨𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑛𐑦𐑓𐑿𐑟𐑛 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑕𐑴 𐑚𐑮𐑷𐑛, 𐑚𐑼𐑴𐑯𐑾𐑤, 𐑯 𐑕𐑵𐑐𐑻𐑚 𐑩 𐑐𐑻𐑕𐑩𐑯. 𐑚𐑳𐑑, 𐑛𐑬𐑑𐑤𐑩𐑕, 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑯𐑴𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑡 𐑓𐑧𐑛 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑪𐑙 𐑯 𐑛𐑮𐑨𐑙𐑒 𐑛𐑰𐑐 𐑝 𐑞 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑺; 𐑯 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑛𐑲𐑤𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑕𐑯𐑳𐑓𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑲𐑥 𐑤𐑲𐑓 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛𐑟. 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑚𐑰𐑓 𐑹 𐑚𐑲 𐑚𐑮𐑧𐑛, 𐑸 𐑡𐑲𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑹 𐑯𐑳𐑮𐑦𐑖𐑑. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜, 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑩 𐑥𐑹𐑑𐑩𐑤, 𐑚𐑸𐑚𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑒 𐑕𐑥𐑨𐑒 𐑝 𐑞 𐑤𐑦𐑐 𐑦𐑯 𐑰𐑑𐑦𐑙—𐑩𐑯 𐑳𐑜𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑳𐑓—𐑕𐑴 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑕𐑴, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑑𐑮𐑧𐑥𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 ·𐑛𐑴-·𐑚𐑶 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑑 𐑑 𐑕𐑰 𐑢𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑥𐑸𐑒𐑕 𐑝 𐑑𐑰𐑔 𐑤𐑻𐑒𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑴𐑯 𐑤𐑰𐑯 𐑸𐑥𐑟. 𐑯 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑣𐑽 ·𐑑𐑨𐑖𐑑𐑱𐑜𐑴 𐑕𐑦𐑙𐑦𐑙 𐑬𐑑 𐑓 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑛𐑿𐑕 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑴𐑯𐑟 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑑, 𐑞 𐑕𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑤-𐑢𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑕𐑑𐑿𐑼𐑛 𐑷𐑤 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑖𐑨𐑑𐑼𐑛 𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑪𐑒𐑼𐑦 𐑣𐑨𐑙𐑦𐑙 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑐𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑦, 𐑚𐑲 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑳𐑛𐑩𐑯 𐑓𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑐𐑷𐑤𐑟𐑦. 𐑯𐑹 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑞 𐑢𐑧𐑑𐑕𐑑𐑴𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑞 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑽𐑟 𐑒𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑐𐑪𐑒𐑩𐑑𐑕, 𐑓 𐑞𐑺 𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑯 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑢𐑧𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑟; 𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑢𐑧𐑑𐑕𐑑𐑴𐑯𐑟, 𐑨𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑯𐑼, 𐑞𐑱 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑪𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑖𐑸𐑐𐑩𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑯𐑲𐑝𐑟; 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑑 𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑤𐑲𐑟 𐑐𐑫𐑼 ·𐑛𐑴-·𐑚𐑶. 𐑣𐑬 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑣𐑰 𐑓𐑼𐑜𐑧𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 ·𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑛𐑱𐑟, ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜, 𐑓 𐑢𐑳𐑯, 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑜𐑦𐑤𐑑𐑦 𐑝 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑥𐑻𐑛𐑼𐑩𐑕, 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑝𐑦𐑝𐑾𐑤 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟. 𐑩𐑤𐑨𐑕! 𐑛𐑴-·𐑚𐑶! 𐑣𐑸𐑛 𐑓𐑺𐑟 𐑞 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑑𐑼 𐑣𐑵 𐑢𐑱𐑑𐑕 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑟. 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑩 𐑯𐑨𐑐𐑒𐑦𐑯 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑨𐑮𐑦 𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑸𐑥, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑩 𐑚𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑼. 𐑦𐑯 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑑𐑲𐑥, 𐑞𐑴, 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑲𐑑, 𐑞 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑕𐑷𐑤𐑑-𐑕𐑰 𐑢𐑹𐑽𐑟 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑮𐑲𐑟 𐑯 𐑛𐑦𐑐𐑸𐑑; 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑮𐑧𐑡𐑵𐑤𐑩𐑕, 𐑓𐑱𐑚𐑩𐑤-𐑥𐑳𐑙𐑜𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑽𐑟, 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑺 𐑥𐑸𐑖𐑩𐑤 𐑚𐑴𐑯𐑟 𐑡𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑨𐑑 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑐, 𐑤𐑲𐑒 ·𐑥𐑫𐑼𐑦𐑖 ·𐑖𐑰𐑥𐑧𐑰𐑑𐑼𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑒𐑨𐑚𐑼𐑛𐑟.

𐑚𐑳𐑑, 𐑞𐑴 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑚𐑸𐑚𐑼𐑾𐑯𐑟 𐑛𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑒𐑨𐑚𐑦𐑯, 𐑯 𐑯𐑪𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑤𐑦𐑝𐑛 𐑞𐑺; 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤, 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑧𐑯𐑦𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑕𐑧𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑦 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑣𐑨𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑕, 𐑞𐑱 𐑢𐑻 𐑕𐑒𐑺𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑦𐑯 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑧𐑐𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑰𐑤𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟, 𐑯 𐑡𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑕𐑤𐑰𐑐𐑦𐑙-𐑑𐑲𐑥, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑞𐑱 𐑐𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑦𐑑 𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑴𐑯 𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑽 𐑒𐑢𐑹𐑑𐑼𐑟.

𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑥𐑨𐑑𐑼, ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑯𐑴 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑧𐑐𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑑 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 ·𐑩𐑥𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑟, 𐑣𐑵, 𐑨𐑟 𐑩 𐑕𐑧𐑑, 𐑮𐑭𐑞𐑼 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑤𐑲𐑯 𐑑 𐑞 𐑩𐑐𐑦𐑯𐑘𐑩𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑮𐑲𐑑𐑕 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐'𐑕 𐑒𐑨𐑚𐑦𐑯 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑪𐑙𐑟 𐑑 𐑞𐑧𐑥; 𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑲 𐑒𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑕𐑦 𐑩𐑤𐑴𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑧𐑯𐑦𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦 𐑧𐑤𐑕 𐑦𐑟, 𐑨𐑑 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑑𐑲𐑥, 𐑐𐑼𐑥𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑞𐑺. 𐑕𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑, 𐑦𐑯 𐑮𐑾𐑤 𐑑𐑮𐑵𐑔, 𐑞 𐑥𐑱𐑑𐑕 𐑯 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑽𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑥𐑹 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑐𐑼𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑰 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑤𐑦𐑝𐑛 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑒𐑨𐑚𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑦𐑑. 𐑓 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑞𐑱 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑼 𐑦𐑑, 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑨𐑟 𐑩 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑰𐑑-𐑛𐑹 𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑟 𐑩 𐑣𐑬𐑕; 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯𐑢𐑼𐑛𐑟 𐑓 𐑩 𐑥𐑴𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑, 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑛 𐑬𐑑 𐑞 𐑯𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑; 𐑯, 𐑨𐑟 𐑩 𐑐𐑻𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑔𐑦𐑙, 𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑲𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑴𐑐𐑩𐑯 𐑺. 𐑯𐑹 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑞𐑱 𐑤𐑵𐑟 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑣𐑽𐑚𐑲; 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑒𐑨𐑚𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑴 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑨𐑯𐑘𐑩𐑯𐑖𐑦𐑐; 𐑕𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑤𐑦, ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑒𐑕𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤. 𐑞𐑴 𐑯𐑪𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑤𐑵𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑕 𐑝 ·𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑥, 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑩𐑯 𐑱𐑤𐑾𐑯 𐑑 𐑦𐑑. 𐑣𐑰 𐑤𐑦𐑝𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛, 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑜𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑤𐑦 ·𐑚𐑺𐑟 𐑤𐑦𐑝𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑧𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑛 ·𐑥𐑦𐑟𐑫𐑼𐑦. 𐑯 𐑨𐑟 𐑢𐑧𐑯 ·𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑙 𐑯 ·𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑼 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑛𐑦𐑐𐑸𐑑𐑩𐑛, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑲𐑤𐑛 ·𐑤𐑴𐑜𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑫𐑛𐑟, 𐑚𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑣𐑪𐑤𐑴 𐑝 𐑩 𐑑𐑮𐑰, 𐑤𐑦𐑝𐑛 𐑬𐑑 𐑞 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼 𐑞𐑺, 𐑕𐑳𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑴𐑯 𐑐𐑷𐑟; 𐑕𐑴, 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑤𐑧𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑, 𐑣𐑬𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑱𐑡, ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚'𐑟 𐑕𐑴𐑤, 𐑖𐑳𐑑 𐑳𐑐 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑒𐑱𐑝𐑛 𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑙𐑒 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦, 𐑞𐑺 𐑓𐑧𐑛 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑤𐑩𐑯 𐑐𐑷𐑟 𐑝 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑜𐑤𐑵𐑥!

·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 35. 𐑞 ·𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑-·𐑣𐑧𐑛.

𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑛𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑥𐑹 𐑐𐑤𐑧𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑢𐑧𐑞𐑼, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑛𐑿 𐑮𐑴𐑑𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑥𐑲 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑-𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑒𐑱𐑥 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛.

𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 ·𐑩𐑥𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑞 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑-𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑟 𐑸 𐑥𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑦𐑥𐑩𐑤𐑑𐑱𐑯𐑾𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑝𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑤'𐑟 𐑤𐑰𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑻 𐑐𐑹𐑑; 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑞𐑴 𐑖𐑰 𐑥𐑱 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑓𐑦𐑓𐑑𐑰𐑯 𐑔𐑬𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑥𐑲𐑤𐑟, 𐑯 𐑥𐑹, 𐑑 𐑕𐑱𐑤 𐑺 𐑮𐑰𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑻 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑐𐑼 𐑒𐑮𐑵𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑜𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛. 𐑯 𐑦𐑓, 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑩 𐑔𐑮𐑰, 𐑓𐑹, 𐑹 𐑓𐑲𐑝 𐑘𐑽𐑟' 𐑝𐑶𐑦𐑡 𐑖𐑰 𐑦𐑟 𐑛𐑮𐑷𐑦𐑙 𐑯𐑲 𐑣𐑴𐑥 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑧𐑯𐑦𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑧𐑥𐑐𐑑𐑦 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑻—𐑕𐑱, 𐑩𐑯 𐑧𐑥𐑐𐑑𐑦 𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑤 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯—𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑣𐑻 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑-𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑟 𐑸 𐑒𐑧𐑐𐑑 𐑥𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑑 𐑞 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑; 𐑯 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑣𐑻 𐑕𐑒𐑲𐑕𐑱𐑤-𐑐𐑴𐑤𐑟 𐑕𐑱𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑲𐑼𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑐𐑹𐑑, 𐑛𐑳𐑟 𐑖𐑰 𐑷𐑤𐑑𐑩𐑜𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑮𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑖 𐑞 𐑣𐑴𐑐 𐑝 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑗𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑥𐑹.

𐑯𐑬, 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑚𐑦𐑟𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑-𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑟, 𐑩𐑖𐑹 𐑹 𐑩𐑓𐑤𐑴𐑑, 𐑦𐑟 𐑩 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑱𐑯𐑗𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑩𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑳𐑯, 𐑤𐑧𐑑 𐑳𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑥𐑧𐑠𐑼 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑱𐑖𐑦𐑱𐑑 𐑣𐑽. 𐑲 𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑦𐑑, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑻𐑤𐑾𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑟 𐑝 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑-𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑞 𐑴𐑤𐑛 ·𐑦𐑡𐑦𐑐𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟; 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑪𐑟, 𐑦𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑥𐑲 𐑮𐑰𐑕𐑻𐑗𐑩𐑟, 𐑲 𐑓𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑯𐑳𐑯 𐑐𐑮𐑲𐑼 𐑑 𐑞𐑧𐑥. 𐑓 𐑞𐑴 𐑞𐑺 𐑐𐑮𐑴𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑼𐑟, 𐑞 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑛𐑼𐑟 𐑝 ·𐑚𐑱𐑚𐑩𐑤, 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑛𐑬𐑑𐑤𐑩𐑕, 𐑚𐑲 𐑞𐑺 𐑑𐑬𐑼, 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑑 𐑮𐑽 𐑞 𐑤𐑪𐑓𐑑𐑾𐑕𐑑 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑-𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑷𐑤 ·𐑱𐑖𐑩, 𐑹 ·𐑨𐑓𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑩 𐑲𐑞𐑼; 𐑘𐑧𐑑 (𐑺 𐑞 𐑓𐑲𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑒 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑐𐑫𐑑 𐑑 𐑦𐑑) 𐑨𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑴𐑯 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑝 𐑞𐑺𐑟 𐑥𐑱 𐑚𐑰 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑜𐑪𐑯 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑚𐑹𐑛, 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑛𐑮𐑧𐑛 𐑜𐑱𐑤 𐑝 ·𐑜𐑪𐑛'𐑟 𐑮𐑪𐑔; 𐑞𐑺𐑓𐑹, 𐑢𐑰 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑜𐑦𐑝 𐑞𐑰𐑟 ·𐑚𐑱𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑛𐑼𐑟 𐑐𐑮𐑲𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑞 ·𐑦𐑡𐑦𐑐𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟. 𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑦𐑡𐑦𐑐𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑩 𐑯𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑-𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑟, 𐑦𐑟 𐑩𐑯 𐑩𐑕𐑻𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑚𐑱𐑕𐑑 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑰𐑓 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑸𐑒𐑦𐑪𐑤𐑩𐑡𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑕, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑐𐑦𐑮𐑩𐑥𐑦𐑛𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑓 𐑨𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑩𐑯𐑪𐑥𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑐𐑻𐑐𐑩𐑕𐑩𐑟: 𐑩 𐑔𐑽𐑦 𐑕𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑿𐑤𐑼𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑩𐑐𐑹𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑽 𐑕𐑑𐑺-𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑓𐑹𐑥𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑷𐑤 𐑓𐑹 𐑕𐑲𐑛𐑟 𐑝 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑧𐑛𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑕𐑩𐑟; 𐑢𐑺𐑚𐑲, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑛𐑦𐑡𐑩𐑕 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑳𐑐𐑤𐑦𐑓𐑑𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑝 𐑞𐑺 𐑤𐑧𐑜𐑟, 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑩𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑪𐑯𐑩𐑥𐑼𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑢𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑑 𐑥𐑬𐑯𐑑 𐑑 𐑞 𐑱𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑕, 𐑯 𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑬𐑑 𐑓 𐑯𐑿 𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑟; 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑤𐑫𐑒-𐑬𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑩 𐑥𐑪𐑛𐑼𐑯 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑬𐑑 𐑓 𐑩 𐑕𐑱𐑤, 𐑹 𐑩 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑡𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑺𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑲𐑑. 𐑦𐑯 ·𐑕𐑱𐑯𐑑 ·𐑕𐑑𐑲𐑤𐑲𐑑𐑕, 𐑞 𐑓𐑱𐑥𐑩𐑕 ·𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑗𐑩𐑯 𐑣𐑻𐑥𐑦𐑑 𐑝 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟, 𐑣𐑵 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑩 𐑤𐑪𐑓𐑑𐑦 𐑕𐑑𐑴𐑯 𐑐𐑦𐑤𐑼 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑟𐑼𐑑 𐑯 𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑞 𐑣𐑴𐑤 𐑤𐑨𐑑𐑼 𐑐𐑹𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑤𐑲𐑓 𐑪𐑯 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑦𐑑, 𐑣𐑶𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑵𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑑𐑨𐑒𐑩𐑤; 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑢𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑩 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑸𐑒𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑝 𐑩 𐑛𐑷𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑼-𐑝-𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑-𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑟; 𐑣𐑵 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑛𐑮𐑦𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕 𐑚𐑲 𐑓𐑪𐑜𐑟 𐑹 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑕𐑑𐑕, 𐑮𐑱𐑯, 𐑣𐑱𐑤, 𐑹 𐑕𐑤𐑰𐑑; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑝𐑨𐑤𐑾𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑓𐑱𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑬𐑑 𐑑 𐑞 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑, 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑼𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑲𐑛 𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑴𐑕𐑑. 𐑝 𐑥𐑪𐑛𐑼𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑟-𐑝-𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑-𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑟 𐑢𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑩 𐑤𐑲𐑓𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑕𐑧𐑑; 𐑥𐑽 𐑕𐑑𐑴𐑯, 𐑲𐑼𐑯, 𐑯 𐑚𐑮𐑪𐑯𐑟 𐑥𐑧𐑯; 𐑣𐑵, 𐑞𐑴 𐑢𐑧𐑤 𐑒𐑱𐑐𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑓𐑱𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑬𐑑 𐑩 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑓 𐑜𐑱𐑤, 𐑸 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑲𐑼𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑐𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑑 𐑞 𐑚𐑦𐑟𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑕𐑦𐑙𐑦𐑙 𐑬𐑑 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑳𐑝𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡 𐑕𐑲𐑑. 𐑞𐑺 𐑦𐑟 ·𐑯𐑩𐑐𐑴𐑤𐑾𐑯; 𐑣𐑵, 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑑𐑪𐑐 𐑝 𐑞 𐑒𐑪𐑤𐑩𐑥 𐑝 ·𐑝𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑴𐑥, 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑸𐑥𐑟 𐑓𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑩𐑛, 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑛 𐑯 𐑓𐑦𐑓𐑑𐑦 𐑓𐑰𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑺; 𐑒𐑺𐑤𐑩𐑕, 𐑯𐑬, 𐑣𐑵 𐑮𐑵𐑤𐑟 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑒𐑕 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑴; 𐑢𐑧𐑞𐑼 ·𐑤𐑵𐑦 ·𐑓𐑦𐑤𐑰𐑐, ·𐑤𐑵𐑦 ·𐑚𐑤𐑭𐑙𐑒, 𐑹 ·𐑤𐑵𐑦 𐑞 ·𐑛𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑤. 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 ·𐑢𐑪𐑖𐑦𐑙𐑑𐑩𐑯, 𐑑𐑵, 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑣𐑲 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑓𐑑 𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑑𐑬𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑱𐑯-𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯 ·𐑚𐑷𐑤𐑑𐑦𐑥𐑹, 𐑯 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝 ·𐑣𐑻𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑰𐑟' 𐑐𐑦𐑤𐑼𐑟, 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑪𐑤𐑩𐑥 𐑥𐑸𐑒𐑕 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑐𐑶𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑣𐑿𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑜𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑡𐑼 𐑚𐑦𐑘𐑪𐑯𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑓𐑿 𐑥𐑹𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑜𐑴. 𐑨𐑛𐑥𐑼𐑩𐑤 ·𐑯𐑧𐑤𐑕𐑩𐑯, 𐑷𐑤𐑕𐑴, 𐑪𐑯 𐑩 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑜𐑳𐑯-𐑥𐑧𐑑𐑩𐑤, 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑-𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑦𐑯 ·𐑑𐑮𐑩𐑓𐑳𐑤𐑜𐑸 ·𐑕𐑒𐑢𐑺; 𐑯 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑩𐑚𐑕𐑒𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑞𐑨𐑑 ·𐑤𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑯 𐑕𐑥𐑴𐑒, 𐑑𐑴𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑟 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑜𐑦𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑩 𐑣𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑯 𐑣𐑽𐑴 𐑦𐑟 𐑞𐑺; 𐑓 𐑢𐑺 𐑞𐑺 𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑥𐑴𐑒, 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑓𐑲𐑼. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑯𐑲𐑞𐑼 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 ·𐑢𐑪𐑖𐑦𐑙𐑑𐑩𐑯, 𐑯𐑹 ·𐑯𐑩𐑐𐑴𐑤𐑾𐑯, 𐑯𐑹 ·𐑯𐑧𐑤𐑕𐑩𐑯, 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑼 𐑩 𐑕𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑩𐑤 𐑣𐑱𐑤 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑴, 𐑣𐑬𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑥𐑨𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑴𐑒𐑑 𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑞𐑺 𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑞 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑛𐑧𐑒𐑕 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑞𐑱 𐑜𐑱𐑟; 𐑣𐑬𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑦𐑑 𐑥𐑱 𐑚𐑰 𐑕𐑼𐑥𐑲𐑟𐑛, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑕𐑐𐑦𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑞 𐑔𐑦𐑒 𐑣𐑱𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑓𐑿𐑗𐑼, 𐑯 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑲 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑖𐑴𐑤𐑟 𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑮𐑪𐑒𐑕 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑖𐑳𐑯𐑛.

𐑦𐑑 𐑥𐑱 𐑕𐑰𐑥 𐑳𐑯𐑢𐑪𐑮𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑑 𐑒𐑳𐑐𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑 𐑞 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑-𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑰; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑑𐑮𐑵𐑔 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑴, 𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑩𐑯 𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑥 𐑓 𐑢𐑦𐑗 ·𐑴𐑚𐑩𐑛 ·𐑥𐑱𐑕𐑦, 𐑞 𐑕𐑴𐑤 𐑣𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑹𐑾𐑯 𐑝 ·𐑯𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑑, 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑩𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤. 𐑞 𐑢𐑻𐑞𐑦 ·𐑴𐑚𐑩𐑛 𐑑𐑧𐑤𐑟 𐑳𐑕, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑻𐑤𐑦 𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑼𐑦, 𐑺 𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑕 𐑢𐑻 𐑮𐑧𐑜𐑿𐑤𐑼𐑤𐑦 𐑤𐑷𐑯𐑗𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑐𐑼𐑕𐑿𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑜𐑱𐑥, 𐑞 𐑐𐑰𐑐𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑤𐑪𐑓𐑑𐑦 𐑕𐑐𐑸𐑟 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑞 𐑕𐑰-𐑒𐑴𐑕𐑑, 𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑞 𐑤𐑫𐑒-𐑬𐑑𐑕 𐑩𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑥𐑰𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑯𐑱𐑤𐑛 𐑒𐑤𐑰𐑑𐑕, 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑨𐑟 𐑓𐑬𐑤𐑟 𐑜𐑴 𐑳𐑐𐑕𐑑𐑺𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑣𐑧𐑯-𐑣𐑬𐑕. 𐑩 𐑓𐑿 𐑘𐑽𐑟 𐑩𐑜𐑴 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑐𐑤𐑨𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩𐑛𐑪𐑐𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 ·𐑚𐑱 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑝 ·𐑯𐑿 ·𐑟𐑰𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛, 𐑣𐑵, 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑜𐑱𐑥, 𐑜𐑱𐑝 𐑯𐑴𐑑𐑦𐑕 𐑑 𐑞 𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑦-𐑥𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕 𐑯𐑲 𐑞 𐑚𐑰𐑗. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑒𐑳𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑥 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑯𐑬 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑪𐑚𐑕𐑩𐑤𐑰𐑑; 𐑑𐑻𐑯 𐑢𐑰 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑑 𐑞 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑐𐑼 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑-𐑣𐑧𐑛, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑝 𐑩 𐑢𐑱𐑤-𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑰. 𐑞 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑-𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑟 𐑸 𐑒𐑧𐑐𐑑 𐑥𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑕𐑳𐑯-𐑮𐑲𐑟 𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑯-𐑕𐑧𐑑; 𐑞 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑺 𐑮𐑧𐑜𐑿𐑤𐑼 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑟 (𐑨𐑟 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑥), 𐑯 𐑮𐑦𐑤𐑰𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑰𐑗 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑑𐑵 𐑬𐑼𐑟. 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑼𐑰𐑯 𐑢𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑝 𐑞 𐑑𐑮𐑪𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑕 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑰𐑛𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑤𐑧𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑞 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑-𐑣𐑧𐑛; 𐑯𐑱, 𐑑 𐑩 𐑛𐑮𐑰𐑥𐑦 𐑥𐑧𐑛𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑑𐑦𐑝 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑲𐑑𐑓𐑩𐑤. 𐑞𐑺 𐑿 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛, 𐑩 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑛 𐑓𐑰𐑑 𐑩𐑚𐑳𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑛𐑧𐑒𐑕, 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑞 𐑛𐑰𐑐, 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑓 𐑞 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑕 𐑢𐑻 𐑡𐑲𐑜𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤𐑑𐑕, 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑚𐑦𐑯𐑰𐑔 𐑿 𐑯 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑢𐑰𐑯 𐑘𐑹 𐑤𐑧𐑜𐑟, 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑻, 𐑕𐑢𐑦𐑥 𐑞 𐑣𐑿𐑡𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑥𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑰, 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑨𐑟 𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑕 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑕 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑛 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑢𐑰𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑵𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑓𐑱𐑥𐑩𐑕 ·𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑕𐑩𐑕 𐑨𐑑 𐑴𐑤𐑛 ·𐑮𐑴𐑛𐑟. 𐑞𐑺 𐑿 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛, 𐑤𐑪𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑓𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑽𐑰𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑰, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑯𐑳𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑮𐑳𐑓𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑝𐑟. 𐑞 𐑑𐑮𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑴𐑤𐑟; 𐑞 𐑛𐑮𐑬𐑟𐑦 𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑚𐑤𐑴; 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑪𐑤𐑝𐑟 𐑿 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑤𐑨𐑙𐑜𐑼. 𐑓 𐑞 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑐𐑸𐑑, 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑑𐑮𐑪𐑐𐑦𐑒 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑤𐑲𐑓, 𐑩 𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑲𐑥 𐑳𐑯𐑦𐑝𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑓𐑩𐑤𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑕 𐑿; 𐑿 𐑣𐑽 𐑯𐑴 𐑯𐑿𐑟; 𐑮𐑰𐑛 𐑯𐑴 𐑜𐑩𐑟𐑧𐑑𐑕; 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑩𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑵𐑛 𐑿 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑳𐑯𐑯𐑧𐑕𐑦𐑕𐑺𐑦 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑲𐑑𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕; 𐑿 𐑣𐑽 𐑝 𐑯𐑴 𐑛𐑩𐑥𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑩𐑓𐑤𐑦𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟; 𐑚𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑮𐑳𐑐𐑑 𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑟; 𐑓𐑷𐑤 𐑝 𐑕𐑑𐑪𐑒𐑕; 𐑸 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑔𐑷𐑑 𐑝 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑿 𐑖𐑨𐑤 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑓 𐑛𐑦𐑯𐑼—𐑓 𐑷𐑤 𐑘𐑹 𐑥𐑰𐑤𐑟 𐑓 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑘𐑽𐑟 𐑯 𐑥𐑹 𐑸 𐑕𐑯𐑳𐑜𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑑𐑴𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑒𐑭𐑕𐑒𐑕, 𐑯 𐑘𐑹 𐑚𐑦𐑤 𐑝 𐑓𐑺 𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑥𐑿𐑑𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤.

𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑕𐑳𐑞𐑼𐑯 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟𐑥𐑧𐑯, 𐑪𐑯 𐑩 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑹 𐑓𐑹 𐑘𐑽𐑟' 𐑝𐑶𐑦𐑡, 𐑨𐑟 𐑪𐑓𐑩𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑟, 𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑝 𐑞 𐑝𐑺𐑾𐑕 𐑬𐑼𐑟 𐑿 𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑-𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑩𐑥𐑬𐑯𐑑 𐑑 𐑕𐑧𐑝𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑲𐑼 𐑥𐑳𐑯𐑔𐑕. 𐑯 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑛𐑦𐑐𐑤𐑹𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕 𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑿 𐑛𐑦𐑝𐑴𐑑 𐑕𐑴 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑼𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑩 𐑐𐑹𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑣𐑴𐑤 𐑑𐑻𐑥 𐑝 𐑘𐑹 𐑯𐑨𐑗𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑤𐑲𐑓, 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑚𐑰 𐑕𐑴 𐑕𐑨𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑑𐑿𐑑 𐑝 𐑧𐑯𐑦𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑐𐑮𐑴𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑩 𐑒𐑴𐑟𐑦 𐑦𐑯𐑣𐑨𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑝𐑯𐑩𐑕, 𐑹 𐑩𐑛𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑑 𐑚𐑮𐑰𐑛 𐑩 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑓𐑼𐑑𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑤𐑴𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑓𐑰𐑤𐑦𐑙, 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑨𐑟 𐑐𐑼𐑑𐑱𐑯𐑟 𐑑 𐑩 𐑚𐑧𐑛, 𐑩 𐑣𐑨𐑥𐑩𐑒, 𐑩 𐑣𐑻𐑕, 𐑩 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑦 𐑚𐑪𐑒𐑕, 𐑩 𐑐𐑫𐑤𐑐𐑦𐑑, 𐑩 𐑒𐑴𐑗, 𐑹 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑝 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑕𐑥𐑷𐑤 𐑯 𐑕𐑯𐑳𐑜 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑝𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑑𐑧𐑥𐑐𐑼𐑺𐑦𐑤𐑦 𐑲𐑕𐑩𐑤𐑱𐑑 𐑞𐑧𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑝𐑟. 𐑘𐑹 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑿𐑠𐑵𐑩𐑤 𐑐𐑶𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑐𐑻𐑗 𐑦𐑟 𐑞 𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑝 𐑞 t' 𐑜𐑨𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑑-𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑, 𐑢𐑺 𐑿 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑑𐑵 𐑔𐑦𐑯 𐑐𐑨𐑮𐑩𐑤𐑧𐑤 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑕 (𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑽 𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑥𐑧𐑯) 𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑛 𐑞 t' 𐑜𐑨𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑒𐑮𐑪𐑕-𐑑𐑮𐑰𐑟. 𐑣𐑽, 𐑑𐑪𐑕𐑑 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑕𐑰, 𐑞 𐑚𐑦𐑜𐑦𐑯𐑼 𐑓𐑰𐑤𐑟 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑒𐑴𐑟𐑦 𐑨𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑪𐑯 𐑩 𐑚𐑫𐑤'𐑟 𐑣𐑹𐑯𐑟. 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑖𐑫𐑼, 𐑦𐑯 𐑒𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑢𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑿 𐑥𐑱 𐑒𐑨𐑮𐑦 𐑘𐑹 𐑣𐑬𐑕 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑓𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑿, 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑖𐑱𐑐 𐑝 𐑩 𐑢𐑪𐑗-𐑒𐑴𐑑; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑐𐑼𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑔𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑗-𐑒𐑴𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑴 𐑥𐑹 𐑝 𐑩 𐑣𐑬𐑕 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑞 𐑳𐑯𐑒𐑤𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦; 𐑓 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑕𐑴𐑤 𐑦𐑟 𐑜𐑤𐑵𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑝 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑓𐑤𐑧𐑖𐑦 𐑑𐑨𐑚𐑼𐑯𐑨𐑒𐑩𐑤, 𐑯 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑰𐑤𐑦 𐑥𐑵𐑝 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑦𐑑, 𐑯𐑹 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑥𐑵𐑝 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑦𐑑, 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑 𐑮𐑳𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑒 𐑝 𐑐𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑖𐑦𐑙 (𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑜𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑐𐑦𐑤𐑜𐑮𐑦𐑥 𐑒𐑮𐑪𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑕𐑯𐑴𐑦 ·𐑨𐑤𐑐𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼); 𐑕𐑴 𐑩 𐑢𐑪𐑗-𐑒𐑴𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑴 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑝 𐑩 𐑣𐑬𐑕 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑩 𐑥𐑽 𐑧𐑯𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑴𐑐, 𐑹 𐑩𐑛𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑒𐑦𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑱𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑿. 𐑿 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑐𐑫𐑑 𐑩 𐑖𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑹 𐑗𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑝 𐑛𐑮𐑷𐑼𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑘𐑹 𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦, 𐑯 𐑯𐑴 𐑥𐑹 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑿 𐑥𐑱𐑒 𐑩 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑝𐑰𐑯𐑾𐑯𐑑 𐑒𐑤𐑪𐑟𐑩𐑑 𐑝 𐑘𐑹 𐑢𐑪𐑗-𐑒𐑴𐑑.

𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑦𐑕, 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑛𐑦𐑐𐑤𐑹𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑-𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑟 𐑝 𐑩 𐑕𐑳𐑞𐑼𐑯 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑸 𐑳𐑯𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑝𐑲𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑧𐑯𐑝𐑾𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑹 𐑐𐑫𐑤𐑐𐑦𐑑𐑕, 𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑛 𐑒𐑮𐑴'𐑟-𐑯𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑕, 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑞 𐑤𐑫𐑒-𐑬𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑩 ·𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑯𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑼 𐑸 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑑𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑤𐑧𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑢𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑝 𐑞 𐑓𐑮𐑴𐑟𐑩𐑯 𐑕𐑰𐑟. 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑲𐑼𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑑𐑦𐑝 𐑝 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 ·𐑕𐑤𐑰𐑑, 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑛 “𐑩 ·𐑝𐑶𐑦𐑡 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑞 ·𐑲𐑕𐑚𐑻𐑜𐑟, 𐑦𐑯 𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑯𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑓 𐑞 𐑮𐑰-𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑳𐑝𐑼𐑦 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑤𐑪𐑕𐑑 ·𐑲𐑕𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑒 ·𐑒𐑪𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑟 𐑝 ·𐑴𐑤𐑛 ·𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑯𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛;” 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑨𐑛𐑥𐑼𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑝𐑪𐑤𐑿𐑥, 𐑷𐑤 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑟 𐑝 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑-𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑟 𐑸 𐑓𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑖𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑗𐑸𐑥𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑻𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑤 𐑩𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑮𐑰𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑒𐑮𐑴'𐑟-𐑯𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑜𐑤𐑱𐑕𐑽, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞 𐑯𐑱𐑥 𐑝 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 ·𐑕𐑤𐑰𐑑'𐑕 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑒𐑮𐑭𐑓𐑑. 𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑛 𐑦𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑤𐑰𐑑'𐑕 𐑒𐑮𐑴'𐑟-𐑯𐑧𐑕𐑑, 𐑦𐑯 𐑪𐑯𐑼 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓; 𐑣𐑰 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑼𐑦𐑡𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑼 𐑯 𐑐𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑰, 𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑰 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑷𐑤 𐑮𐑦𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑓𐑷𐑤𐑕 𐑛𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑕𐑦, 𐑯 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑓 𐑢𐑰 𐑒𐑷𐑤 𐑬𐑼 𐑴𐑯 𐑗𐑦𐑤𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑯 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑬𐑼 𐑴𐑯 𐑯𐑱𐑥𐑟 (𐑢𐑰 𐑓𐑭𐑞𐑼𐑟 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑼𐑦𐑡𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑟 𐑯 𐑐𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑰𐑟), 𐑕𐑴 𐑤𐑲𐑒𐑢𐑲𐑟 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑢𐑰 𐑛𐑦𐑯𐑪𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑱𐑑 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑬𐑼𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑝𐑟 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑨𐑐𐑼𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑕 𐑢𐑰 𐑥𐑱 𐑚𐑦𐑜𐑧𐑑. 𐑦𐑯 𐑖𐑱𐑐, 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑤𐑰𐑑'𐑕 𐑒𐑮𐑴'𐑟-𐑯𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑤𐑸𐑡 𐑑𐑽𐑕 𐑹 𐑐𐑲𐑐; 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑴𐑐𐑩𐑯 𐑩𐑚𐑳𐑝, 𐑣𐑬𐑧𐑝𐑼, 𐑢𐑺 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑖𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑥𐑵𐑝𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑲𐑛-𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑰𐑯 𐑑 𐑒𐑰𐑐 𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑢𐑼𐑛 𐑝 𐑘𐑹 𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑣𐑸𐑛 𐑜𐑱𐑤. 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑑 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑦𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑, 𐑿 𐑩𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑦𐑑 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑩 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑐-𐑣𐑨𐑗 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑪𐑑𐑩𐑥. 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑕𐑲𐑛, 𐑹 𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑯𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑻𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐, 𐑦𐑟 𐑩 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑓𐑼𐑑𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑰𐑑, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑤𐑪𐑒𐑼 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑯𐑰𐑔 𐑓 𐑳𐑥𐑚𐑮𐑧𐑤𐑩𐑟, 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑓𐑼𐑑𐑼𐑟, 𐑯 𐑒𐑴𐑑𐑕. 𐑦𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑳𐑯𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑩 𐑤𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑮𐑨𐑒, 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑑 𐑒𐑰𐑐 𐑘𐑹 𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑑, 𐑐𐑲𐑐, 𐑑𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑴𐑐, 𐑯 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑯𐑷𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑝𐑰𐑯𐑾𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟. 𐑢𐑧𐑯 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 ·𐑕𐑤𐑰𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑐𐑻𐑕𐑩𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑫𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑-𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑒𐑮𐑴'𐑟-𐑯𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟, 𐑣𐑰 𐑑𐑧𐑤𐑟 𐑳𐑕 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑷𐑤𐑢𐑱𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑩 𐑮𐑲𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑥 (𐑷𐑤𐑕𐑴 𐑓𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑮𐑨𐑒), 𐑑𐑩𐑜𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑐𐑬𐑛𐑼 𐑓𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑒 𐑯 𐑖𐑪𐑑, 𐑓 𐑞 𐑐𐑻𐑐𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑐𐑪𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑪𐑓 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱 𐑯𐑸𐑢𐑪𐑤𐑕, 𐑹 𐑝𐑱𐑜𐑮𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑕𐑰 𐑿𐑯𐑦𐑒𐑹𐑯𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑓𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼𐑟; 𐑓 𐑿 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑩𐑒𐑕𐑧𐑕𐑓𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑖𐑵𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑒 𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑞 𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑑 𐑖𐑵𐑑 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑦𐑟 𐑩 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑛𐑦𐑓𐑼𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑔𐑦𐑙. 𐑯𐑬, 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑩 𐑤𐑱𐑚𐑼 𐑝 𐑤𐑳𐑝 𐑓 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 ·𐑕𐑤𐑰𐑑 𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑚, 𐑨𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑛𐑳𐑟, 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑛𐑰𐑑𐑱𐑤𐑛 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑝𐑰𐑯𐑾𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑮𐑴'𐑟-𐑯𐑧𐑕𐑑; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞𐑴 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑴 𐑦𐑯𐑤𐑸𐑡𐑩𐑟 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑝 𐑞𐑰𐑟, 𐑯 𐑞𐑴 𐑣𐑰 𐑑𐑮𐑰𐑑𐑕 𐑳𐑕 𐑑 𐑩 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑕𐑲𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑒 𐑩𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑒𐑮𐑴'𐑟-𐑯𐑧𐑕𐑑, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑕𐑥𐑷𐑤 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑕 𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑧𐑐𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑓 𐑞 𐑐𐑻𐑐𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑨𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑻𐑼𐑟 𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑳𐑤𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑛 𐑞 “𐑤𐑴𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑩𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯” 𐑝 𐑷𐑤 𐑚𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑥𐑨𐑜𐑯𐑩𐑑𐑕; 𐑩𐑯 𐑻𐑼 𐑩𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑚𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑑 𐑞 𐑣𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑝𐑦𐑕𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑝 𐑞 𐑲𐑼𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐'𐑕 𐑐𐑤𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑕, 𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑜𐑤𐑱𐑕𐑽'𐑟 𐑒𐑱𐑕, 𐑐𐑼𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑕, 𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑣𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑕𐑴 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑚𐑮𐑴𐑒𐑩𐑯-𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑒𐑕𐑥𐑦𐑔𐑕 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑣𐑻 𐑒𐑮𐑵; 𐑲 𐑕𐑱, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑴 𐑞 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 𐑦𐑟 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑰𐑑 𐑯 𐑕𐑲𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑒 𐑣𐑽, 𐑘𐑧𐑑, 𐑓 𐑷𐑤 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑤𐑻𐑯𐑛 “𐑚𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑛𐑰𐑝𐑦𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟,” “𐑨𐑟𐑦𐑥𐑩𐑔 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑕 𐑪𐑚𐑟𐑼𐑝𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟,” 𐑯 “𐑩𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑒𐑕𐑦𐑥𐑩𐑑 𐑻𐑼𐑟,” 𐑣𐑰 𐑯𐑴𐑟 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑢𐑧𐑤, ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 ·𐑕𐑤𐑰𐑑, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑴 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑦𐑥𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑥𐑨𐑜𐑯𐑧𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑥𐑧𐑛𐑦𐑑𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟, 𐑨𐑟 𐑑 𐑓𐑱𐑤 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑩𐑒𐑱𐑠𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑑𐑩𐑢𐑹𐑛𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑧𐑤 𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑤𐑧𐑯𐑦𐑖𐑑 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑒𐑱𐑕-𐑚𐑪𐑑𐑩𐑤, 𐑕𐑴 𐑯𐑲𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑑𐑳𐑒𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑪𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑮𐑴'𐑟 𐑯𐑧𐑕𐑑, 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑦𐑯 𐑰𐑟𐑦 𐑮𐑰𐑗 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛. 𐑞𐑴, 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑣𐑴𐑤, 𐑲 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑩𐑛𐑥𐑲𐑼 𐑯 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑤𐑳𐑝 𐑞 𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑝, 𐑞 𐑪𐑯𐑩𐑕𐑑, 𐑯 𐑤𐑻𐑯𐑛 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯; 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑲 𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑦𐑑 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑦𐑤 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑕𐑴 𐑳𐑑𐑼𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑜𐑯𐑹 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑒𐑱𐑕-𐑚𐑪𐑑𐑩𐑤, 𐑕𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑩 𐑓𐑱𐑔𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑯 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑓𐑼𐑑𐑼 𐑦𐑑 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑯, 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑥𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑓𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑼𐑟 𐑯 𐑣𐑫𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑛𐑦𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑥𐑨𐑔𐑩𐑥𐑨𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑕 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑓𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑚𐑻𐑛'𐑟 𐑯𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑦𐑯 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑹 𐑓𐑹 𐑐𐑻𐑗𐑩𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑐𐑴𐑤.

𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑓 𐑢𐑰 ·𐑕𐑳𐑞𐑼𐑯 𐑢𐑱𐑤-𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑼𐑟 𐑸 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑴 𐑕𐑯𐑳𐑜𐑤𐑦 𐑣𐑬𐑟𐑛 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑓𐑑 𐑨𐑟 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 ·𐑕𐑤𐑰𐑑 𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 ·𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑯𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑢𐑻; 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑩𐑛𐑝𐑭𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑡 𐑦𐑟 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑼-𐑚𐑨𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑢𐑲𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑼𐑧𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑝 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑳𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑝 𐑕𐑰𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑢𐑰 ·𐑕𐑬𐑔 𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑼𐑟 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑓𐑤𐑴𐑑. 𐑓 𐑢𐑳𐑯, 𐑲 𐑿𐑕𐑑 𐑑 𐑤𐑬𐑯𐑡 𐑳𐑐 𐑞 𐑮𐑦𐑜𐑦𐑙 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑤𐑧𐑠𐑼𐑤𐑦, 𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑑𐑪𐑐 𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑩 𐑗𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜, 𐑹 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑧𐑤𐑕 𐑪𐑓 𐑛𐑿𐑑𐑦 𐑣𐑵𐑥 𐑲 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑓𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑞𐑺; 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑩𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑱 𐑓𐑻𐑞𐑼, 𐑯 𐑔𐑮𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑤𐑱𐑟𐑦 𐑤𐑧𐑜 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑞 𐑑𐑪𐑐-𐑕𐑱𐑤 𐑘𐑸𐑛, 𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑩 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑼𐑦 𐑝𐑿 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼𐑦 𐑐𐑭𐑕𐑗𐑼𐑟, 𐑯 𐑕𐑴 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑥𐑬𐑯𐑑 𐑑 𐑥𐑲 𐑳𐑤𐑑𐑦𐑥𐑩𐑑 𐑛𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯.

𐑤𐑧𐑑 𐑥𐑰 𐑥𐑱𐑒 𐑩 𐑒𐑤𐑰𐑯 𐑚𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑝 𐑦𐑑 𐑣𐑽, 𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑤𐑦 𐑩𐑛𐑥𐑦𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑲 𐑒𐑧𐑐𐑑 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑕𐑪𐑮𐑦 𐑜𐑸𐑛. 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑚𐑤𐑩𐑥 𐑝 𐑞 𐑿𐑯𐑦𐑝𐑻𐑕 𐑮𐑦𐑝𐑪𐑤𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑰, 𐑣𐑬 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑲—𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑤𐑧𐑓𐑑 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑰𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑑 𐑥𐑲𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩 𐑔𐑷𐑑-𐑦𐑯𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑨𐑤𐑑𐑦𐑑𐑿𐑛—𐑣𐑬 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑲 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑤𐑲𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑥𐑲 𐑪𐑚𐑤𐑦𐑜𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑑 𐑩𐑚𐑟𐑻𐑝 𐑷𐑤 𐑢𐑱𐑤-𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑕' 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑹𐑛𐑼𐑟, “𐑒𐑰𐑐 𐑘𐑹 𐑢𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑲 𐑴𐑐𐑩𐑯, 𐑯 𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑬𐑑 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑑𐑲𐑥.”

𐑯 𐑤𐑧𐑑 𐑥𐑰 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕 𐑥𐑵𐑝𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑨𐑛𐑥𐑪𐑯𐑦𐑖 𐑿, 𐑘𐑰 𐑖𐑦𐑐-𐑴𐑯𐑼𐑟 𐑝 ·𐑯𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑑! 𐑚𐑦𐑢𐑺 𐑝 𐑦𐑯𐑤𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑘𐑹 𐑝𐑦𐑡𐑦𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑼𐑦𐑟 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑤𐑨𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑤𐑰𐑯 𐑚𐑮𐑬 𐑯 𐑣𐑪𐑤𐑴 𐑲; 𐑜𐑦𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑑 𐑳𐑯𐑕𐑰𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑥𐑧𐑛𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑑𐑦𐑝𐑯𐑩𐑕; 𐑯 𐑣𐑵 𐑪𐑓𐑼𐑟 𐑑 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 ·𐑓𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑛 𐑝 ·𐑚𐑬𐑛𐑦𐑗 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑧𐑛. 𐑚𐑦𐑢𐑺 𐑝 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯, 𐑲 𐑕𐑱; 𐑘𐑹 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑕𐑰𐑯 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑞𐑱 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑚𐑰 𐑒𐑦𐑤𐑛; 𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑕𐑳𐑙𐑒𐑩𐑯-𐑲𐑛 𐑘𐑳𐑙 ·𐑐𐑤𐑩𐑑𐑪𐑯𐑦𐑕𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑑𐑴 𐑿 𐑑𐑧𐑯 𐑢𐑱𐑒𐑕 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑞 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛, 𐑯 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑥𐑱𐑒 𐑿 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑐𐑲𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 𐑞 𐑮𐑦𐑗𐑼. 𐑯𐑹 𐑸 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑥𐑴𐑯𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑨𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑳𐑯𐑯𐑰𐑛𐑩𐑛. 𐑓 𐑯𐑬𐑩𐑛𐑱𐑟, 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤-𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑼𐑦 𐑓𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑟 𐑩𐑯 𐑩𐑕𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑥 𐑓 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑮𐑴𐑥𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑒, 𐑥𐑧𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑒𐑪𐑤𐑦, 𐑯 𐑨𐑚𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑑-𐑥𐑲𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑘𐑳𐑙 𐑥𐑧𐑯, 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑜𐑳𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 carking 𐑒𐑺𐑟 𐑝 𐑻𐑔, 𐑯 𐑕𐑰𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑑𐑸 𐑯 𐑚𐑤𐑳𐑚𐑼. ·𐑗𐑲𐑤𐑛 ·𐑣𐑨𐑮𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑳𐑯𐑓𐑮𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑻𐑗𐑩𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑-𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑝 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑤𐑳𐑒𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑩𐑐𐑶𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑱𐑤-𐑖𐑦𐑐, 𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑵𐑛𐑦 𐑓𐑮𐑱𐑟 𐑦𐑡𐑨𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑱𐑑𐑕:—

𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑪𐑓𐑩𐑯 𐑛𐑵 𐑞 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑕 𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑨𐑚𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑑-𐑥𐑲𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑘𐑳𐑙 𐑓𐑦𐑤𐑪𐑕𐑩𐑓𐑼𐑟 𐑑 𐑑𐑭𐑕𐑒, 𐑳𐑐𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑓𐑰𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑩𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑑 “𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑩𐑕𐑑” 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑝𐑶𐑦𐑡; 𐑣𐑭𐑓-𐑣𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑱 𐑸 𐑕𐑴 𐑣𐑴𐑐𐑤𐑩𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑤𐑪𐑕𐑑 𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑪𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑨𐑥𐑚𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯, 𐑨𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑕𐑰𐑒𐑮𐑩𐑑 𐑕𐑴𐑤𐑟 𐑞𐑱 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑮𐑭𐑞𐑼 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑰 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑳𐑞𐑼𐑢𐑲𐑟. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑝𐑱𐑯; 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑘𐑳𐑙 ·𐑐𐑤𐑩𐑑𐑪𐑯𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑕 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑩 𐑯𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑝𐑦𐑠𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑻𐑓𐑦𐑒𐑑; 𐑞𐑱 𐑸 𐑖𐑹𐑑-𐑕𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑛; 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑿𐑕, 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯 𐑞 𐑝𐑦𐑟𐑿𐑩𐑤 𐑯𐑻𐑝? 𐑞𐑱 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑤𐑧𐑓𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑪𐑐𐑼𐑩-𐑜𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑴𐑥.

“𐑢𐑲, 𐑞𐑬 𐑥𐑳𐑙𐑒𐑦,” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑩 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑽 𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑤𐑨𐑛𐑟, “𐑢𐑰'𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑒𐑮𐑵𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑯𐑬 𐑣𐑸𐑛 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑘𐑽𐑟, 𐑯 𐑞𐑬 𐑣𐑨𐑕𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑮𐑱𐑟𐑛 𐑩 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑘𐑧𐑑. 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑸 𐑕𐑒𐑺𐑕 𐑨𐑟 𐑣𐑧𐑯'𐑟 𐑑𐑰𐑔 𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑞𐑬 𐑸𐑑 𐑳𐑐 𐑣𐑽.” 𐑐𐑼𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑕 𐑞𐑱 𐑢𐑻; 𐑹 𐑐𐑼𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑕 𐑞𐑺 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑖𐑴𐑤𐑟 𐑝 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑸 𐑣𐑼𐑲𐑟𐑩𐑯; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑤𐑳𐑤𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩𐑯 𐑴𐑐𐑾𐑥-𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑤𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑤𐑩𐑕𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑝𐑱𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑, 𐑳𐑯𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑕 𐑮𐑧𐑝𐑼𐑦 𐑦𐑟 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑨𐑚𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑑-𐑥𐑲𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑿𐑔 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑚𐑤𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑒𐑱𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑝 𐑢𐑱𐑝𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑔𐑷𐑑𐑕, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑤𐑵𐑟𐑩𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑲𐑛𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑑𐑦; 𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑕 𐑞 𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑰𐑑 𐑓 𐑞 𐑝𐑦𐑟𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑡 𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑛𐑰𐑐, 𐑚𐑤𐑵, 𐑚𐑪𐑑𐑩𐑥𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑕𐑴𐑤, 𐑐𐑼𐑝𐑱𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑨𐑯𐑒𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑯 𐑯𐑱𐑗𐑼; 𐑯 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡, 𐑣𐑭𐑓-𐑕𐑰𐑯, 𐑜𐑤𐑲𐑛𐑦𐑙, 𐑚𐑿𐑑𐑦𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑤𐑵𐑛𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑥; 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑛𐑦𐑥𐑤𐑦-𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑳𐑝𐑼𐑛, 𐑳𐑐𐑮𐑲𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑦𐑯 𐑝 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑻𐑯𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑓𐑹𐑥, 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑟 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑞 𐑦𐑥𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑦𐑤𐑵𐑕𐑦𐑝 𐑔𐑷𐑑𐑕 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑰𐑐𐑩𐑤 𐑞 𐑕𐑴𐑤 𐑚𐑲 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑿𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑓𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑦𐑑. 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑦𐑯𐑗𐑭𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑥𐑵𐑛, 𐑞𐑲 𐑕𐑐𐑦𐑮𐑦𐑑 𐑧𐑚𐑟 𐑩𐑢𐑱 𐑑 𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑕 𐑦𐑑 𐑒𐑱𐑥; 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑟 𐑛𐑦𐑓𐑿𐑟𐑛 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑯 𐑕𐑐𐑱𐑕; 𐑤𐑲𐑒 ·𐑒𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑥𐑼'𐑟 𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑛 ·𐑐𐑨𐑯𐑔𐑰𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑨𐑖𐑩𐑟, 𐑓𐑹𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑩 𐑐𐑸𐑑 𐑝 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑖𐑹 𐑞 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑜𐑤𐑴𐑚 𐑴𐑝𐑼.

𐑞𐑺 𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑴 𐑤𐑲𐑓 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑰, 𐑯𐑬, 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑧𐑐𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑮𐑪𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑤𐑲𐑓 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑸𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑩 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑴𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑖𐑦𐑐; 𐑚𐑲 𐑣𐑻, 𐑚𐑪𐑮𐑴𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑕𐑰; 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑕𐑰, 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑵𐑑𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑑𐑲𐑛𐑟 𐑝 ·𐑜𐑪𐑛. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑕𐑤𐑰𐑐, 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑛𐑮𐑰𐑥 𐑦𐑟 𐑪𐑯 𐑘𐑰, 𐑥𐑵𐑝 𐑘𐑹 𐑓𐑫𐑑 𐑹 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑗; 𐑕𐑤𐑦𐑐 𐑘𐑹 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑨𐑑 𐑷𐑤; 𐑯 𐑘𐑹 𐑲𐑛𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑟 𐑚𐑨𐑒 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑪𐑮𐑼. 𐑴𐑝𐑼 ·𐑛𐑰𐑕𐑒𐑸𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝𐑹𐑑𐑦𐑕𐑰𐑟 𐑿 𐑣𐑪𐑝𐑼. 𐑯 𐑐𐑼𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑕, 𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑦𐑛-𐑛𐑱, 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑺𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑢𐑧𐑞𐑼, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑣𐑭𐑓-𐑔𐑮𐑪𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑖𐑮𐑰𐑒 𐑿 𐑛𐑮𐑪𐑐 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑕𐑐𐑨𐑮𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑺 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑼 𐑕𐑰, 𐑯𐑴 𐑥𐑹 𐑑 𐑮𐑲𐑟 𐑓 𐑧𐑝𐑼. 𐑣𐑰𐑛 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑧𐑤, 𐑘𐑰 ·𐑐𐑨𐑯𐑔𐑰𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑕!

·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 36. 𐑞 ·𐑒𐑢𐑹𐑑𐑼-·𐑛𐑧𐑒.

(𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑼 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚: 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑷𐑤.)

𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑩 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑞 𐑩𐑓𐑺 𐑝 𐑞 𐑐𐑲𐑐, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑥𐑹𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑖𐑹𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑚𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑓𐑩𐑕𐑑, ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚, 𐑨𐑟 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑴𐑯𐑑, 𐑩𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑞 𐑒𐑨𐑚𐑦𐑯-𐑜𐑨𐑙𐑢𐑱 𐑑 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑒. 𐑞𐑺 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑰-𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑟 𐑿𐑠𐑵𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑢𐑷𐑒 𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑬𐑼, 𐑨𐑟 𐑒𐑳𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑦 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑥𐑧𐑯, 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑥𐑰𐑤, 𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑩 𐑓𐑿 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑜𐑸𐑛𐑩𐑯.

𐑕𐑵𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑛𐑦, 𐑲𐑝𐑼𐑦 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑛 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑣𐑻𐑛, 𐑨𐑟 𐑑 𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑴 𐑣𐑰 𐑐𐑱𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑟, 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑐𐑤𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑕 𐑕𐑴 𐑓𐑩𐑥𐑦𐑤𐑽 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑑𐑮𐑧𐑛, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑱 𐑢𐑻 𐑷𐑤 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑛𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛, 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑡𐑾𐑤𐑪𐑡𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑑𐑴𐑯𐑟, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑽 𐑥𐑸𐑒 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑷𐑒. 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑿 𐑓𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑩𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑜𐑱𐑟, 𐑑𐑵, 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑚𐑛 𐑯 𐑛𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑮𐑬; 𐑞𐑺 𐑷𐑤𐑕𐑴, 𐑿 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑕𐑰 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑼 𐑓𐑫𐑑-𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑕—𐑞 𐑓𐑫𐑑-𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑳𐑯𐑕𐑤𐑰𐑐𐑦𐑙, 𐑧𐑝𐑼-𐑐𐑱𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑔𐑷𐑑.

𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑩𐑒𐑱𐑠𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑕𐑗𐑩𐑯, 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑛𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑑 𐑛𐑰𐑐𐑼, 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑨𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑻𐑝𐑩𐑕 𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑐 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑹𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑤𐑧𐑓𐑑 𐑩 𐑛𐑰𐑐𐑼 𐑥𐑸𐑒. 𐑯, 𐑕𐑴 𐑓𐑫𐑤 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑔𐑷𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑿𐑯𐑦𐑓𐑹𐑥 𐑑𐑻𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑥𐑱𐑛, 𐑯𐑬 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑥𐑱𐑯-𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑯 𐑯𐑬 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑚𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑒𐑩𐑤, 𐑿 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑰 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑔𐑷𐑑 𐑑𐑻𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑨𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑛, 𐑯 𐑐𐑱𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑨𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑐𐑱𐑕𐑑; 𐑕𐑴 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑰𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑩𐑟𐑧𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑰𐑛, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑢𐑼𐑛 𐑥𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑝 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑬𐑑𐑼 𐑥𐑵𐑝𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑.

“·𐑛'𐑘𐑰 𐑥𐑸𐑒 𐑣𐑦𐑥, ·𐑓𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑒?” 𐑢𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑼𐑛 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚; “𐑞 𐑗𐑦𐑒 𐑞𐑨𐑑'𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑕 𐑞 𐑖𐑧𐑤. '𐑑𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑕𐑵𐑯 𐑚𐑰 𐑬𐑑.”

𐑞 𐑬𐑼𐑟 𐑢𐑹 𐑪𐑯;—·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑯𐑬 𐑖𐑳𐑑 𐑳𐑐 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑨𐑚𐑦𐑯; 𐑩𐑯𐑪𐑯, 𐑐𐑱𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑒, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑕 𐑚𐑦𐑜𐑩𐑑𐑮𐑦 𐑝 𐑐𐑻𐑐𐑩𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑨𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑.

𐑦𐑑 𐑛𐑮𐑵 𐑯𐑽 𐑞 𐑒𐑤𐑴𐑟 𐑝 𐑛𐑱. 𐑕𐑳𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑱𐑥 𐑑 𐑩 𐑣𐑷𐑤𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑚𐑫𐑤𐑢𐑼𐑒𐑕, 𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑴𐑯 𐑤𐑧𐑜 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑷𐑜𐑼-𐑣𐑴𐑤 𐑞𐑺, 𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑜𐑮𐑭𐑕𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑖𐑮𐑬𐑛, 𐑣𐑰 𐑹𐑛𐑼𐑛 ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒 𐑑 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦 𐑭𐑓𐑑.

“𐑕𐑻!” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑞 𐑥𐑱𐑑, 𐑩𐑕𐑑𐑪𐑯𐑦𐑖𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑩𐑯 𐑹𐑛𐑼 𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑛𐑩𐑥 𐑹 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑜𐑦𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑪𐑯 𐑖𐑦𐑐-𐑚𐑹𐑛 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑧𐑐𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑹𐑛𐑦𐑯𐑼𐑦 𐑒𐑱𐑕.

“𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦 𐑭𐑓𐑑,” 𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑰𐑑𐑩𐑛 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚. “𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑-𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑟, 𐑞𐑺! 𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑛𐑬𐑯!”

𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑲𐑼 𐑖𐑦𐑐'𐑕 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑦 𐑢𐑻 𐑩𐑕𐑧𐑥𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑛, 𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑒𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑾𐑕 𐑯 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑦 𐑳𐑯𐑨𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑣𐑧𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑝 𐑓𐑱𐑕𐑩𐑟, 𐑢𐑻 𐑲𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑓 𐑣𐑰 𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑳𐑯𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑞 𐑢𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑣𐑼𐑲𐑟𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑩 𐑕𐑑𐑹𐑥 𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑳𐑐, ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚, 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑮𐑨𐑐𐑦𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑜𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑞 𐑚𐑫𐑤𐑢𐑼𐑒𐑕, 𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑛𐑸𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑲𐑟 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑵, 𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑐𐑶𐑯𐑑; 𐑯 𐑨𐑟 𐑞𐑴 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑩 𐑕𐑴𐑤 𐑢𐑻 𐑯𐑲 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑿𐑥𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑧𐑝𐑦 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑟 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑒. 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑚𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑯 𐑣𐑭𐑓-𐑕𐑤𐑬𐑗𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑿𐑛 𐑑 𐑐𐑱𐑕, 𐑳𐑯𐑥𐑲𐑯𐑛𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑞 𐑥𐑧𐑯; 𐑑𐑦𐑤 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚 𐑒𐑷𐑖𐑩𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑢𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑼𐑛 𐑑 ·𐑓𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑒, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑞𐑺 𐑓 𐑞 𐑐𐑻𐑐𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑢𐑦𐑑𐑯𐑩𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑐𐑦𐑛𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑾𐑯 𐑓𐑰𐑑. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑤𐑪𐑙. 𐑝𐑾𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑷𐑟𐑦𐑙, 𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛:—

“𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑛𐑵 𐑘𐑰 𐑛𐑵 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑘𐑰 𐑕𐑰 𐑩 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑥𐑧𐑯?”

“𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑬𐑑 𐑓 𐑣𐑦𐑥!” 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑳𐑤𐑕𐑦𐑝 𐑮𐑦𐑡𐑶𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑩 𐑕𐑒𐑹 𐑝 𐑒𐑤𐑳𐑚𐑛 𐑝𐑶𐑕𐑩𐑟.

“𐑜𐑫𐑛!” 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑢𐑲𐑤𐑛 𐑩𐑐𐑮𐑵𐑝𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑑𐑴𐑯𐑟; 𐑩𐑚𐑟𐑻𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑣𐑸𐑑𐑦 𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑥𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑳𐑯𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑕𐑗𐑩𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑕𐑴 𐑥𐑨𐑜𐑯𐑧𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑦 𐑔𐑮𐑴𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑥.

“𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑛𐑵 𐑘𐑰 𐑯𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑, 𐑥𐑧𐑯?”

“𐑤𐑴𐑼 𐑩𐑢𐑱, 𐑯 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑣𐑦𐑥!”

“𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑑𐑿𐑯 𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑘𐑰 𐑐𐑫𐑤 𐑑, 𐑥𐑧𐑯?”

“𐑩 𐑛𐑧𐑛 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑹 𐑩 𐑕𐑑𐑴𐑝 𐑚𐑴𐑑!”

𐑥𐑹 𐑯 𐑥𐑹 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑤𐑦 𐑯 𐑓𐑽𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑜𐑤𐑨𐑛 𐑯 𐑩𐑐𐑮𐑵𐑝𐑦𐑙, 𐑜𐑮𐑵 𐑞 𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑨𐑑 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑖𐑬𐑑; 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑞 𐑥𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑯𐑼𐑟 𐑚𐑦𐑜𐑨𐑯 𐑑 𐑜𐑱𐑟 𐑒𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑾𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑨𐑑 𐑰𐑗 𐑳𐑞𐑼, 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑓 𐑥𐑸𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑬 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑱 𐑞𐑧𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑝𐑟 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑱𐑥 𐑕𐑴 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑻𐑐𐑩𐑕𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑕𐑗𐑩𐑯𐑟.

𐑚𐑳𐑑, 𐑞𐑱 𐑢𐑻 𐑷𐑤 𐑰𐑜𐑼𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯, 𐑨𐑟 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚, 𐑯𐑬 𐑣𐑭𐑓-𐑮𐑦𐑝𐑪𐑤𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑦𐑝𐑩𐑑-𐑣𐑴𐑤, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑮𐑰𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑲 𐑳𐑐 𐑩 𐑖𐑮𐑬𐑛, 𐑯 𐑑𐑲𐑑𐑤𐑦, 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑝𐑳𐑤𐑕𐑦𐑝𐑤𐑦 𐑜𐑮𐑭𐑕𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑑, 𐑩𐑛𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑞𐑳𐑕:—

“𐑷𐑤 𐑘𐑰 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑-𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑼𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑯𐑬 𐑣𐑻𐑛 𐑥𐑰 𐑜𐑦𐑝 𐑹𐑛𐑼𐑟 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑩 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑤. 𐑤𐑫𐑒 𐑘𐑰! 𐑛'𐑘𐑰 𐑕𐑰 𐑞𐑦𐑕 ·𐑕𐑐𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑖 𐑬𐑯𐑕 𐑝 𐑜𐑴𐑤𐑛?”—𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑳𐑐 𐑩 𐑚𐑮𐑷𐑛 𐑚𐑮𐑲𐑑 𐑒𐑶𐑯 𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑯—“𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑩 𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑰𐑯 𐑛𐑪𐑤𐑼 𐑐𐑰𐑕, 𐑥𐑧𐑯. ·𐑛'𐑘𐑰 𐑕𐑰 𐑦𐑑? ·𐑥𐑼 ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒, 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑥𐑰 𐑘𐑪𐑯 𐑑𐑪𐑐-𐑥𐑷𐑤.”

𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑞 𐑥𐑱𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑜𐑧𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑣𐑨𐑥𐑼, ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚, 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑 𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑦𐑙, 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑤𐑴𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑳𐑚𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑜𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑐𐑰𐑕 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑒𐑻𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑡𐑨𐑒𐑩𐑑, 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑓 𐑑 𐑣𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑤𐑳𐑕𐑑𐑼, 𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑 𐑿𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑢𐑻𐑛𐑟 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑥𐑰𐑯𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑤𐑴𐑤𐑦 𐑣𐑳𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓, 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑛𐑿𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑕𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑕𐑴 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑤𐑦 𐑥𐑳𐑓𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑸𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑩𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑞 𐑥𐑦𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑣𐑳𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑰𐑤𐑟 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑝𐑲𐑑𐑨𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥.

𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑰𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑑𐑪𐑐-𐑥𐑷𐑤 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒, 𐑣𐑰 𐑩𐑛𐑝𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑑𐑩𐑢𐑹𐑛𐑟 𐑞 𐑥𐑱𐑯-𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑣𐑨𐑥𐑼 𐑳𐑐𐑤𐑦𐑓𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛, 𐑦𐑜𐑟𐑦𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑜𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑳𐑞𐑼, 𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑣𐑲 𐑮𐑱𐑟𐑛 𐑝𐑶𐑕 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑒𐑤𐑱𐑥𐑦𐑙: “𐑣𐑵𐑕𐑴𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑝 𐑘𐑰 𐑮𐑱𐑟𐑩𐑟 𐑥𐑰 𐑩 𐑢𐑲𐑑-𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑮𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑚𐑮𐑬 𐑯 𐑩 𐑒𐑮𐑫𐑒𐑩𐑛 𐑡𐑷; 𐑣𐑵𐑕𐑴𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑝 𐑘𐑰 𐑮𐑱𐑟𐑩𐑟 𐑥𐑰 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑲𐑑-𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑟 𐑐𐑳𐑙𐑒𐑗𐑼𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑼𐑛 𐑓𐑤𐑵𐑒—𐑤𐑫𐑒 𐑘𐑰, 𐑣𐑵𐑕𐑴𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑝 𐑘𐑰 𐑮𐑱𐑟𐑩𐑟 𐑥𐑰 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑣𐑰 𐑖𐑨𐑤 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑜𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑬𐑯𐑕, 𐑥𐑲 𐑚𐑶𐑟!”

“𐑣𐑩𐑟𐑭! 𐑣𐑩𐑟𐑭!” 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 𐑞 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑧𐑯, 𐑨𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑕𐑢𐑦𐑙𐑦𐑙 𐑑𐑸𐑐𐑷𐑤𐑦𐑯𐑟 𐑞𐑱 𐑣𐑱𐑤𐑛 𐑞 𐑨𐑒𐑑 𐑝 𐑯𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑜𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑑 𐑞 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑.

“𐑦𐑑'𐑕 𐑩 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑲 𐑕𐑱,” 𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑿𐑥𐑛 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚, 𐑨𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑞 𐑑𐑪𐑐𐑥𐑷𐑤: “𐑩 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑤. 𐑕𐑒𐑦𐑯 𐑘𐑹 𐑲𐑟 𐑓 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑥𐑧𐑯; 𐑤𐑫𐑒 𐑖𐑸𐑐 𐑓 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼; 𐑦𐑓 𐑘𐑰 𐑕𐑰 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑩 𐑚𐑳𐑚𐑩𐑤, 𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑬𐑑.”

𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑲𐑤 ·𐑑𐑨𐑖𐑑𐑱𐑜𐑴, ·𐑛𐑨𐑜𐑵, 𐑯 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑑 𐑪𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑥𐑹 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑕 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑯 𐑕𐑼𐑐𐑮𐑲𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑞 𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑑, 𐑯 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑮𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑚𐑮𐑬 𐑯 𐑒𐑮𐑫𐑒𐑑 𐑡𐑷 𐑞𐑱 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑓 𐑰𐑗 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑧𐑐𐑼𐑩𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑑𐑳𐑗𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑕𐑐𐑩𐑕𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑒 𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑧𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯.

“𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚,” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 ·𐑑𐑨𐑖𐑑𐑱𐑜𐑴, “𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑒𐑷𐑤 ·𐑥𐑪𐑚𐑦 ·𐑛𐑦𐑒.”

“𐑥𐑪𐑚𐑦 ·𐑛𐑦𐑒?” 𐑖𐑬𐑑𐑩𐑛 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚. “𐑛𐑵 𐑘𐑰 𐑯𐑴 𐑞 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑞𐑧𐑯, ·𐑑𐑨𐑖?”

“𐑛𐑳𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑓𐑨𐑯-𐑑𐑱𐑤 𐑩 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑒𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑾𐑕, 𐑕𐑻, 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑣𐑰 𐑜𐑴𐑟 𐑛𐑬𐑯?” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑞 ·𐑜𐑱-·𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑼 𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑚𐑼𐑩𐑑𐑤𐑦.

“𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑩 𐑒𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑾𐑕 𐑕𐑐𐑬𐑑, 𐑑𐑵,” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 ·𐑛𐑨𐑜𐑵, “𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑚𐑫𐑖𐑦, 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑓 𐑩 ·𐑐𐑸𐑥𐑩𐑕𐑧𐑑𐑦, 𐑯 𐑥𐑲𐑑𐑦 𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑒, ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚?”

“𐑯 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑢𐑳𐑯, 𐑑𐑵, 𐑔𐑮𐑰—𐑴! 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑲𐑼𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑣𐑲𐑛, 𐑑𐑵, ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯,” 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑡𐑶𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛𐑤𐑦, “𐑷𐑤 𐑑𐑢𐑦𐑕𐑒-𐑑𐑰 𐑚𐑰-𐑑𐑢𐑲𐑕𐑒, 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑣𐑦𐑥—𐑣𐑦𐑥—” 𐑓𐑷𐑤𐑑𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑸𐑛 𐑓 𐑩 𐑢𐑻𐑛, 𐑯 𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑵𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑯 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑨𐑟 𐑞𐑴 𐑳𐑯𐑒𐑹𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑚𐑪𐑑𐑩𐑤—“𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑣𐑦𐑥—𐑣𐑦𐑥—”

“𐑒𐑹𐑒𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑵!” 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚, “𐑲, ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜, 𐑞 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑟 𐑤𐑲 𐑷𐑤 𐑑𐑢𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑯 𐑮𐑧𐑯𐑗𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥; 𐑲, ·𐑛𐑨𐑜𐑵, 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑐𐑬𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑩 𐑚𐑦𐑜 𐑢𐑳𐑯, 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑣𐑴𐑤 𐑖𐑪𐑒 𐑝 𐑢𐑰𐑑, 𐑯 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑩 𐑐𐑲𐑤 𐑝 𐑬𐑼 ·𐑯𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑑 𐑢𐑫𐑤 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑨𐑯𐑿𐑩𐑤 𐑖𐑰𐑐-𐑖𐑽𐑦𐑙; 𐑲, ·𐑑𐑨𐑖𐑑𐑱𐑜𐑴, 𐑯 𐑣𐑰 𐑓𐑨𐑯-𐑑𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑕𐑐𐑤𐑦𐑑 𐑡𐑦𐑚 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑕𐑒𐑢𐑷𐑤. 𐑛𐑧𐑔 𐑯 𐑛𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑟! 𐑥𐑧𐑯, 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 ·𐑥𐑪𐑚𐑦 ·𐑛𐑦𐑒 𐑘𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑕𐑰𐑯—·𐑥𐑪𐑚𐑦 ·𐑛𐑦𐑒—·𐑥𐑪𐑚𐑦 ·𐑛𐑦𐑒!”

“𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚,” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒, 𐑣𐑵, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚 𐑯 ·𐑓𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑒, 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑞𐑳𐑕 𐑓𐑸 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑲𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑵𐑐𐑽𐑽 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑮𐑰𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑼𐑐𐑮𐑲𐑟, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑒 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑔𐑷𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑯𐑛 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼. “𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚, 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑣𐑻𐑛 𐑝 ·𐑥𐑪𐑚𐑦 ·𐑛𐑦𐑒—𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 ·𐑥𐑪𐑚𐑦 ·𐑛𐑦𐑒 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑑𐑫𐑒 𐑪𐑓 𐑞𐑲 𐑤𐑧𐑜?”

“𐑣𐑵 𐑑𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑞𐑰 𐑞𐑨𐑑?” 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚; 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑐𐑷𐑟𐑦𐑙, “𐑲, ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒; 𐑲, 𐑥𐑲 𐑣𐑸𐑑𐑦𐑟 𐑷𐑤 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛; 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 ·𐑥𐑪𐑚𐑦 ·𐑛𐑦𐑒 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑥𐑰; ·𐑥𐑪𐑚𐑦 ·𐑛𐑦𐑒 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑚𐑮𐑷𐑑 𐑥𐑰 𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑛𐑧𐑛 𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑥𐑐 𐑲 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑪𐑯 𐑯𐑬. 𐑲, 𐑲,” 𐑣𐑰 𐑖𐑬𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑑𐑼𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑒, 𐑤𐑬𐑛, 𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑥𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑪𐑚, 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑝 𐑩 𐑣𐑸𐑑-𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑥𐑵𐑕; “𐑲, 𐑲! 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑩𐑒𐑻𐑕𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑮𐑱𐑟𐑛 𐑥𐑰; 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑩 𐑐𐑫𐑼 𐑐𐑧𐑜𐑦𐑙 𐑤𐑳𐑚𐑼 𐑝 𐑥𐑰 𐑓 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑯 𐑩 𐑛𐑱!” 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑑𐑪𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑴𐑔 𐑸𐑥𐑟, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑥𐑧𐑠𐑼𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑖𐑬𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑬𐑑: “𐑲, 𐑲! 𐑯 𐑲'𐑤 𐑗𐑱𐑕 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑜𐑫𐑛 ·𐑣𐑴𐑐, 𐑯 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑞 ·𐑣𐑹𐑯, 𐑯 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑞 ·𐑯𐑹𐑢𐑱 ·𐑥𐑱𐑤𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑩𐑥, 𐑯 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑐𐑼𐑛𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯'𐑟 𐑓𐑤𐑱𐑥𐑟 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑲 𐑜𐑦𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑳𐑐. 𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑘𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑑 𐑓, 𐑥𐑧𐑯! 𐑑 𐑗𐑱𐑕 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑪𐑯 𐑚𐑴𐑔 𐑕𐑲𐑛𐑟 𐑝 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛, 𐑯 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑷𐑤 𐑕𐑲𐑛𐑟 𐑝 𐑻𐑔, 𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑐𐑬𐑑𐑕 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑒 𐑚𐑤𐑳𐑛 𐑯 𐑮𐑴𐑤𐑟 𐑓𐑦𐑯 𐑬𐑑. 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑱 𐑘𐑰, 𐑥𐑧𐑯, 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑘𐑰 𐑕𐑐𐑤𐑲𐑕 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑪𐑯 𐑦𐑑, 𐑯𐑬? 𐑲 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒 𐑘𐑰 𐑛𐑵 𐑤𐑫𐑒 𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑝.”

“𐑲, 𐑲!” 𐑖𐑬𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑞 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑽𐑟 𐑯 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑧𐑯, 𐑮𐑳𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑒𐑤𐑴𐑕𐑼 𐑑 𐑞 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑥𐑨𐑯: “𐑩 𐑖𐑸𐑐 𐑲 𐑓 𐑞 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑤; 𐑩 𐑖𐑸𐑐 𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑕 𐑓 ·𐑥𐑪𐑚𐑦 ·𐑛𐑦𐑒!”

“𐑜𐑪𐑛 𐑚𐑤𐑧𐑕 𐑘𐑰,” 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑑 𐑣𐑭𐑓 𐑕𐑪𐑚 𐑯 𐑣𐑭𐑓 𐑖𐑬𐑑. “𐑜𐑪𐑛 𐑚𐑤𐑧𐑕 𐑘𐑰, 𐑥𐑧𐑯. 𐑕𐑑𐑿𐑼𐑛! 𐑜𐑴 𐑛𐑮𐑷 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑥𐑧𐑠𐑼 𐑝 𐑜𐑮𐑪𐑜. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑑'𐑕 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑓𐑱𐑕 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑, ·𐑥𐑼 ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒; 𐑢𐑦𐑤𐑑 𐑞𐑬 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑗𐑱𐑕 𐑞 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑤? 𐑸𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑜𐑱𐑥 𐑓 ·𐑥𐑪𐑚𐑦 ·𐑛𐑦𐑒?”

“𐑲 𐑨𐑥 𐑜𐑱𐑥 𐑓 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑮𐑫𐑒𐑩𐑛 𐑡𐑷, 𐑯 𐑓 𐑞 𐑡𐑷𐑟 𐑝 ·𐑛𐑧𐑔 𐑑𐑵, ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚, 𐑦𐑓 𐑦𐑑 𐑓𐑺𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑱 𐑝 𐑞 𐑚𐑦𐑟𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑢𐑰 𐑓𐑪𐑤𐑴; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑲 𐑒𐑱𐑥 𐑣𐑽 𐑑 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟, 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑥𐑲 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑭𐑯𐑛𐑼'𐑟 𐑝𐑧𐑯𐑡𐑩𐑯𐑕. 𐑣𐑬 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑚𐑨𐑮𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑞𐑲 𐑝𐑧𐑯𐑡𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑘𐑰𐑤𐑛 𐑞𐑰 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑓 𐑞𐑬 𐑜𐑧𐑑𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑑, ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚? 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑓𐑧𐑗 𐑞𐑰 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑦𐑯 𐑬𐑼 ·𐑯𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑑 𐑥𐑸𐑒𐑩𐑑.”

“·𐑯𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑑 𐑥𐑸𐑒𐑩𐑑! 𐑣𐑵𐑑! 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑒𐑤𐑴𐑕𐑼, ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒; 𐑞𐑬 𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑢𐑲𐑼𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑩 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑤𐑴𐑼 𐑤𐑱𐑼. 𐑦𐑓 𐑥𐑳𐑯𐑦'𐑟 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑞 𐑥𐑧𐑠𐑼𐑼, 𐑥𐑨𐑯, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑩𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑿𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑞𐑺 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑙-𐑣𐑬𐑕 𐑞 𐑜𐑤𐑴𐑚, 𐑚𐑲 𐑜𐑻𐑛𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑜𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑟, 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑑 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑐𐑸𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑗; 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑤𐑧𐑑 𐑥𐑰 𐑑𐑧𐑤 𐑞𐑰, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑲 𐑝𐑧𐑯𐑡𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑓𐑧𐑗 𐑩 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑰𐑥𐑾𐑥 𐑣𐑽!”

“𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑥𐑲𐑑𐑕 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑗𐑧𐑕𐑑,” 𐑢𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑼𐑛 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚, “𐑢𐑪𐑑'𐑕 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑓? 𐑥𐑦𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑕 𐑦𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑝𐑭𐑕𐑑, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑣𐑪𐑤𐑴.”

“𐑝𐑧𐑯𐑡𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑪𐑯 𐑩 𐑛𐑳𐑥 𐑚𐑮𐑵𐑑!” 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒, “𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑥𐑴𐑑 𐑞𐑰 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑚𐑤𐑲𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑑! 𐑥𐑨𐑛𐑯𐑩𐑕! 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑦𐑯𐑮𐑱𐑡𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑛𐑳𐑥 𐑔𐑦𐑙, ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚, 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑟 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑕𐑓𐑩𐑥𐑩𐑕.”

“𐑣𐑸𐑒 𐑘𐑰 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯—𐑞 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑤𐑴𐑼 𐑤𐑱𐑼. 𐑷𐑤 𐑝𐑦𐑟𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑪𐑚𐑡𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑕, 𐑥𐑨𐑯, 𐑸 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑐𐑱𐑕𐑑𐑚𐑹𐑛 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑒𐑕. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑰𐑗 𐑦𐑝𐑧𐑯𐑑—𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑤𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑨𐑒𐑑, 𐑞 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑬𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑛𐑰𐑛—𐑞𐑺, 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑳𐑯𐑯𐑴𐑯 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑮𐑰𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑐𐑫𐑑𐑕 𐑓𐑹𐑔 𐑞 𐑥𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑝 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑓𐑰𐑗𐑼𐑟 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑚𐑦𐑣𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑞 𐑳𐑯𐑮𐑰𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑒. 𐑦𐑓 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑒, 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑒 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑞 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑒! 𐑣𐑬 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑼 𐑮𐑰𐑗 𐑬𐑑𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑧𐑐𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑔𐑮𐑳𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑞 𐑢𐑷𐑤? 𐑑 𐑥𐑰, 𐑞 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑦𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑷𐑤, 𐑖𐑳𐑝𐑛 𐑯𐑽 𐑑 𐑥𐑰. 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑲 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒 𐑞𐑺'𐑟 𐑯𐑷𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑘𐑪𐑯𐑛. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 '𐑑𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑳𐑓. 𐑣𐑰 𐑑𐑭𐑕𐑒𐑕 𐑥𐑰; 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑰𐑐𐑕 𐑥𐑰; 𐑲 𐑕𐑰 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑬𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑡𐑩𐑕 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑧𐑙𐑔, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑵𐑑𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑥𐑨𐑤𐑦𐑕 𐑕𐑦𐑯𐑿𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑑. 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑵𐑑𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑟 𐑗𐑰𐑓𐑤𐑦 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑲 𐑣𐑱𐑑; 𐑯 𐑚𐑰 𐑞 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑱𐑡𐑩𐑯𐑑, 𐑹 𐑚𐑰 𐑞 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑐𐑩𐑤, 𐑲 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑮𐑰𐑒 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑱𐑑 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥. 𐑑𐑷𐑒 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑑 𐑥𐑰 𐑝 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑕𐑓𐑩𐑥𐑦, 𐑥𐑨𐑯; 𐑲'𐑛 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑒 𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑯 𐑦𐑓 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑳𐑤𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑥𐑰. 𐑓 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑯 𐑛𐑵 𐑞𐑨𐑑, 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑲 𐑛𐑵 𐑞 𐑳𐑞𐑼; 𐑕𐑦𐑯𐑕 𐑞𐑺 𐑦𐑟 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑩 𐑕𐑹𐑑 𐑝 𐑓𐑺 𐑐𐑤𐑱 𐑣𐑽𐑦𐑯, 𐑡𐑧𐑤𐑩𐑕𐑦 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑲𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑷𐑤 𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑥𐑲 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑼, 𐑥𐑨𐑯, 𐑦𐑟 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑓𐑺 𐑐𐑤𐑱. 𐑣𐑵'𐑟 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑥𐑰? 𐑑𐑮𐑵𐑔 𐑣𐑨𐑔 𐑯𐑴 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑓𐑲𐑯𐑟. 𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑪𐑓 𐑞𐑲𐑯 𐑲! 𐑥𐑹 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑪𐑤𐑼𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑓𐑰𐑯𐑛𐑟' 𐑜𐑤𐑺𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑦𐑟 𐑩 𐑛𐑴𐑤𐑑𐑦𐑖 𐑕𐑑𐑺! 𐑕𐑴, 𐑕𐑴; 𐑞𐑬 𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑯 𐑐𐑱𐑤𐑩𐑕𐑑; 𐑥𐑲 𐑣𐑰𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑥𐑧𐑤𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑞𐑰 𐑑 𐑨𐑙𐑜𐑼-𐑜𐑤𐑴. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑤𐑫𐑒 𐑘𐑰, ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒, 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑰𐑑, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑳𐑯𐑕𐑧𐑟 𐑦𐑑𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓. 𐑞𐑺 𐑸 𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑣𐑵𐑥 𐑢𐑹𐑥 𐑢𐑻𐑛𐑟 𐑸 𐑕𐑥𐑷𐑤 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑜𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑦. 𐑲 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑕 𐑞𐑰. 𐑤𐑧𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑜𐑴. 𐑤𐑫𐑒! 𐑕𐑰 𐑘𐑪𐑯𐑛𐑼 ·𐑑𐑻𐑒𐑦𐑖 𐑗𐑰𐑒𐑕 𐑝 𐑕𐑐𐑪𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑑𐑷𐑯—𐑤𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑙, 𐑚𐑮𐑰𐑞𐑦𐑙 𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑗𐑼𐑟 𐑐𐑱𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑯. 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑱𐑜𐑩𐑯 𐑤𐑧𐑐𐑼𐑛𐑟—𐑞 𐑳𐑯𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑯 𐑳𐑯𐑢𐑻𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑟, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑦𐑝; 𐑯 𐑕𐑰𐑒, 𐑯 𐑜𐑦𐑝 𐑯𐑴 𐑮𐑰𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑓 𐑞 𐑑𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑛 𐑤𐑲𐑓 𐑞𐑱 𐑓𐑰𐑤! 𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑵, 𐑥𐑨𐑯, 𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑵! 𐑸 𐑞𐑱 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑢𐑦𐑞 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚, 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑥𐑨𐑑𐑼 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤? 𐑕𐑰 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚! 𐑣𐑰 𐑤𐑭𐑓𐑕! 𐑕𐑰 𐑘𐑪𐑯𐑛𐑼 ·𐑗𐑦𐑤𐑾𐑯! 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑯𐑹𐑑𐑕 𐑑 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒 𐑝 𐑦𐑑. 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑳𐑐 𐑩𐑥𐑦𐑛 𐑞 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑣𐑳𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑱𐑯, 𐑞𐑲 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑑𐑪𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑨𐑐𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑪𐑑, ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒! 𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑑? 𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑑. '𐑑𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑑 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑐 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑓𐑦𐑯; 𐑯𐑴 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑕 𐑓𐑰𐑑 𐑓 ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒. 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑥𐑹? 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑐𐑫𐑼 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑑, 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑞 𐑚𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑕 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑷𐑤 ·𐑯𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑑, 𐑖𐑫𐑼𐑤𐑦 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑙 𐑚𐑨𐑒, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑓𐑹𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑-𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑒𐑤𐑳𐑗𐑑 𐑩 𐑢𐑧𐑑𐑕𐑑𐑴𐑯? 𐑭! 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑕𐑰𐑟 𐑞𐑰; 𐑲 𐑕𐑰! 𐑞 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑴 𐑤𐑦𐑓𐑑𐑕 𐑞𐑰! 𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑒, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑒!—𐑲, 𐑲! 𐑞𐑲 𐑕𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑕, 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑝𐑶𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑞𐑰. (𐑩𐑕𐑲𐑛) ·𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑖𐑪𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑥𐑲 𐑛𐑲𐑤𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑩𐑤𐑟, 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑣𐑱𐑤𐑛 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑤𐑳𐑙𐑟. 𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒 𐑯𐑬 𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑲𐑯; 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑩𐑐𐑴𐑟 𐑥𐑰 𐑯𐑬, 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑚𐑧𐑤𐑘𐑩𐑯.”

“𐑜𐑪𐑛 𐑒𐑰𐑐 𐑥𐑰!—𐑒𐑰𐑐 𐑳𐑕 𐑷𐑤!” 𐑥𐑻𐑥𐑼𐑛 ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒, 𐑤𐑴𐑤𐑦.

𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑡𐑶 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑗𐑭𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛, 𐑑𐑨𐑕𐑦𐑑 𐑨𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑥𐑱𐑑, ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑣𐑽 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑹𐑚𐑴𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑩𐑒𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯; 𐑯𐑹 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑞 𐑤𐑴 𐑤𐑭𐑓 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛; 𐑯𐑹 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑱𐑡𐑦𐑙 𐑝𐑲𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑒𐑹𐑛𐑦𐑡; 𐑯𐑹 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑞 𐑣𐑪𐑤𐑴 𐑓𐑤𐑨𐑐 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑞 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑕, 𐑨𐑟 𐑓 𐑩 𐑥𐑴𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑣𐑸𐑑𐑕 𐑕𐑨𐑙𐑒 𐑦𐑯. 𐑓 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯 ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒'𐑕 𐑛𐑬𐑯𐑒𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑲𐑟 𐑤𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑳𐑐 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚𐑼𐑯𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑤𐑲𐑓; 𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑚𐑑𐑼𐑱𐑯𐑾𐑯 𐑤𐑭𐑓 𐑛𐑲𐑛 𐑩𐑢𐑱; 𐑞 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑚𐑤𐑵 𐑪𐑯; 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑓𐑦𐑤𐑛 𐑬𐑑; 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑣𐑰𐑝𐑛 𐑯 𐑮𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑨𐑟 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹. 𐑭, 𐑘𐑰 𐑨𐑛𐑥𐑪𐑯𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑯 𐑢𐑹𐑯𐑦𐑙𐑟! 𐑢𐑲 𐑕𐑑𐑱 𐑘𐑰 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑘𐑰 𐑒𐑳𐑥? 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑮𐑭𐑞𐑼 𐑸 𐑘𐑰 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑢𐑹𐑯𐑦𐑙𐑟, 𐑘𐑰 𐑖𐑨𐑛𐑴𐑟! 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑴 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑, 𐑨𐑟 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑒𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑓𐑹𐑜𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑦𐑯. 𐑓 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑑 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯 𐑳𐑕, 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑼𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑯𐑦𐑕𐑧𐑕𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑬𐑼 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙, 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑛𐑮𐑲𐑝 𐑳𐑕 𐑪𐑯.

“𐑞 𐑥𐑧𐑠𐑼! 𐑞 𐑥𐑧𐑠𐑼!” 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚.

𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑰𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑚𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑐𐑿𐑑𐑼, 𐑯 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑞 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑽𐑟, 𐑣𐑰 𐑹𐑛𐑼𐑛 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑛𐑿𐑕 𐑞𐑺 𐑢𐑧𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑟. 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑯𐑽 𐑞 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞𐑺 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟, 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑥𐑱𐑑𐑕 𐑕𐑑𐑫𐑛 𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞𐑺 𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐'𐑕 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑦 𐑓𐑹𐑥𐑛 𐑩 𐑕𐑻𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑵𐑐; 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑑𐑫𐑛 𐑓 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑕𐑻𐑗𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑲𐑦𐑙 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑮𐑵. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑢𐑲𐑤𐑛 𐑲𐑟 𐑥𐑧𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟, 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑚𐑤𐑳𐑛𐑖𐑪𐑑 𐑲𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑺𐑦 𐑢𐑫𐑤𐑝𐑟 𐑥𐑰𐑑 𐑞 𐑲 𐑝 𐑞𐑺 𐑤𐑰𐑛𐑼, 𐑺 𐑣𐑰 𐑮𐑳𐑖𐑩𐑟 𐑪𐑯 𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑤 𐑝 𐑞 𐑚𐑲𐑕𐑩𐑯; 𐑚𐑳𐑑, 𐑩𐑤𐑨𐑕! 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑑 𐑓𐑷𐑤 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑯 𐑕𐑯𐑺 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑾𐑯.

“𐑛𐑮𐑦𐑙𐑒 𐑯 𐑐𐑭𐑕!” 𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛, 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑣𐑧𐑝𐑦 𐑗𐑸𐑡𐑛 𐑓𐑤𐑨𐑜𐑩𐑯 𐑑 𐑞 𐑯𐑽𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑩𐑯. “𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑵 𐑩𐑤𐑴𐑯 𐑯𐑬 𐑛𐑮𐑦𐑙𐑒. 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑦𐑑, 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛! 𐑖𐑹𐑑 𐑛𐑮𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑕—𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑕𐑢𐑪𐑤𐑴𐑟, 𐑥𐑧𐑯; '𐑑𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑪𐑑 𐑨𐑟 ·𐑕𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑯'𐑟 𐑣𐑵𐑓. 𐑕𐑴, 𐑕𐑴; 𐑦𐑑 𐑜𐑴𐑟 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑩𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦. 𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑐𐑲𐑮𐑩𐑤𐑲𐑟𐑩𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑘𐑰; 𐑓𐑹𐑒𐑕 𐑬𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑻𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑑-𐑕𐑯𐑨𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑲. 𐑢𐑧𐑤 𐑛𐑳𐑯; 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑛𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑛. 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑱 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑑, 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑱 𐑦𐑑 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑟. 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑑 𐑥𐑰—𐑣𐑽'𐑟 𐑩 𐑣𐑪𐑤𐑴! 𐑥𐑧𐑯, 𐑘𐑰 𐑕𐑰𐑥 𐑞 𐑘𐑽𐑟; 𐑕𐑴 𐑚𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑤𐑲𐑓 𐑦𐑟 𐑜𐑳𐑤𐑐𐑑 𐑯 𐑜𐑪𐑯. 𐑕𐑑𐑿𐑼𐑛, 𐑮𐑰𐑓𐑦𐑤!

“𐑩𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑯𐑬, 𐑥𐑲 𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑝𐑟. 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑛 𐑘𐑰 𐑷𐑤 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯; 𐑯 𐑘𐑰 𐑥𐑱𐑑𐑕, 𐑓𐑤𐑨𐑙𐑒 𐑥𐑰 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑘𐑹 𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟; 𐑯 𐑘𐑰 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑽𐑟, 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑞𐑺 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑘𐑹 𐑲𐑼𐑯𐑟; 𐑯 𐑘𐑰, 𐑕𐑑𐑬𐑑 𐑥𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑯𐑼𐑟, 𐑮𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑰 𐑦𐑯, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑲 𐑥𐑱 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑕𐑹𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑝𐑲𐑝 𐑩 𐑯𐑴𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑒𐑳𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑥 𐑝 𐑥𐑲 𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑼𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑓𐑭𐑞𐑼𐑟 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑥𐑰. 𐑴 𐑥𐑧𐑯, 𐑿 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑕𐑰 𐑞𐑨𐑑—·𐑣𐑭! 𐑚𐑶, 𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑚𐑨𐑒? 𐑚𐑨𐑛 𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑵𐑯𐑼. 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑑 𐑥𐑰. 𐑢𐑲, 𐑯𐑬, 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑐𐑿𐑑𐑼 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑮𐑳𐑯 𐑚𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯, 𐑢𐑻'𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑞𐑬 ·𐑕𐑑 ·𐑝𐑰𐑑𐑵𐑕' 𐑦𐑥𐑐—𐑩𐑢𐑱, 𐑞𐑬 𐑱𐑜𐑿!

“𐑩𐑛𐑝𐑭𐑯𐑕, 𐑘𐑰 𐑥𐑱𐑑𐑕! 𐑒𐑮𐑪𐑕 𐑘𐑹 𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑓𐑫𐑤 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑥𐑰. 𐑢𐑧𐑤 𐑛𐑳𐑯! 𐑤𐑧𐑑 𐑥𐑰 𐑑𐑳𐑗 𐑞 𐑨𐑒𐑕𐑦𐑕.” 𐑕𐑴 𐑕𐑱𐑦𐑙, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑸𐑥, 𐑣𐑰 𐑜𐑮𐑭𐑕𐑐𐑑 𐑞 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑤𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑤, 𐑮𐑱𐑛𐑦𐑱𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑒𐑮𐑪𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑼; 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑕𐑴 𐑛𐑵𐑦𐑙, 𐑕𐑳𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑯 𐑯𐑻𐑝𐑩𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑑𐑢𐑦𐑗𐑑 𐑞𐑧𐑥; 𐑥𐑰𐑯𐑢𐑲𐑤, 𐑜𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒 𐑑 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚; 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚 𐑑 ·𐑓𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑒. 𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑨𐑟 𐑞𐑴, 𐑚𐑲 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑯𐑱𐑥𐑤𐑩𐑕, 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑽𐑽 𐑝𐑴𐑤𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯, 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑓𐑱𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑖𐑪𐑒𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑓𐑲𐑼𐑦 𐑦𐑥𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑩𐑒𐑿𐑥𐑿𐑤𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑦𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑤𐑱𐑛𐑩𐑯 𐑡𐑸 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑴𐑯 𐑥𐑨𐑜𐑯𐑧𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑤𐑲𐑓. 𐑞 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑥𐑱𐑑𐑕 𐑒𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑛 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑪𐑙, 𐑕𐑩𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑯𐑛, 𐑯 𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑨𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑. 𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚 𐑯 ·𐑓𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑒 𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑑 𐑕𐑲𐑛𐑢𐑱𐑟 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑣𐑦𐑥; 𐑞 𐑪𐑯𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑲 𐑝 ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒 𐑓𐑧𐑤 𐑛𐑬𐑯𐑮𐑲𐑑.

“𐑦𐑯 𐑝𐑱𐑯!” 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚; “𐑚𐑳𐑑, 𐑥𐑱𐑚𐑰, '𐑑𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑧𐑤. 𐑓 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑘𐑰 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑕 𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑞 𐑓𐑫𐑤-𐑓𐑹𐑕𐑑 𐑖𐑪𐑒, 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑥𐑲𐑯 𐑴𐑯 𐑦𐑤𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑒 𐑔𐑦𐑙, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑐𐑼𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑕 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑲𐑼𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑬𐑑 𐑥𐑰. 𐑐𐑼𐑗𐑨𐑯𐑕, 𐑑𐑵, 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑛𐑮𐑪𐑐𐑑 𐑘𐑰 𐑛𐑧𐑛. 𐑐𐑼𐑗𐑨𐑯𐑕 𐑘𐑰 𐑯𐑰𐑛 𐑦𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑑. 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟! 𐑯 𐑯𐑬, 𐑘𐑰 𐑥𐑱𐑑𐑕, 𐑲 𐑛𐑵 𐑩𐑐𐑶𐑯𐑑 𐑘𐑰 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑒𐑳𐑐𐑚𐑺𐑼𐑟 𐑑 𐑥𐑲 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑐𐑱𐑜𐑩𐑯 𐑒𐑦𐑯𐑟𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑞𐑺—𐑘𐑪𐑯 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑪𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑯 𐑯𐑴𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑥𐑧𐑯, 𐑥𐑲 𐑝𐑨𐑤𐑾𐑯𐑑 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑽𐑟. 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑛𐑱𐑯 𐑞 𐑑𐑭𐑕𐑒? 𐑢𐑪𐑑, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 ·𐑐𐑴𐑐 𐑢𐑪𐑖𐑩𐑟 𐑞 𐑓𐑰𐑑 𐑝 𐑚𐑧𐑜𐑼𐑟, 𐑿𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑑𐑦𐑸𐑩 𐑓 𐑿𐑼? 𐑴, 𐑥𐑲 𐑕𐑢𐑰𐑑 𐑒𐑸𐑛𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑤𐑟! 𐑘𐑹 𐑴𐑯 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑯, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑖𐑨𐑤 𐑚𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑘𐑰 𐑑 𐑦𐑑. 𐑲 𐑛𐑵 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑹𐑛𐑼 𐑘𐑰; 𐑘𐑰 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑦𐑑. 𐑒𐑳𐑑 𐑘𐑹 𐑕𐑰𐑟𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑯 𐑛𐑮𐑷 𐑞 𐑐𐑴𐑤𐑟, 𐑘𐑰 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑽𐑟!”

𐑕𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑴𐑚𐑱𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑹𐑛𐑼, 𐑞 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑽𐑟 𐑯𐑬 𐑕𐑑𐑫𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑛𐑦𐑑𐑨𐑗𐑑 𐑲𐑼𐑯 𐑐𐑸𐑑 𐑝 𐑞𐑺 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑟, 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑓𐑰𐑑 𐑤𐑪𐑙, 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑛, 𐑚𐑸𐑚𐑟 𐑳𐑐, 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑣𐑦𐑥.

“𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑚 𐑥𐑰 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑒𐑰𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑰𐑤! 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑑 𐑞𐑧𐑥; 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑑 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑴𐑝𐑼! 𐑯𐑴 𐑘𐑰 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑞 𐑜𐑪𐑚𐑤𐑩𐑑 𐑧𐑯𐑛? 𐑑𐑻𐑯 𐑳𐑐 𐑞 𐑕𐑪𐑒𐑩𐑑! 𐑕𐑴, 𐑕𐑴; 𐑯𐑬, 𐑘𐑰 𐑒𐑳𐑐-𐑚𐑺𐑼𐑟, 𐑩𐑛𐑝𐑭𐑯𐑕. 𐑞 𐑲𐑼𐑯𐑟! 𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑞𐑧𐑥; 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑲 𐑓𐑦𐑤!” 𐑓𐑹𐑔𐑢𐑦𐑔, 𐑕𐑤𐑴𐑤𐑦 𐑜𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑪𐑓𐑦𐑕𐑼 𐑑 𐑞 𐑳𐑞𐑼, 𐑣𐑰 𐑚𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑛 𐑞 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯 𐑕𐑪𐑒𐑩𐑑𐑕 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑓𐑲𐑼𐑦 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼𐑟 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑐𐑿𐑑𐑼.

“𐑯𐑬, 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑑 𐑔𐑮𐑰, 𐑘𐑰 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛. 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑞 𐑥𐑻𐑛𐑼𐑩𐑕 𐑗𐑨𐑤𐑦𐑕𐑩𐑟! 𐑚𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑴 𐑞𐑧𐑥, 𐑘𐑰 𐑣𐑵 𐑸 𐑯𐑬 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑐𐑸𐑑𐑦𐑟 𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑪𐑤𐑿𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑤𐑰𐑜. 𐑣𐑭! 𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒! 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞 𐑛𐑰𐑛 𐑦𐑟 𐑛𐑳𐑯! 𐑘𐑪𐑯 𐑮𐑨𐑑𐑦𐑓𐑲𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑳𐑯 𐑯𐑬 𐑢𐑱𐑑𐑕 𐑑 𐑕𐑦𐑑 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑦𐑑. 𐑛𐑮𐑦𐑙𐑒, 𐑘𐑰 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑽𐑟! 𐑛𐑮𐑦𐑙𐑒 𐑯 𐑕𐑢𐑺, 𐑘𐑰 𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑔𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑚𐑴𐑑'𐑕 𐑚𐑬—·𐑛𐑧𐑔 𐑑 ·𐑥𐑪𐑚𐑦 ·𐑛𐑦𐑒! 𐑜𐑪𐑛 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑑 𐑳𐑕 𐑷𐑤, 𐑦𐑓 𐑢𐑰 𐑛𐑵 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑑 ·𐑥𐑪𐑚𐑦 ·𐑛𐑦𐑒 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑛𐑧𐑔!” 𐑞 𐑤𐑪𐑙, 𐑚𐑸𐑚𐑛 𐑕𐑑𐑰𐑤 𐑜𐑪𐑚𐑤𐑩𐑑𐑕 𐑢𐑻 𐑤𐑦𐑓𐑑𐑩𐑛; 𐑯 𐑑 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑟 𐑯 𐑥𐑨𐑤𐑩𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑞 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑦𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑢𐑻 𐑕𐑦𐑥𐑩𐑤𐑑𐑱𐑯𐑾𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑓𐑑 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑣𐑦𐑕. 𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒 𐑐𐑱𐑤𐑛, 𐑯 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑛, 𐑯 𐑖𐑦𐑝𐑼𐑛. 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑕 𐑥𐑹, 𐑯 𐑓𐑲𐑯𐑩𐑤𐑦, 𐑞 𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑤𐑧𐑯𐑦𐑖𐑑 𐑐𐑿𐑑𐑼 𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑞 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑞 𐑓𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑒𐑮𐑵; 𐑢𐑧𐑯, 𐑢𐑱𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑮𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑑 𐑞𐑧𐑥, 𐑞𐑱 𐑷𐑤 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑕𐑑; 𐑯 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑲𐑼𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑨𐑚𐑦𐑯.

·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 37. 𐑕𐑳𐑯𐑕𐑧𐑑.

𐑞 𐑒𐑨𐑚𐑦𐑯; 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑻𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑴𐑟; ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑕𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑤𐑴𐑯, 𐑯 𐑜𐑱𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑬𐑑.

𐑲 𐑤𐑰𐑝 𐑩 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑯 𐑑𐑻𐑚𐑦𐑛 𐑢𐑱𐑒; 𐑐𐑱𐑤 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼𐑟, 𐑐𐑱𐑤𐑼 𐑗𐑰𐑒𐑕, 𐑢𐑺'𐑼 𐑲 𐑕𐑱𐑤. 𐑞 𐑧𐑯𐑝𐑾𐑕 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑴𐑟 𐑕𐑲𐑛𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑕𐑢𐑧𐑤 𐑑 𐑢𐑧𐑤𐑥 𐑥𐑲 𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑒; 𐑤𐑧𐑑 𐑞𐑧𐑥; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑲 𐑐𐑭𐑕.

𐑘𐑪𐑯𐑛𐑼, 𐑚𐑲 𐑧𐑝𐑼-𐑚𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑜𐑪𐑚𐑤𐑩𐑑'𐑕 𐑮𐑦𐑥, 𐑞 𐑢𐑹𐑥 𐑢𐑱𐑝𐑟 𐑚𐑤𐑳𐑖 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑢𐑲𐑯. 𐑞 𐑜𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑚𐑮𐑬 𐑐𐑤𐑳𐑥𐑟 𐑞 𐑚𐑤𐑵. 𐑞 𐑛𐑲𐑝𐑼 𐑕𐑳𐑯—𐑕𐑤𐑴 𐑛𐑲𐑝𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑯𐑵𐑯—𐑜𐑴𐑟 𐑛𐑬𐑯; 𐑥𐑲 𐑕𐑴𐑤 𐑥𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑳𐑐! 𐑖𐑰 𐑢𐑽𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑻 𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑣𐑦𐑤. 𐑦𐑟, 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑬𐑯 𐑑𐑵 𐑣𐑧𐑝𐑦 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑲 𐑢𐑺? 𐑞𐑦𐑕 ·𐑲𐑼𐑯 ·𐑒𐑮𐑬𐑯 𐑝 ·𐑤𐑴𐑥𐑚𐑸𐑛𐑦. 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑚𐑮𐑲𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑩 𐑡𐑧𐑥; 𐑲 𐑞 𐑢𐑺𐑼, 𐑕𐑰 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑓𐑸 𐑓𐑤𐑨𐑖𐑦𐑙𐑟; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑛𐑸𐑒𐑤𐑦 𐑓𐑰𐑤 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑲 𐑢𐑺 𐑞𐑨𐑑, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑛𐑨𐑟𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑟. '𐑑𐑦𐑟 𐑲𐑼𐑯—𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑲 𐑯𐑴—𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑜𐑴𐑤𐑛. '𐑑𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑐𐑤𐑦𐑑, 𐑑𐑵—𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑲 𐑓𐑰𐑤; 𐑞 𐑡𐑨𐑜𐑩𐑛 𐑧𐑡 𐑜𐑷𐑤𐑟 𐑥𐑰 𐑕𐑴, 𐑥𐑲 𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑯 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑟 𐑑 𐑚𐑰𐑑 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑪𐑤𐑦𐑛 𐑥𐑧𐑑𐑩𐑤; 𐑲, 𐑕𐑑𐑰𐑤 𐑕𐑒𐑳𐑤, 𐑥𐑲𐑯; 𐑞 𐑕𐑹𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑯𐑰𐑛𐑟 𐑯𐑴 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑥𐑩𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑯-𐑚𐑨𐑑𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑲𐑑!

𐑛𐑮𐑲 𐑣𐑰𐑑 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑥𐑲 𐑚𐑮𐑬? 𐑴! 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑢𐑪𐑟, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑯𐑮𐑲𐑟 𐑯𐑴𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑛 𐑥𐑰, 𐑕𐑴 𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑯𐑕𐑧𐑑 𐑕𐑵𐑞𐑛. 𐑯𐑴 𐑥𐑹. 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑤𐑳𐑝𐑤𐑦 𐑤𐑲𐑑, 𐑦𐑑 𐑤𐑲𐑑𐑕 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑥𐑰; 𐑷𐑤 𐑤𐑳𐑝𐑤𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑦𐑟 𐑨𐑙𐑜𐑢𐑦𐑖 𐑑 𐑥𐑰, 𐑕𐑦𐑯𐑕 𐑲 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑯𐑺 𐑦𐑯𐑡𐑶. 𐑜𐑦𐑓𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑣𐑲 𐑐𐑼𐑕𐑧𐑐𐑖𐑩𐑯, 𐑲 𐑤𐑨𐑒 𐑞 𐑤𐑴, 𐑦𐑯𐑡𐑶𐑦𐑙 𐑐𐑬𐑼; 𐑛𐑨𐑥𐑛, 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑯 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑥𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑜𐑯𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦! 𐑛𐑨𐑥𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑥𐑦𐑛𐑕𐑑 𐑝 ·𐑐𐑨𐑮𐑩𐑛𐑲𐑕! 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑯𐑲𐑑—𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑯𐑲𐑑! (𐑢𐑱𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛, 𐑣𐑰 𐑥𐑵𐑝𐑟 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑴.)

'𐑑𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑴 𐑣𐑸𐑛 𐑩 𐑑𐑭𐑕𐑒. 𐑲 𐑔𐑷𐑑 𐑑 𐑓𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚𐑼𐑯, 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑤𐑰𐑕𐑑; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑥𐑲 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑒𐑪𐑜𐑛 𐑕𐑻𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑓𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑺 𐑝𐑺𐑾𐑕 𐑢𐑰𐑤𐑟, 𐑯 𐑞𐑱 𐑮𐑦𐑝𐑪𐑤𐑝. 𐑹, 𐑦𐑓 𐑿 𐑢𐑦𐑤, 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑕𐑴 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑨𐑯𐑑-𐑣𐑦𐑤𐑟 𐑝 𐑐𐑬𐑛𐑼, 𐑞𐑱 𐑷𐑤 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑥𐑰; 𐑯 𐑲 𐑞𐑺 𐑥𐑨𐑗. 𐑴, 𐑣𐑸𐑛! 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑑 𐑓𐑲𐑼 𐑳𐑞𐑼𐑟, 𐑞 𐑥𐑨𐑗 𐑦𐑑𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑯𐑰𐑛𐑟 𐑚𐑰 𐑢𐑱𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙! 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑲'𐑝 𐑛𐑺𐑛, 𐑲'𐑝 𐑢𐑦𐑤𐑛; 𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑲'𐑝 𐑢𐑦𐑤𐑛, 𐑲'𐑤 𐑛𐑵! 𐑞𐑱 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒 𐑥𐑰 𐑥𐑨𐑛—·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒 𐑛𐑳𐑟; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑲'𐑥 𐑛𐑦𐑥𐑴𐑯𐑦𐑨𐑒, 𐑲 𐑨𐑥 𐑥𐑨𐑛𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑥𐑨𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑛! 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑲𐑤𐑛 𐑥𐑨𐑛𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑞𐑨𐑑'𐑕 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑭𐑥 𐑑 𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑣𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑑𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓! 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑓𐑩𐑕𐑦 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑲 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑚𐑰 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑥𐑧𐑥𐑚𐑼𐑛; 𐑯—·𐑲! 𐑲 𐑤𐑪𐑕𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑤𐑧𐑜. 𐑲 𐑯𐑬 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑓𐑩𐑕𐑲 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑲 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑥𐑧𐑥𐑚𐑼 𐑥𐑲 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑥𐑧𐑥𐑚𐑼𐑼. 𐑯𐑬, 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑚𐑰 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑓𐑩𐑑 𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑫𐑤𐑓𐑦𐑤𐑼 𐑢𐑳𐑯. 𐑞𐑨𐑑'𐑕 𐑥𐑹 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑘𐑰, 𐑘𐑰 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑜𐑪𐑛𐑟, 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑢𐑻. 𐑲 𐑤𐑭𐑓 𐑯 𐑣𐑵𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑘𐑰, 𐑘𐑰 𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑑-𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑼𐑟, 𐑘𐑰 𐑐𐑿𐑡𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑕, 𐑘𐑰 𐑛𐑧𐑓 ·𐑚𐑻𐑒𐑕 𐑯 𐑚𐑤𐑲𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 ·𐑚𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑜𐑴𐑟! 𐑲 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑱 𐑨𐑟 𐑕𐑒𐑵𐑤𐑚𐑶𐑟 𐑛𐑵 𐑑 𐑚𐑫𐑤𐑦𐑟—𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑘𐑹 𐑴𐑯 𐑕𐑲𐑟; 𐑛𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑐𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑤 𐑥𐑰! 𐑯𐑴, 𐑘𐑰'𐑝 𐑯𐑪𐑒𐑑 𐑥𐑰 𐑛𐑬𐑯, 𐑯 𐑲 𐑨𐑥 𐑳𐑐 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑘𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑮𐑳𐑯 𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑯. 𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑓𐑹𐑔 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑚𐑦𐑣𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑘𐑹 𐑒𐑪𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑚𐑨𐑜𐑟! 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑯𐑴 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑜𐑳𐑯 𐑑 𐑮𐑰𐑗 𐑘𐑰. 𐑒𐑳𐑥, ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚'𐑟 𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑦𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑑 𐑘𐑰; 𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑯 𐑕𐑰 𐑦𐑓 𐑘𐑰 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑕𐑢𐑻𐑝 𐑥𐑰. 𐑕𐑢𐑻𐑝 𐑥𐑰? 𐑘𐑰 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑢𐑻𐑝 𐑥𐑰, 𐑧𐑤𐑕 𐑘𐑰 𐑕𐑢𐑻𐑝 𐑘𐑹𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑝𐑟! 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑘𐑰 𐑞𐑺. 𐑕𐑢𐑻𐑝 𐑥𐑰? 𐑞 𐑐𐑭𐑔 𐑑 𐑥𐑲 𐑓𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑑 𐑐𐑻𐑐𐑩𐑕 𐑦𐑟 𐑤𐑱𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑲𐑼𐑯 𐑮𐑱𐑤𐑟, 𐑢𐑺𐑪𐑯 𐑥𐑲 𐑕𐑴𐑤 𐑦𐑟 𐑜𐑮𐑵𐑝𐑛 𐑑 𐑮𐑳𐑯. 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑳𐑯𐑕𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑜𐑹𐑡𐑩𐑟, 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑞 𐑮𐑲𐑓𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑣𐑸𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑥𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑟, 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑑𐑪𐑮𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕' 𐑚𐑧𐑛𐑟, 𐑳𐑯𐑻𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑲 𐑮𐑳𐑖! 𐑯𐑷𐑑'𐑕 𐑩𐑯 𐑪𐑚𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑒𐑩𐑤, 𐑯𐑷𐑑'𐑕 𐑩𐑯 𐑨𐑙𐑜𐑩𐑤 𐑑 𐑞 𐑲𐑼𐑯 𐑢𐑱!

·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 38. 𐑛𐑳𐑕𐑒.

𐑚𐑲 𐑞 ·𐑥𐑱𐑯𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑; ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒 𐑤𐑰𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑑.

𐑥𐑲 𐑕𐑴𐑤 𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑹 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑥𐑨𐑗𐑑; 𐑖𐑰'𐑟 𐑴𐑝𐑼𐑥𐑨𐑯𐑛; 𐑯 𐑚𐑲 𐑩 𐑥𐑨𐑛𐑥𐑩𐑯! 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑳𐑓𐑼𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑜𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑸𐑥𐑟 𐑪𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩 𐑓𐑰𐑤𐑛! 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑛𐑮𐑦𐑤𐑛 𐑛𐑰𐑐 𐑛𐑬𐑯, 𐑯 𐑚𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑷𐑤 𐑥𐑲 𐑮𐑰𐑟𐑩𐑯 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑥𐑰! 𐑲 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒 𐑲 𐑕𐑰 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑲𐑩𐑕 𐑧𐑯𐑛; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑓𐑰𐑤 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑲 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑐 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑑 𐑦𐑑. 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑲, 𐑯𐑦𐑤 𐑲, 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑧𐑓𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑑𐑲𐑛 𐑥𐑰 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥; 𐑑𐑴𐑟 𐑥𐑰 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑒𐑱𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑯𐑴 𐑯𐑲𐑓 𐑑 𐑒𐑳𐑑. 𐑣𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑥𐑨𐑯! 𐑣𐑵'𐑟 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑟;—𐑲, 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑚𐑰 𐑩 𐑛𐑧𐑥𐑩𐑒𐑮𐑨𐑑 𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑩𐑚𐑳𐑝; 𐑤𐑫𐑒, 𐑣𐑬 𐑣𐑰 𐑤𐑹𐑛𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑷𐑤 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑴! 𐑴! 𐑲 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑰 𐑥𐑲 𐑥𐑦𐑟𐑼𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑪𐑓𐑦𐑕,—𐑑 𐑴𐑚𐑱, 𐑮𐑦𐑚𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑙; 𐑯 𐑢𐑻𐑕 𐑘𐑧𐑑, 𐑑 𐑣𐑱𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑑𐑳𐑗 𐑝 𐑐𐑦𐑑𐑦! 𐑓 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑲𐑟 𐑲 𐑮𐑰𐑛 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑤𐑫𐑼𐑦𐑛 𐑢𐑴 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑖𐑮𐑦𐑝𐑩𐑤 𐑥𐑰 𐑳𐑐, 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑲 𐑦𐑑. 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑞𐑺 𐑣𐑴𐑐. 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑯 𐑑𐑲𐑛 𐑓𐑤𐑴 𐑢𐑲𐑛. 𐑞 𐑣𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼𐑦 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛 𐑑 𐑕𐑢𐑦𐑥 𐑦𐑯, 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑕𐑥𐑷𐑤 𐑜𐑴𐑤𐑛-𐑓𐑦𐑖 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑜𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑦 𐑜𐑤𐑴𐑚. 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑯-𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑳𐑤𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑐𐑻𐑐𐑩𐑕, ·𐑜𐑪𐑛 𐑥𐑱 𐑢𐑧𐑡 𐑩𐑕𐑲𐑛. 𐑲 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑳𐑐 𐑣𐑸𐑑, 𐑢𐑻 𐑦𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑤𐑧𐑛. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑥𐑲 𐑣𐑴𐑤 𐑒𐑤𐑪𐑒'𐑕 𐑮𐑳𐑯 𐑛𐑬𐑯; 𐑥𐑲 𐑣𐑸𐑑 𐑞 𐑷𐑤-𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑴𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑱𐑑, 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑯𐑴 𐑒𐑰 𐑑 𐑤𐑦𐑓𐑑 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯.

[𐑩 𐑚𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑝 𐑮𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑮𐑦 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑓𐑴𐑒𐑕𐑩𐑤.]

𐑴, ·𐑜𐑪𐑛! 𐑑 𐑕𐑱𐑤 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩 𐑣𐑰𐑞𐑩𐑯 𐑒𐑮𐑵 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑕𐑥𐑷𐑤 𐑑𐑳𐑗 𐑝 𐑣𐑿𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑥𐑳𐑞𐑼𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑥! 𐑢𐑧𐑤𐑐𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑢𐑺 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑖𐑸𐑒𐑦𐑖 𐑕𐑰. 𐑞 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑦𐑟 𐑞𐑺 𐑛𐑧𐑥𐑦𐑜𐑹𐑜𐑩𐑯. 𐑣𐑸𐑒! 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑓𐑻𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑹𐑡𐑦𐑟! 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑮𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑮𐑦 𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑹𐑢𐑼𐑛! 𐑥𐑸𐑒 𐑞 𐑳𐑯𐑓𐑷𐑤𐑑𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑭𐑓𐑑! 𐑥𐑦𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑕 𐑦𐑑 𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑗𐑼𐑟 𐑤𐑲𐑓. 𐑓𐑹𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑸𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑰 𐑖𐑵𐑑𐑕 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑜𐑱, 𐑦𐑥𐑚𐑨𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑛, 𐑚𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑬, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑑 𐑛𐑮𐑨𐑜 𐑛𐑸𐑒 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑦𐑑, 𐑢𐑺 𐑣𐑰 𐑚𐑮𐑵𐑛𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑢𐑼𐑛 𐑒𐑨𐑚𐑦𐑯, 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑛 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑒, 𐑯 𐑓𐑻𐑞𐑼 𐑪𐑯, 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑢𐑫𐑤𐑓𐑦𐑖 𐑜𐑻𐑜𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙𐑟. 𐑞 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑣𐑬𐑤 𐑔𐑮𐑦𐑤𐑟 𐑥𐑰 𐑔𐑮𐑵! 𐑐𐑰𐑕! 𐑘𐑰 𐑮𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑼𐑟, 𐑯 𐑕𐑧𐑑 𐑞 𐑢𐑪𐑗! 𐑴, 𐑤𐑲𐑓! '𐑑𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑩𐑯 𐑬𐑼 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑞𐑦𐑕, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑕𐑴𐑤 𐑚𐑰𐑑 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑯 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑛 𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑤𐑦𐑡,—𐑨𐑟 𐑢𐑲𐑤𐑛, 𐑳𐑯𐑑𐑿𐑑𐑼𐑛 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑸 𐑓𐑹𐑕𐑑 𐑑 𐑓𐑰𐑛—𐑴, 𐑤𐑲𐑓! '𐑑𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑬 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑲 𐑛𐑵 𐑓𐑰𐑤 𐑞 𐑤𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑣𐑪𐑮𐑼 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑰! 𐑚𐑳𐑑 '𐑑𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑥𐑰! 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑪𐑮𐑼'𐑟 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑥𐑰! 𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑕𐑪𐑓𐑑 𐑓𐑰𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑞 𐑣𐑿𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑰, 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑲 𐑑𐑮𐑲 𐑑 𐑓𐑲𐑑 𐑘𐑰, 𐑘𐑰 𐑜𐑮𐑦𐑥, 𐑓𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑥 𐑓𐑿𐑗𐑼𐑟! 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑥𐑰, 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑥𐑰, 𐑚𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑥𐑰, 𐑴 𐑘𐑰 𐑚𐑤𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑓𐑤𐑵𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟!

·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 40. 𐑥𐑦𐑛𐑯𐑲𐑑, ·𐑓𐑴𐑒𐑕𐑩𐑤.

·𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑽𐑟 𐑯 ·𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑼𐑟.

(𐑓𐑹𐑕𐑱𐑤 𐑮𐑲𐑟𐑩𐑟 𐑯 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑳𐑝𐑼𐑟 𐑞 𐑢𐑪𐑗 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙, 𐑤𐑬𐑯𐑡𐑦𐑙, 𐑤𐑰𐑯𐑦𐑙, 𐑯 𐑤𐑲𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑝𐑺𐑾𐑕 𐑨𐑑𐑦𐑑𐑿𐑛𐑟, 𐑷𐑤 𐑕𐑦𐑙𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑒𐑹𐑩𐑕.)

1·𐑕𐑑 ·𐑯𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑑 ·𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑼. 𐑴, 𐑚𐑶𐑟, 𐑛𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤; 𐑦𐑑'𐑕 𐑚𐑨𐑛 𐑓 𐑞 𐑛𐑲𐑡𐑧𐑕𐑗𐑩𐑯! 𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑩 𐑑𐑪𐑯𐑦𐑒, 𐑓𐑪𐑤𐑴 𐑥𐑰!

(𐑕𐑦𐑙𐑟, 𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑓𐑪𐑤𐑴.)

·𐑥𐑱𐑑'𐑕 ·𐑝𐑶𐑕 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 ·𐑒𐑢𐑹𐑑𐑼-·𐑛𐑧𐑒. 𐑱𐑑 𐑚𐑧𐑤𐑟 𐑞𐑺, 𐑓𐑹𐑢𐑼𐑛!

2·𐑛 ·𐑯𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑑 ·𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑼. 𐑩𐑝𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑞 𐑒𐑹𐑩𐑕! 𐑱𐑑 𐑚𐑧𐑤𐑟 𐑞𐑺! 𐑛'𐑘𐑰 𐑣𐑽, 𐑚𐑧𐑤-𐑚𐑶? 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑒 𐑞 𐑚𐑧𐑤 𐑱𐑑, 𐑞𐑬 ·𐑐𐑦𐑐! 𐑞𐑬 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑒𐑤𐑦𐑙! 𐑯 𐑤𐑧𐑑 𐑥𐑰 𐑒𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑢𐑪𐑗. 𐑲'𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑹𐑑 𐑝 𐑥𐑬𐑔 𐑓 𐑞𐑨𐑑—𐑞 𐑣𐑪𐑜𐑟𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑥𐑬𐑔. 𐑕𐑴, 𐑕𐑴, (𐑔𐑮𐑳𐑕𐑑𐑕 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑒𐑳𐑑𐑩𐑤,) ·𐑕𐑑𐑸-𐑚𐑴-l-𐑰-𐑰-n-𐑟, 𐑩-h-𐑴-𐑦! 𐑱𐑑 𐑚𐑧𐑤𐑟 𐑞𐑺 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑴! 𐑑𐑳𐑥𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑳𐑐!

·𐑛𐑳𐑗 ·𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑼. 𐑜𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑕𐑯𐑵𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑑-𐑯𐑲𐑑, 𐑥𐑱𐑑𐑦; 𐑓𐑨𐑑 𐑯𐑲𐑑 𐑓 𐑞𐑨𐑑. 𐑲 𐑥𐑸𐑒 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑬𐑼 𐑴𐑤𐑛 ·𐑥𐑴𐑜𐑩𐑤'𐑟 𐑢𐑲𐑯; 𐑦𐑑'𐑕 𐑒𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑛𐑧𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑨𐑟 𐑓𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑳𐑞𐑼𐑟. 𐑢𐑰 𐑕𐑦𐑙; 𐑞𐑱 𐑕𐑤𐑰𐑐—𐑲, 𐑤𐑲 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑞𐑺, 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑜𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛-𐑑𐑽 𐑚𐑳𐑑𐑕. 𐑨𐑑 '𐑩𐑥 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯! 𐑞𐑺, 𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑒𐑪𐑐𐑼-𐑐𐑳𐑥𐑐, 𐑯 𐑣𐑱𐑤 '𐑩𐑥 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑦𐑑. 𐑑𐑧𐑤 '𐑩𐑥 𐑑 𐑩𐑝𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑛𐑮𐑰𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑞𐑺 𐑤𐑨𐑕𐑩𐑟. 𐑑𐑧𐑤 '𐑩𐑥 𐑦𐑑'𐑕 𐑞 𐑮𐑧𐑟𐑼𐑧𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯; 𐑞𐑱 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑒𐑦𐑕 𐑞𐑺 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑, 𐑯 𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑑 𐑡𐑳𐑡𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑. 𐑞𐑨𐑑'𐑕 𐑞 𐑢𐑱—𐑞𐑨𐑑'𐑕 𐑦𐑑; 𐑞𐑲 𐑔𐑮𐑴𐑑 𐑱𐑯𐑑 𐑕𐑐𐑶𐑤𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑰𐑑𐑦𐑙 ·𐑨𐑥𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑛𐑨𐑥 𐑚𐑳𐑑𐑼.

·𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑯𐑗 ·𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑼. 𐑣𐑦𐑕𐑑, 𐑚𐑶𐑟! 𐑤𐑧𐑑'𐑕 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑩 𐑡𐑦𐑜 𐑹 𐑑𐑵 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑢𐑰 𐑮𐑲𐑛 𐑑 𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑼 𐑦𐑯 ·𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑩𐑑 ·𐑚𐑱. 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑱 𐑘𐑰? 𐑞𐑺 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑟 𐑞 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑢𐑪𐑗. 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑷𐑤 𐑤𐑧𐑜𐑟! 𐑐𐑦𐑐! 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 ·𐑐𐑦𐑐! 𐑣𐑼𐑭 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑘𐑹 𐑑𐑨𐑥𐑚𐑼𐑰𐑯!

·𐑐𐑦𐑐. (𐑕𐑳𐑤𐑒𐑦 𐑯 𐑕𐑤𐑰𐑐𐑦.) 𐑛𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑯𐑴 𐑢𐑺 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟.

·𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑯𐑗 ·𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑼. 𐑚𐑰𐑑 𐑞𐑲 𐑚𐑧𐑤𐑦, 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑯 𐑢𐑨𐑜 𐑞𐑲 𐑽𐑟. 𐑡𐑦𐑜 𐑦𐑑, 𐑥𐑧𐑯, 𐑲 𐑕𐑱; 𐑥𐑧𐑮𐑦'𐑟 𐑞 𐑢𐑻𐑛; 𐑣𐑼𐑭! 𐑛𐑨𐑥 𐑥𐑰, 𐑢𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑿 𐑛𐑭𐑯𐑕? 𐑓𐑹𐑥, 𐑯𐑬, ·𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑾𐑯-𐑓𐑲𐑤, 𐑯 𐑜𐑨𐑤𐑩𐑐 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑛𐑳𐑚𐑩𐑤-𐑖𐑳𐑓𐑩𐑤? 𐑔𐑮𐑴 𐑘𐑹𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑝𐑟! 𐑤𐑧𐑜𐑟! 𐑤𐑧𐑜𐑟!

·𐑲𐑕𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛 ·𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑼. 𐑲 𐑛𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑘𐑹 𐑓𐑤𐑹, 𐑥𐑱𐑑𐑦; 𐑦𐑑'𐑕 𐑑𐑵 𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑙𐑦 𐑑 𐑥𐑲 𐑑𐑱𐑕𐑑. 𐑲'𐑥 𐑿𐑕𐑑 𐑑 𐑲𐑕-𐑓𐑤𐑹𐑟. 𐑲'𐑥 𐑕𐑪𐑮𐑦 𐑑 𐑔𐑮𐑴 𐑒𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑚𐑡𐑧𐑒𐑑; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑒𐑿𐑕 𐑥𐑰.

·𐑥𐑷𐑤𐑑𐑰𐑟 ·𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑼. 𐑥𐑰 𐑑𐑵; 𐑢𐑺'𐑟 𐑘𐑹 𐑜𐑻𐑤𐑟? 𐑣𐑵 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑩 𐑓𐑵𐑤 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑤𐑧𐑓𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑮𐑲𐑑, 𐑯 𐑕𐑱 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓, 𐑣𐑬 𐑛'𐑘𐑰 𐑛𐑵? 𐑐𐑸𐑑𐑯𐑼𐑟! 𐑲 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑐𐑸𐑑𐑯𐑼𐑟!

·𐑕𐑦𐑕𐑦𐑤𐑾𐑯 ·𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑼. 𐑲; 𐑜𐑻𐑤𐑟 𐑯 𐑩 𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑯!—𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑲'𐑤 𐑣𐑪𐑐 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑘𐑰; 𐑘𐑱, 𐑑𐑻𐑯 𐑜𐑮𐑭𐑕𐑣𐑪𐑐𐑼!

·𐑤𐑪𐑙-·𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛 ·𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑼. 𐑢𐑧𐑤, 𐑢𐑧𐑤, 𐑘𐑰 𐑕𐑳𐑤𐑒𐑦𐑟, 𐑞𐑺'𐑟 𐑐𐑤𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑦 𐑥𐑹 𐑝 𐑳𐑕. 𐑣𐑴 𐑒𐑹𐑯 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑿 𐑥𐑱, 𐑕𐑱 𐑲. 𐑷𐑤 𐑤𐑧𐑜𐑟 𐑜𐑴 𐑑 𐑣𐑸𐑝𐑦𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑵𐑯. 𐑭! 𐑣𐑽 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑟 𐑞 𐑥𐑿𐑟𐑦𐑒; 𐑯𐑬 𐑓 𐑦𐑑!

·𐑩𐑟𐑹 ·𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑼. (𐑩𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙, 𐑯 𐑐𐑦𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑑𐑨𐑥𐑚𐑼𐑰𐑯 𐑳𐑐 𐑞 𐑕𐑒𐑳𐑑𐑩𐑤.) 𐑣𐑽 𐑿 𐑸, ·𐑐𐑦𐑐; 𐑯 𐑞𐑺'𐑟 𐑞 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑤𐑩𐑕-𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑕; 𐑳𐑐 𐑿 𐑥𐑬𐑯𐑑! 𐑯𐑬, 𐑚𐑶𐑟! (𐑞 𐑣𐑭𐑓 𐑝 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑛𐑭𐑯𐑕 𐑑 𐑞 𐑑𐑨𐑥𐑚𐑼𐑰𐑯; 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑜𐑴 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑴; 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑕𐑤𐑰𐑐 𐑹 𐑤𐑲 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑞 𐑒𐑶𐑤𐑟 𐑝 𐑮𐑦𐑜𐑦𐑙. 𐑴𐑞𐑟 𐑩-𐑐𐑤𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑦.)

·𐑩𐑟𐑹 ·𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑼. (𐑛𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑙) 𐑜𐑴 𐑦𐑑, ·𐑐𐑦𐑐! 𐑚𐑨𐑙 𐑦𐑑, 𐑚𐑧𐑤-𐑚𐑶! 𐑮𐑦𐑜 𐑦𐑑, 𐑛𐑦𐑜 𐑦𐑑, 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑜 𐑦𐑑, 𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑜 𐑦𐑑, 𐑚𐑧𐑤-𐑚𐑶! 𐑥𐑱𐑒 𐑓𐑲𐑼-𐑓𐑤𐑲𐑟; 𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑒 𐑞 𐑡𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑩𐑤𐑼𐑟!

·𐑐𐑦𐑐. 𐑡𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑩𐑤𐑼𐑟, 𐑿 𐑕𐑱?—𐑞𐑺 𐑜𐑴𐑟 𐑩𐑯𐑳𐑞𐑼, 𐑛𐑮𐑪𐑐𐑑 𐑪𐑓; 𐑲 𐑐𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑴.

·𐑗𐑲𐑯𐑩 ·𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑼. 𐑮𐑨𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑞𐑲 𐑑𐑰𐑔, 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑯 𐑐𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑩𐑢𐑱; 𐑥𐑱𐑒 𐑩 𐑐𐑩𐑜𐑴𐑛𐑩 𐑝 𐑞𐑲𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓.

·𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑯𐑗 ·𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑼. 𐑥𐑧𐑮𐑦-𐑥𐑨𐑛! 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑳𐑐 𐑞𐑲 𐑣𐑵𐑐, ·𐑐𐑦𐑐, 𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑲 𐑡𐑳𐑥𐑐 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑦𐑑! 𐑕𐑐𐑤𐑦𐑑 𐑡𐑦𐑚𐑟! 𐑑𐑺 𐑘𐑹𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑝𐑟!

·𐑑𐑨𐑖𐑑𐑱𐑜𐑴. (𐑒𐑢𐑲𐑩𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑥𐑴𐑒𐑦𐑙.) 𐑞𐑨𐑑'𐑕 𐑩 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑥𐑨𐑯; 𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑓𐑳𐑯: 𐑣𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑓! 𐑲 𐑕𐑱𐑝 𐑥𐑲 𐑕𐑢𐑧𐑑.

·𐑴𐑤𐑛 ·𐑥𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑕 ·𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑼. 𐑲 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑢𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑡𐑪𐑤𐑦 𐑤𐑨𐑛𐑟 𐑚𐑦𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑝 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑞𐑱 𐑸 𐑛𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑴𐑝𐑼. 𐑲'𐑤 𐑛𐑭𐑯𐑕 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑘𐑹 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑝, 𐑲 𐑢𐑦𐑤—𐑞𐑨𐑑'𐑕 𐑞 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑼𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑔𐑮𐑧𐑑 𐑝 𐑘𐑹 𐑯𐑲𐑑-𐑢𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑯, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑚𐑰𐑑 𐑣𐑧𐑛-𐑢𐑲𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑒𐑹𐑯𐑼𐑟. 𐑴 ·𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑕𐑑! 𐑑 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒 𐑝 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑯 𐑯𐑱𐑝𐑦𐑟 𐑯 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑯-𐑕𐑒𐑳𐑤𐑛 𐑒𐑮𐑵𐑟! 𐑢𐑧𐑤, 𐑢𐑧𐑤; 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑞 𐑣𐑴𐑤 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛'𐑟 𐑩 𐑚𐑷𐑤, 𐑨𐑟 𐑿 𐑕𐑒𐑪𐑤𐑼𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑦𐑑; 𐑯 𐑕𐑴 '𐑑𐑦𐑟 𐑮𐑲𐑑 𐑑 𐑥𐑱𐑒 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑚𐑷𐑤𐑮𐑵𐑥 𐑝 𐑦𐑑. 𐑛𐑭𐑯𐑕 𐑪𐑯, 𐑤𐑨𐑛𐑟, 𐑿'𐑼 𐑘𐑳𐑙; 𐑲 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑕.

3D ·𐑯𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑑 ·𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑼. 𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑤 𐑴!—𐑓𐑿! 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑻𐑕 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑐𐑫𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑒𐑭𐑥—𐑜𐑦𐑝 𐑳𐑕 𐑩 𐑢𐑦𐑓, ·𐑑𐑨𐑖.

(𐑞𐑱 𐑕𐑰𐑕 𐑛𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑙, 𐑯 𐑜𐑨𐑞𐑼 𐑦𐑯 𐑒𐑤𐑳𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑟. 𐑥𐑰𐑯𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑞 𐑕𐑒𐑲 𐑛𐑸𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑟—𐑞 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛 𐑮𐑲𐑟𐑩𐑟.)

·𐑤𐑨𐑕𐑒𐑼 ·𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑼. 𐑚𐑲 ·𐑚𐑮𐑭𐑥𐑩! 𐑚𐑶𐑟, 𐑦𐑑'𐑤 𐑚𐑰 𐑛𐑬𐑕 𐑕𐑱𐑤 𐑕𐑵𐑯. 𐑞 𐑕𐑒𐑲-𐑚𐑹𐑯, 𐑣𐑲-𐑑𐑲𐑛 ·𐑜𐑨𐑯𐑡𐑦𐑟 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑛 𐑑 𐑢𐑲𐑯𐑛! 𐑞𐑬 𐑖𐑴𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑞𐑲 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑒 𐑚𐑮𐑬, ·𐑕𐑰𐑝𐑩!

·𐑥𐑷𐑤𐑑𐑰𐑟 ·𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑼. (𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑲𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑯 𐑖𐑱𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑨𐑐.) 𐑦𐑑'𐑕 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑝𐑟—𐑞 𐑕𐑯𐑴'𐑟 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑕 𐑑𐑻𐑯 𐑑 𐑡𐑦𐑜 𐑦𐑑 𐑯𐑬. 𐑞𐑱'𐑤 𐑖𐑱𐑒 𐑞𐑺 𐑑𐑨𐑕𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑕𐑵𐑯. 𐑯𐑬 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑝𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑢𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑯, 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑲'𐑛 𐑜𐑴 𐑛𐑮𐑬𐑯, 𐑯 𐑖𐑨𐑕𐑱𐑰 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑧𐑝𐑼𐑥𐑹! 𐑞𐑺'𐑟 𐑯𐑷𐑑 𐑕𐑴 𐑕𐑢𐑰𐑑 𐑪𐑯 𐑻𐑔—𐑣𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑥𐑱 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑥𐑨𐑗 𐑦𐑑!—𐑨𐑟 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑕𐑢𐑦𐑓𐑑 𐑜𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑝 𐑢𐑹𐑥, 𐑢𐑲𐑤𐑛 𐑚𐑫𐑟𐑩𐑥𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑛𐑭𐑯𐑕, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑞 𐑴𐑝𐑼-𐑸𐑚𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑸𐑥𐑟 𐑣𐑲𐑛 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑮𐑲𐑐, 𐑚𐑻𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑐𐑕.

·𐑕𐑦𐑕𐑦𐑤𐑾𐑯 ·𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑼. (𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑲𐑯𐑦𐑙.) 𐑑𐑧𐑤 𐑥𐑰 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑝 𐑦𐑑! 𐑣𐑸𐑒 𐑘𐑰, 𐑤𐑨𐑛—𐑓𐑤𐑰𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑤𐑱𐑕𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑤𐑦𐑥𐑟—𐑤𐑲𐑞 𐑕𐑢𐑱𐑦𐑙𐑟—𐑒𐑶𐑦𐑙𐑟—𐑓𐑤𐑳𐑑𐑼𐑦𐑙𐑟! 𐑤𐑦𐑐! 𐑣𐑸𐑑! 𐑣𐑦𐑐! 𐑷𐑤 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑟: 𐑳𐑯𐑕𐑰𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑑𐑳𐑗 𐑯 𐑜𐑴! 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑑𐑱𐑕𐑑, 𐑩𐑚𐑟𐑻𐑝 𐑘𐑰, 𐑧𐑤𐑕 𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑕𐑩𐑑𐑲𐑩𐑑𐑦. 𐑱, ·𐑐𐑱𐑜𐑩𐑯? (𐑯𐑳𐑡𐑦𐑙.)

·𐑑𐑩𐑙𐑰𐑑𐑩𐑯 ·𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑼. (𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑲𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑪𐑯 𐑩 𐑥𐑨𐑑.) 𐑣𐑱𐑤, 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑦 𐑯𐑱𐑒𐑩𐑛𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑬𐑼 𐑛𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑜𐑻𐑤𐑟!—𐑞 ·𐑙𐑰𐑝𐑩-·𐑙𐑰𐑝𐑩! 𐑭! 𐑤𐑴 𐑝𐑱𐑤𐑛, 𐑣𐑲 𐑐𐑭𐑥𐑛 ·𐑑𐑭𐑣𐑰𐑑𐑦! 𐑲 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑥𐑰 𐑪𐑯 𐑞𐑲 𐑥𐑨𐑑, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑪𐑓𐑑 𐑕𐑶𐑤 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑕𐑤𐑦𐑛! 𐑲 𐑕𐑷 𐑞𐑰 𐑢𐑴𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑫𐑛, 𐑥𐑲 𐑥𐑨𐑑! 𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑛𐑱 𐑲 𐑚𐑮𐑷𐑑 𐑘𐑰 𐑞𐑧𐑯𐑕; 𐑯𐑬 𐑢𐑹𐑯 𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑤𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑒𐑢𐑲𐑑. 𐑭 𐑥𐑰!—𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑞𐑬 𐑯𐑹 𐑲 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑚𐑺 𐑞 𐑗𐑱𐑯𐑡! 𐑣𐑬 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑦𐑓 𐑕𐑴 𐑚𐑰 𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑕𐑐𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑑 𐑘𐑪𐑯 𐑕𐑒𐑲? 𐑣𐑽 𐑲 𐑞 𐑮𐑹𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑰𐑥𐑟 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 ·𐑐𐑦𐑮𐑴𐑙𐑦𐑑𐑦'𐑟 𐑐𐑰𐑒 𐑝 𐑕𐑐𐑽𐑟, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑞𐑱 𐑤𐑰𐑐 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑨𐑜𐑟 𐑯 𐑛𐑮𐑬𐑯 𐑞 𐑝𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑡𐑩𐑟?—𐑞 𐑚𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑! 𐑞 𐑚𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑! 𐑳𐑐, 𐑕𐑐𐑲𐑯, 𐑯 𐑥𐑰𐑑 𐑦𐑑! (𐑤𐑰𐑐𐑕 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑰𐑑.)

·𐑐𐑹𐑗𐑩𐑜𐑰𐑟 ·𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑼. 𐑣𐑬 𐑞 𐑕𐑰 𐑮𐑴𐑤𐑟 𐑕𐑢𐑭𐑖𐑦𐑙 '𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑲𐑛! 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑓 𐑮𐑰𐑓𐑦𐑙, 𐑣𐑸𐑑𐑦𐑟! 𐑞 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑸 𐑡𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑒𐑮𐑪𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑹𐑛𐑟, 𐑐𐑧𐑤-𐑥𐑧𐑤 𐑞𐑱'𐑤 𐑜𐑴 𐑤𐑳𐑯𐑡𐑦𐑙 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦.

·𐑛𐑱𐑯𐑦𐑖 ·𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑼. 𐑒𐑮𐑨𐑒, 𐑒𐑮𐑨𐑒, 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑖𐑦𐑐! 𐑕𐑴 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑨𐑟 𐑞𐑬 𐑒𐑮𐑨𐑒𐑩𐑕𐑑, 𐑞𐑬 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑩𐑕𐑑! 𐑢𐑧𐑤 𐑛𐑳𐑯! 𐑞 𐑥𐑱𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑟 𐑘𐑰 𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑓𐑤𐑦. 𐑣𐑰'𐑟 𐑯𐑴 𐑥𐑹 𐑩𐑓𐑮𐑱𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑞 𐑲𐑤 𐑓𐑹𐑑 𐑨𐑑 ·𐑒𐑨𐑑𐑩𐑜𐑨𐑑, 𐑐𐑫𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑑 𐑓𐑲𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑚𐑷𐑤𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑹𐑥-𐑤𐑨𐑖𐑑 𐑜𐑳𐑯𐑟, 𐑪𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑞 𐑕𐑰-𐑕𐑷𐑤𐑑 𐑒𐑱𐑒𐑕!

4·𐑔 ·𐑯𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑑 ·𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑼. 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑹𐑛𐑼𐑟, 𐑥𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑘𐑰 𐑞𐑨𐑑. 𐑲 𐑣𐑻𐑛 𐑴𐑤𐑛 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑑𐑧𐑤 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑣𐑰 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑷𐑤𐑢𐑱𐑟 𐑒𐑦𐑤 𐑩 𐑕𐑒𐑢𐑷𐑤, 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑨𐑟 𐑞𐑱 𐑚𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑩 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼𐑕𐑐𐑬𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑐𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑤—𐑓𐑲𐑼 𐑘𐑹 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑮𐑲𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑦𐑑!

·𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑤𐑦𐑖 ·𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑼. 𐑚𐑤𐑳𐑛! 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑥𐑨𐑯'𐑟 𐑩 𐑜𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑒𐑴𐑝! 𐑢𐑰 𐑸 𐑞 𐑤𐑨𐑛𐑟 𐑑 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑳𐑐 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑱𐑤!

𐑷𐑤. 𐑲! 𐑲!

·𐑴𐑤𐑛 ·𐑥𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑕 ·𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑼. 𐑣𐑬 𐑞 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑐𐑲𐑯𐑟 𐑖𐑱𐑒! 𐑐𐑲𐑯𐑟 𐑸 𐑞 𐑣𐑸𐑛𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑹𐑑 𐑝 𐑑𐑮𐑰 𐑑 𐑤𐑦𐑝 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑖𐑦𐑓𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑑 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑕𐑶𐑤, 𐑯 𐑣𐑽 𐑞𐑺'𐑟 𐑯𐑳𐑯 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑵'𐑟 𐑒𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑒𐑤𐑱. 𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑛𐑦, 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑥𐑟𐑥𐑩𐑯! 𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑛𐑦. 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑦𐑟 𐑞 𐑕𐑹𐑑 𐑝 𐑢𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑝 𐑣𐑸𐑑𐑕 𐑕𐑯𐑨𐑐 𐑩𐑖𐑹, 𐑯 𐑒𐑰𐑤𐑛 𐑣𐑳𐑤𐑟 𐑕𐑐𐑤𐑦𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑰. 𐑬𐑼 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑻𐑔𐑥𐑸𐑒; 𐑤𐑫𐑒 𐑘𐑪𐑯𐑛𐑼, 𐑚𐑶𐑟, 𐑞𐑺'𐑟 𐑩𐑯𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑒𐑲—𐑤𐑫𐑼𐑦𐑛-𐑤𐑲𐑒, 𐑘𐑰 𐑕𐑰, 𐑷𐑤 𐑧𐑤𐑕 𐑐𐑦𐑗 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑒.

·𐑛𐑨𐑜𐑵. 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑? 𐑣𐑵'𐑟 𐑩𐑓𐑮𐑱𐑛 𐑝 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑒'𐑕 𐑩𐑓𐑮𐑱𐑛 𐑝 𐑥𐑰! 𐑲'𐑥 𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑛 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑦𐑑!

·𐑕𐑐𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑖 ·𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑼. (𐑩𐑕𐑲𐑛.) 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑑 𐑚𐑫𐑤𐑦, 𐑭!—𐑞 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑜𐑮𐑳𐑡 𐑥𐑱𐑒𐑕 𐑥𐑰 𐑑𐑳𐑗𐑦 (·𐑩𐑛𐑝𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑙.) 𐑲, 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑽, 𐑞𐑲 𐑮𐑱𐑕 𐑦𐑟 𐑞 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑯𐑲𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑛𐑸𐑒 𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑝 𐑥𐑨𐑯𐑒𐑲𐑯𐑛—𐑛𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑖 𐑛𐑸𐑒 𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑. 𐑯𐑴 𐑩𐑓𐑧𐑯𐑕.

·𐑛𐑨𐑜𐑵 (𐑜𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑤𐑦). 𐑯𐑳𐑯.

·𐑕𐑑 ·𐑡𐑨𐑜𐑴'𐑟 ·𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑼. 𐑞𐑨𐑑 ·𐑕𐑐𐑨𐑯𐑘𐑼𐑛'𐑟 𐑥𐑨𐑛 𐑹 𐑛𐑮𐑳𐑙𐑒. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑒𐑭𐑯𐑑 𐑚𐑰, 𐑹 𐑧𐑤𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑒𐑱𐑕 𐑬𐑼 𐑴𐑤𐑛 ·𐑥𐑴𐑜𐑩𐑤'𐑟 𐑓𐑲𐑼-𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼𐑟 𐑸 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑻𐑒𐑦𐑙.

5·𐑔 ·𐑯𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑑 ·𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑼. 𐑢𐑪𐑑'𐑕 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑲 𐑕𐑷—𐑤𐑲𐑑𐑯𐑦𐑙? 𐑘𐑧𐑕.

·𐑕𐑐𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑖 ·𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑼. 𐑯𐑴; ·𐑛𐑨𐑜𐑵 𐑖𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑑𐑰𐑔.

·𐑛𐑨𐑜𐑵 (𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑙𐑦𐑙). 𐑕𐑢𐑪𐑤𐑴 𐑞𐑲𐑯, 𐑥𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑒𐑦𐑯! 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑕𐑒𐑦𐑯, 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑤𐑦𐑝𐑼!

·𐑕𐑐𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑖 ·𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑼 (𐑥𐑰𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑥). 𐑯𐑲𐑓 𐑞𐑰 𐑣𐑸𐑑𐑦𐑤𐑦! 𐑚𐑦𐑜 𐑓𐑮𐑱𐑥, 𐑕𐑥𐑷𐑤 𐑕𐑐𐑦𐑮𐑦𐑑!

𐑷𐑤. 𐑩 𐑮𐑴! 𐑩 𐑮𐑴! 𐑩 𐑮𐑴!

·𐑑𐑨𐑖𐑑𐑱𐑜𐑴 (𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑢𐑦𐑓). 𐑩 𐑮𐑴 𐑩'𐑤𐑴, 𐑯 𐑩 𐑮𐑴 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑓𐑑—·𐑜𐑪𐑛𐑟 𐑯 𐑥𐑧𐑯—𐑚𐑴𐑔 𐑚𐑮𐑷𐑤𐑼𐑟! 𐑣𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑓!

·𐑚𐑧𐑤𐑓𐑭𐑕𐑑 ·𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑼. 𐑩 𐑮𐑴! ·𐑸𐑮𐑮𐑩 𐑩 𐑮𐑴! 𐑞 ·𐑝𐑻𐑡𐑦𐑯 𐑚𐑰 𐑚𐑤𐑧𐑕𐑑, 𐑩 𐑮𐑴! 𐑐𐑤𐑳𐑯𐑡 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑘𐑰!

·𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑤𐑦𐑖 ·𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑼. 𐑓𐑺 𐑐𐑤𐑱! 𐑕𐑯𐑨𐑗 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑐𐑨𐑯𐑘𐑼𐑛'𐑟 𐑯𐑲𐑓! 𐑩 𐑮𐑦𐑙, 𐑩 𐑮𐑦𐑙!

·𐑴𐑤𐑛 ·𐑥𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑕 ·𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑼. 𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑦 𐑓𐑹𐑥𐑛. 𐑞𐑺! 𐑞 𐑮𐑦𐑙𐑛 𐑣𐑼𐑲𐑟𐑩𐑯. 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑙 ·𐑒𐑱𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑒 ·𐑱𐑚𐑩𐑤. 𐑕𐑢𐑰𐑑 𐑢𐑻𐑒, 𐑮𐑲𐑑 𐑢𐑻𐑒! 𐑯𐑴? 𐑢𐑲 𐑞𐑧𐑯, ·𐑜𐑪𐑛, 𐑥𐑨𐑛'𐑕𐑑 𐑞𐑬 𐑞 𐑮𐑦𐑙?

·𐑥𐑱𐑑'𐑕 ·𐑝𐑶𐑕 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 ·𐑒𐑢𐑹𐑑𐑼-·𐑛𐑧𐑒. 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑣𐑨𐑤𐑘𐑼𐑛𐑟! 𐑦𐑯 𐑑𐑪𐑐-𐑜𐑨𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑟! 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑑 𐑮𐑰𐑓 𐑑𐑪𐑐𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑟!

𐑷𐑤. 𐑞 𐑕𐑒𐑢𐑷𐑤! 𐑞 𐑕𐑒𐑢𐑷𐑤! 𐑡𐑳𐑥𐑐, 𐑥𐑲 𐑡𐑪𐑤𐑦𐑟! (𐑞𐑱 𐑕𐑒𐑨𐑑𐑼.)

·𐑐𐑦𐑐 (𐑖𐑮𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑞 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑤𐑩𐑕). 𐑡𐑪𐑤𐑦𐑟? 𐑤𐑹𐑛 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑐 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑡𐑪𐑤𐑦𐑟! 𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑖, 𐑒𐑮𐑨𐑖! 𐑞𐑺 𐑜𐑴𐑟 𐑞 𐑡𐑦𐑚-𐑕𐑑𐑱! 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑙-𐑢𐑨𐑙! 𐑜𐑪𐑛! 𐑛𐑳𐑒 𐑤𐑴𐑼, ·𐑐𐑦𐑐, 𐑣𐑽 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑟 𐑞 𐑮𐑶𐑩𐑤 𐑘𐑸𐑛! 𐑦𐑑'𐑕 𐑢𐑻𐑕 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛 𐑢𐑫𐑛𐑟, 𐑞 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑛𐑱 𐑝 𐑞 𐑘𐑽! 𐑣𐑵'𐑛 𐑜𐑴 𐑒𐑤𐑲𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑗𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑯𐑳𐑑𐑕 𐑯𐑬? 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑞𐑱 𐑜𐑴, 𐑷𐑤 𐑒𐑻𐑕𐑦𐑙, 𐑯 𐑣𐑽 𐑲 𐑛𐑴𐑯𐑑. 𐑓𐑲𐑯 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑕 𐑑 '𐑩𐑥; 𐑞𐑱'𐑼 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑮𐑴𐑛 𐑑 𐑣𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑯. 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑸𐑛! 𐑡𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑦, 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑩 𐑕𐑒𐑢𐑷𐑤! 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑕 𐑞𐑺 𐑸 𐑢𐑻𐑕 𐑘𐑧𐑑—𐑞𐑱 𐑸 𐑘𐑹 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑕𐑒𐑢𐑷𐑤𐑟, 𐑞𐑱. 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑕𐑒𐑢𐑷𐑤𐑟? 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑖𐑻! 𐑖𐑻! 𐑣𐑽 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑲 𐑣𐑻𐑛 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑺 𐑗𐑨𐑑 𐑡𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑯𐑬, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑤—𐑖𐑻! 𐑖𐑻!—𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑕𐑐𐑴𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑕! 𐑯 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑰𐑝𐑯𐑦𐑙—𐑦𐑑 𐑥𐑱𐑒𐑕 𐑥𐑰 𐑡𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑩𐑤 𐑷𐑤 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑥𐑲 𐑑𐑨𐑥𐑚𐑼𐑰𐑯—𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑨𐑯𐑩𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑛𐑩 𐑝 𐑩𐑯 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑕𐑢𐑹 '𐑩𐑥 𐑦𐑯 𐑑 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥! 𐑴, 𐑞𐑬 𐑚𐑦𐑜 𐑢𐑲𐑑 ·𐑜𐑪𐑛 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑓𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑢𐑺 𐑦𐑯 𐑘𐑪𐑯 𐑛𐑸𐑒𐑯𐑩𐑕, 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑥𐑻𐑕𐑦 𐑪𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑕𐑥𐑷𐑤 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑒 𐑚𐑶 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑣𐑽; 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑻𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑷𐑤 𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑯𐑴 𐑚𐑬𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑑 𐑓𐑰𐑤 𐑓𐑽!

·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 41. 𐑥𐑪𐑚𐑦 ·𐑛𐑦𐑒.

𐑲, ·𐑦𐑖𐑥𐑱𐑩𐑤, 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑒𐑮𐑵; 𐑥𐑲 𐑖𐑬𐑑𐑕 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑜𐑪𐑯 𐑳𐑐 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑑; 𐑥𐑲 𐑴𐑔 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑢𐑧𐑤𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞𐑺𐑟; 𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑪𐑙𐑜𐑼 𐑲 𐑖𐑬𐑑𐑩𐑛, 𐑯 𐑥𐑹 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑥𐑼 𐑯 𐑒𐑤𐑦𐑯𐑗 𐑥𐑲 𐑴𐑔, 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑪𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑛𐑮𐑧𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑲 𐑕𐑴𐑤. 𐑩 𐑢𐑲𐑤𐑛, 𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤, 𐑕𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑔𐑧𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑓𐑰𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑰; ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚'𐑟 𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑗𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑓𐑿𐑛 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑥𐑲𐑯. 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑛𐑦 𐑽𐑟 𐑲 𐑤𐑻𐑯𐑛 𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑦 𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑻𐑛𐑼𐑩𐑕 𐑥𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑼 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑵𐑥 𐑲 𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑳𐑞𐑼𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑬𐑼 𐑴𐑞𐑟 𐑝 𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑯 𐑮𐑦𐑝𐑧𐑯𐑡.

𐑓 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑐𐑭𐑕𐑑, 𐑞𐑴 𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦, 𐑞 𐑳𐑯𐑩𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑛, 𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑵𐑛𐑩𐑛 ·𐑢𐑲𐑑 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑣𐑷𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑳𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑤𐑲𐑟𐑛 𐑕𐑰𐑟 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑓𐑮𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑼𐑥𐑧𐑯. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑝 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑯𐑿 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑜𐑟𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕; 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑩 𐑓𐑿 𐑝 𐑞𐑧𐑥, 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑨𐑮𐑩𐑑𐑦𐑝𐑤𐑦, 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑯𐑴𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑰𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥; 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑞 𐑯𐑳𐑥𐑚𐑼 𐑣𐑵 𐑨𐑟 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑨𐑒𐑗𐑵𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑯 𐑯𐑴𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑜𐑦𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑚𐑨𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑥𐑷𐑤 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑰𐑛. 𐑓, 𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑞 𐑤𐑸𐑡 𐑯𐑳𐑥𐑚𐑼 𐑝 𐑢𐑱𐑤-𐑒𐑮𐑵𐑟𐑼𐑟; 𐑞 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑹𐑛𐑼𐑤𐑦 𐑢𐑱 𐑞𐑱 𐑢𐑻 𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑲𐑼 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼𐑦 𐑕𐑼𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑓𐑼𐑩𐑯𐑕, 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑝 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑩𐑛𐑝𐑧𐑯𐑗𐑼𐑩𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑫𐑖𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑺 𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑕𐑪𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑼𐑦 𐑤𐑨𐑑𐑦𐑑𐑿𐑛𐑟, 𐑕𐑴 𐑨𐑟 𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑛𐑩𐑥 𐑹 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑓 𐑩 𐑣𐑴𐑤 𐑑𐑢𐑧𐑤𐑝𐑥𐑳𐑯𐑔 𐑹 𐑥𐑹 𐑪𐑯 𐑩 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑧𐑗, 𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑼 𐑩 𐑕𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑩𐑤 𐑯𐑿𐑟-𐑑𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑱𐑤 𐑝 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑕𐑹𐑑; 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑹𐑛𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑑 𐑤𐑧𐑙𐑔 𐑝 𐑰𐑗 𐑕𐑧𐑐𐑼𐑩𐑑 𐑝𐑶𐑦𐑡; 𐑞 𐑦𐑮𐑧𐑜𐑿𐑤𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑝 𐑞 𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑝 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑣𐑴𐑥; 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑰𐑟, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑕𐑻𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟, 𐑛𐑦𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑑 𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑑, 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑩𐑚𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑛 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑞 𐑣𐑴𐑤 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛-𐑢𐑲𐑛 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙-𐑓𐑤𐑰𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑡𐑵𐑩𐑤𐑲𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑑𐑲𐑛𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑙 ·𐑥𐑪𐑚𐑦 ·𐑛𐑦𐑒. 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑣𐑸𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑛𐑬𐑑𐑩𐑛, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑧𐑝𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑝𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑹𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑛, 𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑹 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩 𐑑𐑲𐑥, 𐑹 𐑪𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑹 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩 𐑥𐑼𐑦𐑛𐑾𐑯, 𐑩 ·𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑝 𐑳𐑯𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑥𐑨𐑜𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑿𐑛 𐑯 𐑥𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑜𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑦, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑛𐑵𐑦𐑙 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑗𐑦𐑓 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑩𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕, 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑰𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑱𐑐𐑑 𐑞𐑧𐑥; 𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑥𐑲𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑩𐑯 𐑳𐑯𐑓𐑺 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑖𐑩𐑯, 𐑲 𐑕𐑱, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑕𐑗𐑩𐑯 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑯𐑴 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑞𐑨𐑯 ·𐑥𐑪𐑚𐑦 ·𐑛𐑦𐑒. 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑝 𐑤𐑱𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑼𐑦 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑥𐑸𐑒𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑝𐑺𐑾𐑕 𐑯 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑳𐑯𐑓𐑮𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑝 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑓𐑼𐑪𐑕𐑦𐑑𐑦, 𐑒𐑳𐑯𐑦𐑙, 𐑯 𐑥𐑨𐑤𐑦𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑥𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑼 𐑩𐑑𐑨𐑒𐑑; 𐑞𐑺𐑓𐑹 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑣𐑵 𐑚𐑲 𐑨𐑒𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑦𐑜𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑜𐑱𐑝 𐑚𐑨𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑑 ·𐑥𐑪𐑚𐑦 ·𐑛𐑦𐑒; 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑟, 𐑐𐑼𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑕, 𐑓 𐑞 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑐𐑸𐑑, 𐑢𐑻 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑑 𐑩𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑚 𐑞 𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑽 𐑑𐑧𐑮𐑼 𐑣𐑰 𐑚𐑮𐑧𐑛, 𐑥𐑹, 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑻, 𐑑 𐑞 𐑐𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑤𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑼𐑦 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑸𐑡, 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑑 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑡𐑵𐑩𐑤 𐑒𐑷𐑟. 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑱, 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑𐑤𐑦, 𐑞 𐑛𐑦𐑟𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑩𐑕 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑼 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑢𐑰𐑯 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑞𐑼𐑑𐑵 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑐𐑪𐑐𐑿𐑤𐑼𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑦𐑜𐑸𐑛𐑩𐑛.

𐑯 𐑨𐑟 𐑓 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑣𐑵, 𐑐𐑮𐑰𐑝𐑾𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑣𐑽𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑢𐑲𐑑 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑚𐑲 𐑗𐑭𐑯𐑕 𐑒𐑷𐑑 𐑕𐑲𐑑 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑥; 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑦𐑜𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑞 𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑱 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑞𐑧𐑥, 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑, 𐑨𐑟 𐑚𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑯 𐑓𐑽𐑤𐑩𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑤𐑴𐑼𐑛 𐑓 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑨𐑟 𐑓 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑖𐑰𐑟. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑧𐑙𐑔, 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑨𐑥𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑟 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑿 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑩𐑕𐑷𐑤𐑑𐑕—𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑑 𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑛 𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑕 𐑯 𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑟, 𐑚𐑮𐑴𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑤𐑦𐑥𐑟, 𐑹 𐑛𐑦𐑝𐑬𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑨𐑥𐑐𐑿𐑑𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟—𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑓𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑑 𐑞 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑜𐑮𐑰 𐑝 𐑓𐑩𐑑𐑨𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑦; 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑰𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑛𐑦𐑟𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑩𐑕 𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑳𐑤𐑕𐑩𐑟, 𐑷𐑤 𐑩𐑒𐑿𐑥𐑿𐑤𐑱𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑯 𐑐𐑲𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑺 𐑑𐑧𐑮𐑼𐑟 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 ·𐑥𐑪𐑚𐑦 ·𐑛𐑦𐑒; 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑜𐑪𐑯 𐑓𐑸 𐑑 𐑖𐑱𐑒 𐑞 𐑓𐑹𐑑𐑦𐑑𐑿𐑛 𐑝 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑝 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑟, 𐑑 𐑣𐑵𐑥 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑹𐑦 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑢𐑲𐑑 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑦𐑝𐑧𐑯𐑗𐑵𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑳𐑥.

𐑯𐑹 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑢𐑲𐑤𐑛 𐑮𐑵𐑥𐑼𐑟 𐑝 𐑷𐑤 𐑕𐑹𐑑𐑕 𐑓𐑱𐑤 𐑑 𐑦𐑜𐑟𐑨𐑡𐑼𐑱𐑑, 𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑞 𐑥𐑹 𐑣𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑓𐑲 𐑞 𐑑𐑮𐑵 𐑣𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑦𐑟 𐑝 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑛𐑧𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑟. 𐑓 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑵 𐑓𐑨𐑚𐑿𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑮𐑵𐑥𐑼𐑟 𐑯𐑨𐑗𐑼𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑜𐑮𐑴 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦 𐑝 𐑷𐑤 𐑕𐑼𐑐𐑮𐑲𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑑𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑝𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑕,—𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑕𐑥𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑑𐑮𐑰 𐑜𐑦𐑝𐑟 𐑚𐑻𐑔 𐑑 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑓𐑳𐑙𐑜𐑲; 𐑚𐑳𐑑, 𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑤𐑲𐑓, 𐑓𐑸 𐑥𐑹 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑝 𐑑𐑧𐑮𐑩 𐑓𐑻𐑥𐑩, 𐑢𐑲𐑤𐑛 𐑮𐑵𐑥𐑼𐑟 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑯𐑛, 𐑢𐑺𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑞𐑺 𐑦𐑟 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑨𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑢𐑩𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑨𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑓 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑑 𐑒𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑑. 𐑯 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑕𐑰 𐑕𐑼𐑐𐑭𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑞 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑥𐑨𐑑𐑼, 𐑕𐑴 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑼𐑦 𐑕𐑼𐑐𐑭𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑕𐑹𐑑 𐑝 𐑥𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑤𐑲𐑓, 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑓𐑩𐑤𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑯 𐑓𐑽𐑓𐑩𐑤𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑮𐑵𐑥𐑼𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑕𐑻𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑱𐑑 𐑞𐑺. 𐑓 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑸 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑨𐑟 𐑩 𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦 𐑳𐑯𐑦𐑜𐑟𐑧𐑥𐑐𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑜𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑯 𐑕𐑵𐑐𐑼𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑕𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑣𐑼𐑧𐑛𐑦𐑑𐑼𐑦 𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑼𐑟; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑝 𐑷𐑤 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑼𐑟, 𐑞𐑱 𐑸 𐑚𐑲 𐑷𐑤 𐑪𐑛𐑟 𐑞 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑮𐑷𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑨𐑒𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑢𐑪𐑑𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑦𐑟 𐑩𐑐𐑷𐑤𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑩𐑕𐑑𐑪𐑯𐑦𐑖𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑰; 𐑓𐑱𐑕 𐑑 𐑓𐑱𐑕 𐑞𐑱 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑲 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑥𐑸𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑟, 𐑚𐑳𐑑, 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑑 𐑡𐑷, 𐑜𐑦𐑝 𐑚𐑨𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑑 𐑞𐑧𐑥. 𐑩𐑤𐑴𐑯, 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑴𐑑𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼𐑟, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑴 𐑿 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑛 𐑩 𐑔𐑬𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑥𐑲𐑤𐑟, 𐑯 𐑐𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑩 𐑔𐑬𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑖𐑹𐑟, 𐑿 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑑 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑗𐑦𐑟𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑣𐑸𐑔-𐑕𐑑𐑴𐑯, 𐑹 𐑷𐑑 𐑣𐑪𐑕𐑐𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑚𐑦𐑯𐑰𐑔 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑐𐑸𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑯; 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑤𐑨𐑑𐑦𐑑𐑿𐑛𐑟 𐑯 𐑤𐑪𐑯𐑜𐑦𐑑𐑿𐑛𐑟, 𐑐𐑼𐑕𐑿𐑦𐑙 𐑑𐑵 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩 𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑨𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑛𐑳𐑟, 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑟 𐑮𐑨𐑐𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑦𐑯𐑓𐑤𐑵𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑷𐑤 𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑥𐑱𐑒 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑨𐑯𐑕𐑦 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑜𐑯𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑩 𐑥𐑲𐑑𐑦 𐑚𐑻𐑔.

𐑯𐑴 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼, 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑜𐑨𐑞𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑝𐑪𐑤𐑿𐑥 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑥𐑽 𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑟𐑦𐑑 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑞 𐑢𐑲𐑛𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼𐑦 𐑕𐑐𐑱𐑕𐑩𐑟, 𐑞 𐑬𐑑𐑚𐑤𐑴𐑯 𐑮𐑵𐑥𐑼𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑢𐑲𐑑 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑹𐑐𐑼𐑱𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞𐑧𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑝𐑟 𐑷𐑤 𐑥𐑨𐑯𐑼 𐑝 𐑥𐑹𐑚𐑦𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑕, 𐑯 𐑣𐑭𐑓-𐑓𐑹𐑥𐑛 𐑓𐑰𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑩𐑡𐑧𐑕𐑗𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑕𐑵𐑐𐑼𐑯𐑨𐑗𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑱𐑡𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑟, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑦𐑝𐑧𐑯𐑗𐑵𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛 ·𐑥𐑪𐑚𐑦 ·𐑛𐑦𐑒 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑯𐑿 𐑑𐑧𐑮𐑼𐑟 𐑳𐑯𐑚𐑪𐑮𐑴𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑧𐑯𐑦𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑝𐑦𐑟𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑩𐑐𐑽𐑟. 𐑕𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑒𐑱𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩 𐑐𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑒 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑣𐑰 𐑓𐑲𐑯𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑒, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑓𐑿 𐑣𐑵 𐑚𐑲 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑮𐑵𐑥𐑼𐑟, 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑰𐑕𐑑, 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑣𐑻𐑛 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑢𐑲𐑑 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑓𐑿 𐑝 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑢𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑼 𐑞 𐑐𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑤𐑟 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑡𐑷.

𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑢𐑻 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑯 𐑥𐑹 𐑝𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑐𐑮𐑨𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑯𐑓𐑤𐑵𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑻𐑒. 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑛𐑱 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑼𐑦𐑡𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑰𐑠 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑨𐑟 𐑓𐑽𐑓𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑢𐑦𐑖𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑷𐑤 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑖𐑰𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑤𐑩𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑔𐑩𐑯, 𐑛𐑲𐑛 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑥𐑲𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑨𐑟 𐑩 𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦. 𐑞𐑺 𐑸 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑛𐑱 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑞𐑧𐑥, 𐑣𐑵, 𐑞𐑴 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑡𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑯 𐑒𐑼𐑱𐑡𐑩𐑕 𐑦𐑯𐑳𐑓 𐑦𐑯 𐑪𐑓𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑨𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑯𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑹 ·𐑮𐑲𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑐𐑼𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑕—𐑲𐑞𐑼 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑓𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑽𐑾𐑯𐑕, 𐑹 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑐𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦, 𐑹 𐑑𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑛𐑦𐑑𐑦, 𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑲𐑯 𐑩 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤; 𐑨𐑑 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑮𐑱𐑑, 𐑞𐑺 𐑸 𐑐𐑤𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑦 𐑝 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑥𐑧𐑯, 𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑯𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑞 ·𐑩𐑥𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑓𐑤𐑨𐑜, 𐑣𐑵 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑣𐑪𐑕𐑑𐑲𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑛 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑣𐑵𐑟 𐑕𐑴𐑤 𐑯𐑪𐑤𐑦𐑡 𐑝 𐑞 𐑤𐑩𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑔𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑟 𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑑 𐑞 𐑦𐑜𐑯𐑴𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑥𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑼 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑝𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑼𐑕𐑿𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑯𐑹𐑔; 𐑕𐑰𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑪𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑣𐑨𐑗𐑩𐑟, 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑣𐑸𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑗𐑲𐑤𐑛𐑦𐑖 𐑓𐑲𐑼𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑯 𐑷, 𐑑 𐑞 𐑢𐑲𐑤𐑛, 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡 𐑑𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑝 ·𐑕𐑳𐑞𐑼𐑯 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙. 𐑯𐑹 𐑦𐑟 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑰-𐑧𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑕𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 ·𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑧𐑯𐑦𐑢𐑺 𐑥𐑹 𐑓𐑰𐑤𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑣𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛, 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑪𐑯 𐑚𐑹𐑛 𐑝 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑐𐑮𐑬𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑥 𐑣𐑦𐑥.

𐑯 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑓 𐑞 𐑯𐑬 𐑑𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑮𐑦𐑨𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑓𐑹𐑥𐑼 𐑤𐑧𐑡𐑩𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑦 𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑔𐑮𐑴𐑯 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑖𐑨𐑛𐑴 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑦𐑑; 𐑢𐑰 𐑓𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑚𐑫𐑒 𐑯𐑨𐑗𐑼𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑕—·𐑴𐑤𐑨𐑕𐑩𐑯 𐑯 ·𐑐𐑴𐑝𐑤𐑕𐑩𐑯—𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑺𐑦𐑙 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑩 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑯𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑑 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑒𐑮𐑰𐑗𐑼 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑰, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑷𐑤𐑕𐑴 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑕𐑴 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑓𐑼𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑕 𐑨𐑟 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑿𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑩𐑔𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑓 𐑣𐑿𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑚𐑤𐑳𐑛. 𐑯𐑹 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑑 𐑕𐑴 𐑤𐑱𐑑 𐑩 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑨𐑟 ·𐑒𐑿𐑝𐑽'𐑟, 𐑢𐑻 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑹 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑤𐑼 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑦𐑓𐑱𐑕𐑑. 𐑓 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 ·𐑯𐑨𐑗𐑼𐑩𐑤 ·𐑣𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑦, 𐑞 ·𐑚𐑨𐑮𐑩𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑩𐑓𐑻𐑥𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑲𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑷𐑤 𐑓𐑦𐑖 (𐑖𐑸𐑒𐑕 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑤𐑵𐑛𐑩𐑛) 𐑸 “𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑒 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑤𐑲𐑝𐑤𐑦 𐑑𐑧𐑮𐑼𐑟,” 𐑯 “𐑪𐑓𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑦𐑐𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦 𐑝 𐑞𐑺 𐑓𐑤𐑲𐑑 𐑛𐑨𐑖 𐑞𐑧𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑝𐑟 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑞 𐑮𐑪𐑒𐑕 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑨𐑟 𐑑 𐑒𐑷𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑱𐑯𐑾𐑕 𐑛𐑧𐑔.” 𐑯 𐑣𐑬𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑞 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑽𐑾𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑼𐑦 𐑥𐑱 𐑩𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑹𐑑𐑕 𐑨𐑟 𐑞𐑰𐑟; 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑓𐑫𐑤 𐑑𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑯𐑩𐑕, 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑑 𐑞 𐑚𐑤𐑳𐑛𐑔𐑻𐑕𐑑𐑦 𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑥 𐑝 ·𐑐𐑴𐑝𐑤𐑕𐑩𐑯, 𐑞 𐑕𐑵𐑐𐑼𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑕 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑰𐑓 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑦𐑟, 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑝𐑦𐑕𐑦𐑕𐑦𐑑𐑿𐑛𐑟 𐑝 𐑞𐑺 𐑝𐑴𐑒𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯, 𐑮𐑦𐑝𐑲𐑝𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑥𐑲𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑟.

𐑕𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑴𐑝𐑼𐑷𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑮𐑵𐑥𐑼𐑟 𐑯 𐑐𐑹𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑩 𐑓𐑿 𐑝 𐑞 𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑼𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑛, 𐑦𐑯 𐑮𐑧𐑓𐑼𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑑 ·𐑥𐑪𐑚𐑦 ·𐑛𐑦𐑒, 𐑞 𐑻𐑤𐑽 𐑛𐑱𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑼𐑦, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑪𐑓𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑣𐑸𐑛 𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑿𐑕 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑐𐑮𐑨𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑕𐑑 ·𐑮𐑲𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑑 𐑦𐑥𐑚𐑸𐑒 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑐𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑤𐑟 𐑝 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑯𐑿 𐑯 𐑛𐑺𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑹𐑓𐑺; 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑐𐑮𐑴𐑑𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑷𐑤𐑞𐑴 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑤𐑩𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑔𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑣𐑴𐑐𐑓𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑼𐑕𐑿𐑛, 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑑 𐑗𐑱𐑕 𐑯 𐑐𐑶𐑯𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑕 𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩𐑯 𐑨𐑐𐑼𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑓 𐑥𐑹𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑥𐑨𐑯. 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑑 𐑩𐑑𐑧𐑥𐑐𐑑 𐑦𐑑, 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑚𐑰 𐑦𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑑𐑹𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑩 𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑒 𐑦𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑦. 𐑪𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑣𐑧𐑛, 𐑞𐑺 𐑸 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑸𐑒𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑛𐑪𐑒𐑿𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑱 𐑚𐑰 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑳𐑤𐑑𐑩𐑛.

𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼𐑞𐑩𐑤𐑧𐑕, 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑞𐑺 𐑢𐑻, 𐑣𐑵 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑱𐑕 𐑝 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑦 𐑑 𐑜𐑦𐑝 𐑗𐑱𐑕 𐑑 ·𐑥𐑪𐑚𐑦 ·𐑛𐑦𐑒; 𐑯 𐑩 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑𐑼 𐑯𐑳𐑥𐑚𐑼 𐑣𐑵, 𐑗𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑑 𐑣𐑽 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑯 𐑝𐑱𐑜𐑤𐑦, 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑩𐑕𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑒 𐑛𐑰𐑑𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑝 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑨𐑥𐑦𐑑𐑦, 𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑 𐑕𐑵𐑐𐑼𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑕 𐑩𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕, 𐑢𐑻 𐑕𐑩𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑣𐑸𐑛𐑦 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑑 𐑓𐑤𐑰 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑚𐑨𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑓 𐑪𐑓𐑼𐑛.

𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑲𐑤𐑛 𐑕𐑩𐑡𐑧𐑕𐑗𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑮𐑦𐑓𐑻𐑛 𐑑, 𐑨𐑟 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑤𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 ·𐑢𐑲𐑑 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑥𐑲𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑵𐑐𐑼𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑤𐑲𐑯𐑛, 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞 𐑳𐑯𐑻𐑔𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑰𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 ·𐑥𐑪𐑚𐑦 ·𐑛𐑦𐑒 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑿𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑕; 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑨𐑒𐑗𐑵𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑪𐑐𐑩𐑟𐑦𐑑 𐑤𐑨𐑑𐑦𐑑𐑿𐑛𐑟 𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑑𐑲𐑥.

𐑯𐑹, 𐑒𐑮𐑧𐑡𐑵𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑨𐑟 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑥𐑲𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑯, 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑰𐑑 𐑷𐑤𐑑𐑩𐑜𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑓𐑱𐑯𐑑 𐑖𐑴 𐑝 𐑕𐑵𐑐𐑼𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑕 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑚𐑩𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑦. 𐑓 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑕𐑰𐑒𐑮𐑩𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑒𐑳𐑮𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑰𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑛𐑲𐑝𐑳𐑤𐑡𐑛, 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑑 𐑞 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑧𐑮𐑫𐑛𐑲𐑑 𐑮𐑰𐑕𐑻𐑗; 𐑕𐑴 𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑱𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑚𐑦𐑯𐑰𐑔 𐑞 𐑕𐑻𐑓𐑦𐑕 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑱𐑯, 𐑦𐑯 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑐𐑸𐑑, 𐑳𐑯𐑩𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑼𐑕𐑿𐑼𐑟; 𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑑 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑼𐑦𐑡𐑦𐑯𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑞 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑒𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑾𐑕 𐑯 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑩𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑑𐑼𐑦 𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑮𐑦𐑜𐑸𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑧𐑥, 𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑥𐑴𐑛𐑟 𐑢𐑺𐑚𐑲, 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑕𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑩 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑛𐑧𐑐𐑔, 𐑣𐑰 𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑕𐑐𐑹𐑑𐑕 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑝𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑢𐑦𐑓𐑑𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑑 𐑞 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑢𐑲𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑐𐑶𐑯𐑑𐑕.

𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑩 𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑧𐑤 𐑯𐑴𐑯 𐑑 𐑚𐑴𐑔 ·𐑩𐑥𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑯 ·𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑤𐑦𐑖 𐑢𐑱𐑤-𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑕, 𐑯 𐑨𐑟 𐑢𐑧𐑤 𐑩 𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕𐑑 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑷𐑔𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑑𐑦𐑝 𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑹𐑛 𐑘𐑽𐑟 𐑩𐑜𐑴 𐑚𐑲 ·𐑕𐑒𐑹𐑟𐑚𐑦, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑗𐑼𐑛 𐑓𐑸 𐑯𐑹𐑔 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑩𐑕𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑒, 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑵𐑟 𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑞 𐑚𐑸𐑚𐑟 𐑝 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑟 𐑛𐑸𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑯𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑕𐑰𐑟. 𐑯𐑹 𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑕𐑧𐑛, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑝 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑺𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑝𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑢𐑰𐑯 𐑞 𐑑𐑵 𐑩𐑕𐑷𐑤𐑑𐑕 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑰𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑛𐑱𐑟. 𐑣𐑧𐑯𐑕, 𐑚𐑲 𐑦𐑯𐑓𐑼𐑩𐑯𐑕, 𐑦𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑰𐑝𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑥𐑧𐑯, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑯𐑹' ·𐑢𐑧𐑕𐑑 ·𐑐𐑨𐑕𐑦𐑡, 𐑕𐑴 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑩 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑚𐑤𐑩𐑥 𐑑 𐑥𐑨𐑯, 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑩 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑚𐑤𐑩𐑥 𐑑 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤. 𐑕𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑽, 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑮𐑾𐑤 𐑤𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑽𐑾𐑯𐑕 𐑝 𐑤𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑧𐑯, 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑛𐑦𐑡𐑦𐑟 𐑮𐑦𐑤𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛 ·𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑧𐑤𐑴 𐑥𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯 ·𐑐𐑹𐑗𐑩𐑜𐑩𐑤 (𐑯𐑽 𐑣𐑵𐑟 𐑑𐑪𐑐 𐑞𐑺 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑩 𐑤𐑱𐑒 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑞 𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑕 𐑝 𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑕 𐑓𐑤𐑴𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑳𐑐 𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑻𐑓𐑦𐑕); 𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑥𐑹 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑑𐑹𐑦 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑱𐑮𐑰𐑞𐑳𐑕𐑩 𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑯𐑽 ·𐑕𐑲𐑮𐑩𐑒𐑿𐑟 (𐑣𐑵𐑟 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑰𐑝𐑛 𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 ·𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑦 ·𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑩𐑯 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑜𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑐𐑨𐑕𐑦𐑡); 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑓𐑨𐑚𐑿𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑯𐑼𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑸 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑓𐑫𐑤𐑦 𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑮𐑦𐑨𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑥𐑧𐑯.

𐑓𐑹𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑓𐑩𐑥𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑦, 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑛𐑦𐑡𐑦𐑟 𐑨𐑟 𐑞𐑰𐑟; 𐑯 𐑯𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑰𐑑𐑩𐑛, 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑧𐑐𐑦𐑛 𐑩𐑕𐑷𐑤𐑑𐑕, 𐑞 ·𐑢𐑲𐑑 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑱𐑐𐑑 𐑩𐑤𐑲𐑝; 𐑦𐑑 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑥𐑨𐑑𐑼 𐑝 𐑕𐑼𐑐𐑮𐑲𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑜𐑴 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑓𐑻𐑞𐑼 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑕𐑵𐑐𐑼𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟; 𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑺𐑦𐑙 ·𐑥𐑪𐑚𐑦 ·𐑛𐑦𐑒 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑿𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑕, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑥𐑹𐑑𐑩𐑤 (𐑓 𐑦𐑥𐑹𐑑𐑨𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑿𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑦𐑯 𐑑𐑲𐑥); 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑴 𐑜𐑮𐑴𐑝𐑟 𐑝 𐑕𐑐𐑽𐑟 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑚𐑰 𐑐𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑤𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑕, 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑕𐑢𐑦𐑥 𐑩𐑢𐑱 𐑳𐑯𐑣𐑸𐑥𐑛; 𐑹 𐑦𐑓 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑰𐑛 𐑣𐑰 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑚𐑰 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑑 𐑕𐑐𐑬𐑑 𐑔𐑦𐑒 𐑚𐑤𐑳𐑛, 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩 𐑕𐑲𐑑 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑚𐑰 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑩 𐑜𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑧𐑐𐑖𐑩𐑯; 𐑓 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑳𐑯𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑨𐑙𐑜𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑴𐑟 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑛𐑟 𐑝 𐑤𐑰𐑜𐑟 𐑩𐑢𐑱, 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑳𐑯𐑕𐑳𐑤𐑦𐑛 𐑡𐑧𐑑 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑕 𐑥𐑹 𐑚𐑰 𐑕𐑰𐑯.

𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑑 𐑝 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑕𐑵𐑐𐑼𐑯𐑨𐑗𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑼𐑥𐑲𐑟𐑦𐑙𐑟, 𐑞𐑺 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑳𐑓 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑻𐑔𐑤𐑦 𐑥𐑱𐑒 𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑒𐑨𐑮𐑩𐑒𐑑𐑼 𐑝 𐑞 𐑥𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑼 𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑒 𐑞 𐑦𐑥𐑨𐑡𐑦𐑯𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑳𐑯𐑢𐑴𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑐𐑬𐑼. 𐑓, 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑴 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑳𐑯𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑚𐑳𐑤𐑒 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑴 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑢𐑦𐑖𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟, 𐑚𐑳𐑑, 𐑨𐑟 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑧𐑤𐑕𐑢𐑺 𐑔𐑮𐑴𐑯 𐑬𐑑—𐑩 𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑽 𐑕𐑯𐑴-𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑓𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑛, 𐑯 𐑩 𐑣𐑲, 𐑐𐑦𐑮𐑩𐑥𐑦𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑣𐑳𐑥𐑐. 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑓𐑰𐑗𐑼𐑟; 𐑞 𐑑𐑴𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑢𐑺𐑚𐑲, 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑤𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑑𐑤𐑩𐑕, 𐑳𐑯𐑗𐑸𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑕𐑰𐑟, 𐑣𐑰 𐑮𐑦𐑝𐑰𐑤𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑲𐑛𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑑𐑦, 𐑨𐑑 𐑩 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕, 𐑑 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑣𐑵 𐑯𐑿 𐑣𐑦𐑥.

𐑞 𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑴 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑰𐑒𐑑, 𐑯 𐑕𐑐𐑪𐑑𐑩𐑛, 𐑯 𐑥𐑸𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑖𐑮𐑬𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑣𐑿, 𐑞𐑨𐑑, 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑧𐑯𐑛, 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑝 𐑨𐑐𐑩𐑤𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑢𐑲𐑑 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤; 𐑩 𐑯𐑱𐑥, 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑰𐑛, 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑼𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑡𐑳𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑓𐑲𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑝𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑛 𐑨𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑕𐑰𐑯 𐑜𐑤𐑲𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑲 𐑯𐑵𐑯 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑩 𐑛𐑸𐑒 𐑚𐑤𐑵 𐑕𐑰, 𐑤𐑰𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑥𐑦𐑤𐑒𐑦-𐑢𐑱 𐑢𐑱𐑒 𐑝 𐑒𐑮𐑰𐑥𐑦 𐑓𐑴𐑥, 𐑷𐑤 𐑕𐑐𐑨𐑙𐑜𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑜𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑩𐑯 𐑜𐑤𐑰𐑥𐑦𐑙𐑟.

𐑯𐑹 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑳𐑯𐑢𐑴𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑥𐑨𐑜𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑿𐑛, 𐑯𐑹 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑸𐑒𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑣𐑿, 𐑯𐑹 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑛𐑦𐑓𐑹𐑥𐑛 𐑤𐑴𐑼 𐑡𐑷, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑴 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑯𐑨𐑗𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑑𐑧𐑮𐑼, 𐑨𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑳𐑯𐑦𐑜𐑟𐑭𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑤𐑛, 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑡𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑥𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑜𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑢𐑦𐑗, 𐑩𐑒𐑹𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑕𐑐𐑩𐑕𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑒 𐑩𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑕, 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑯 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯 𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑩𐑕𐑷𐑤𐑑𐑕. 𐑥𐑹 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑷𐑤, 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑑𐑮𐑧𐑗𐑼𐑩𐑕 𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑮𐑰𐑑𐑕 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑒 𐑥𐑹 𐑝 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑥𐑱 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑐𐑼𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑕 𐑷𐑑 𐑧𐑤𐑕. 𐑓, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑕𐑢𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑜𐑟𐑳𐑤𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑐𐑼𐑕𐑿𐑼𐑟, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑩𐑐𐑨𐑮𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑕𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑑𐑩𐑥 𐑝 𐑩𐑤𐑸𐑥, 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑕𐑧𐑝𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑯𐑴𐑯 𐑑 𐑑𐑻𐑯 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑕𐑳𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑦, 𐑯, 𐑚𐑺𐑦𐑙 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑥, 𐑲𐑞𐑼 𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑝 𐑞𐑺 𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕 𐑑 𐑕𐑐𐑤𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑟, 𐑹 𐑛𐑮𐑲𐑝 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑚𐑨𐑒 𐑦𐑯 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑯𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑖𐑦𐑐.

𐑷𐑤𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑦 𐑕𐑧𐑝𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑓𐑩𐑑𐑨𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑩𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑗𐑱𐑕. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞𐑴 𐑕𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑤𐑼 𐑛𐑦𐑟𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑟, 𐑣𐑬𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑚𐑮𐑵𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑩𐑖𐑹, 𐑢𐑻 𐑚𐑲 𐑯𐑴 𐑥𐑰𐑯𐑟 𐑳𐑯𐑿𐑠𐑵𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑼𐑦; 𐑘𐑧𐑑, 𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟, 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑞 ·𐑢𐑲𐑑 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤'𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑓𐑻𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑩𐑓𐑹𐑔𐑷𐑑 𐑝 𐑓𐑼𐑪𐑕𐑦𐑑𐑦, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑥𐑧𐑥𐑚𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑹 𐑛𐑧𐑔 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑷𐑟𐑛, 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑦𐑜𐑸𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑨𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑓𐑤𐑦𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑩𐑯 𐑳𐑯𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑡𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑱𐑡𐑩𐑯𐑑.

𐑡𐑳𐑡, 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑐𐑦𐑗𐑩𐑟 𐑝 𐑦𐑯𐑓𐑤𐑱𐑥𐑛, 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑓𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑦 𐑞 𐑥𐑲𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑹 𐑛𐑧𐑕𐑐𐑼𐑩𐑑 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑧𐑤𐑛, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑩𐑥𐑦𐑛 𐑞 𐑗𐑦𐑐𐑕 𐑝 𐑗𐑵𐑛 𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑤𐑦𐑥𐑟 𐑝 𐑑𐑹𐑯 𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑮𐑱𐑛𐑟, 𐑞𐑱 𐑕𐑢𐑨𐑥 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑒𐑻𐑛𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤'𐑟 𐑛𐑲𐑼𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑮𐑪𐑔 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑕𐑼𐑰𐑯, 𐑦𐑜𐑟𐑨𐑕𐑐𐑼𐑱𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑳𐑯𐑤𐑲𐑑, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑥𐑲𐑤𐑛 𐑪𐑯, 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑓 𐑨𐑑 𐑩 𐑚𐑻𐑔 𐑹 𐑩 𐑚𐑮𐑲𐑛𐑩𐑤.

𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕 𐑕𐑑𐑴𐑝 𐑼𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑯 𐑹𐑟 𐑯 𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑚𐑴𐑔 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑧𐑛𐑦𐑟; 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯, 𐑕𐑰𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑤𐑲𐑯-𐑯𐑲𐑓 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑮𐑴𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑐𐑮𐑬, 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑛𐑨𐑖𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑨𐑟 𐑩𐑯 ·𐑸𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑷 𐑛𐑿𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑕𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑴, 𐑚𐑤𐑲𐑯𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑰𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑕 𐑦𐑯𐑗 𐑚𐑤𐑱𐑛 𐑑 𐑮𐑰𐑗 𐑞 𐑓𐑨𐑞𐑩𐑥-𐑛𐑰𐑐 𐑤𐑲𐑓 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤. 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑟 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚. 𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑢𐑰𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤-𐑖𐑱𐑐𐑑 𐑤𐑴𐑼 𐑡𐑷 𐑚𐑦𐑯𐑰𐑔 𐑣𐑦𐑥, ·𐑥𐑪𐑚𐑦 ·𐑛𐑦𐑒 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑮𐑰𐑐𐑑 𐑩𐑢𐑱 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚'𐑟 𐑤𐑧𐑜, 𐑨𐑟 𐑩 𐑥𐑴𐑼 𐑩 𐑚𐑤𐑱𐑛 𐑝 𐑜𐑮𐑭𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑰𐑤𐑛. 𐑯𐑴 𐑑𐑻𐑚𐑩𐑯𐑛 ·𐑑𐑻𐑒, 𐑯𐑴 𐑣𐑲𐑼𐑛 ·𐑝𐑩𐑯𐑰𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑹 ·𐑥𐑩𐑤𐑱, 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑕𐑥𐑴𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑥𐑹 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑨𐑤𐑦𐑕. 𐑕𐑥𐑷𐑤 𐑮𐑰𐑟𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞𐑺 𐑑 𐑛𐑬𐑑, 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑕𐑦𐑯𐑕 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑓𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑼, ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑗𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑖𐑑 𐑩 𐑢𐑲𐑤𐑛 𐑝𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑝𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑥𐑹 𐑓𐑧𐑤 𐑓 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑥𐑹𐑚𐑦𐑛𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑣𐑰 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑒𐑱𐑥 𐑑 𐑲𐑛𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑓𐑲 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑷𐑤 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑦 𐑢𐑴𐑟, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑧𐑒𐑗𐑵𐑩𐑤 𐑯 𐑕𐑐𐑦𐑮𐑦𐑗𐑵𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑜𐑟𐑨𐑕𐑐𐑼𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟. 𐑞 ·𐑢𐑲𐑑 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑕𐑢𐑨𐑥 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑥𐑪𐑯𐑩𐑥𐑱𐑯𐑦𐑨𐑒 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑸𐑯𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑥𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑕 𐑱𐑡𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑛𐑰𐑐 𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑓𐑰𐑤 𐑰𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑥, 𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑞𐑱 𐑸 𐑤𐑧𐑓𐑑 𐑤𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑪𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑭𐑓 𐑩 𐑣𐑸𐑑 𐑯 𐑣𐑭𐑓 𐑩 𐑤𐑳𐑙. 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑡𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑥𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑜𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑚𐑦𐑜𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑙; 𐑑 𐑣𐑵𐑟 𐑛𐑩𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑾𐑯 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑞 𐑥𐑪𐑛𐑼𐑯 ·𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑗𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑩𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑚 𐑢𐑳𐑯-𐑣𐑭𐑓 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛𐑟; 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑞 𐑱𐑯𐑗𐑩𐑯𐑑 ·𐑪𐑓𐑲𐑑𐑰𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑰𐑕𐑑 𐑮𐑧𐑝𐑼𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑗𐑿 𐑛𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑤;—·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑓𐑷𐑤 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑯 𐑢𐑻𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑦𐑑 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑞𐑧𐑥; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑽𐑾𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑕𐑓𐑻𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑲𐑛𐑾 𐑑 𐑞 𐑩𐑚𐑣𐑹𐑛 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑣𐑰 𐑐𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓, 𐑷𐑤 𐑥𐑿𐑑𐑦𐑤𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛, 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑑. 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑥𐑨𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑯 𐑑𐑹𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑕; 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑻𐑟 𐑳𐑐 𐑞 𐑤𐑰𐑟 𐑝 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑟; 𐑷𐑤 𐑑𐑮𐑵𐑔 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑥𐑨𐑤𐑦𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑦𐑑; 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑒𐑮𐑨𐑒𐑕 𐑞 𐑕𐑦𐑯𐑿𐑟 𐑯 𐑒𐑱𐑒𐑕 𐑞 𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑯; 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑛𐑰𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑟𐑩𐑥𐑟 𐑝 𐑤𐑲𐑓 𐑯 𐑔𐑷𐑑; 𐑷𐑤 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑤, 𐑑 𐑒𐑮𐑱𐑟𐑦 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚, 𐑢𐑻 𐑝𐑦𐑟𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑼𐑕𐑪𐑯𐑦𐑓𐑲𐑛, 𐑯 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑐𐑮𐑨𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑦 𐑩𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑯 ·𐑥𐑪𐑚𐑦 ·𐑛𐑦𐑒. 𐑣𐑰 𐑐𐑲𐑤𐑛 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤'𐑟 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑣𐑳𐑥𐑐 𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑝 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑮𐑱𐑡 𐑯 𐑣𐑱𐑑 𐑓𐑧𐑤𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑴𐑤 𐑮𐑱𐑕 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 ·𐑨𐑛𐑩𐑥 𐑛𐑬𐑯; 𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑓 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑗𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑩 𐑥𐑹𐑑𐑼, 𐑣𐑰 𐑚𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑪𐑑 𐑣𐑸𐑑'𐑕 𐑖𐑧𐑤 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑦𐑑.

𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑚𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑥𐑪𐑯𐑩𐑥𐑱𐑯𐑾 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑑𐑫𐑒 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑮𐑲𐑟 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑲𐑕 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑥𐑧𐑥𐑚𐑼𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑. 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑦𐑯 𐑛𐑸𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑥𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑼, 𐑯𐑲𐑓 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛, 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑜𐑦𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑤𐑵𐑕 𐑑 𐑩 𐑕𐑳𐑛𐑩𐑯, 𐑐𐑨𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑑, 𐑒𐑹𐑐𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑥𐑪𐑕𐑦𐑑𐑦; 𐑯 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑣𐑰 𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑰𐑝𐑛 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑴𐑒 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑑𐑹 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑣𐑰 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑚𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑓𐑧𐑤𐑑 𐑞 𐑨𐑜𐑩𐑯𐑲𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑦 𐑤𐑨𐑕𐑼𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑯𐑳𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑹. 𐑘𐑧𐑑, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑚𐑲 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑠𐑩𐑯 𐑓𐑹𐑕𐑑 𐑑 𐑑𐑻𐑯 𐑑𐑩𐑢𐑹𐑛𐑟 𐑣𐑴𐑥, 𐑯 𐑓 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑥𐑳𐑯𐑔𐑕 𐑝 𐑛𐑱𐑟 𐑯 𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑕, ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑯 𐑨𐑙𐑜𐑢𐑦𐑖 𐑤𐑱 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑧𐑗𐑑 𐑑𐑩𐑜𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑥𐑩𐑒, 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑦𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑛𐑮𐑽𐑦, 𐑣𐑬𐑤𐑦𐑙 ·𐑐𐑨𐑑𐑩𐑜𐑴𐑯𐑾𐑯 ·𐑒𐑱𐑐; 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑑𐑹𐑯 𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦 𐑯 𐑜𐑨𐑖𐑑 𐑕𐑴𐑤 𐑚𐑤𐑧𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑩𐑯𐑳𐑞𐑼; 𐑯 𐑕𐑴 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑓𐑿𐑟𐑦𐑙, 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑥𐑨𐑛. 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑣𐑴𐑥𐑢𐑼𐑛 𐑝𐑶𐑦𐑡, 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑼, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑓𐑲𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑥𐑪𐑯𐑩𐑥𐑱𐑯𐑾 𐑕𐑰𐑟𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑟 𐑷𐑤 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑓𐑨𐑒𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑, 𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑛𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑐𐑨𐑕𐑦𐑡, 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩 𐑮𐑱𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑤𐑵𐑯𐑩𐑑𐑦𐑒; 𐑯, 𐑞𐑴 𐑳𐑯𐑤𐑦𐑥𐑛 𐑝 𐑩 𐑤𐑧𐑜, 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑝𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑧𐑙𐑔 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑤𐑻𐑒𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 ·𐑦𐑡𐑦𐑐𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑗𐑧𐑕𐑑, 𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑥𐑹𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑓𐑲𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑽𐑾𐑥, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑱𐑑𐑕 𐑢𐑻 𐑓𐑹𐑕𐑑 𐑑 𐑤𐑱𐑕 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑓𐑭𐑕𐑑, 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑞𐑺, 𐑨𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑛, 𐑮𐑱𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑥𐑩𐑒. 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑑-𐑡𐑨𐑒𐑩𐑑, 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑢𐑳𐑙 𐑑 𐑞 𐑥𐑨𐑛 𐑮𐑪𐑒𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑜𐑱𐑤𐑟. 𐑯, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑮𐑳𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑥𐑹 𐑕𐑳𐑓𐑼𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑤𐑨𐑑𐑦𐑑𐑿𐑛𐑟, 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑥𐑲𐑤𐑛 𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑯'𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑛, 𐑓𐑤𐑴𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑩𐑒𐑮𐑪𐑕 𐑞 𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑑𐑮𐑪𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑕, 𐑯, 𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑩𐑐𐑽𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟, 𐑞 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑥𐑨𐑯'𐑟 𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑽𐑾𐑥 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑤𐑧𐑓𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑣𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 ·𐑒𐑱𐑐 ·𐑣𐑹𐑯 𐑕𐑢𐑧𐑤𐑟, 𐑯 𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑱𐑥 𐑓𐑹𐑔 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑛𐑸𐑒 𐑛𐑧𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑚𐑤𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑤𐑲𐑑 𐑯 𐑺; 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑣𐑰 𐑚𐑹 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑓𐑻𐑥, 𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑳𐑯𐑑, 𐑣𐑬𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑐𐑱𐑤, 𐑯 𐑦𐑖𐑿𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑭𐑥 𐑹𐑛𐑼𐑟 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑕 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯; 𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑱𐑑𐑕 𐑔𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑑 ·𐑜𐑪𐑛 𐑞 𐑛𐑲𐑼𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑥𐑨𐑛𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑬 𐑜𐑪𐑯; 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯, ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚, 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑯 𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓, 𐑮𐑱𐑝𐑛 𐑪𐑯. 𐑣𐑿𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑥𐑨𐑛𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑦𐑟 𐑪𐑓𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑩 𐑒𐑳𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑯 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑓𐑰𐑤𐑲𐑯 𐑔𐑦𐑙. 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑿 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒 𐑦𐑑 𐑓𐑤𐑧𐑛, 𐑦𐑑 𐑥𐑱 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑕𐑓𐑦𐑜𐑼𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑕𐑳𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑼 𐑓𐑹𐑥. 𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚'𐑟 𐑓𐑫𐑤 𐑤𐑵𐑯𐑩𐑕𐑦 𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑕𐑲𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑛𐑰𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑛; 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑞 𐑳𐑯𐑩𐑚𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 ·𐑣𐑳𐑛𐑕𐑩𐑯, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑯𐑴𐑚𐑩𐑤 ·𐑯𐑹𐑔𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑓𐑤𐑴𐑟 𐑯𐑼𐑴𐑤𐑦, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑳𐑯𐑓𐑨𐑞𐑩𐑥𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑞 ·𐑣𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑜𐑹𐑡. 𐑚𐑳𐑑, 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑼𐑴-𐑓𐑤𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑪𐑯𐑩𐑥𐑱𐑯𐑾, 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑡𐑪𐑑 𐑝 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚'𐑟 𐑚𐑮𐑷𐑛 𐑥𐑨𐑛𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑤𐑧𐑓𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑣𐑲𐑯𐑛; 𐑕𐑴 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑚𐑮𐑷𐑛 𐑥𐑨𐑛𐑯𐑩𐑕, 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑡𐑪𐑑 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑯𐑨𐑗𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑧𐑒𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑐𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑖𐑑. 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑤𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑱𐑡𐑩𐑯𐑑, 𐑯𐑬 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑱𐑥 𐑞 𐑤𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑩𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑. 𐑦𐑓 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩 𐑓𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑾𐑕 𐑑𐑮𐑴𐑐 𐑥𐑱 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛, 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑤 𐑤𐑵𐑯𐑩𐑕𐑦 𐑕𐑑𐑹𐑥𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑦, 𐑯 𐑒𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑛 𐑦𐑑, 𐑯 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑛 𐑷𐑤 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑛 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑩𐑯 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑴𐑯 𐑥𐑨𐑛 𐑥𐑸𐑒; 𐑕𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑓𐑸 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑣𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑤𐑪𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑧𐑙𐑔, ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚, 𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑧𐑯𐑛, 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑯𐑬 𐑐𐑩𐑟𐑧𐑕 𐑩 𐑔𐑬𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑓𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑥𐑹 𐑐𐑴𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑕𐑱𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑮𐑷𐑑 𐑑 𐑚𐑺 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑮𐑰𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑪𐑚𐑡𐑧𐑒𐑑.

𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑳𐑗; 𐑘𐑧𐑑 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚'𐑟 𐑤𐑸𐑡𐑼, 𐑛𐑸𐑒𐑼, 𐑛𐑰𐑐𐑼 𐑐𐑸𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑱𐑯𐑟 𐑳𐑯𐑣𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑝𐑱𐑯 𐑑 𐑐𐑪𐑐𐑿𐑤𐑼𐑲𐑟 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑓𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑟, 𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑑𐑮𐑵𐑔 𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛. 𐑢𐑲𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑸 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑣𐑸𐑑 𐑝 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑕𐑐𐑲𐑒𐑑 ·𐑣𐑴𐑑𐑧𐑤 𐑛𐑦 ·𐑒𐑤𐑵𐑯𐑦 𐑢𐑺 𐑢𐑰 𐑣𐑽 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛—𐑣𐑬𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑜𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑓𐑩𐑤, 𐑯𐑬 𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑑;—𐑯 𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑘𐑹 𐑢𐑱, 𐑘𐑰 𐑯𐑴𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑼, 𐑕𐑨𐑛𐑼 𐑕𐑴𐑤𐑟, 𐑑 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑝𐑭𐑕𐑑 ·𐑮𐑴𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑣𐑷𐑤𐑟 𐑝 ·𐑑𐑻𐑥𐑩𐑟; 𐑢𐑺 𐑓𐑸 𐑚𐑦𐑯𐑰𐑔 𐑞 𐑓𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑨𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑑𐑬𐑼𐑟 𐑝 𐑥𐑨𐑯'𐑟 𐑳𐑐𐑼 𐑻𐑔, 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑮𐑵𐑑 𐑝 𐑜𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑡𐑼, 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑴𐑤 𐑷𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑕𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑚𐑽𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑑; 𐑩𐑯 𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑰𐑒 𐑚𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑛 𐑚𐑦𐑯𐑰𐑔 𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑟, 𐑯 𐑔𐑮𐑴𐑯𐑛 𐑪𐑯 𐑑𐑹𐑕𐑴𐑟! 𐑕𐑴 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑚𐑮𐑴𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑔𐑮𐑴𐑯, 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑜𐑪𐑛𐑟 𐑥𐑪𐑒 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑝 𐑒𐑦𐑙; 𐑕𐑴 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 ·𐑒𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑨𐑑𐑦𐑛, 𐑣𐑰 𐑐𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑕𐑦𐑑𐑕, 𐑳𐑐𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑮𐑴𐑟𐑩𐑯 𐑚𐑮𐑬 𐑞 𐑐𐑲𐑤𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑱𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑩𐑗𐑼𐑟 𐑝 𐑱𐑡𐑩𐑟. 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛 𐑘𐑰 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑞𐑺, 𐑘𐑰 𐑐𐑮𐑬𐑛𐑼, 𐑕𐑨𐑛𐑼 𐑕𐑴𐑤𐑟! 𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑕𐑗𐑩𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑬𐑛, 𐑕𐑨𐑛 𐑒𐑦𐑙! 𐑩 𐑓𐑨𐑥𐑤𐑦 𐑤𐑲𐑒𐑯𐑩𐑕! 𐑲, 𐑣𐑰 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑚𐑦𐑜𐑧𐑑 𐑘𐑰, 𐑘𐑰 𐑘𐑳𐑙 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑲𐑤𐑛 𐑮𐑶𐑩𐑤𐑑𐑦𐑟; 𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑘𐑹 𐑜𐑮𐑦𐑥 𐑕𐑲𐑼 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑞 𐑴𐑤𐑛 ·𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑑-𐑕𐑰𐑒𐑮𐑩𐑑 𐑒𐑳𐑥.

𐑯𐑬, 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑸𐑑, ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑜𐑤𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑕 𐑝 𐑞𐑦𐑕, 𐑯𐑱𐑥𐑤𐑦: 𐑷𐑤 𐑥𐑲 𐑥𐑰𐑯𐑟 𐑸 𐑕𐑱𐑯, 𐑥𐑲 𐑥𐑴𐑑𐑦𐑝 𐑯 𐑥𐑲 𐑪𐑚𐑡𐑧𐑒𐑑 𐑥𐑨𐑛. 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑 𐑐𐑬𐑼 𐑑 𐑒𐑦𐑤, 𐑹 𐑗𐑱𐑯𐑡, 𐑹 𐑖𐑳𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑨𐑒𐑑; 𐑣𐑰 𐑤𐑲𐑒𐑢𐑲𐑟 𐑯𐑿 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑑 𐑥𐑨𐑯𐑒𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑣𐑰 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑧𐑥𐑚𐑩𐑤; 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑕𐑹𐑑, 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑧𐑥𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑳𐑚𐑡𐑧𐑒𐑑 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑼𐑕𐑧𐑐𐑑𐑩𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑦, 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑛𐑦𐑑𐑻𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑑. 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼𐑞𐑩𐑤𐑧𐑕, 𐑕𐑴 𐑢𐑧𐑤 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑩𐑒𐑕𐑰𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑧𐑥𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑲𐑝𐑼𐑦 𐑤𐑧𐑜 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑐𐑑 𐑩𐑖𐑹 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑, 𐑯𐑴 ·𐑯𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑑𐑼 𐑔𐑷𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑳𐑞𐑼𐑢𐑲𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑯𐑨𐑗𐑼𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑝𐑛, 𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑑 𐑞 𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑒, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑑𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑒𐑨𐑠𐑵𐑩𐑤𐑑𐑦 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑴𐑝𐑼𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥.

𐑞 𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑹𐑑 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑯𐑲𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑽𐑾𐑥 𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑤𐑲𐑒𐑢𐑲𐑟 𐑐𐑪𐑐𐑿𐑤𐑼𐑤𐑦 𐑩𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑚𐑛 𐑑 𐑩 𐑒𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑛 𐑒𐑷𐑟. 𐑯 𐑕𐑴 𐑑𐑵, 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑨𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑥𐑵𐑛𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑷𐑤𐑢𐑱𐑟 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼𐑢𐑼𐑛𐑟, 𐑑 𐑞 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑛𐑱 𐑝 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑝𐑶𐑦𐑡, 𐑕𐑨𐑑 𐑚𐑮𐑵𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑮𐑬. 𐑯𐑹 𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑴 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑳𐑯𐑤𐑲𐑒𐑤𐑦, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑓𐑸 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑦𐑑𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑓 𐑩𐑯𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑝𐑶𐑦𐑡, 𐑪𐑯 𐑩𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑛𐑸𐑒 𐑕𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑑𐑩𐑥𐑟, 𐑞 𐑒𐑨𐑤𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑱𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑐𐑰𐑐𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑵𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑲𐑤 𐑢𐑻 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑤𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑑 𐑣𐑸𐑚𐑼 𐑞 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑰𐑑, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑓 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑮𐑰𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑚𐑧𐑑𐑼 𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑤𐑦𐑓𐑲𐑛 𐑯 𐑕𐑧𐑑 𐑪𐑯 𐑧𐑡, 𐑓 𐑩 𐑐𐑼𐑕𐑿𐑑 𐑕𐑴 𐑓𐑫𐑤 𐑝 𐑮𐑱𐑡 𐑯 𐑢𐑲𐑤𐑛𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑚𐑤𐑳𐑛𐑦 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟. 𐑯𐑷𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑦𐑯 𐑯 𐑕𐑒𐑹𐑗𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑓𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑑, 𐑳𐑯𐑮𐑦𐑤𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑨𐑙𐑟 𐑝 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑲𐑛𐑾; 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯, 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑣𐑰 𐑚𐑰 𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛, 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑕𐑰𐑥 𐑞 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑑 𐑛𐑸𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑲𐑼𐑯 𐑯 𐑤𐑦𐑓𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑕 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑞 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑩𐑐𐑷𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑷𐑤 𐑚𐑮𐑵𐑑𐑕. 𐑹, 𐑦𐑓 𐑓 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑮𐑰𐑟𐑩𐑯 𐑔𐑷𐑑 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑒𐑹𐑐𐑹𐑾𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑩𐑐𐑨𐑕𐑦𐑑𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑓 𐑞𐑨𐑑, 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑕𐑰𐑥 𐑕𐑵𐑐𐑻𐑤𐑩𐑑𐑦𐑝𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑐𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑑 𐑗𐑽 𐑯 𐑣𐑬𐑤 𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑤𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑑 𐑞 𐑩𐑑𐑨𐑒. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑥𐑱, 𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑥𐑨𐑛 𐑕𐑰𐑒𐑮𐑩𐑑 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑳𐑯𐑩𐑚𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑮𐑱𐑡 𐑚𐑴𐑤𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑳𐑐 𐑯 𐑒𐑰𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥, ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑐𐑻𐑐𐑩𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑛 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑝𐑶𐑦𐑡 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑯 𐑷𐑤-𐑦𐑯𐑜𐑮𐑴𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑪𐑚𐑡𐑧𐑒𐑑 𐑝 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑞 ·𐑢𐑲𐑑 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤. 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑩𐑒𐑢𐑱𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑪𐑯 𐑖𐑹 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑣𐑭𐑓 𐑛𐑮𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑝 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑤𐑻𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑣𐑬 𐑕𐑵𐑯 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑞𐑺 𐑩𐑜𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑯 𐑮𐑲𐑗𐑩𐑕 𐑕𐑴𐑤𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑮𐑧𐑯𐑗𐑑 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩 𐑓𐑰𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑖 𐑥𐑨𐑯! 𐑞𐑱 𐑢𐑻 𐑚𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑪𐑯 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑓𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑒𐑮𐑵𐑟𐑩𐑟, 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑓𐑦𐑑 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑛𐑪𐑤𐑼𐑟 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑑. 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑪𐑯 𐑩𐑯 𐑷𐑛𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑕, 𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑜𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤, 𐑯 𐑕𐑵𐑐𐑼𐑯𐑨𐑗𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑮𐑦𐑝𐑧𐑯𐑡.

𐑣𐑽, 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑜𐑮𐑱-𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑩𐑛, 𐑳𐑯𐑜𐑪𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑥𐑨𐑯, 𐑗𐑱𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑒𐑻𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑩 ·𐑡𐑴𐑚'𐑟 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑞 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛, 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑝 𐑩 𐑒𐑮𐑵, 𐑑𐑵, 𐑗𐑰𐑓𐑤𐑦 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑳𐑐 𐑝 𐑥𐑳𐑙𐑜𐑮𐑩𐑤 𐑮𐑧𐑯𐑦𐑜𐑱𐑛𐑟, 𐑯 𐑒𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑢𐑱𐑟, 𐑯 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑟—𐑥𐑪𐑮𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑯𐑓𐑰𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑷𐑤𐑕𐑴, 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑐𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑝 𐑥𐑽 𐑳𐑯𐑱𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑝𐑻𐑗𐑵 𐑹 𐑮𐑲𐑑-𐑥𐑲𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑦𐑯 ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒, 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑳𐑤𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑡𐑪𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑝 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑓𐑼𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑯 𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑤𐑩𐑕𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑦𐑯 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑐𐑼𐑝𐑱𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑰𐑛𐑦𐑪𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑦𐑯 ·𐑓𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑒. 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩 𐑒𐑮𐑵, 𐑕𐑴 𐑪𐑓𐑦𐑕𐑼𐑛, 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑑 𐑯 𐑐𐑨𐑒𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑦𐑯𐑓𐑻𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑓𐑩𐑑𐑨𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑑 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑐 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑪𐑯𐑩𐑥𐑱𐑯𐑦𐑨𐑒 𐑮𐑦𐑝𐑧𐑯𐑡. 𐑣𐑬 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑱 𐑕𐑴 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑪𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑑 𐑞 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑥𐑨𐑯'𐑟 𐑲𐑼—𐑚𐑲 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑤 𐑥𐑨𐑡𐑦𐑒 𐑞𐑺 𐑕𐑴𐑤𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑐𐑩𐑟𐑧𐑕𐑑, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑱𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑞𐑺𐑟; 𐑞 ·𐑢𐑲𐑑 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑨𐑟 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑞𐑺 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑳𐑓𐑼𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑓𐑴 𐑨𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑟; 𐑣𐑬 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑒𐑱𐑥 𐑑 𐑚𐑰—𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑢𐑲𐑑 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑑 𐑞𐑧𐑥, 𐑹 𐑣𐑬 𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑳𐑯𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑕 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙𐑟, 𐑷𐑤𐑕𐑴, 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑛𐑦𐑥, 𐑳𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑱, 𐑣𐑰 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑞 𐑜𐑤𐑲𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑛𐑰𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑰𐑟 𐑝 𐑤𐑲𐑓,—𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑑 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑯, 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑚𐑰 𐑑 𐑛𐑲𐑝 𐑛𐑰𐑐𐑼 𐑞𐑨𐑯 ·𐑦𐑖𐑥𐑱𐑩𐑤 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑜𐑴. 𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑚𐑑𐑼𐑱𐑯𐑾𐑯 𐑥𐑲𐑯𐑼 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑻𐑒𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑳𐑕 𐑷𐑤, 𐑣𐑬 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑑𐑧𐑤 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑼 𐑤𐑰𐑛𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑖𐑭𐑓𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑖𐑦𐑓𐑑𐑦𐑙, 𐑥𐑳𐑓𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑕𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑦𐑒? 𐑣𐑵 𐑛𐑳𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑓𐑰𐑤 𐑞 𐑦𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑸𐑥 𐑛𐑮𐑨𐑜? 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑒𐑦𐑓 𐑦𐑯 𐑑𐑴 𐑝 𐑩 𐑕𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑦-𐑓𐑹 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤? 𐑓 𐑢𐑳𐑯, 𐑲 𐑜𐑱𐑝 𐑥𐑲𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑳𐑐 𐑑 𐑞 𐑩𐑚𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑯 𐑞 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑩-𐑮𐑳𐑖 𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑼 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑕𐑰 𐑯𐑷𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑚𐑮𐑵𐑑 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑛𐑤𐑾𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑤.

·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 42. 𐑞 ·𐑢𐑲𐑑𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤.

𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑞 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑑 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚, 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛; 𐑢𐑪𐑑, 𐑨𐑑 𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟, 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑑 𐑥𐑰, 𐑨𐑟 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑱𐑯𐑟 𐑳𐑯𐑕𐑧𐑛.

𐑩𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑥𐑹 𐑪𐑚𐑝𐑾𐑕 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑼𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑑𐑳𐑗𐑦𐑙 ·𐑥𐑪𐑚𐑦 ·𐑛𐑦𐑒, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑩𐑒𐑱𐑠𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑩𐑢𐑱𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑥𐑨𐑯'𐑟 𐑕𐑴𐑤 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑩𐑤𐑸𐑥, 𐑞𐑺 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩𐑯𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑔𐑷𐑑, 𐑹 𐑮𐑭𐑞𐑼 𐑝𐑱𐑜, 𐑯𐑱𐑥𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑣𐑪𐑮𐑼 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑨𐑑 𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑚𐑲 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑰𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑴𐑝𐑼𐑐𐑬𐑼𐑛 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑑; 𐑯 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑕𐑴 𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑯 𐑢𐑧𐑤 𐑯𐑲 𐑦𐑯𐑧𐑓𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑦𐑑, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑲 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑺 𐑝 𐑐𐑫𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑣𐑧𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑓𐑹𐑥. 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞 𐑢𐑲𐑑𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑩𐑚𐑳𐑝 𐑷𐑤 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑩𐑐𐑷𐑤𐑛 𐑥𐑰. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑣𐑬 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑲 𐑣𐑴𐑐 𐑑 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑯 𐑥𐑲𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑣𐑽; 𐑯 𐑘𐑧𐑑, 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑛𐑦𐑥, 𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑥 𐑢𐑱, 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑯 𐑥𐑲𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑲 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑, 𐑧𐑤𐑕 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼𐑟 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑯𐑷𐑑.

𐑞𐑴 𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑯𐑨𐑗𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑪𐑚𐑡𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑕, 𐑢𐑲𐑑𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑮𐑦𐑓𐑲𐑯𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑯𐑣𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑚𐑿𐑑𐑦, 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑓 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑸𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑤 𐑝𐑻𐑗𐑵 𐑝 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑴𐑯, 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑸𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑟, 𐑡𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑟, 𐑯 𐑐𐑻𐑤𐑟; 𐑯 𐑞𐑴 𐑝𐑺𐑾𐑕 𐑯𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑢𐑱 𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑩𐑜𐑯𐑲𐑟𐑛 𐑩 𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑮𐑶𐑩𐑤 𐑐𐑮𐑰𐑧𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑣𐑿; 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑸𐑚𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑒, 𐑜𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑒𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑝 ·𐑐𐑧𐑜𐑵 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑑𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑤 “𐑤𐑹𐑛 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑢𐑲𐑑 ·𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑓𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕” 𐑩𐑚𐑳𐑝 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑺 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑥𐑨𐑜𐑯𐑦𐑤𐑩𐑒𐑢𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑩𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑛𐑩𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑾𐑯; 𐑯 𐑞 𐑥𐑪𐑛𐑼𐑯 𐑒𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑝 ·𐑕𐑲𐑨𐑥 𐑳𐑯𐑓𐑻𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑕𐑯𐑴-𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑐𐑧𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑮𐑶𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑛; 𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑴𐑝𐑺𐑾𐑯 𐑓𐑤𐑨𐑜 𐑚𐑺𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑓𐑦𐑜𐑼 𐑝 𐑩 𐑕𐑯𐑴-𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑗𐑸𐑡𐑼; 𐑯 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 ·𐑪𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑾𐑯 ·𐑧𐑥𐑐𐑲𐑼, ·𐑕𐑦𐑟𐑺𐑾𐑯, 𐑺 𐑑 𐑴𐑝𐑼𐑤𐑹𐑛𐑦𐑙 ·𐑮𐑴𐑥, 𐑣𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑓 𐑞 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑽𐑾𐑤 𐑒𐑳𐑤𐑼 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑽𐑾𐑤 𐑣𐑿; 𐑯 𐑞𐑴 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑐𐑮𐑰-𐑧𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑦𐑑 𐑩𐑐𐑤𐑲𐑟 𐑑 𐑞 𐑣𐑿𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑮𐑱𐑕 𐑦𐑑𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓, 𐑜𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑲𐑛𐑾𐑤 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑛𐑳𐑕𐑒𐑦 𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑚; 𐑯 𐑞𐑴, 𐑚𐑦𐑕𐑲𐑛𐑟, 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑦𐑕, 𐑢𐑲𐑑𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑕𐑦𐑜𐑯𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑜𐑤𐑨𐑛𐑯𐑩𐑕, 𐑓 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑞 ·𐑮𐑴𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑩 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑴𐑯 𐑥𐑸𐑒𐑑 𐑩 𐑡𐑶𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑛𐑱; 𐑯 𐑞𐑴 𐑦𐑯 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑥𐑹𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑔𐑦𐑟 𐑯 𐑕𐑦𐑥𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑲𐑟𐑦𐑙𐑟, 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑣𐑿 𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑞 𐑧𐑥𐑚𐑤𐑩𐑥 𐑝 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑑𐑳𐑗𐑦𐑙, 𐑯𐑴𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑟—𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑝 𐑚𐑮𐑲𐑛𐑟, 𐑞 𐑚𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑜𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑝 𐑱𐑡; 𐑞𐑴 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑞 ·𐑮𐑧𐑛 ·𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑝 ·𐑩𐑥𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑩 𐑞 𐑜𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑚𐑧𐑤𐑑 𐑝 𐑢𐑪𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑥 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞 𐑛𐑰𐑐𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑐𐑤𐑧𐑡 𐑝 𐑪𐑯𐑼; 𐑞𐑴 𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑒𐑤𐑲𐑥𐑟, 𐑢𐑲𐑑𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑑𐑦𐑐𐑦𐑓𐑲𐑟 𐑞 𐑥𐑨𐑡𐑩𐑕𐑑𐑦 𐑝 ·𐑡𐑳𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑻𐑥𐑦𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑡𐑳𐑡, 𐑯 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑚𐑿𐑑𐑕 𐑑 𐑞 𐑛𐑱𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑑 𐑝 𐑒𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑯 𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑯𐑟 𐑛𐑮𐑷𐑯 𐑚𐑲 𐑥𐑦𐑤𐑒-𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑰𐑛𐑟; 𐑞𐑴 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑣𐑲𐑼 𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑦𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑷𐑜𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑡𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑞 𐑕𐑦𐑥𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑞 𐑛𐑦𐑝𐑲𐑯 𐑕𐑐𐑪𐑑𐑤𐑩𐑕𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑯 𐑐𐑬𐑼; 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑻𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑓𐑲𐑼 𐑢𐑻𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑼𐑟, 𐑞 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑓𐑹𐑒𐑑 𐑓𐑤𐑱𐑥 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑛 𐑞 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑾𐑕𐑑 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑷𐑤𐑑𐑼; 𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑒 𐑥𐑦𐑔𐑪𐑤𐑩𐑡𐑦𐑟, ·𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 ·𐑡𐑴𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑸𐑯𐑩𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑕𐑯𐑴-𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑚𐑫𐑤; 𐑯 𐑞𐑴 𐑑 𐑞 𐑯𐑴𐑚𐑩𐑤 ·𐑽𐑩𐑒𐑢𐑭, 𐑞 𐑥𐑦𐑛𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼 𐑕𐑨𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑓𐑲𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑒𐑮𐑩𐑛 ·𐑢𐑲𐑑 ·𐑛𐑪𐑜 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑚𐑲 𐑓𐑸 𐑞 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑾𐑕𐑑 𐑓𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑝𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑞𐑺 𐑔𐑦𐑪𐑤𐑩𐑡𐑦, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑐𐑪𐑑𐑤𐑩𐑕, 𐑓𐑱𐑔𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑒𐑮𐑰𐑗𐑼 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑛 𐑞 𐑐𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑧𐑯𐑝𐑶 𐑞𐑱 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 ·𐑕𐑐𐑦𐑮𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑨𐑯𐑿𐑩𐑤 𐑑𐑲𐑛𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑝 𐑞𐑺 𐑴𐑯 𐑓𐑦𐑛𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑦; 𐑯 𐑞𐑴 𐑛𐑦𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 ·𐑤𐑨𐑑𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑻𐑛 𐑓 𐑢𐑲𐑑, 𐑷𐑤 ·𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑗𐑩𐑯 𐑐𐑮𐑰𐑕𐑑𐑕 𐑛𐑦𐑮𐑲𐑝 𐑞 𐑯𐑱𐑥 𐑝 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑐𐑸𐑑 𐑝 𐑞𐑺 𐑕𐑱𐑒𐑮𐑩𐑛 𐑝𐑧𐑕𐑗𐑼, 𐑞 𐑨𐑤𐑚 𐑹 𐑑𐑿𐑯𐑦𐑒, 𐑢𐑹𐑯 𐑚𐑦𐑯𐑰𐑔 𐑞 𐑒𐑨𐑕𐑩𐑒; 𐑯 𐑞𐑴 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑞 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑪𐑥𐑐𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑮𐑴𐑥𐑦𐑖 𐑓𐑱𐑔, 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑶𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑩𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑭𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑬𐑼 ·𐑤𐑹𐑛; 𐑞𐑴 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑝𐑦𐑠𐑩𐑯 𐑝 ·𐑕𐑑 ·𐑡𐑪𐑯, 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑮𐑴𐑚𐑟 𐑸 𐑜𐑦𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑑 𐑞 𐑮𐑦𐑛𐑰𐑥𐑛, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑹-𐑯-𐑑𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑦 𐑧𐑤𐑛𐑼𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑒𐑤𐑴𐑞𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑔𐑮𐑴𐑯, 𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑦 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑔 𐑞𐑺 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑢𐑫𐑤; 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑓 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑩𐑒𐑿𐑥𐑿𐑤𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑩𐑕𐑴𐑖𐑦𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑢𐑪𐑑𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑢𐑰𐑑, 𐑯 𐑪𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤, 𐑯 𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑲𐑥, 𐑞𐑺 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑤𐑻𐑒𐑕 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑤𐑵𐑕𐑦𐑝 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑼𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑲𐑛𐑾 𐑝 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑣𐑿, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑒𐑕 𐑥𐑹 𐑝 𐑐𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑒 𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑴𐑤 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑩𐑓𐑮𐑲𐑑𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑚𐑤𐑳𐑛.

𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑦𐑤𐑵𐑕𐑦𐑝 𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑒𐑷𐑟𐑩𐑟 𐑞 𐑔𐑷𐑑 𐑝 𐑢𐑲𐑑𐑯𐑩𐑕, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑛𐑦𐑝𐑹𐑕𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑥𐑹 𐑒𐑲𐑯𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑩𐑕𐑴𐑖𐑦𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟, 𐑯 𐑒𐑳𐑐𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑪𐑚𐑡𐑧𐑒𐑑 𐑑𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑦𐑑𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓, 𐑑 𐑣𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑑𐑧𐑮𐑼 𐑑 𐑞 𐑓𐑻𐑞𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑟. 𐑢𐑦𐑑𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑞 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑚𐑺 𐑝 𐑞 𐑐𐑴𐑤𐑟, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑖𐑸𐑒 𐑝 𐑞 𐑑𐑮𐑪𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑕; 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑕𐑥𐑵𐑞, 𐑓𐑤𐑱𐑒𐑦 𐑢𐑲𐑑𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑥𐑱𐑒𐑕 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑞 𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑣𐑪𐑮𐑼𐑟 𐑞𐑱 𐑸? 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑜𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑢𐑲𐑑𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑸𐑑𐑕 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩𐑯 𐑩𐑚𐑣𐑹𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑥𐑲𐑤𐑛𐑯𐑩𐑕, 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑥𐑹 𐑤𐑴𐑞𐑕𐑩𐑥 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑑𐑼𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑒, 𐑑 𐑞 𐑛𐑳𐑥 𐑜𐑤𐑴𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑞𐑺 𐑨𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑. 𐑕𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑞 𐑓𐑽𐑕-𐑓𐑨𐑙𐑛 𐑑𐑲𐑜𐑼 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑼𐑨𐑤𐑛𐑦𐑒 𐑒𐑴𐑑 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑕𐑴 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑜𐑼 𐑒𐑳𐑮𐑦𐑡 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑢𐑲𐑑-𐑖𐑮𐑬𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑺 𐑹 𐑖𐑸𐑒.*

*𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑮𐑧𐑓𐑼𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑴𐑤𐑼 𐑚𐑺, 𐑦𐑑 𐑥𐑱 𐑐𐑪𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑰 𐑻𐑡𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑣𐑵 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑓𐑱𐑯 𐑜𐑴 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑛𐑰𐑐𐑼 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑥𐑨𐑑𐑼, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑞 𐑢𐑲𐑑𐑯𐑩𐑕, 𐑕𐑧𐑐𐑼𐑩𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑦𐑜𐑸𐑛𐑩𐑛, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑣𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑪𐑤𐑼𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑣𐑦𐑛𐑾𐑕𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑚𐑮𐑵𐑑; 𐑓, 𐑨𐑯𐑩𐑤𐑲𐑟𐑛, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑛𐑾𐑕𐑯𐑩𐑕, 𐑦𐑑 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑕𐑧𐑛, 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑲𐑟𐑩𐑟 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑕𐑻𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑕, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑦𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑓𐑼𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑕𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑰𐑗𐑼 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑤𐑰𐑕 𐑝 𐑕𐑦𐑤𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑾𐑤 𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑯 𐑤𐑳𐑝; 𐑯 𐑣𐑧𐑯𐑕, 𐑚𐑲 𐑚𐑮𐑦𐑙𐑦𐑙 𐑑𐑩𐑜𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑑𐑵 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑪𐑐𐑩𐑟𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑥𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑬𐑼 𐑥𐑲𐑯𐑛𐑟, 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑴𐑤𐑼 𐑚𐑺 𐑓𐑮𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑳𐑕 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑕𐑴 𐑳𐑯𐑯𐑨𐑗𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑩 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑭𐑕𐑑. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑩𐑕𐑿𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑑𐑮𐑵; 𐑘𐑧𐑑, 𐑢𐑻 𐑦𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑓 𐑞 𐑢𐑲𐑑𐑯𐑩𐑕, 𐑿 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑓𐑲𐑛 𐑑𐑧𐑮𐑼.

𐑨𐑟 𐑓 𐑞 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑖𐑸𐑒, 𐑞 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑜𐑤𐑲𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑜𐑴𐑕𐑑𐑤𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑴𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑒𐑮𐑰𐑗𐑼, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑚𐑦𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑹𐑛𐑦𐑯𐑼𐑦 𐑥𐑵𐑛𐑟, 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑤𐑦 𐑑𐑨𐑤𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑴𐑤𐑼 𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑐𐑧𐑛. 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑦𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑝𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑣𐑦𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 ·𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑯𐑗 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑯𐑱𐑥 𐑞𐑱 𐑚𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑴 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑓𐑦𐑖. 𐑞 ·𐑮𐑴𐑥𐑦𐑖 𐑥𐑨𐑕 𐑓 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑛 𐑚𐑦𐑜𐑦𐑯𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑞 “𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑢𐑾𐑥 𐑰𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑩𐑥” (𐑦𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑑), 𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑕 ·𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑢𐑾𐑥 𐑛𐑦𐑯𐑪𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑱𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑥𐑨𐑕 𐑦𐑑𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓, 𐑯 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑓𐑿𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑥𐑿𐑟𐑦𐑒. 𐑯𐑬, 𐑦𐑯 𐑩𐑤𐑵𐑠𐑩𐑯 𐑑 𐑞 𐑢𐑲𐑑, 𐑕𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑛𐑧𐑔 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑖𐑸𐑒, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑥𐑲𐑤𐑛 𐑛𐑧𐑛𐑤𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑕, 𐑞 ·𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑯𐑗 𐑒𐑷𐑤 𐑣𐑦𐑥 ·𐑮𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑯.

𐑚𐑦𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒 𐑞𐑰 𐑝 𐑞 𐑨𐑤𐑚𐑩𐑑𐑮𐑪𐑕, 𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑕 𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑒𐑤𐑬𐑛𐑟 𐑝 𐑕𐑐𐑦𐑮𐑦𐑗𐑵𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑯 𐑐𐑱𐑤 𐑛𐑮𐑧𐑛, 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑓𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑥 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑦𐑥𐑨𐑡𐑦𐑯𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟? 𐑯𐑪𐑑 ·𐑒𐑴𐑤𐑮𐑦𐑡 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑤; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 ·𐑜𐑪𐑛'𐑟 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑, 𐑳𐑯𐑓𐑤𐑨𐑑𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑤𐑹𐑾𐑑, ·𐑯𐑱𐑗𐑼.*

*𐑲 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑧𐑥𐑚𐑼 𐑞 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑨𐑤𐑚𐑩𐑑𐑮𐑪𐑕 𐑲 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑕𐑷. 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑛𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑐𐑮𐑴𐑤𐑪𐑙𐑛 𐑜𐑱𐑤, 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼𐑟 𐑣𐑸𐑛 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑸𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑕𐑰𐑟. 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑥𐑲 𐑓𐑹𐑯𐑵𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑗 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑴, 𐑲 𐑩𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑑 𐑞 𐑴𐑝𐑼𐑒𐑤𐑬𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑛𐑧𐑒; 𐑯 𐑞𐑺, 𐑛𐑨𐑖𐑑 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑥𐑱𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑗𐑩𐑟, 𐑲 𐑕𐑷 𐑩 𐑮𐑰𐑜𐑩𐑤, 𐑓𐑧𐑞𐑼𐑦 𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑳𐑯𐑕𐑐𐑪𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑲𐑑𐑯𐑩𐑕, 𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑣𐑫𐑒𐑑, ·𐑮𐑴𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑚𐑦𐑤 𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑲𐑥. 𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑟, 𐑦𐑑 𐑸𐑗𐑑 𐑓𐑹𐑔 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑝𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑸𐑒𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑦𐑙𐑟, 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑓 𐑑 𐑦𐑥𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑕 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑦 𐑸𐑒. 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑕 𐑓𐑤𐑳𐑑𐑼𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑯 𐑔𐑮𐑪𐑚𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑖𐑫𐑒 𐑦𐑑. 𐑞𐑴 𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑦 𐑳𐑯𐑣𐑸𐑥𐑛, 𐑦𐑑 𐑳𐑑𐑼𐑛 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑟, 𐑨𐑟 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑒𐑦𐑙'𐑟 𐑜𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑵𐑐𐑼𐑯𐑨𐑗𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑧𐑕. 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤, 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡 𐑲𐑟, 𐑥𐑦𐑔𐑷𐑑 𐑲 𐑐𐑰𐑐𐑑 𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑒𐑮𐑩𐑑𐑕 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑑𐑫𐑒 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑝 ·𐑜𐑪𐑛. 𐑨𐑟 ·𐑱𐑚𐑮𐑩𐑣𐑨𐑥 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑞 𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑩𐑤𐑟, 𐑲 𐑚𐑬𐑛 𐑥𐑲𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓; 𐑞 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑴 𐑢𐑲𐑑, 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑢𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑕𐑴 𐑢𐑲𐑛, 𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑓 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑲𐑤𐑛 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼𐑟, 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑤𐑪𐑕𐑑 𐑞 𐑥𐑦𐑟𐑼𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑹𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑧𐑥𐑼𐑦𐑟 𐑝 𐑑𐑮𐑩𐑛𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑯 𐑝 𐑑𐑬𐑯𐑟. 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑲 𐑜𐑱𐑟𐑛 𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑛𐑦𐑡𐑦 𐑝 𐑐𐑤𐑵𐑥𐑦𐑡. 𐑲 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑑𐑧𐑤, 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑣𐑦𐑯𐑑, 𐑞 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑛𐑸𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑥𐑰 𐑞𐑧𐑯. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑲 𐑩𐑢𐑴𐑒; 𐑯 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑙, 𐑭𐑕𐑒𐑑 𐑩 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑼 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑚𐑻𐑛 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞𐑦𐑕. 𐑩 𐑜𐑪𐑯𐑦, 𐑣𐑰 𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑤𐑲𐑛. 𐑜𐑪𐑯𐑦! 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑣𐑻𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑯𐑱𐑥 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹; 𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑜𐑤𐑹𐑾𐑕 𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑟 𐑳𐑑𐑼𐑤𐑦 𐑳𐑯𐑯𐑴𐑯 𐑑 𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑩𐑖𐑹! 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼! 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼, 𐑲 𐑤𐑻𐑯𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑜𐑪𐑯𐑦 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑩𐑯'𐑟 𐑯𐑱𐑥 𐑓 𐑨𐑤𐑚𐑩𐑑𐑮𐑪𐑕. 𐑕𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑯𐑴 𐑐𐑪𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑒𐑫𐑛 ·𐑒𐑴𐑤𐑮𐑦𐑡'𐑩𐑟 𐑢𐑲𐑤𐑛 ·𐑮𐑲𐑥 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑷𐑑 𐑑 𐑛𐑵 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑢𐑻 𐑥𐑲𐑯, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑲 𐑕𐑷 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑚𐑻𐑛 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑬𐑼 𐑛𐑧𐑒. 𐑓 𐑯𐑲𐑞𐑼 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑲 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑮𐑧𐑛 𐑞 ·𐑮𐑲𐑥, 𐑯𐑹 𐑯𐑿 𐑞 𐑚𐑻𐑛 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑩𐑯 𐑨𐑤𐑚𐑩𐑑𐑮𐑪𐑕. 𐑘𐑧𐑑, 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑱𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑦𐑕, 𐑲 𐑛𐑵 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑖 𐑩 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑚𐑮𐑲𐑑𐑼 𐑞 𐑯𐑴𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑥𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑐𐑴𐑩𐑥 𐑯 𐑞 𐑐𐑴𐑩𐑑.

𐑲 𐑩𐑕𐑻𐑑, 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑕 𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑦 𐑢𐑲𐑑𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑚𐑻𐑛 𐑗𐑰𐑓𐑤𐑦 𐑤𐑻𐑒𐑕 𐑞 𐑕𐑰𐑒𐑮𐑩𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑤; 𐑩 𐑑𐑮𐑵𐑔 𐑞 𐑥𐑹 𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑩 𐑕𐑪𐑤𐑦𐑕𐑦𐑟𐑩𐑥 𐑝 𐑑𐑻𐑥𐑟 𐑞𐑺 𐑸 𐑚𐑻𐑛𐑟 𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑛 𐑜𐑮𐑱 𐑨𐑤𐑚𐑩𐑑𐑮𐑪𐑕𐑩𐑟; 𐑯 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑓𐑮𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑰𐑯, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑦𐑥𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑨𐑟 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑲 𐑚𐑦𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑛 𐑞 ·𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑸𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑓𐑬𐑤.

𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑣𐑬 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑞 𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑒𐑷𐑑? 𐑢𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑼 𐑦𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑑, 𐑯 𐑲 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑑𐑧𐑤; 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑑𐑮𐑧𐑗𐑼𐑩𐑕 𐑣𐑫𐑒 𐑯 𐑤𐑲𐑯, 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑓𐑬𐑤 𐑓𐑤𐑴𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑰. 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑩 𐑐𐑴𐑕𐑑𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑦𐑑; 𐑑𐑲𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑤𐑧𐑑𐑼𐑛, 𐑤𐑧𐑞𐑼𐑯 𐑑𐑨𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑯𐑧𐑒, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐'𐑕 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑯 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕; 𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑤𐑧𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑱𐑐. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑲 𐑛𐑬𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑑, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑧𐑞𐑼𐑯 𐑑𐑨𐑤𐑦, 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑓 𐑥𐑨𐑯, 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑪𐑓 𐑦𐑯 ·𐑣𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑯, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑓𐑬𐑤 𐑓𐑤𐑵 𐑑 𐑡𐑶𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑦𐑙-𐑓𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑦𐑙, 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑴𐑒𐑦𐑙, 𐑯 𐑩𐑛𐑹𐑦𐑙 𐑗𐑧𐑮𐑩𐑚𐑦𐑥!

𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑓𐑱𐑥𐑩𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑬𐑼 ·𐑢𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑯 𐑨𐑯𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑯 ·𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑾𐑯 𐑑𐑮𐑩𐑛𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑦𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑢𐑲𐑑 ·𐑕𐑑𐑰𐑛 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑮𐑺𐑦𐑟; 𐑩 𐑥𐑨𐑜𐑯𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑥𐑦𐑤𐑒-𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑗𐑸𐑡𐑼, 𐑤𐑸𐑡-𐑲𐑛, 𐑕𐑥𐑷𐑤-𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑩𐑛, 𐑚𐑤𐑳𐑓-𐑗𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛, 𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑛𐑦𐑜𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑝 𐑩 𐑔𐑬𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑥𐑪𐑯𐑸𐑒𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑤𐑪𐑓𐑑𐑦, 𐑴𐑝𐑼𐑕𐑒𐑹𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑒𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑡. 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞 𐑦𐑤𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑛 ·𐑟𐑻𐑒𐑕𐑰𐑟 𐑝 𐑝𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑻𐑛𐑟 𐑝 𐑢𐑲𐑤𐑛 𐑣𐑹𐑕𐑩𐑟, 𐑣𐑵𐑟 𐑐𐑭𐑕𐑗𐑼𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑛𐑱𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑓𐑧𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 ·𐑮𐑪𐑒𐑦 ·𐑥𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑨𐑤𐑦𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑦𐑟. 𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑓𐑤𐑱𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑢𐑼𐑛 𐑑𐑮𐑵𐑐𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑗𐑴𐑟𐑩𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑸 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑰𐑝𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑤𐑰𐑛𐑟 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑣𐑴𐑕𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑤𐑲𐑑. 𐑞 𐑓𐑤𐑨𐑖𐑦𐑙 𐑒𐑨𐑕𐑒𐑱𐑛 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑱𐑯, 𐑞 𐑒𐑻𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑑 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑑𐑱𐑤, 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑬𐑟𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑥𐑹 𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑤𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑜𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑯 𐑕𐑦𐑤𐑝𐑼-𐑚𐑰𐑑𐑼𐑟 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑓𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑖𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥. 𐑩 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑽𐑾𐑤 𐑯 𐑸𐑒𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑨𐑐𐑼𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑳𐑯𐑓𐑷𐑤𐑩𐑯, 𐑢𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑯 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑑 𐑞 𐑲𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑐𐑼𐑟 𐑯 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑟 𐑮𐑦𐑝𐑲𐑝𐑛 𐑞 𐑜𐑤𐑹𐑦𐑟 𐑝 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑐𐑮𐑲𐑥𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑤 𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑢𐑧𐑯 ·𐑨𐑛𐑩𐑥 𐑢𐑷𐑒𐑑 𐑥𐑩𐑡𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑨𐑟 𐑩 𐑜𐑪𐑛, 𐑚𐑤𐑳𐑓-𐑚𐑮𐑬𐑛 𐑯 𐑓𐑽𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑨𐑟 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑥𐑲𐑑𐑦 𐑕𐑑𐑰𐑛. 𐑢𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑥𐑸𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑥𐑦𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑱𐑛𐑟 𐑯 𐑥𐑸𐑖𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑝𐑨𐑯 𐑝 𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑒𐑴𐑣𐑹𐑑𐑕 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑤𐑩𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑦𐑑 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑞 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑯𐑟, 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩𐑯 ·𐑴𐑣𐑲𐑴; 𐑹 𐑢𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑻𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑨𐑥𐑚𐑾𐑯𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑚𐑡𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑕 𐑚𐑮𐑬𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑷𐑤 𐑼𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑣𐑼𐑲𐑟𐑩𐑯, 𐑞 ·𐑢𐑲𐑑 ·𐑕𐑑𐑰𐑛 𐑜𐑨𐑤𐑩𐑐𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑦𐑝𐑿𐑛 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑢𐑹𐑥 𐑯𐑪𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑵𐑤 𐑥𐑦𐑤𐑒𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑕; 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑑𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑨𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓, 𐑷𐑤𐑢𐑱𐑟 𐑑 𐑞 𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑝𐑩𐑕𐑑 ·𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑾𐑯𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞 𐑪𐑚𐑡𐑧𐑒𐑑 𐑝 𐑑𐑮𐑧𐑥𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑮𐑧𐑝𐑼𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑯 𐑷. 𐑯𐑹 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑦𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑕𐑗𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑪𐑯 𐑤𐑧𐑡𐑩𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑦 𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑹𐑛 𐑝 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑯𐑴𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑣𐑹𐑕, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑐𐑦𐑮𐑦𐑗𐑵𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑲𐑑𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑗𐑰𐑓𐑤𐑦, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑕𐑴 𐑒𐑤𐑴𐑞𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑛𐑦𐑝𐑲𐑯𐑯𐑩𐑕; 𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑛𐑦𐑝𐑲𐑯𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑗, 𐑞𐑴 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑭𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑻𐑖𐑦𐑐, 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑦𐑯𐑓𐑹𐑕𐑑 𐑩 𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑯𐑱𐑥𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑑𐑧𐑮𐑼.

𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑸 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑢𐑺 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑲𐑑𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑤𐑵𐑟𐑩𐑟 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑩𐑒𐑕𐑧𐑕𐑼𐑦 𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡 𐑜𐑤𐑹𐑦 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑕 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑢𐑲𐑑 ·𐑕𐑑𐑰𐑛 𐑯 ·𐑨𐑤𐑚𐑩𐑑𐑮𐑪𐑕.

𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑨𐑤𐑚𐑰𐑯𐑴 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑕𐑴 𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑽𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑧𐑤𐑟 𐑯 𐑪𐑓𐑩𐑯 𐑖𐑪𐑒𐑕 𐑞 𐑲, 𐑨𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑦𐑟 𐑤𐑴𐑞𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑴𐑯 𐑒𐑦𐑔 𐑯 𐑒𐑦𐑯! 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑲𐑑𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑕 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑩 𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑯𐑱𐑥 𐑣𐑰 𐑚𐑺𐑟. 𐑞 ·𐑨𐑤𐑚𐑰𐑯𐑴 𐑦𐑟 𐑨𐑟 𐑢𐑧𐑤 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑨𐑟 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑥𐑧𐑯—𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑯𐑴 𐑕𐑳𐑚𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑝 𐑛𐑦𐑓𐑹𐑥𐑦𐑑𐑦—𐑯 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑥𐑽 𐑨𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑 𐑝 𐑷𐑤-𐑐𐑼𐑝𐑱𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑲𐑑𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑥𐑱𐑒𐑕 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑥𐑹 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑤𐑦 𐑣𐑦𐑛𐑾𐑕 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑞 𐑳𐑜𐑤𐑾𐑕𐑑 𐑩𐑚𐑹𐑖𐑩𐑯. 𐑢𐑲 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑚𐑰 𐑕𐑴?

𐑯𐑹, 𐑦𐑯 𐑒𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑨𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑕, 𐑛𐑳𐑟 ·𐑯𐑱𐑗𐑼 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑻 𐑤𐑰𐑕𐑑 𐑐𐑨𐑤𐑐𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑞 𐑤𐑧𐑕 𐑥𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑕 𐑱𐑡𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑟, 𐑓𐑱𐑤 𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑤𐑦𐑕𐑑 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑣𐑻 𐑓𐑹𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑒𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑨𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑚𐑿𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑑𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑚𐑩𐑤. 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑕𐑯𐑴𐑦 𐑨𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑, 𐑞 𐑜𐑷𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑩𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑜𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑳𐑞𐑼𐑯 ·𐑕𐑰𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑛𐑦𐑯𐑪𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑞 ·𐑢𐑲𐑑 ·𐑕𐑒𐑢𐑷𐑤. 𐑯𐑹, 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑣𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑒 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟, 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑸𐑑 𐑝 𐑣𐑿𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑥𐑨𐑤𐑦𐑕 𐑴𐑥𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑕𐑴 𐑐𐑴𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑩𐑯 𐑷𐑜𐑟𐑦𐑤𐑽𐑦. 𐑣𐑬 𐑢𐑲𐑤𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑑 𐑣𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑞 𐑦𐑓𐑧𐑒𐑑 𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑐𐑨𐑕𐑦𐑡 𐑦𐑯 ·𐑓𐑮𐑢𐑩𐑕𐑸, 𐑢𐑧𐑯, 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑒𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑯𐑴𐑦 𐑕𐑦𐑥𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑞𐑺 𐑓𐑨𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯, 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑕𐑐𐑼𐑩𐑑 ·𐑢𐑲𐑑 ·𐑣𐑫𐑛𐑟 𐑝 ·𐑣𐑜𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑥𐑻𐑛𐑼 𐑞𐑺 𐑚𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑓 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑥𐑸𐑒𐑩𐑑-𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕!

𐑯𐑹, 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑟, 𐑛𐑳𐑟 𐑞 𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑯, 𐑣𐑼𐑧𐑛𐑦𐑑𐑼𐑦 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑽𐑾𐑯𐑕 𐑝 𐑷𐑤 𐑥𐑨𐑯𐑒𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑓𐑱𐑤 𐑑 𐑚𐑺 𐑢𐑦𐑑𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑵𐑐𐑼𐑯𐑨𐑗𐑼𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑟𐑩𐑥 𐑝 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑣𐑿. 𐑦𐑑 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑢𐑧𐑤 𐑚𐑰 𐑛𐑬𐑑𐑩𐑛, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝𐑦𐑟𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑨𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑩𐑐𐑷𐑤𐑟 𐑞 𐑜𐑱𐑟𐑼, 𐑦𐑟 𐑞 𐑥𐑸𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑐𐑨𐑤𐑼 𐑤𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑺; 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑓 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑰𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑐𐑨𐑤𐑼 𐑢𐑻 𐑨𐑟 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑞 𐑚𐑨𐑡 𐑝 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑯𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛, 𐑨𐑟 𐑝 𐑥𐑹𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑑𐑮𐑧𐑐𐑦𐑛𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑣𐑽. 𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑐𐑨𐑤𐑼 𐑝 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑛, 𐑢𐑰 𐑚𐑪𐑮𐑴 𐑞 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑦𐑝 𐑣𐑿 𐑝 𐑞 𐑖𐑮𐑬𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑢𐑰 𐑮𐑨𐑐 𐑞𐑧𐑥. 𐑯𐑹 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑬𐑼 𐑕𐑵𐑐𐑼𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑛𐑵 𐑢𐑰 𐑓𐑱𐑤 𐑑 𐑔𐑮𐑴 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑕𐑯𐑴𐑦 𐑥𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑬𐑼 𐑓𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑥𐑟; 𐑷𐑤 𐑜𐑴𐑕𐑑𐑕 𐑮𐑲𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑥𐑦𐑤𐑒-𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑓𐑪𐑜—·𐑘𐑱, 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑑𐑧𐑮𐑼𐑟 𐑕𐑰𐑟 𐑳𐑕, 𐑤𐑧𐑑 𐑳𐑕 𐑨𐑛, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑞 𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑑𐑧𐑮𐑼𐑟, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑐𐑼𐑕𐑪𐑯𐑦𐑓𐑲𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑦𐑝𐑨𐑯𐑡𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑕𐑑, 𐑮𐑲𐑛𐑟 𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑨𐑤𐑦𐑛 𐑣𐑹𐑕.

𐑞𐑺𐑓𐑹, 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑥𐑵𐑛𐑟, 𐑕𐑦𐑥𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑲𐑟 𐑢𐑪𐑑𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑜𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑹 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑕 𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑚𐑲 𐑢𐑲𐑑𐑯𐑩𐑕, 𐑯𐑴 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑛𐑦𐑯𐑲 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑲𐑛𐑾𐑤𐑲𐑟𐑛 𐑕𐑦𐑜𐑯𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑦𐑑 𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑟 𐑳𐑐 𐑩 𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑽 𐑨𐑐𐑼𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑴𐑤.

𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞𐑴 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑐𐑶𐑯𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑓𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑑, 𐑣𐑬 𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑹𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑑 𐑩𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑 𐑓 𐑦𐑑? 𐑑 𐑨𐑯𐑩𐑤𐑲𐑟 𐑦𐑑, 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑕𐑰𐑥 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑪𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤. 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑢𐑰, 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑕𐑲𐑑𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑝 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑢𐑺𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑢𐑲𐑑𐑯𐑩𐑕—𐑞𐑴 𐑓 𐑞 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑲𐑞𐑼 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑦 𐑹 𐑦𐑯 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑐𐑸𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑑 𐑝 𐑷𐑤 𐑛𐑦𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑑 𐑩𐑕𐑴𐑖𐑦𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑒𐑨𐑤𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑑 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑸𐑑 𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑷𐑑 𐑓𐑽𐑓𐑩𐑤, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼𐑞𐑩𐑤𐑧𐑕, 𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑑 𐑦𐑜𐑟𐑻𐑑 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑳𐑕 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑕𐑹𐑕𐑼𐑦, 𐑣𐑬𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑥𐑪𐑛𐑦𐑓𐑲𐑛;—𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑢𐑰 𐑞𐑳𐑕 𐑣𐑴𐑐 𐑑 𐑤𐑲𐑑 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑗𐑭𐑯𐑕 𐑒𐑤𐑵 𐑑 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑛𐑳𐑒𐑑 𐑳𐑕 𐑑 𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑯 𐑒𐑷𐑟 𐑢𐑰 𐑕𐑰𐑒?

𐑤𐑧𐑑 𐑳𐑕 𐑑𐑮𐑲. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑥𐑨𐑑𐑼 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑞𐑦𐑕, 𐑕𐑳𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑑𐑦 𐑩𐑐𐑰𐑤𐑟 𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑑𐑦, 𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑 𐑦𐑥𐑨𐑡𐑦𐑯𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑯𐑴 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑓𐑪𐑤𐑴 𐑩𐑯𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑣𐑷𐑤𐑟. 𐑯 𐑞𐑴, 𐑛𐑬𐑑𐑤𐑩𐑕, 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑰𐑕𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑦𐑥𐑨𐑡𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑑𐑦𐑝 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑥𐑱 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑖𐑺𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑥𐑧𐑯, 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑓𐑿 𐑐𐑼𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑕 𐑢𐑻 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑲𐑼𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑑𐑲𐑥, 𐑯 𐑞𐑺𐑓𐑹 𐑥𐑱 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑱𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑯𐑬.

𐑢𐑲 𐑑 𐑞 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑝 𐑳𐑯𐑑𐑿𐑑𐑼𐑛 𐑲𐑛𐑦𐑨𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑦, 𐑣𐑵 𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑤𐑵𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑩𐑒𐑢𐑱𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑽 𐑒𐑨𐑮𐑩𐑒𐑑𐑼 𐑝 𐑞 𐑛𐑱, 𐑛𐑳𐑟 𐑞 𐑚𐑺 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 ·𐑢𐑦𐑑𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑲𐑛 𐑥𐑸𐑖𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑨𐑯𐑕𐑦 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑤𐑪𐑙, 𐑛𐑮𐑽𐑦, 𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑗𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑕𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑕𐑤𐑴-𐑐𐑱𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑐𐑦𐑤𐑜𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑟, 𐑛𐑬𐑯-𐑒𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑯 𐑣𐑫𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑯𐑿-𐑓𐑷𐑤𐑩𐑯 𐑕𐑯𐑴? 𐑹, 𐑑 𐑞 𐑳𐑯𐑮𐑧𐑛, 𐑳𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑓𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 ·𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑑𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑥𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑤 ·𐑩𐑥𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑯 ·𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑑𐑕, 𐑢𐑲 𐑛𐑳𐑟 𐑞 𐑐𐑭𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑩 ·𐑢𐑲𐑑 ·𐑓𐑮𐑲𐑼 𐑹 𐑩 ·𐑢𐑲𐑑 ·𐑯𐑳𐑯, 𐑦𐑝𐑴𐑒 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩𐑯 𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑗𐑿 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑴𐑤?

𐑹 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑞𐑺 𐑩𐑐𐑸𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑑𐑮𐑩𐑛𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑛𐑳𐑯𐑡𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑢𐑹𐑽𐑟 𐑯 𐑒𐑦𐑙𐑟 (𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑦 𐑩𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑 𐑓 𐑦𐑑) 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑱𐑒𐑕 𐑞 ·𐑢𐑲𐑑 ·𐑑𐑬𐑼 𐑝 ·𐑤𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑯 𐑑𐑧𐑤 𐑕𐑴 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑥𐑹 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑪𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑦𐑥𐑨𐑡𐑦𐑯𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑩𐑯 𐑳𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑛 ·𐑩𐑥𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑯, 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑕𐑑𐑹𐑦𐑛 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑒𐑗𐑼𐑟, 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑯𐑱𐑚𐑼𐑟—𐑞 ·𐑚𐑲𐑢𐑼𐑛 ·𐑑𐑬𐑼, 𐑹 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑚𐑤𐑳𐑛𐑦? 𐑯 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑲𐑥𐑼 𐑑𐑬𐑼𐑟, 𐑞 ·𐑢𐑲𐑑 ·𐑥𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑝 ·𐑯𐑿 ·𐑣𐑨𐑥𐑐𐑖𐑼, 𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑕, 𐑦𐑯 𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑽 𐑥𐑵𐑛𐑟, 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑡𐑲𐑜𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑜𐑴𐑕𐑑𐑤𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑞 𐑕𐑴𐑤 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑚𐑺 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑯𐑱𐑥, 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑞 𐑔𐑷𐑑 𐑝 ·𐑝𐑼𐑡𐑦𐑯𐑾'𐑟 ·𐑚𐑤𐑵 ·𐑮𐑦𐑡 𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑫𐑤 𐑝 𐑩 𐑕𐑪𐑓𐑑, 𐑛𐑿𐑦, 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑛𐑮𐑰𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑕? 𐑹 𐑢𐑲, 𐑦𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑝 𐑝 𐑷𐑤 𐑤𐑨𐑑𐑦𐑑𐑿𐑛𐑟 𐑯 𐑤𐑪𐑯𐑜𐑦𐑑𐑿𐑛𐑟, 𐑛𐑳𐑟 𐑞 𐑯𐑱𐑥 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑢𐑲𐑑 ·𐑕𐑰 𐑦𐑜𐑟𐑻𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩 𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑮𐑩𐑤𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑞 𐑓𐑨𐑯𐑕𐑦, 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑘𐑧𐑤𐑴 ·𐑕𐑰 𐑤𐑳𐑤𐑟 𐑳𐑕 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑥𐑹𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑔𐑷𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑤𐑨𐑒𐑼𐑛 𐑥𐑲𐑤𐑛 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼𐑯𐑵𐑯𐑟 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑝𐑟, 𐑓𐑪𐑤𐑴𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑜𐑷𐑛𐑾𐑕𐑑 𐑯 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑕𐑤𐑰𐑐𐑾𐑕𐑑 𐑝 𐑕𐑳𐑯𐑕𐑧𐑑𐑕? 𐑹, 𐑑 𐑗𐑵𐑟 𐑩 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑦 𐑳𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕, 𐑐𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑤𐑦 𐑩𐑛𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑑 𐑞 𐑓𐑨𐑯𐑕𐑦, 𐑢𐑲, 𐑦𐑯 𐑮𐑰𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑓𐑺𐑦 𐑑𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑝 ·𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑩𐑤 ·𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑩𐑐, 𐑛𐑳𐑟 “𐑞 𐑑𐑷𐑤 𐑐𐑱𐑤 𐑥𐑨𐑯” 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑣𐑸𐑑𐑕 𐑓𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑕, 𐑣𐑵𐑟 𐑗𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑐𐑨𐑤𐑼 𐑳𐑯𐑮𐑳𐑕𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑜𐑤𐑲𐑛𐑟 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑴𐑝𐑟—𐑢𐑲 𐑦𐑟 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑓𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑥 𐑥𐑹 𐑑𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑣𐑵𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑚𐑤𐑪𐑒𐑕𐑚𐑼𐑜?

𐑯𐑹 𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑑, 𐑷𐑤𐑑𐑩𐑜𐑧𐑞𐑼, 𐑞 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑧𐑥𐑚𐑮𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑝 𐑣𐑻 𐑒𐑩𐑔𐑰𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑤-𐑑𐑪𐑐𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑻𐑔𐑒𐑢𐑱𐑒𐑕; 𐑯𐑹 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑥𐑐𐑰𐑛𐑴𐑟 𐑝 𐑣𐑻 𐑓𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑕𐑰𐑟; 𐑯𐑹 𐑞 𐑑𐑽𐑤𐑩𐑕𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑛 𐑕𐑒𐑲𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑮𐑱𐑯; 𐑯𐑹 𐑞 𐑕𐑲𐑑 𐑝 𐑣𐑻 𐑢𐑲𐑛 𐑓𐑰𐑤𐑛 𐑝 𐑤𐑰𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑐𐑲𐑼𐑟, 𐑮𐑧𐑯𐑗𐑑 𐑒𐑴𐑐-𐑕𐑑𐑴𐑯𐑟, 𐑯 𐑒𐑮𐑪𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑷𐑤 𐑱𐑛𐑮𐑵𐑐 (𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑘𐑸𐑛𐑟 𐑝 𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑼𐑛 𐑓𐑤𐑰𐑑𐑕); 𐑯 𐑣𐑻 𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑻𐑚𐑩𐑯 𐑨𐑝𐑩𐑯𐑿𐑟 𐑝 𐑣𐑬𐑕-𐑢𐑷𐑤𐑟 𐑤𐑲𐑦𐑙 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑰𐑗 𐑳𐑞𐑼, 𐑨𐑟 𐑩 𐑑𐑪𐑕𐑑 𐑐𐑨𐑒 𐑝 𐑒𐑸𐑛𐑟;—𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑩𐑤𐑴𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑥𐑱𐑒 𐑑𐑽𐑤𐑩𐑕 ·𐑤𐑰𐑥𐑩, 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑩𐑕𐑑, 𐑕𐑨𐑛𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑞𐑬 𐑒𐑨𐑯'𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑰. 𐑓 ·𐑤𐑰𐑥𐑩 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑝𐑱𐑤; 𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑦𐑟 𐑩 𐑣𐑲𐑼 𐑣𐑪𐑮𐑼 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑲𐑑𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑣𐑻 𐑢𐑴. 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑨𐑟 ·𐑐𐑦𐑟𐑸𐑴, 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑲𐑑𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑒𐑰𐑐𐑕 𐑣𐑻 𐑮𐑵𐑦𐑯𐑟 𐑓 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑯𐑿; 𐑩𐑛𐑥𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑞 𐑗𐑽𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑯𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑰𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑱; 𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑟 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑣𐑻 𐑚𐑮𐑴𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑮𐑨𐑥𐑐𐑸𐑑𐑕 𐑞 𐑮𐑦𐑡𐑦𐑛 𐑐𐑨𐑤𐑼 𐑝 𐑩𐑯 𐑨𐑐𐑩𐑐𐑤𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑦 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑓𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑴𐑯 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑹𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟.

𐑲 𐑯𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑, 𐑑 𐑞 𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑨𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑣𐑧𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑯, 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑓𐑦𐑯𐑪𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑪𐑯 𐑝 𐑢𐑲𐑑𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑓𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑲𐑥 𐑱𐑡𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑦𐑜𐑟𐑨𐑡𐑼𐑱𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑑𐑧𐑮𐑼 𐑝 𐑪𐑚𐑡𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑕 𐑳𐑞𐑼𐑢𐑲𐑟 𐑑𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑚𐑩𐑤; 𐑯𐑹 𐑑 𐑞 𐑳𐑯𐑦𐑥𐑨𐑡𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑑𐑦𐑝 𐑥𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑟 𐑞𐑺 𐑷𐑑 𐑝 𐑑𐑧𐑮𐑼 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑩𐑐𐑽𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑣𐑵𐑟 𐑷𐑓𐑩𐑤𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑑 𐑩𐑯𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑥𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑴𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑓𐑦𐑯𐑪𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑪𐑯, 𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑦𐑜𐑟𐑦𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑓𐑹𐑥 𐑨𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑩𐑐𐑮𐑴𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑥𐑿𐑑𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑹 𐑿𐑯𐑦𐑝𐑻𐑕𐑨𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑦. 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑲 𐑥𐑰𐑯 𐑚𐑲 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑑𐑵 𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑑𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑥𐑱 𐑐𐑼𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑕 𐑚𐑰 𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑝𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑤𐑵𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑓𐑪𐑤𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑜𐑟𐑭𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑤𐑟.

𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑: 𐑞 𐑥𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑯𐑼, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑛𐑮𐑷𐑦𐑙 𐑯𐑲 𐑞 𐑒𐑴𐑕𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑓𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑯 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟, 𐑦𐑓 𐑚𐑲 𐑯𐑲𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑽 𐑞 𐑮𐑹 𐑝 𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑒𐑼𐑟, 𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑑𐑕 𐑑 𐑝𐑦𐑡𐑦𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑕, 𐑯 𐑓𐑰𐑤𐑟 𐑡𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑳𐑓 𐑝 𐑑𐑮𐑧𐑐𐑦𐑛𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑑 𐑖𐑸𐑐𐑩𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑨𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑑𐑦𐑟; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑲𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑤𐑼 𐑕𐑻𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟, 𐑤𐑧𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑚𐑰 𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑥𐑩𐑒 𐑑 𐑝𐑿 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑩 𐑥𐑦𐑛𐑯𐑲𐑑 𐑕𐑰 𐑝 𐑥𐑦𐑤𐑒𐑦 𐑢𐑲𐑑𐑯𐑩𐑕—𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑓 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑻𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑖𐑴𐑤𐑟 𐑝 𐑒𐑴𐑥𐑛 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑚𐑺𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑕𐑢𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑣𐑰 𐑓𐑰𐑤𐑟 𐑩 𐑕𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑑, 𐑕𐑵𐑐𐑼𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑕 𐑛𐑮𐑧𐑛; 𐑞 𐑖𐑮𐑬𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑓𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑥 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼𐑟 𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑨𐑟 𐑩 𐑮𐑾𐑤 𐑜𐑴𐑕𐑑; 𐑦𐑯 𐑝𐑱𐑯 𐑞 𐑤𐑧𐑛 𐑩𐑖𐑫𐑼𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑣𐑰 𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑪𐑓 𐑕𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙𐑟; 𐑣𐑸𐑑 𐑯 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑥 𐑞𐑱 𐑚𐑴𐑔 𐑜𐑴 𐑛𐑬𐑯; 𐑣𐑰 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑕 𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑚𐑤𐑵 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼 𐑦𐑟 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯. 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑢𐑺 𐑦𐑟 𐑞 𐑥𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑯𐑼 𐑣𐑵 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑑𐑧𐑤 𐑞𐑰, “𐑕𐑻, 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑴 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑞 𐑓𐑽 𐑝 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑯 𐑮𐑪𐑒𐑕, 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑓𐑽 𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑛𐑾𐑕 𐑢𐑲𐑑𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑴 𐑕𐑑𐑻𐑛 𐑥𐑰?”

𐑕𐑧𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑛: 𐑑 𐑞 𐑯𐑱𐑑𐑦𐑝 ·𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑾𐑯 𐑝 ·𐑐𐑼𐑵, 𐑞 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑿𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑲𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑯𐑴-𐑣𐑬𐑛𐑩𐑛 ·𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑰𐑟 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑝𐑱𐑟 𐑯𐑷𐑑 𐑝 𐑛𐑮𐑧𐑛, 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑧𐑐𐑑, 𐑐𐑼𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑕, 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑥𐑽 𐑓𐑨𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑞 𐑦𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑛𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑤𐑩𐑑𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑝𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑨𐑤𐑑𐑦𐑑𐑿𐑛𐑟, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑯𐑨𐑗𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑰𐑑 𐑝 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑩 𐑓𐑽𐑓𐑩𐑤𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑚𐑰 𐑑 𐑤𐑵𐑟 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑦𐑯𐑣𐑿𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑕𐑪𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑿𐑛𐑟. 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑚𐑨𐑒𐑢𐑫𐑛𐑟𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑢𐑧𐑕𐑑, 𐑣𐑵 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑨𐑮𐑩𐑑𐑦𐑝 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑓𐑼𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑝𐑿𐑟 𐑩𐑯 𐑳𐑯𐑚𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑐𐑮𐑺𐑦 𐑖𐑰𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑛𐑮𐑦𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑕𐑯𐑴, 𐑯𐑴 𐑖𐑨𐑛𐑴 𐑝 𐑑𐑮𐑰 𐑹 𐑑𐑢𐑦𐑜 𐑑 𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑒 𐑞 𐑓𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑑 𐑑𐑮𐑭𐑯𐑕 𐑝 𐑢𐑲𐑑𐑯𐑩𐑕. 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑴 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑼, 𐑚𐑦𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑕𐑰𐑯𐑼𐑦 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑸𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑕𐑰𐑟; 𐑢𐑺 𐑨𐑑 𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟, 𐑚𐑲 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑦𐑯𐑓𐑻𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑒 𐑝 𐑤𐑧𐑡𐑼𐑛𐑩𐑥𐑱𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑐𐑬𐑼𐑟 𐑝 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑕𐑑 𐑯 𐑺, 𐑣𐑰, 𐑖𐑦𐑝𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑯 𐑣𐑭𐑓 𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑑, 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑛 𐑝 𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑚𐑴𐑟 𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑴𐑐 𐑯 𐑕𐑪𐑤𐑦𐑕 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑦𐑟𐑼𐑦, 𐑝𐑿𐑟 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑟 𐑩 𐑚𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑗𐑻𐑗𐑘𐑸𐑛 𐑜𐑮𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑤𐑰𐑯 𐑲𐑕 𐑥𐑪𐑯𐑿𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑯 𐑕𐑐𐑤𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑛 𐑒𐑮𐑪𐑕𐑩𐑟.

𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞𐑬 𐑕𐑱𐑩𐑕𐑑, 𐑥𐑦𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑕 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑲𐑑-𐑤𐑧𐑛 𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑢𐑲𐑑𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑩 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑓𐑤𐑨𐑜 𐑣𐑳𐑙 𐑬𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑩 𐑒𐑮𐑱𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑕𐑴𐑤; 𐑞𐑬 𐑕𐑼𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑑 𐑩 𐑣𐑲𐑐𐑴, ·𐑦𐑖𐑥𐑱𐑩𐑤.

𐑑𐑧𐑤 𐑥𐑰, 𐑢𐑲 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑪𐑙 𐑘𐑳𐑙 𐑒𐑴𐑤𐑑, 𐑓𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑐𐑰𐑕𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑝𐑨𐑤𐑦 𐑝 ·𐑝𐑼𐑥𐑪𐑯𐑑, 𐑓𐑸 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑵𐑝𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑷𐑤 𐑚𐑰𐑕𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑐𐑮𐑱—𐑢𐑲 𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑯𐑾𐑕𐑑 𐑛𐑱, 𐑦𐑓 𐑿 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑖𐑱𐑒 𐑩 𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑖 𐑚𐑳𐑓𐑩𐑤𐑴 𐑮𐑴𐑚 𐑚𐑦𐑣𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑕𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑕𐑰 𐑦𐑑, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑥𐑧𐑤𐑟 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑢𐑲𐑤𐑛 𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑥𐑩𐑤 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑒𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑕—𐑢𐑲 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑑, 𐑕𐑯𐑹𐑑, 𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑚𐑻𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑲𐑟 𐑐𐑷 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑯𐑟𐑦𐑟 𐑝 𐑩𐑓𐑮𐑲𐑑? 𐑞𐑺 𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑴 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑧𐑥𐑚𐑮𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑝 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑜𐑹𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑝 𐑢𐑲𐑤𐑛 𐑒𐑮𐑰𐑗𐑼𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑯 𐑯𐑹𐑞𐑼𐑯 𐑣𐑴𐑥, 𐑕𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑒𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑥𐑧𐑤𐑟 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑷𐑤 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑧𐑯𐑦𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑕𐑴𐑖𐑦𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑽𐑾𐑯𐑕 𐑝 𐑓𐑹𐑥𐑼 𐑐𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑤𐑟; 𐑓 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑯𐑴𐑟 𐑣𐑰, 𐑞𐑦𐑕 ·𐑯𐑿 ·𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑒𐑴𐑤𐑑, 𐑝 𐑞 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑒 𐑚𐑲𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑 ·𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑜𐑪𐑯?

𐑯𐑴: 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑣𐑽 𐑞𐑬 𐑚𐑦𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑛𐑳𐑥 𐑚𐑮𐑵𐑑, 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑯𐑪𐑤𐑦𐑡 𐑝 𐑞 𐑛𐑰𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑟𐑩𐑥 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛. 𐑞𐑴 𐑔𐑬𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑝 𐑥𐑲𐑤𐑟 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 ·𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑜𐑪𐑯, 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑥𐑧𐑤𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑡 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑒, 𐑞 𐑮𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙, 𐑜𐑹𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑲𐑕𐑩𐑯 𐑣𐑻𐑛𐑟 𐑸 𐑨𐑟 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑑 𐑞 𐑛𐑦𐑟𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑲𐑤𐑛 𐑓𐑴𐑤 𐑝 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑺𐑦𐑟, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑞𐑱 𐑥𐑱 𐑚𐑰 𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑛𐑳𐑕𐑑.

𐑞𐑳𐑕, 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑞 𐑥𐑳𐑓𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑮𐑴𐑤𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑝 𐑩 𐑥𐑦𐑤𐑒𐑦 𐑕𐑰; 𐑞 𐑚𐑤𐑰𐑒 𐑮𐑳𐑕𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑓𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑵𐑯𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑕𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑥𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑟; 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑤𐑩𐑑 𐑖𐑦𐑓𐑑𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑮𐑴𐑛 𐑕𐑯𐑴𐑟 𐑝 𐑐𐑮𐑺𐑦𐑟; 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑰𐑟, 𐑑 ·𐑦𐑖𐑥𐑱𐑩𐑤, 𐑸 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑖𐑱𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑚𐑳𐑓𐑩𐑤𐑴 𐑮𐑴𐑚 𐑑 𐑞 𐑓𐑮𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑒𐑴𐑤𐑑!

𐑞𐑴 𐑯𐑲𐑞𐑼 𐑯𐑴𐑟 𐑢𐑺 𐑤𐑲 𐑞 𐑯𐑱𐑥𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑝 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑞 𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑕𐑲𐑯 𐑜𐑦𐑝𐑟 𐑓𐑹𐑔 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑣𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑕; 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑥𐑰, 𐑨𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑒𐑴𐑤𐑑, 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑢𐑺 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑜𐑟𐑦𐑕𐑑. 𐑞𐑴 𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑝 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑨𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑕 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑝𐑦𐑟𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑟 𐑓𐑹𐑥𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑤𐑳𐑝, 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑦𐑟𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑓𐑽𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑓𐑹𐑥𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑲𐑑.

𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑢𐑰 𐑕𐑪𐑤𐑝𐑛 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑲𐑑𐑯𐑩𐑕, 𐑯 𐑤𐑻𐑯𐑛 𐑢𐑲 𐑦𐑑 𐑩𐑐𐑰𐑤𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑐𐑬𐑼 𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑴𐑤; 𐑯 𐑥𐑹 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡 𐑯 𐑓𐑸 𐑥𐑹 𐑐𐑹𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑕—𐑢𐑲, 𐑨𐑟 𐑢𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑕𐑰𐑯, 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑕 𐑞 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑥𐑰𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑦𐑥𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑕𐑐𐑦𐑮𐑦𐑗𐑵𐑩𐑤 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑟, 𐑯𐑱, 𐑞 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑝𐑱𐑤 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑗𐑩𐑯'𐑟 ·𐑛𐑰𐑦𐑑𐑦; 𐑯 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑚𐑰 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟, 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑓𐑲𐑦𐑙 𐑱𐑡𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑞 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑩𐑐𐑷𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑥𐑨𐑯𐑒𐑲𐑯𐑛.

𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑧𐑓𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑦𐑑 𐑖𐑨𐑛𐑴𐑟 𐑓𐑹𐑔 𐑞 𐑣𐑸𐑑𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑝𐑶𐑛𐑟 𐑯 𐑦𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑿𐑯𐑦𐑝𐑻𐑕, 𐑯 𐑞𐑳𐑕 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑚𐑟 𐑳𐑕 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑚𐑦𐑣𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑔𐑷𐑑 𐑝 𐑩𐑯𐑲𐑩𐑤𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑚𐑦𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑛𐑧𐑐𐑔𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑥𐑦𐑤𐑒𐑦 𐑢𐑱? 𐑹 𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑑, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑢𐑲𐑑𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑴 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑩 𐑒𐑳𐑤𐑼 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑝𐑦𐑟𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑨𐑚𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑝 𐑒𐑳𐑤𐑼; 𐑯 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑞 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑒𐑮𐑰𐑑 𐑝 𐑷𐑤 𐑒𐑳𐑤𐑼𐑟; 𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑓 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑮𐑰𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩 𐑛𐑳𐑥 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑯𐑩𐑕, 𐑓𐑫𐑤 𐑝 𐑥𐑰𐑯𐑦𐑙, 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑢𐑲𐑛 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑕𐑒𐑱𐑐 𐑝 𐑕𐑯𐑴𐑟—𐑩 𐑒𐑳𐑤𐑼𐑤𐑩𐑕, 𐑷𐑤-𐑒𐑳𐑤𐑼 𐑝 𐑱𐑔𐑦𐑦𐑟𐑩𐑥 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑢𐑰 𐑖𐑮𐑦𐑙𐑒? 𐑯 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑢𐑰 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑼 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑔𐑽𐑦 𐑝 𐑞 𐑯𐑨𐑗𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑓𐑦𐑤𐑪𐑕𐑩𐑓𐑼𐑟, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑻𐑔𐑤𐑦 𐑣𐑿𐑟—𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑹 𐑤𐑳𐑝𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑥𐑚𐑤𐑱𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑙—𐑞 𐑕𐑢𐑰𐑑 𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑡𐑩𐑟 𐑝 𐑕𐑳𐑯𐑕𐑧𐑑 𐑕𐑒𐑲𐑟 𐑯 𐑢𐑫𐑛𐑟; 𐑘𐑱, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑜𐑦𐑤𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑝𐑧𐑤𐑝𐑩𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑚𐑳𐑑𐑼𐑓𐑤𐑲𐑟, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑳𐑑𐑼𐑓𐑤𐑲 𐑗𐑰𐑒𐑕 𐑝 𐑘𐑳𐑙 𐑜𐑻𐑤𐑟; 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑸 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑚𐑑𐑲𐑤 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑰𐑑𐑕, 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑨𐑒𐑗𐑵𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑯𐑣𐑧𐑮𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑚𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑤𐑱𐑛 𐑪𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑; 𐑕𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑛𐑰𐑦𐑓𐑲𐑛 ·𐑯𐑱𐑗𐑼 𐑨𐑚𐑕𐑩𐑤𐑵𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑱𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑞 𐑣𐑸𐑤𐑩𐑑, 𐑣𐑵𐑟 𐑩𐑤𐑫𐑼𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑒𐑳𐑝𐑼 𐑯𐑳𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞 𐑗𐑸𐑯𐑩𐑤-𐑣𐑬𐑕 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑦𐑯; 𐑯 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑢𐑰 𐑐𐑮𐑴𐑕𐑰𐑛 𐑓𐑻𐑞𐑼, 𐑯 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑼 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑒𐑪𐑟𐑥𐑧𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑛𐑿𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑣𐑻 𐑣𐑿𐑟, 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑐𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑤𐑲𐑑, 𐑓 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑱𐑯𐑟 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑹 𐑒𐑳𐑤𐑼𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑦𐑑𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓, 𐑯 𐑦𐑓 𐑪𐑐𐑼𐑱𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑 𐑥𐑰𐑛𐑾𐑥 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑥𐑨𐑑𐑼, 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑑𐑳𐑗 𐑷𐑤 𐑪𐑚𐑡𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑕, 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑑𐑿𐑤𐑦𐑐𐑕 𐑯 𐑮𐑴𐑟𐑩𐑟, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑴𐑯 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑙𐑒 𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑡—𐑐𐑪𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑦𐑕, 𐑞 𐑐𐑷𐑤𐑟𐑦𐑛 𐑿𐑯𐑦𐑝𐑻𐑕 𐑤𐑲𐑟 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑳𐑕 𐑩 𐑤𐑧𐑐𐑼; 𐑯 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑢𐑦𐑤𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑼𐑟 𐑦𐑯 ·𐑤𐑨𐑐𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛, 𐑣𐑵 𐑮𐑦𐑓𐑿𐑟 𐑑 𐑢𐑺 𐑒𐑳𐑤𐑼𐑛 𐑯 𐑒𐑳𐑤𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑜𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑲𐑟, 𐑕𐑴 𐑞 𐑮𐑧𐑗𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑓𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑤 𐑜𐑱𐑟𐑩𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑚𐑤𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑥𐑪𐑯𐑿𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑖𐑮𐑬𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑮𐑨𐑐𐑕 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑 𐑼𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥. 𐑯 𐑝 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑞 ·𐑨𐑤𐑚𐑰𐑯𐑴 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞 𐑕𐑦𐑥𐑚𐑩𐑤. 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑘𐑰 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑓𐑲𐑼𐑦 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑑?

·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 43. 𐑣𐑸𐑒!

“·𐑣𐑦𐑕𐑑! 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑿 𐑣𐑽 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑯𐑶𐑟, ·𐑒𐑱𐑚𐑩𐑒𐑴?”

𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞 𐑥𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑤-𐑢𐑪𐑗: 𐑩 𐑓𐑺 𐑥𐑵𐑯𐑤𐑲𐑑; 𐑞 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑢𐑻 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑒𐑹𐑛𐑩𐑯, 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑖-𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼 𐑚𐑳𐑑𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑕𐑑, 𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑒𐑳𐑑𐑩𐑤-𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑯𐑽 𐑞 𐑑𐑨𐑓𐑮𐑱𐑤. 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑥𐑨𐑯𐑼, 𐑞𐑱 𐑐𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑞 𐑚𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑑𐑕 𐑑 𐑓𐑦𐑤 𐑞 𐑕𐑒𐑳𐑑𐑩𐑤-𐑚𐑳𐑑. 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙, 𐑓 𐑞 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑐𐑸𐑑, 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑣𐑨𐑤𐑴𐑛 𐑐𐑮𐑰𐑕𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑒𐑢𐑹𐑑𐑼-𐑛𐑧𐑒, 𐑞𐑱 𐑢𐑻 𐑒𐑺𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑑 𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑒 𐑹 𐑮𐑳𐑕𐑩𐑤 𐑞𐑺 𐑓𐑰𐑑. 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛, 𐑞 𐑚𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑑𐑕 𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑛𐑰𐑐𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑕, 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑮𐑴𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑩𐑒𐑱𐑠𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑓𐑤𐑨𐑐 𐑝 𐑩 𐑕𐑱𐑤, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑛𐑦 𐑣𐑳𐑥 𐑝 𐑞 𐑳𐑯𐑕𐑰𐑕𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑩𐑛𐑝𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑒𐑰𐑤.

𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑥𐑦𐑛𐑕𐑑 𐑝 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑴𐑟, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 ·𐑸𐑒𐑦, 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑒𐑹𐑛𐑩𐑯, 𐑣𐑵𐑟 𐑐𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑽 𐑞 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼-𐑣𐑨𐑗𐑩𐑟, 𐑢𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑼𐑛 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑱𐑚𐑼, 𐑩 ·𐑗𐑴𐑤𐑴, 𐑞 𐑢𐑻𐑛𐑟 𐑩𐑚𐑳𐑝.

“𐑣𐑦𐑕𐑑! 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑿 𐑣𐑽 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑯𐑶𐑟, ·𐑒𐑱𐑚𐑩𐑒𐑴?”

“𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑞 𐑚𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑑, 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑘𐑰, ·𐑸𐑒𐑦? 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑯𐑶𐑟 𐑛'𐑘𐑰 𐑥𐑰𐑯?”

“𐑞𐑺 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯—𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑞 𐑣𐑨𐑗𐑩𐑟—𐑛𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑿 𐑣𐑽 𐑦𐑑—𐑩 𐑒𐑪𐑓—𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑒𐑪𐑓.”

“𐑒𐑪𐑓 𐑚𐑰 𐑛𐑨𐑥𐑛! 𐑐𐑭𐑕 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑻𐑯 𐑚𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑑.”

“𐑞𐑺 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯—𐑞𐑺 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟!—𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑑𐑵 𐑹 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑕𐑤𐑰𐑐𐑼𐑟 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑴𐑝𐑼, 𐑯𐑬!”

“𐑒𐑸𐑭𐑥𐑚𐑩! 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑛𐑳𐑯, 𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑥𐑱𐑑, 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑘𐑰? 𐑦𐑑'𐑕 𐑞 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑕𐑴𐑒𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑘𐑰 𐑰𐑑 𐑓 𐑕𐑳𐑐𐑼 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑝 𐑘𐑰—𐑯𐑳𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑧𐑤𐑕. 𐑤𐑫𐑒 𐑑 𐑞 𐑚𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑑!”

“𐑕𐑱 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑘𐑰 𐑢𐑦𐑤, 𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑥𐑱𐑑; 𐑲'𐑝 𐑖𐑸𐑐 𐑽𐑟.”

“𐑲, 𐑿 𐑸 𐑞 𐑗𐑨𐑐, 𐑱𐑯𐑑 𐑘𐑰, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑻𐑛 𐑞 𐑣𐑳𐑥 𐑝 𐑞 𐑴𐑤𐑛 ·𐑒𐑢𐑱𐑒𐑼𐑧𐑕'𐑩𐑟 𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑙-𐑯𐑰𐑛𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑓𐑦𐑓𐑑𐑦 𐑥𐑲𐑤𐑟 𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑰 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 ·𐑯𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑑; 𐑿'𐑼 𐑞 𐑗𐑨𐑐.”

“𐑜𐑮𐑦𐑯 𐑩𐑢𐑱; 𐑢𐑰'𐑤 𐑕𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑟 𐑳𐑐. 𐑣𐑸𐑒 𐑘𐑰, ·𐑒𐑱𐑚𐑩𐑒𐑴, 𐑞𐑺 𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼-𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑕𐑰𐑯 𐑪𐑯 𐑛𐑧𐑒; 𐑯 𐑲 𐑕𐑩𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑 𐑬𐑼 𐑴𐑤𐑛 ·𐑥𐑴𐑜𐑩𐑤 𐑯𐑴𐑟 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑦𐑑 𐑑𐑵. 𐑲 𐑣𐑻𐑛 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚 𐑑𐑧𐑤 ·𐑓𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑒, 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑥𐑹𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑪𐑗, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑹𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛.”

“·𐑑𐑦𐑖! 𐑞 𐑚𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑑!”

·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 44. 𐑞 ·𐑗𐑸𐑑.

𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑿 𐑓𐑪𐑤𐑴𐑛 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑨𐑚𐑦𐑯 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑞 𐑕𐑒𐑢𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑑𐑫𐑒 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑯𐑲𐑑 𐑕𐑩𐑒𐑕𐑰𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑲𐑤𐑛 𐑮𐑨𐑑𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑒𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑻𐑐𐑩𐑕 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑮𐑵, 𐑿 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑕𐑰𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑜𐑴 𐑑 𐑩 𐑤𐑪𐑒𐑼 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑥, 𐑯 𐑚𐑮𐑦𐑙𐑦𐑙 𐑬𐑑 𐑩 𐑤𐑸𐑡 𐑮𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑮𐑴𐑤 𐑝 𐑘𐑧𐑤𐑴𐑦𐑖 𐑕𐑰 𐑗𐑸𐑑𐑕, 𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑛 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑵𐑛-𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑑𐑱𐑚𐑩𐑤. 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑕𐑰𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑦𐑑, 𐑿 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑕𐑰𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑛𐑦 𐑞 𐑝𐑺𐑾𐑕 𐑤𐑲𐑯𐑟 𐑯 𐑖𐑱𐑛𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑞𐑺 𐑥𐑧𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑲; 𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑕𐑤𐑴 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑛𐑦 𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑤 𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑕 𐑩𐑛𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑒𐑹𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑕𐑐𐑱𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑢𐑻 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑙𐑒. 𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑟, 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑮𐑦𐑓𐑻 𐑑 𐑐𐑲𐑤𐑟 𐑝 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑤𐑪𐑜-𐑚𐑫𐑒𐑕 𐑚𐑦𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑢𐑺𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑻 𐑕𐑧𐑑 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑰𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑯 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑗, 𐑪𐑯 𐑝𐑺𐑾𐑕 𐑓𐑹𐑥𐑼 𐑝𐑶𐑦𐑡𐑩𐑟 𐑝 𐑝𐑺𐑾𐑕 𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑕, 𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑗𐑼𐑛 𐑹 𐑕𐑰𐑯.

𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑞𐑳𐑕 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑶𐑛, 𐑞 𐑣𐑧𐑝𐑦 𐑐𐑿𐑑𐑼 𐑤𐑨𐑥𐑐 𐑕𐑩𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑗𐑱𐑯𐑟 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑧𐑛, 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑿𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑪𐑒𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑥𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐, 𐑯 𐑓 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑖𐑦𐑓𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑜𐑤𐑰𐑥𐑟 𐑯 𐑖𐑨𐑛𐑴𐑟 𐑝 𐑤𐑲𐑯𐑟 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑮𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑚𐑮𐑬, 𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑦𐑑 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑥𐑸𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑬𐑑 𐑤𐑲𐑯𐑟 𐑯 𐑒𐑹𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑮𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑗𐑸𐑑𐑕, 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑦𐑟𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑤 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑷𐑤𐑕𐑴 𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑤𐑲𐑯𐑟 𐑯 𐑒𐑹𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑛𐑰𐑐𐑤𐑦 𐑥𐑸𐑒𐑑 𐑗𐑸𐑑 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑛.

𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑯𐑲𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑐𐑼𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑼 𐑞𐑨𐑑, 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑪𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑿𐑛 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑨𐑚𐑦𐑯, ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑞𐑳𐑕 𐑐𐑪𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑛 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑗𐑸𐑑𐑕. 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑯𐑲𐑑 𐑞𐑱 𐑢𐑻 𐑚𐑮𐑷𐑑 𐑬𐑑; 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑯𐑲𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑤 𐑥𐑸𐑒𐑕 𐑢𐑻 𐑦𐑓𐑱𐑕𐑑, 𐑯 𐑳𐑞𐑼𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑕𐑳𐑚𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑑𐑿𐑑𐑩𐑛. 𐑓 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑗𐑸𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑷𐑤 𐑓𐑹 𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑣𐑦𐑥, ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑔𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑥𐑱𐑟 𐑝 𐑒𐑳𐑮𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑯 𐑧𐑛𐑦𐑟, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑝𐑿 𐑑 𐑞 𐑥𐑹 𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑩𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑦𐑖𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑪𐑯𐑩𐑥𐑱𐑯𐑦𐑨𐑒 𐑔𐑷𐑑 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑴𐑤.

𐑯𐑬, 𐑑 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑓𐑫𐑤𐑦 𐑩𐑒𐑢𐑱𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑤𐑩𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑔𐑩𐑯𐑟, 𐑦𐑑 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑥 𐑩𐑯 𐑩𐑚𐑕𐑻𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑣𐑴𐑐𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑑𐑭𐑕𐑒 𐑞𐑳𐑕 𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑒 𐑬𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑕𐑪𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑼𐑦 𐑒𐑮𐑰𐑗𐑼 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑳𐑯𐑣𐑵𐑐𐑑 𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑐𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑩𐑑. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑴 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑥 𐑑 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚, 𐑣𐑵 𐑯𐑿 𐑞 𐑕𐑧𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑷𐑤 𐑑𐑲𐑛𐑟 𐑯 𐑒𐑳𐑮𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕; 𐑯 𐑞𐑺𐑚𐑲 𐑒𐑨𐑤𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑱𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑛𐑮𐑦𐑓𐑑𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 𐑢𐑱𐑤'𐑟 𐑓𐑵𐑛; 𐑯, 𐑷𐑤𐑕𐑴, 𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑥𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑞 𐑮𐑧𐑜𐑿𐑤𐑼, 𐑨𐑕𐑼𐑑𐑱𐑯𐑛 𐑕𐑰𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑓 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑦𐑯 𐑐𐑼𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑼 𐑤𐑨𐑑𐑦𐑑𐑿𐑛𐑟; 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑼𐑲𐑝 𐑨𐑑 𐑮𐑰𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑼𐑥𐑲𐑟𐑩𐑟, 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑩𐑐𐑮𐑴𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑟, 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑤𐑾𐑕𐑑 𐑛𐑱 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑹 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑜𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑻𐑗 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑮𐑱.

𐑕𐑴 𐑩𐑖𐑫𐑼𐑛, 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑰𐑛, 𐑦𐑟 𐑞 𐑓𐑨𐑒𐑑 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑐𐑽𐑦𐑪𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 𐑢𐑱𐑤'𐑟 𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑹𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑜𐑦𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼𐑟, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑟 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑰𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑, 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑣𐑰 𐑚𐑰 𐑒𐑤𐑴𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑩𐑚𐑟𐑻𐑝𐑛 𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑔𐑮𐑵𐑬𐑑 𐑞 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛; 𐑢𐑻 𐑞 𐑤𐑪𐑜𐑟 𐑓 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝𐑶𐑦𐑡 𐑝 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑲𐑼 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑓𐑤𐑰𐑑 𐑒𐑺𐑓𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛, 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑞 𐑥𐑲𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑚𐑰 𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑑 𐑒𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑪𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑺𐑾𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑑 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑣𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑙-𐑖𐑴𐑤𐑟 𐑹 𐑞 𐑓𐑤𐑲𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑕𐑢𐑪𐑤𐑴𐑟. 𐑪𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑣𐑦𐑯𐑑, 𐑩𐑑𐑧𐑥𐑐𐑑𐑕 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑑 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑒𐑑 𐑦𐑤𐑨𐑚𐑼𐑩𐑑 𐑥𐑲𐑜𐑮𐑩𐑑𐑼𐑦 𐑗𐑸𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 𐑢𐑱𐑤.*

*𐑕𐑦𐑯𐑕 𐑞 𐑩𐑚𐑳𐑝 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑯, 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑑𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑦𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑹𐑯 𐑬𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑩𐑯 𐑩𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑻𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑼, 𐑦𐑖𐑿𐑛 𐑚𐑲 ·𐑤𐑧𐑓𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑩𐑯𐑑 ·𐑥𐑹𐑦, 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑯𐑨𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑤 ·𐑩𐑚𐑟𐑻𐑝𐑩𐑑𐑼𐑦, ·𐑢𐑪𐑖𐑦𐑙𐑑𐑩𐑯, 𐑱𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑤 16𐑔, 1851. 𐑚𐑲 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑻𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑼, 𐑦𐑑 𐑩𐑐𐑽𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑲𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩 𐑗𐑸𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑒𐑹𐑕 𐑝 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑰𐑖𐑩𐑯; 𐑯 𐑐𐑹𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑦𐑑 𐑸 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑻𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑼. “𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑗𐑸𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑝𐑲𐑛𐑟 𐑞 𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑓𐑲𐑝 𐑛𐑦𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑟 𐑝 𐑤𐑨𐑑𐑦𐑑𐑿𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑓𐑲𐑝 𐑛𐑦𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑟 𐑝 𐑤𐑪𐑯𐑜𐑦𐑑𐑿𐑛; 𐑐𐑻𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑼𐑤𐑦 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑰𐑗 𐑝 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑑𐑕 𐑸 𐑑𐑢𐑧𐑤𐑝 𐑒𐑪𐑤𐑩𐑥𐑟 𐑓 𐑞 𐑑𐑢𐑧𐑤𐑝 𐑥𐑳𐑯𐑔𐑕; 𐑯 𐑣𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑰𐑗 𐑝 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑑𐑕 𐑸 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑤𐑲𐑯𐑟; 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑑 𐑖𐑴 𐑞 𐑯𐑳𐑥𐑚𐑼 𐑝 𐑛𐑱𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑰𐑗 𐑥𐑳𐑯𐑔 𐑦𐑯 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑑, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑑𐑵 𐑳𐑞𐑼𐑟 𐑑 𐑖𐑴 𐑞 𐑯𐑳𐑥𐑚𐑼 𐑝 𐑛𐑱𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟, 𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 𐑹 𐑮𐑲𐑑, 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑕𐑰𐑯.”

𐑚𐑦𐑕𐑲𐑛𐑟, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑥𐑱𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑐𐑨𐑕𐑦𐑡 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑓𐑰𐑛𐑦𐑙-𐑜𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑑 𐑩𐑯𐑳𐑞𐑼, 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟, 𐑜𐑲𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑦𐑯𐑓𐑨𐑤𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑑—𐑕𐑱, 𐑮𐑭𐑞𐑼, 𐑕𐑰𐑒𐑮𐑩𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑡𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 ·𐑛𐑱𐑦𐑑𐑦—𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑢𐑦𐑥 𐑦𐑯 𐑝𐑱𐑯𐑟, 𐑨𐑟 𐑞𐑱 𐑸 𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑛; 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑿𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑺 𐑢𐑱 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑩 𐑜𐑦𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯-𐑤𐑲𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑰𐑝𐑦𐑱𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑜𐑟𐑨𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑑𐑿𐑛, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑯𐑴 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑛 𐑣𐑻 𐑒𐑹𐑕, 𐑚𐑲 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑗𐑸𐑑, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑑𐑲𐑞 𐑝 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑥𐑸𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑦𐑠𐑩𐑯. 𐑞𐑴, 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑒𐑱𐑕𐑩𐑟, 𐑞 𐑛𐑦𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑚𐑲 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑚𐑰 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑩 𐑕𐑼𐑝𐑱𐑼'𐑟 𐑐𐑨𐑮𐑩𐑤𐑧𐑤, 𐑯 𐑞𐑴 𐑞 𐑤𐑲𐑯 𐑝 𐑩𐑛𐑝𐑭𐑯𐑕 𐑚𐑰 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑓𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑑 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑴𐑯 𐑳𐑯𐑩𐑝𐑶𐑛𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤, 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑒, 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑞 𐑸𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑮𐑼𐑦 𐑝𐑱𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑑 𐑕𐑢𐑦𐑥, 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑥𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑓𐑿 𐑥𐑲𐑤𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑛𐑔 (𐑥𐑹 𐑹 𐑤𐑧𐑕, 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑝𐑱𐑯 𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑿𐑥𐑛 𐑑 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑹 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑒𐑑); 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑰𐑛𐑟 𐑞 𐑝𐑦𐑟𐑿𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑢𐑰𐑐 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤-𐑖𐑦𐑐'𐑕 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑-𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑟, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑕𐑻𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑜𐑤𐑲𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑥𐑨𐑡𐑦𐑒 𐑟𐑴𐑯. 𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑦𐑟, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑐𐑼𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑼 𐑕𐑰𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑚𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑔 𐑯 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑐𐑭𐑔, 𐑥𐑲𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑥𐑱 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑓𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑚𐑰 𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑑 𐑓.

𐑯 𐑣𐑧𐑯𐑕 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑖𐑦𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟, 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑢𐑧𐑤 𐑯𐑴𐑯 𐑕𐑧𐑐𐑼𐑩𐑑 𐑓𐑰𐑛𐑦𐑙-𐑜𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑟, 𐑒𐑫𐑛 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑣𐑴𐑐 𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑼 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑮𐑱; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑒𐑮𐑪𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑢𐑲𐑛𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑨𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑝 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑢𐑰𐑯 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑜𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑫𐑛, 𐑚𐑲 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑸𐑑, 𐑕𐑴 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕 𐑯 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑱, 𐑨𐑟 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑦 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑 𐑝 𐑩 𐑥𐑰𐑑𐑦𐑙.

𐑞𐑺 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩 𐑕𐑻𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑕 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑨𐑑 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑲𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑨𐑙𐑜𐑩𐑤 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑽𐑾𐑕 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑥𐑦𐑔𐑪𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑒𐑰𐑥. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑴 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑮𐑦𐑨𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑦, 𐑐𐑼𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑕. 𐑞𐑴 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑦𐑜𐑺𐑾𐑕 𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑞𐑺 𐑮𐑧𐑜𐑿𐑤𐑼 𐑕𐑰𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑓 𐑐𐑼𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑼 𐑜𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑟, 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑿 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑒𐑤𐑵𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑣𐑻𐑛𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑣𐑷𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩 𐑤𐑨𐑑𐑦𐑑𐑿𐑛 𐑹 𐑤𐑪𐑯𐑜𐑦𐑑𐑿𐑛 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑘𐑽, 𐑕𐑱, 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑑𐑻𐑯 𐑬𐑑 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑲𐑛𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑦 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑻 𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑞𐑺 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑰𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑰𐑟𐑩𐑯; 𐑞𐑴 𐑞𐑺 𐑸 𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑽 𐑯 𐑳𐑯𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑕𐑗𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑢𐑺 𐑞 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑺𐑦 𐑝 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑐𐑮𐑵𐑝𐑛 𐑑𐑮𐑵. 𐑦𐑯 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑤, 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑸𐑒, 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑤𐑧𐑕 𐑢𐑲𐑛 𐑤𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑑, 𐑩𐑐𐑤𐑲𐑟 𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑪𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑼𐑦𐑟 𐑯 𐑣𐑻𐑥𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑞 𐑥𐑩𐑗𐑫𐑼𐑛, 𐑱𐑡𐑛 𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟. 𐑕𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑴 ·𐑥𐑪𐑚𐑦 ·𐑛𐑦𐑒 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑓𐑹𐑥𐑼 𐑘𐑽 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑕𐑰𐑯, 𐑓 𐑦𐑜𐑟𐑭𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑤, 𐑪𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑛 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑱𐑖𐑧𐑤 𐑜𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑾𐑯 𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯, 𐑹 ·𐑝𐑪𐑤𐑒𐑱𐑯𐑴 ·𐑚𐑱 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑡𐑨𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑰𐑟 ·𐑒𐑴𐑕𐑑; 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑓𐑪𐑤𐑴, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑻 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛 𐑑 𐑝𐑦𐑟𐑦𐑑 𐑲𐑞𐑼 𐑝 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑕𐑐𐑪𐑑𐑕 𐑨𐑑 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑕𐑳𐑚𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑢𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑒𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑪𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑰𐑟𐑩𐑯, 𐑖𐑰 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑓𐑨𐑤𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑼 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑞𐑺. 𐑕𐑴, 𐑑𐑵, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑓𐑰𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑜𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑟, 𐑢𐑺 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑨𐑑 𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑮𐑦𐑝𐑰𐑤𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑨𐑠𐑵𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑑𐑪𐑐𐑦𐑙-𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑯 𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯-𐑦𐑯𐑟, 𐑕𐑴 𐑑 𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑒, 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑝 𐑐𐑮𐑴𐑤𐑪𐑙𐑛 𐑩𐑚𐑴𐑛. 𐑯 𐑢𐑺 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚'𐑟 𐑗𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑝 𐑩𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑦𐑖𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑪𐑚𐑡𐑧𐑒𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑞𐑼𐑑𐑵 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑕𐑐𐑴𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑝, 𐑩𐑤𐑵𐑠𐑩𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑑𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑢𐑱-𐑕𐑲𐑛, 𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑕𐑰𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑑, 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑩 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑕 𐑢𐑻 𐑣𐑦𐑟, 𐑺 𐑩 𐑐𐑼𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑼 𐑕𐑧𐑑 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑹 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕 𐑢𐑻 𐑩𐑑𐑱𐑯𐑛, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑐𐑪𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑚𐑩𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑟, 𐑯, 𐑨𐑟 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑓𐑪𐑯𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑔𐑷𐑑, 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑐𐑪𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑞 𐑯𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑 𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑩 𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑦. 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑐𐑼𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑼 𐑕𐑧𐑑 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑯 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕 𐑢𐑻 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑡𐑶𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑑𐑧𐑒𐑯𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑓𐑮𐑱𐑟—𐑞 ·𐑕𐑰𐑟𐑩𐑯-𐑪𐑯-𐑞-·𐑤𐑲𐑯. 𐑓 𐑞𐑺 𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑓 𐑕𐑧𐑝𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑧𐑒𐑿𐑑𐑦𐑝 𐑘𐑽𐑟, ·𐑥𐑪𐑚𐑦 ·𐑛𐑦𐑒 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑐𐑽𐑦𐑪𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛, 𐑤𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼𐑟 𐑓 𐑩𐑢𐑲𐑤, 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑯, 𐑦𐑯 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑨𐑯𐑿𐑩𐑤 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛, 𐑤𐑶𐑑𐑼𐑟 𐑓 𐑩 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑝𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑕𐑲𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑟𐑴𐑛𐑦𐑨𐑒. 𐑞𐑺 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟, 𐑑𐑵, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕; 𐑞𐑺 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑝𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑕𐑑𐑹𐑦𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑛𐑰𐑛𐑟; 𐑞𐑺 𐑷𐑤𐑕𐑴 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑡𐑦𐑒 𐑕𐑐𐑪𐑑 𐑢𐑺 𐑞 𐑥𐑪𐑯𐑩𐑥𐑱𐑯𐑦𐑨𐑒 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑞 𐑷𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑥𐑴𐑑𐑦𐑝 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑝𐑧𐑯𐑡𐑩𐑯𐑕. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑒𐑷𐑖𐑩𐑕 𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑣𐑧𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑝𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑯 𐑳𐑯𐑤𐑶𐑑𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑝𐑦𐑡𐑦𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑢𐑦𐑗 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑮𐑵𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑴𐑤 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑳𐑯𐑓𐑷𐑤𐑑𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑑, 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑐𐑼𐑥𐑦𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑑 𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑴𐑐𐑕 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑒𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑨𐑒𐑑 𐑩𐑚𐑳𐑝 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑛, 𐑣𐑬𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑓𐑤𐑨𐑑𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑑 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑑 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑣𐑴𐑐𐑕; 𐑯𐑹 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑤𐑰𐑐𐑤𐑩𐑕𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑝𐑬 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑴 𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑤𐑲𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑳𐑯𐑒𐑢𐑲𐑩𐑑 𐑣𐑸𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑑 𐑐𐑴𐑕𐑑𐑐𐑴𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑝𐑰𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑕𐑑.

𐑯𐑬, 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 ·𐑯𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑚𐑦𐑜𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑰𐑟𐑩𐑯-𐑪𐑯-𐑞-·𐑤𐑲𐑯. 𐑯𐑴 𐑐𐑪𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑱𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑣𐑻 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑭𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑑 𐑥𐑱𐑒 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑐𐑨𐑕𐑦𐑡 𐑕𐑬𐑔𐑢𐑼𐑛𐑟, 𐑛𐑳𐑚𐑩𐑤 ·𐑒𐑱𐑐 ·𐑣𐑹𐑯, 𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑮𐑳𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑦 𐑛𐑦𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑟 𐑝 𐑤𐑨𐑑𐑦𐑑𐑿𐑛 𐑼𐑲𐑝 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑧𐑒𐑢𐑩𐑑𐑹𐑾𐑤 ·𐑐𐑩𐑕𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑒 𐑦𐑯 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑑 𐑒𐑮𐑵𐑟 𐑞𐑺. 𐑞𐑺𐑓𐑹, 𐑣𐑰 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑑 𐑓 𐑞 𐑯𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑿𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑰𐑟𐑩𐑯. 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑥𐑩𐑗𐑫𐑼 𐑬𐑼 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛'𐑟 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑨𐑛, 𐑐𐑼𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑕, 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑒𐑼𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑦𐑤𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑲 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑝𐑿 𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑧𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑟. 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑪𐑟, 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑝𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑛 𐑯 𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑦-𐑓𐑲𐑝 𐑛𐑱𐑟 𐑯 𐑯𐑲𐑑𐑕 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑣𐑦𐑥; 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑝𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑦𐑗, 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑛 𐑝 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑻𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑖𐑹, 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑩𐑤𐑱𐑯𐑾𐑕 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑑; 𐑦𐑓 𐑚𐑲 𐑗𐑭𐑯𐑕 𐑞 ·𐑢𐑲𐑑 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑝𐑱𐑒𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑰𐑟 𐑓𐑸 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑴𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑽𐑦𐑪𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑓𐑰𐑛𐑦𐑙-𐑜𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑟, 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑑𐑻𐑯 𐑳𐑐 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑮𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑚𐑮𐑬 𐑪𐑓 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑻𐑖𐑩𐑯 ·𐑜𐑳𐑤𐑓, 𐑹 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑚𐑧𐑯𐑜𐑨𐑤 ·𐑚𐑱, 𐑹 ·𐑗𐑲𐑯𐑩 ·𐑕𐑰𐑟, 𐑹 𐑦𐑯 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼𐑟 𐑣𐑷𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑮𐑱𐑕. 𐑕𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑 ·𐑥𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑵𐑯𐑟, ·𐑐𐑨𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑕, ·𐑯𐑹'-·𐑢𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑟, ·𐑣𐑸𐑥𐑩𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑟, ·𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑛𐑟; 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑤𐑩𐑝𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑼 𐑯 ·𐑕𐑦𐑥𐑵𐑯, 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑚𐑤𐑴 ·𐑥𐑪𐑚𐑦 ·𐑛𐑦𐑒 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑛𐑰𐑝𐑾𐑕 𐑟𐑦𐑜-𐑟𐑨𐑜 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛-𐑕𐑻𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛'𐑟 𐑕𐑻𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑯𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑜𐑱𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑱𐑒.

𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑜𐑮𐑭𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑦𐑕; 𐑘𐑧𐑑, 𐑮𐑦𐑜𐑸𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑰𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑯 𐑒𐑵𐑤𐑦, 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑩 𐑥𐑨𐑛 𐑲𐑛𐑾, 𐑞𐑦𐑕; 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑮𐑷𐑛 𐑚𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯, 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑕𐑪𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑼𐑦 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑓 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑛, 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑚𐑰 𐑔𐑷𐑑 𐑒𐑱𐑐𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑡𐑵𐑩𐑤 𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑩𐑜𐑯𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑑𐑼, 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑨𐑟 𐑩 𐑢𐑲𐑑-𐑚𐑽𐑛𐑩𐑛 ·𐑥𐑳𐑓𐑑𐑦 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑔𐑮𐑪𐑙𐑛 𐑔𐑳𐑮𐑴𐑓𐑺𐑟 𐑝 ·𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑴𐑐𐑩𐑤? 𐑘𐑧𐑕. 𐑓 𐑞 𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑽 𐑕𐑯𐑴-𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑚𐑮𐑬 𐑝 ·𐑥𐑪𐑚𐑦 ·𐑛𐑦𐑒, 𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑯𐑴-𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑣𐑳𐑥𐑐, 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑳𐑯𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤. 𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑲 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑑𐑨𐑤𐑦𐑛 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤, ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑥𐑳𐑑𐑼 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓, 𐑨𐑟 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑐𐑹𐑦𐑙 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑗𐑸𐑑𐑕 𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑥𐑦𐑛𐑯𐑲𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑔𐑮𐑴 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑚𐑨𐑒 𐑦𐑯 𐑮𐑧𐑝𐑼𐑦𐑟—𐑑𐑨𐑤𐑦𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑯 𐑖𐑨𐑤 𐑣𐑰 𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑱𐑐? 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑮𐑷𐑛 𐑓𐑦𐑯𐑟 𐑸 𐑚𐑹𐑛, 𐑯 𐑕𐑒𐑪𐑤𐑩𐑐𐑑 𐑬𐑑 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑤𐑪𐑕𐑑 𐑖𐑰𐑐'𐑕 𐑽! 𐑯 𐑣𐑽, 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑨𐑛 𐑥𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑮𐑳𐑯 𐑪𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑚𐑮𐑧𐑔𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑮𐑱𐑕; 𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑩 𐑢𐑽𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑯 𐑓𐑱𐑯𐑑𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑐𐑪𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑒𐑱𐑥 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑣𐑦𐑥; 𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑴𐑐𐑩𐑯 𐑺 𐑝 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑒 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑕𐑰𐑒 𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑳𐑝𐑼 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑧𐑙𐑔. 𐑭, ·𐑜𐑪𐑛! 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑑𐑮𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑝 𐑑𐑹𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑛𐑳𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑻 𐑣𐑵 𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑿𐑥𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑳𐑯𐑩𐑗𐑰𐑝𐑛 𐑮𐑦𐑝𐑧𐑯𐑡𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑛𐑦𐑟𐑲𐑼. 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑤𐑰𐑐𐑕 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑒𐑤𐑧𐑯𐑗𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟; 𐑯 𐑢𐑱𐑒𐑕 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑴𐑯 𐑚𐑤𐑳𐑛𐑦 𐑯𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑭𐑥𐑟.

𐑪𐑓𐑩𐑯, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑓𐑹𐑕𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑥𐑩𐑒 𐑚𐑲 𐑦𐑜𐑟𐑷𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑪𐑤𐑼𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑝𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑛 𐑛𐑮𐑰𐑥𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑯𐑲𐑑, 𐑢𐑦𐑗, 𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑿𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑴𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑕 𐑔𐑷𐑑𐑕 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑞 𐑛𐑱, 𐑒𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑛 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑪𐑯 𐑩𐑥𐑦𐑛 𐑩 𐑒𐑤𐑨𐑖𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑯𐑟𐑦𐑟, 𐑯 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑯 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑯 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑤𐑱𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑯, 𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑞 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑔𐑮𐑪𐑚𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑤𐑲𐑓-𐑕𐑐𐑪𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑱𐑥 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑳𐑓𐑼𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑨𐑙𐑜𐑢𐑦𐑖; 𐑯 𐑢𐑧𐑯, 𐑨𐑟 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑞 𐑒𐑱𐑕, 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑕𐑐𐑦𐑮𐑦𐑗𐑵𐑩𐑤 𐑔𐑮𐑴𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑣𐑰𐑝𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑳𐑐 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑚𐑱𐑕, 𐑯 𐑩 𐑒𐑨𐑟𐑩𐑥 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑴𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑓𐑹𐑒𐑑 𐑓𐑤𐑱𐑥𐑟 𐑯 𐑤𐑲𐑑𐑯𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑖𐑪𐑑 𐑳𐑐, 𐑯 𐑩𐑒𐑻𐑕𐑩𐑛 𐑓𐑰𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑚𐑧𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑑 𐑤𐑰𐑐 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑞𐑧𐑥; 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑣𐑧𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑘𐑷𐑯𐑛 𐑚𐑦𐑯𐑰𐑔 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑩 𐑢𐑲𐑤𐑛 𐑒𐑮𐑲 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑚𐑰 𐑣𐑻𐑛 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐; 𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑜𐑤𐑺𐑦𐑙 𐑲𐑟 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑚𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑑 𐑮𐑵𐑥, 𐑨𐑟 𐑞𐑴 𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑱𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑩 𐑚𐑧𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑪𐑯 𐑓𐑲𐑼. 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑞𐑰𐑟, 𐑐𐑼𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑕, 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑛 𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑳𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑑𐑩𐑥𐑟 𐑝 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑤𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑯𐑩𐑕, 𐑹 𐑓𐑮𐑲𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑴𐑯 𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑪𐑤𐑝, 𐑢𐑻 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑯𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑑𐑴𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑑𐑦. 𐑓, 𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟, 𐑒𐑮𐑱𐑟𐑦 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚, 𐑞 𐑕𐑒𐑰𐑥𐑦𐑙, 𐑳𐑯𐑩𐑐𐑰𐑟𐑩𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑛𐑓𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑑𐑼 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑤; 𐑞𐑦𐑕 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑜𐑪𐑯 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑥𐑩𐑒, 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑞 𐑱𐑡𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑴 𐑒𐑷𐑟𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑑 𐑚𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑪𐑮𐑼 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯. 𐑞 𐑤𐑨𐑑𐑼 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞 𐑦𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑩𐑤, 𐑤𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑐𐑩𐑤 𐑹 𐑕𐑴𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥; 𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑤𐑰𐑐, 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑓 𐑞 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑴𐑕𐑦𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑒𐑨𐑮𐑩𐑒𐑑𐑼𐑲𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑲𐑯𐑛, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑨𐑑 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑶𐑛 𐑦𐑑 𐑓 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑬𐑑𐑼 𐑝𐑰𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑹 𐑱𐑡𐑩𐑯𐑑, 𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑐𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑱𐑯𐑾𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑷𐑑 𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑱𐑐 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑕𐑒𐑹𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑜𐑿𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑝 𐑞 𐑓𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑔𐑦𐑙, 𐑝 𐑢𐑦𐑗, 𐑓 𐑞 𐑑𐑲𐑥, 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑴 𐑤𐑪𐑙𐑜𐑼 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑜𐑮𐑩𐑤. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑥𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑛𐑳𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑦𐑜𐑟𐑦𐑕𐑑 𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑧𐑕 𐑤𐑰𐑜𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑕𐑴𐑤, 𐑞𐑺𐑓𐑹 𐑦𐑑 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑, 𐑦𐑯 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚'𐑟 𐑒𐑱𐑕, 𐑘𐑰𐑤𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑳𐑐 𐑷𐑤 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑔𐑷𐑑𐑕 𐑯 𐑓𐑨𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑟 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑕𐑵𐑐𐑮𐑰𐑥 𐑐𐑻𐑐𐑩𐑕; 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑐𐑻𐑐𐑩𐑕, 𐑚𐑲 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑴𐑯 𐑖𐑽 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑧𐑑𐑼𐑩𐑕𐑦 𐑝 𐑢𐑦𐑤, 𐑓𐑹𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑑𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑜𐑪𐑛𐑟 𐑯 𐑛𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑩 𐑒𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑝 𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓-𐑩𐑕𐑿𐑥𐑛, 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑴𐑯. 𐑯𐑱, 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑜𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑤𐑦 𐑤𐑲𐑝 𐑯 𐑚𐑻𐑯, 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑞 𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑝𐑲𐑑𐑨𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑡𐑶𐑯𐑛, 𐑓𐑤𐑧𐑛 𐑣𐑪𐑮𐑼-𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑳𐑯𐑚𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑯 𐑯 𐑳𐑯𐑓𐑭𐑞𐑼𐑛 𐑚𐑻𐑔. 𐑞𐑺𐑓𐑹, 𐑞 𐑑𐑹𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑕𐑐𐑦𐑮𐑦𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑜𐑤𐑺𐑛 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑦 𐑲𐑟, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑮𐑳𐑖𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑮𐑵𐑥, 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑓 𐑞 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑩 𐑝𐑱𐑒𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑔𐑦𐑙, 𐑩 𐑓𐑹𐑥𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑕𐑪𐑥𐑯𐑨𐑥𐑚𐑿𐑤𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙, 𐑩 𐑮𐑱 𐑝 𐑤𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑤𐑲𐑑, 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑖𐑫𐑼, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑 𐑩𐑯 𐑪𐑚𐑡𐑧𐑒𐑑 𐑑 𐑒𐑳𐑤𐑼, 𐑯 𐑞𐑺𐑓𐑹 𐑩 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑦𐑑𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓. 𐑜𐑪𐑛 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑐 𐑞𐑰, 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑥𐑨𐑯, 𐑞𐑲 𐑔𐑷𐑑𐑕 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑩 𐑒𐑮𐑰𐑗𐑼 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑰; 𐑯 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑵𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑕 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑳𐑕 𐑥𐑱𐑒𐑕 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑩 ·𐑐𐑮𐑴𐑥𐑰𐑔𐑾𐑕; 𐑩 𐑝𐑳𐑤𐑗𐑼 𐑓𐑰𐑛𐑟 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑸𐑑 𐑓 𐑧𐑝𐑼; 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑝𐑳𐑤𐑗𐑼 𐑞 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑒𐑮𐑰𐑗𐑼 𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑱𐑑𐑕.

·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 45. 𐑞 ·𐑨𐑓𐑦𐑛𐑱𐑝𐑦𐑑.

𐑕𐑴 𐑓𐑸 𐑨𐑟 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑥𐑱 𐑚𐑰 𐑝 𐑩 𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑑𐑦𐑝 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑚𐑫𐑒; 𐑯, 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑰𐑛, 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑑𐑳𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑹 𐑑𐑵 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑩𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑯 𐑒𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑾𐑕 𐑐𐑼𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑼𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑣𐑨𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟, 𐑞 𐑓𐑹𐑜𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼, 𐑦𐑯 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑻𐑤𐑽 𐑐𐑸𐑑, 𐑦𐑟 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑹𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑩 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑨𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑚𐑰 𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑝𐑪𐑤𐑿𐑥; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞 𐑤𐑰𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑨𐑑𐑼 𐑝 𐑦𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑢𐑲𐑼𐑟 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑓𐑻𐑞𐑼 𐑯 𐑥𐑹 𐑓𐑩𐑥𐑦𐑤𐑽𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑯𐑤𐑸𐑡𐑛 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯, 𐑦𐑯 𐑹𐑛𐑼 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑨𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑢𐑩𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑕𐑑𐑫𐑛, 𐑯 𐑥𐑹𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑑 𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑩𐑢𐑱 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑮𐑧𐑡𐑵𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑩 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑜𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑲𐑼 𐑕𐑳𐑚𐑡𐑧𐑒𐑑 𐑥𐑱 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑿𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑥𐑲𐑯𐑛𐑟, 𐑨𐑟 𐑑 𐑞 𐑯𐑨𐑗𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑝 𐑞 𐑥𐑱𐑯 𐑐𐑶𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑩𐑓𐑺.

𐑲 𐑒𐑺 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑑 𐑐𐑼𐑓𐑹𐑥 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑐𐑸𐑑 𐑝 𐑥𐑲 𐑑𐑭𐑕𐑒 𐑥𐑦𐑔𐑪𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑦; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑖𐑨𐑤 𐑚𐑰 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑛𐑿𐑕 𐑞 𐑛𐑦𐑟𐑲𐑼𐑛 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑚𐑲 𐑕𐑧𐑐𐑼𐑩𐑑 𐑕𐑲𐑑𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑥𐑟, 𐑐𐑮𐑨𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑦 𐑹 𐑮𐑦𐑤𐑲𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑯𐑴𐑯 𐑑 𐑥𐑰 𐑨𐑟 𐑩 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑥𐑩𐑯; 𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑕𐑲𐑑𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟, 𐑲 𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑦𐑑—𐑞 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑒𐑤𐑵𐑠𐑩𐑯 𐑱𐑥𐑛 𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑯𐑨𐑗𐑼𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑓𐑪𐑤𐑴 𐑝 𐑦𐑑𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓.

𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑: 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑐𐑻𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑯𐑴𐑯 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑢𐑺 𐑩 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑰𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯, 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑓𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑩 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑰𐑑 𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑱𐑐; 𐑯, 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑝𐑩𐑤 (𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑝 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑘𐑽𐑟), 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑒 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛, 𐑯 𐑕𐑤𐑱𐑯; 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑞 𐑑𐑵 𐑲𐑼𐑯𐑟, 𐑚𐑴𐑔 𐑥𐑸𐑒𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑐𐑮𐑲𐑝𐑩𐑑 𐑕𐑲𐑓𐑼, 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦. 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑢𐑺 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑘𐑽𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑝𐑰𐑯𐑛 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑢𐑰𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑤𐑦𐑙𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑞 𐑑𐑵 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑟; 𐑯 𐑲 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒 𐑦𐑑 𐑥𐑱 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑹 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑; 𐑞 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑣𐑵 𐑛𐑸𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑙, 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑝𐑩𐑤, 𐑑 𐑜𐑴 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑪𐑯 𐑩 𐑝𐑶𐑦𐑡 𐑑 ·𐑨𐑓𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑩, 𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑩𐑖𐑹 𐑞𐑺, 𐑡𐑶𐑯𐑛 𐑩 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑳𐑝𐑼𐑦 𐑐𐑸𐑑𐑦, 𐑯 𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑓𐑸 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑽𐑽, 𐑢𐑺 𐑣𐑰 𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑓 𐑩 𐑐𐑽𐑾𐑛 𐑝 𐑯𐑽𐑤𐑦 𐑑𐑵 𐑘𐑽𐑟, 𐑪𐑓𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑼𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑕𐑻𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕, 𐑕𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑡𐑩𐑟, 𐑑𐑲𐑜𐑼𐑟, 𐑐𐑶𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑥𐑲𐑨𐑟𐑥𐑩𐑟, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑐𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑤𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑣𐑸𐑑 𐑝 𐑳𐑯𐑯𐑴𐑯 𐑮𐑰𐑡𐑩𐑯𐑟. 𐑥𐑰𐑯𐑢𐑲𐑤, 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑒 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑷𐑤𐑕𐑴 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑪𐑯 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑟; 𐑯𐑴 𐑛𐑬𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑔𐑮𐑲𐑕 𐑕𐑻𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑯𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑜𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑞 𐑜𐑤𐑴𐑚, 𐑚𐑮𐑳𐑖𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑓𐑤𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑕 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑒𐑴𐑕𐑑𐑕 𐑝 ·𐑨𐑓𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑩; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑑 𐑯𐑴 𐑐𐑻𐑐𐑩𐑕. 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯 𐑒𐑱𐑥 𐑑𐑩𐑜𐑧𐑞𐑼, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑖𐑑 𐑞 𐑳𐑞𐑼. 𐑲 𐑕𐑱 𐑲, 𐑥𐑲𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓, 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑯𐑴𐑯 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑕𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑤𐑼 𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕; 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑑𐑵 𐑝 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑲 𐑕𐑷 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑒; 𐑯, 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑧𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑩𐑑𐑨𐑒, 𐑕𐑷 𐑞 𐑑𐑵 𐑲𐑼𐑯𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑝 𐑥𐑸𐑒𐑕 𐑒𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑥, 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼𐑢𐑼𐑛𐑟 𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑛 𐑓𐑦𐑖. 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑔𐑮𐑰-𐑘𐑽 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕, 𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑴 𐑓𐑧𐑤 𐑬𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑲 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑 𐑚𐑴𐑔 𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟, 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑯 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑩𐑜𐑯𐑲𐑟𐑛 𐑩 𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑽 𐑕𐑹𐑑 𐑝 𐑣𐑿𐑡 𐑥𐑴𐑤 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤'𐑟 𐑲, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑩𐑚𐑟𐑻𐑝𐑛 𐑞𐑺 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑘𐑽𐑟 𐑐𐑮𐑰𐑝𐑾𐑕. 𐑲 𐑕𐑱 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑘𐑽𐑟, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑲 𐑨𐑥 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑖𐑫𐑼 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑥𐑹 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑. 𐑣𐑽 𐑸 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟, 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑲 𐑐𐑻𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑯𐑴 𐑞 𐑑𐑮𐑵𐑔 𐑝; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑣𐑻𐑛 𐑝 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑐𐑻𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑣𐑵𐑟 𐑝𐑼𐑨𐑕𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑥𐑨𐑑𐑼 𐑞𐑺 𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑴 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑜𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑑 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑰𐑗.

𐑕𐑧𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑛𐑤𐑦: 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑧𐑤 𐑯𐑴𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤 ·𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑼𐑦, 𐑣𐑬𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑦𐑜𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑞 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛 𐑩𐑖𐑹 𐑥𐑱 𐑚𐑰 𐑝 𐑦𐑑, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑕𐑧𐑝𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑥𐑧𐑥𐑼𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑣𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑢𐑺 𐑩 𐑐𐑼𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑼 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑨𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑯 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑐𐑪𐑐𐑿𐑤𐑼𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑪𐑜𐑯𐑦𐑟𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤. 𐑢𐑲 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑱𐑥 𐑞𐑳𐑕 𐑥𐑸𐑒𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑷𐑤𐑑𐑩𐑜𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑯 𐑼𐑦𐑡𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑦𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑟 𐑨𐑟 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑢𐑦𐑖𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟; 𐑓 𐑣𐑬𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑽 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑗𐑭𐑯𐑕 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑥𐑱 𐑚𐑰, 𐑞𐑱 𐑕𐑵𐑯 𐑐𐑫𐑑 𐑩𐑯 𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑦𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑲 𐑒𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑯 𐑚𐑶𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑩 𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑽𐑤𐑦 𐑝𐑨𐑤𐑿𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑶𐑤. 𐑯𐑴: 𐑞 𐑮𐑰𐑟𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞𐑦𐑕: 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑓𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑽𐑾𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑼𐑦 𐑞𐑺 𐑣𐑳𐑙 𐑩 𐑑𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑰𐑠 𐑝 𐑐𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑤𐑩𐑕𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑨𐑟 𐑞𐑺 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 ·𐑮𐑦𐑯𐑨𐑤𐑛𐑴 ·𐑮𐑦𐑯𐑨𐑤𐑛𐑰𐑯𐑦, 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑴𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑼𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑢𐑻 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑑 𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑩𐑜𐑯𐑲𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑚𐑲 𐑥𐑽𐑤𐑦 𐑑𐑳𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑺 𐑑𐑸𐑐𐑷𐑤𐑦𐑯𐑟 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑚𐑰 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑳𐑝𐑼𐑛 𐑤𐑬𐑯𐑡𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑲 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑰, 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑒𐑳𐑤𐑑𐑦𐑝𐑱𐑑 𐑩 𐑥𐑹 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑥𐑩𐑑 𐑩𐑒𐑢𐑱𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕. 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑐𐑫𐑼 𐑛𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑩𐑖𐑹 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑩𐑯 𐑑 𐑯𐑴 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑮𐑨𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑥𐑨𐑯, 𐑞𐑱 𐑥𐑱𐑒 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑳𐑯𐑩𐑚𐑑𐑮𐑵𐑕𐑦𐑝 𐑕𐑨𐑤𐑿𐑑𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑰𐑑, 𐑤𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑓 𐑞𐑱 𐑐𐑼𐑕𐑿𐑛 𐑞 𐑩𐑒𐑢𐑱𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑓𐑻𐑞𐑼, 𐑞𐑱 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑰𐑝 𐑩 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑼𐑦 𐑔𐑳𐑥𐑐 𐑓 𐑞𐑺 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑖𐑩𐑯.

𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑰𐑗 𐑝 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑓𐑱𐑥𐑩𐑕 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑡𐑶 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑡𐑵𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑩𐑤𐑧𐑚𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑦—·𐑯𐑱, 𐑿 𐑥𐑱 𐑒𐑷𐑤 𐑦𐑑 𐑩𐑯 𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯-𐑢𐑲𐑛 𐑮𐑦𐑯𐑬𐑯; 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑓𐑱𐑥𐑩𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑤𐑲𐑓 𐑯 𐑯𐑬 𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑥𐑹𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑓𐑴𐑒𐑕𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑑𐑹𐑦𐑟 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑛𐑧𐑔, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩𐑛𐑥𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑮𐑲𐑑𐑕, 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑡𐑩𐑟, 𐑯 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑩 𐑯𐑱𐑥; 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑨𐑟 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑩 𐑯𐑱𐑥 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑰𐑛 𐑨𐑟 ·𐑒𐑨𐑥𐑚𐑦𐑟𐑩𐑟 𐑹 ·𐑕𐑰𐑟𐑼. 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑴, 𐑴 ·𐑑𐑰𐑥𐑹 ·𐑑𐑪𐑥! 𐑞𐑬 𐑓𐑱𐑥𐑛 𐑤𐑩𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑔𐑩𐑯, 𐑕𐑒𐑸𐑛 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩𐑯 𐑲𐑕𐑚𐑻𐑜, 𐑣𐑵 𐑕𐑴 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑛𐑲𐑛'𐑕𐑑 𐑤𐑻𐑒 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑹𐑦𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑯𐑱𐑥, 𐑣𐑵𐑟 𐑕𐑐𐑬𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑪𐑓𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑐𐑭𐑥𐑦 𐑚𐑰𐑗 𐑝 ·𐑪𐑥𐑚𐑱? 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑴, 𐑴 ·𐑯𐑿 ·𐑟𐑰𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛 ·𐑡𐑨𐑒! 𐑞𐑬 𐑑𐑧𐑮𐑼 𐑝 𐑷𐑤 𐑒𐑮𐑵𐑟𐑼𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑒𐑮𐑪𐑕𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑢𐑱𐑒𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑝𐑦𐑕𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑑𐑩𐑑𐑵 ·𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛? 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑴, 𐑴 Morquan! 𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑝 ·𐑡𐑩𐑐𐑨𐑯, 𐑣𐑵𐑟 𐑤𐑪𐑓𐑑𐑦 𐑡𐑧𐑑 𐑞𐑱 𐑕𐑱 𐑨𐑑 𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑩𐑕𐑿𐑥𐑛 𐑞 𐑕𐑧𐑥𐑚𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑝 𐑩 𐑕𐑯𐑴-𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑒𐑮𐑪𐑕 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑒𐑲? 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑴, 𐑴 ·𐑛𐑪𐑯 ·𐑥𐑦𐑜𐑘𐑧𐑤! 𐑞𐑬 ·𐑗𐑦𐑤𐑾𐑯 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑥𐑸𐑒𐑑 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩𐑯 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑑𐑹𐑑𐑩𐑕 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑣𐑲𐑮𐑩𐑜𐑤𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑒𐑕 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑨𐑒! 𐑦𐑯 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑯 𐑐𐑮𐑴𐑟, 𐑣𐑽 𐑸 𐑓𐑹 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑨𐑟 𐑢𐑧𐑤 𐑯𐑴𐑯 𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑿𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑝 ·𐑕𐑩𐑑𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 ·𐑣𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑦 𐑨𐑟 ·𐑥𐑸𐑾𐑕 𐑹 ·𐑕𐑦𐑤𐑩 𐑑 𐑞 𐑒𐑤𐑨𐑕𐑦𐑒 𐑕𐑒𐑪𐑤𐑼.

𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑷𐑤. 𐑯𐑿 ·𐑟𐑰𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛 ·𐑑𐑪𐑥 𐑯 ·𐑛𐑪𐑯 ·𐑥𐑦𐑜𐑘𐑧𐑤, 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑨𐑑 𐑝𐑺𐑾𐑕 𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑱𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝𐑩𐑒 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑛𐑦𐑓𐑼𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑝𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑤𐑟, 𐑢𐑻 𐑓𐑲𐑯𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑜𐑪𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑝, 𐑕𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑥𐑨𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑦 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑬𐑑, 𐑗𐑱𐑕𐑑 𐑯 𐑒𐑦𐑤𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑝𐑨𐑤𐑾𐑯𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑟, 𐑣𐑵 𐑣𐑰𐑝𐑛 𐑳𐑐 𐑞𐑺 𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑼𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑕 𐑩𐑚𐑡𐑧𐑒𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑦𐑯 𐑝𐑿, 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑧𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑬𐑑 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑞 ·𐑯𐑨𐑮𐑩𐑜𐑨𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑑 ·𐑢𐑫𐑛𐑟, ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 ·𐑚𐑳𐑑𐑤𐑼 𐑝 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑑 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑗𐑼 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑯𐑴𐑑𐑹𐑾𐑕 𐑥𐑻𐑛𐑼𐑩𐑕 𐑕𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑡 ·𐑩𐑯𐑷𐑩𐑯, 𐑞 𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑢𐑹𐑽 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑾𐑯 ·𐑒𐑦𐑙 ·𐑓𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑐.

𐑲 𐑛𐑵 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑯𐑴 𐑢𐑺 𐑲 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑓𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑩 𐑚𐑧𐑑𐑼 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑡𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑽, 𐑑 𐑥𐑱𐑒 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑹 𐑑𐑵 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑟, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑑 𐑥𐑰 𐑕𐑰𐑥 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑹𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑, 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑓𐑹𐑥 𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑚𐑤𐑦𐑖𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑕 𐑞 𐑮𐑰𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑣𐑴𐑤 𐑕𐑑𐑹𐑦 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑢𐑲𐑑 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑥𐑹 𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑞 𐑒𐑩𐑑𐑨𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑩𐑓𐑦. 𐑓 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑣𐑸𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑢𐑺 𐑑𐑮𐑵𐑔 𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑢𐑲𐑼𐑟 𐑓𐑫𐑤 𐑨𐑟 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑚𐑴𐑤𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑨𐑟 𐑻𐑼. 𐑕𐑴 𐑦𐑜𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑸 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑝 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑝 𐑞 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑯𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑯 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑐𐑨𐑤𐑐𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑣𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑑𐑳𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑯 𐑓𐑨𐑒𐑑𐑕, 𐑣𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑯 𐑳𐑞𐑼𐑢𐑲𐑟, 𐑝 𐑞 𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑼𐑦, 𐑞𐑱 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑕𐑒𐑬𐑑 𐑨𐑑 ·𐑥𐑪𐑚𐑦 ·𐑛𐑦𐑒 𐑨𐑟 𐑩 𐑥𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑩𐑕 𐑓𐑱𐑚𐑩𐑤, 𐑹 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑢𐑻𐑕 𐑯 𐑥𐑹 𐑛𐑦𐑑𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤, 𐑩 𐑣𐑦𐑛𐑾𐑕 𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑪𐑤𐑼𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑨𐑤𐑦𐑜𐑼𐑦.

𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑: 𐑞𐑴 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑝𐑱𐑜 𐑓𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑲𐑛𐑾𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑐𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑤𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑼𐑦, 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑞𐑱 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑯𐑳𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑓𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑑, 𐑝𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑛 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑧𐑐𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑐𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑤𐑟, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑮𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑞𐑱 𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑳𐑮. 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑮𐑰𐑟𐑩𐑯 𐑐𐑼𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑕 𐑦𐑟, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑓𐑦𐑓𐑑𐑦 𐑝 𐑞 𐑨𐑒𐑗𐑵𐑩𐑤 𐑛𐑦𐑟𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑟 𐑯 𐑛𐑧𐑔𐑕 𐑚𐑲 𐑒𐑨𐑠𐑵𐑩𐑤𐑑𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑼𐑦, 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑓𐑲𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑩 𐑐𐑳𐑚𐑤𐑦𐑒 𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑹𐑛 𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑴𐑥, 𐑣𐑬𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑟𐑾𐑯𐑑 𐑯 𐑦𐑥𐑰𐑛𐑾𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑓𐑼𐑜𐑪𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑹𐑛. 𐑛𐑵 𐑿 𐑕𐑩𐑐𐑴𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑐𐑫𐑼 𐑓𐑧𐑤𐑴 𐑞𐑺, 𐑣𐑵 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑥𐑴𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑐𐑼𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑕 𐑒𐑷𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤-𐑤𐑲𐑯 𐑪𐑓 𐑞 𐑒𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑝 ·𐑯𐑿 ·𐑜𐑦𐑯𐑦, 𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑒𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑛 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑑 𐑞 𐑚𐑪𐑑𐑩𐑥 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑰 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑕𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑤𐑩𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑔𐑩𐑯—𐑛𐑵 𐑿 𐑕𐑩𐑐𐑴𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑐𐑫𐑼 𐑓𐑧𐑤𐑴'𐑟 𐑯𐑱𐑥 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑩𐑐𐑽 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑯𐑿𐑟𐑐𐑱𐑐𐑼 𐑴𐑚𐑦𐑗𐑫𐑼𐑦 𐑿 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑮𐑰𐑛 𐑑-𐑥𐑪𐑮𐑴 𐑨𐑑 𐑘𐑹 𐑚𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑓𐑩𐑕𐑑? 𐑯𐑴: 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑪𐑟 𐑞 𐑥𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑸 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑦𐑮𐑧𐑜𐑿𐑤𐑼 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑢𐑰𐑯 𐑣𐑽 𐑯 ·𐑯𐑿 ·𐑜𐑦𐑯𐑦. 𐑦𐑯 𐑓𐑨𐑒𐑑, 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑿 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑣𐑽 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑛 𐑮𐑧𐑜𐑿𐑤𐑼 𐑯𐑿𐑟 𐑛𐑦𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑑 𐑹 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 ·𐑯𐑿 ·𐑜𐑦𐑯𐑦? 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑲 𐑑𐑧𐑤 𐑿 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑐𐑼𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑼 𐑝𐑶𐑦𐑡 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑲 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑩𐑕𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑒, 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑳𐑞𐑼𐑟 𐑢𐑰 𐑕𐑐𐑴𐑒 𐑔𐑻𐑑𐑦 𐑛𐑦𐑓𐑼𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑕, 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑩 𐑛𐑧𐑔 𐑚𐑲 𐑩 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑝 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑥𐑹 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯, 𐑯 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑰𐑗 𐑤𐑪𐑕𐑑 𐑩 𐑚𐑴𐑑'𐑕 𐑒𐑮𐑵. 𐑓 ·𐑜𐑪𐑛'𐑟 𐑕𐑱𐑒, 𐑚𐑰 𐑰𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑪𐑥𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑘𐑹 𐑤𐑨𐑥𐑐𐑕 𐑯 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑤𐑟! 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑩 𐑜𐑨𐑤𐑩𐑯 𐑿 𐑚𐑻𐑯, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑰𐑕𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑛𐑮𐑪𐑐 𐑝 𐑥𐑨𐑯'𐑟 𐑚𐑤𐑳𐑛 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑐𐑦𐑤𐑛 𐑓 𐑦𐑑.

𐑕𐑧𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑛𐑤𐑦: 𐑐𐑰𐑐𐑩𐑤 𐑩𐑖𐑹 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑰𐑛 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑧𐑓𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑑 𐑲𐑛𐑾 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑩 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑦𐑟 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑹𐑥𐑩𐑕 𐑒𐑮𐑰𐑗𐑼 𐑝 𐑦𐑯𐑹𐑥𐑩𐑕 𐑐𐑬𐑼; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑯𐑼𐑱𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑕𐑐𐑩𐑕𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑒 𐑦𐑜𐑟𐑭𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑑𐑵-𐑓𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑹𐑥𐑩𐑕𐑯𐑩𐑕, 𐑞𐑱 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑕𐑦𐑜𐑯𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑦𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑥𐑰 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑥𐑲 𐑓𐑩𐑕𐑰𐑖𐑩𐑕𐑯𐑩𐑕; 𐑢𐑧𐑯, 𐑲 𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑺 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑥𐑲 𐑕𐑴𐑤, 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑯𐑴 𐑥𐑹 𐑲𐑛𐑾 𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑩𐑕𐑰𐑖𐑩𐑕 𐑞𐑨𐑯 ·𐑥𐑴𐑟𐑩𐑟, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑣𐑰 𐑮𐑴𐑑 𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑦 𐑝 𐑞 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑜𐑟 𐑝 ·𐑰𐑡𐑦𐑐𐑑.

𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑓𐑹𐑗𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑤 𐑐𐑶𐑯𐑑 𐑲 𐑣𐑽 𐑕𐑰𐑒 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑚𐑰 𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑚𐑤𐑦𐑖𐑑 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑑𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑦 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑲𐑼𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑥𐑲 𐑴𐑯. 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑐𐑶𐑯𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑞𐑦𐑕: 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑒𐑱𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑕𐑩𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑬𐑼𐑓𐑩𐑤, 𐑯𐑴𐑦𐑙, 𐑯 𐑡𐑵𐑛𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑥𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑕, 𐑨𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑛𐑦𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑑 𐑩𐑓𐑹𐑔𐑷𐑑 𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑝 𐑦𐑯, 𐑳𐑑𐑼𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑶, 𐑯 𐑕𐑦𐑙𐑒 𐑩 𐑤𐑸𐑡 𐑖𐑦𐑐; 𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑹, 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑛𐑳𐑯 𐑦𐑑.

𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑: 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑘𐑽 1820 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐 ·𐑧𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑕, ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 ·𐑐𐑪𐑤𐑼𐑛, 𐑝 ·𐑯𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑑, 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑒𐑮𐑵𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑩𐑕𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑒 ·𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯. 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑛𐑱 𐑖𐑰 𐑕𐑷 𐑕𐑐𐑬𐑑𐑕, 𐑤𐑴𐑼𐑛 𐑣𐑻 𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕, 𐑯 𐑜𐑱𐑝 𐑗𐑱𐑕 𐑑 𐑩 𐑖𐑴𐑤 𐑝 𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟. 𐑺 𐑤𐑪𐑙, 𐑕𐑧𐑝𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑢𐑵𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛; 𐑢𐑧𐑯, 𐑕𐑳𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑦, 𐑩 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑤𐑸𐑡 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑱𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕, 𐑦𐑖𐑿𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑖𐑴𐑤, 𐑯 𐑚𐑹 𐑛𐑦𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐. 𐑛𐑨𐑖𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑛 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑻 𐑣𐑳𐑤, 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑴 𐑕𐑑𐑴𐑝 𐑣𐑻 𐑦𐑯, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑤𐑧𐑕 𐑞𐑨𐑯 “𐑑𐑧𐑯 𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑕” 𐑖𐑰 𐑕𐑧𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑯 𐑓𐑧𐑤 𐑴𐑝𐑼. 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑩 𐑕𐑼𐑝𐑲𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑐𐑤𐑨𐑙𐑒 𐑝 𐑣𐑻 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑕𐑰𐑯 𐑕𐑦𐑯𐑕. 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑞 𐑕𐑦𐑝𐑽𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑴𐑠𐑼, 𐑐𐑸𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑵 𐑮𐑰𐑗𐑑 𐑞 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕. 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑮𐑩𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑛 𐑣𐑴𐑥 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑, ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 ·𐑐𐑪𐑤𐑼𐑛 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑕 𐑥𐑹 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑛 𐑓 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑩𐑕𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑒 𐑦𐑯 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑭𐑯𐑛 𐑝 𐑩𐑯𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑖𐑦𐑐, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞 𐑜𐑪𐑛𐑟 𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑳𐑯𐑯𐑴𐑯 𐑮𐑪𐑒𐑕 𐑯 𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑒𐑼𐑟; 𐑓 𐑞 𐑕𐑧𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑳𐑑𐑼𐑤𐑦 𐑤𐑪𐑕𐑑, 𐑯 𐑓𐑹𐑔𐑢𐑦𐑔 𐑓𐑹𐑕𐑢𐑺𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑕𐑰, 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑑𐑧𐑥𐑐𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑦𐑯𐑕. 𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑛𐑱 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 ·𐑐𐑪𐑤𐑼𐑛 𐑦𐑟 𐑩 𐑮𐑧𐑟𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑝 ·𐑯𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑑. 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑕𐑰𐑯 ·𐑴𐑢𐑧𐑯 ·𐑗𐑱𐑕, 𐑣𐑵 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑗𐑰𐑓 𐑥𐑱𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑧𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑕 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑝 𐑞 𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑡𐑩𐑛𐑦; 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑮𐑧𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑯 𐑯 𐑓𐑱𐑔𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑑𐑦𐑝; 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑝𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑳𐑯; 𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑓𐑿 𐑥𐑲𐑤𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑰𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑒𐑩𐑑𐑨𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑩𐑓𐑦.*

*𐑞 𐑓𐑪𐑤𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑸 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑒𐑑𐑕 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 ·𐑗𐑱𐑕'𐑩𐑟 𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑑𐑦𐑝: “𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑓𐑨𐑒𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑮𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑥𐑰 𐑦𐑯 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑒𐑤𐑵𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑧𐑯𐑦𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑗𐑭𐑯𐑕 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑛𐑦𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑪𐑐𐑼𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟; 𐑣𐑰 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑑𐑵 𐑕𐑧𐑝𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑩𐑑𐑨𐑒𐑕 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐, 𐑨𐑑 𐑩 𐑖𐑹𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑝𐑩𐑤 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑢𐑰𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑥, 𐑚𐑴𐑔 𐑝 𐑢𐑦𐑗, 𐑩𐑒𐑹𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑛𐑦𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯, 𐑢𐑻 𐑒𐑨𐑤𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑑 𐑛𐑵 𐑳𐑕 𐑞 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑡𐑼𐑦, 𐑚𐑲 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑩𐑣𐑧𐑛, 𐑯 𐑞𐑺𐑚𐑲 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑚𐑲𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑛 𐑝 𐑞 𐑑𐑵 𐑪𐑚𐑡𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑕 𐑓 𐑞 𐑖𐑪𐑒; 𐑑 𐑦𐑓𐑧𐑒𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑗, 𐑞 𐑦𐑜𐑟𐑨𐑒𐑑 𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑵𐑝𐑼𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑣𐑰 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑢𐑻 𐑯𐑧𐑕𐑦𐑕𐑺𐑦. 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑨𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑚𐑩𐑤, 𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑯 𐑓𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑦. 𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑱𐑥 𐑛𐑦𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑖𐑴𐑤 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑢𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑡𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑛, 𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑢𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑒 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑨𐑯𐑘𐑩𐑯𐑟, 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑓 𐑓𐑲𐑼𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑮𐑦𐑝𐑧𐑯𐑡 𐑓 𐑞𐑺 𐑕𐑳𐑓𐑼𐑦𐑙𐑟.” 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯: “𐑨𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑦𐑝𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑕, 𐑞 𐑣𐑴𐑤 𐑕𐑻𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑑𐑩𐑜𐑧𐑞𐑼, 𐑷𐑤 𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑥𐑲 𐑴𐑯 𐑲𐑟, 𐑯 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑛𐑿𐑕𐑦𐑙, 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑑𐑲𐑥, 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑲 𐑥𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑝 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑲𐑛𐑩𐑛, 𐑒𐑨𐑤𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑱𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑗𐑦𐑓, 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑐𐑸𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 (𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑝 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑲 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑯𐑬 𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑷𐑤), 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑿𐑕 𐑥𐑰 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑕𐑨𐑑𐑦𐑕𐑓𐑲𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑲 𐑨𐑥 𐑒𐑼𐑧𐑒𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑲 𐑩𐑐𐑦𐑯𐑘𐑩𐑯.”

𐑣𐑽 𐑸 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑮𐑦𐑓𐑤𐑧𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐, 𐑛𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑒 𐑯𐑲𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑩𐑯 𐑴𐑐𐑩𐑯 𐑚𐑴𐑑, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑺𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑮𐑰𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑣𐑪𐑕𐑐𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑖𐑹. “𐑞 𐑛𐑸𐑒 𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑯 𐑕𐑢𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑯𐑳𐑔𐑦𐑙; 𐑞 𐑓𐑽𐑟 𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑢𐑪𐑤𐑴𐑛 𐑳𐑐 𐑚𐑲 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑛𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑑𐑧𐑥𐑐𐑦𐑕𐑑, 𐑹 𐑛𐑨𐑖𐑑 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑯 𐑮𐑪𐑒𐑕, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑹𐑛𐑦𐑯𐑼𐑦 𐑕𐑳𐑚𐑡𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑓𐑽𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯, 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑕𐑒𐑺𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑑 𐑩 𐑥𐑴𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑'𐑕 𐑔𐑷𐑑; 𐑞 𐑛𐑦𐑟𐑥𐑩𐑤 𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑮𐑧𐑒, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑣𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑛 𐑨𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑 𐑯 𐑮𐑦𐑝𐑧𐑯𐑡 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑯𐑜𐑮𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑥𐑲 𐑮𐑦𐑓𐑤𐑧𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟, 𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑛𐑱 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑩𐑐𐑽𐑩𐑯𐑕.”

𐑦𐑯 𐑩𐑯𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕—p. 45,—𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑕 𐑝 “𐑞 𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑽𐑾𐑕 𐑯 𐑥𐑹𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑩𐑑𐑨𐑒 𐑝 𐑞 𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑥𐑩𐑤.”

𐑕𐑧𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑛𐑤𐑦: 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐 ·𐑿𐑯𐑾𐑯, 𐑷𐑤𐑕𐑴 𐑝 ·𐑯𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑑, 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑘𐑽 1807 𐑑𐑴𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑤𐑪𐑕𐑑 𐑪𐑓 𐑞 ·𐑩𐑟𐑹𐑟 𐑚𐑲 𐑩 𐑕𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑤𐑼 𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑧𐑑, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞 𐑷𐑔𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑐𐑼𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑼𐑟 𐑝 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑒𐑩𐑑𐑨𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑩𐑓𐑦 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑗𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑼, 𐑞𐑴 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑟 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑯𐑬 𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑣𐑻𐑛 𐑒𐑨𐑠𐑵𐑩𐑤 𐑩𐑤𐑵𐑠𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑑 𐑦𐑑.

𐑔𐑻𐑛𐑤𐑦: 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑱𐑑𐑰𐑯 𐑹 𐑑𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑦 𐑘𐑽𐑟 𐑩𐑜𐑴 ·𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑛𐑹 J——, 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑭𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑯 ·𐑩𐑥𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑕𐑤𐑵𐑐-𐑝-𐑢𐑹 𐑝 𐑞 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑒𐑤𐑭𐑕, 𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑛𐑲𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑐𐑸𐑑𐑦 𐑝 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑟, 𐑪𐑯 𐑚𐑹𐑛 𐑩 ·𐑯𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑑 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑣𐑸𐑚𐑼 𐑝 ·𐑴𐑭𐑣𐑵, ·𐑕𐑨𐑯𐑢𐑦𐑡 ·𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛𐑟. 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑝𐑼𐑕𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟, 𐑞 ·𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑛𐑹 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑐𐑤𐑰𐑟𐑛 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑕𐑒𐑧𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑑𐑳𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑩𐑥𐑱𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑧𐑙𐑔 𐑩𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑚𐑛 𐑑 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑓𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑑. 𐑣𐑰 𐑐𐑼𐑧𐑥𐑐𐑑𐑼𐑦𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑦𐑯𐑲𐑛 𐑓 𐑦𐑜𐑟𐑭𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑤, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑕𐑴 𐑕𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑬𐑑 𐑕𐑤𐑵𐑐-𐑝-𐑢𐑹 𐑨𐑟 𐑑 𐑒𐑷𐑟 𐑣𐑻 𐑑 𐑤𐑰𐑒 𐑕𐑴 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑨𐑟 𐑩 𐑔𐑦𐑥𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑓𐑫𐑤. 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑜𐑫𐑛; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑹 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑦𐑙. 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑕 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼, 𐑞 ·𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑛𐑹 𐑕𐑧𐑑 𐑕𐑱𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑜𐑯𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑒𐑮𐑭𐑓𐑑 𐑓 ·𐑝𐑭𐑤𐑐𐑸𐑩𐑦𐑕𐑴. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑪𐑐𐑑 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑱 𐑚𐑲 𐑩 𐑐𐑹𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑚𐑧𐑜𐑛 𐑩 𐑓𐑿 𐑥𐑴𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑕' 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑓𐑦𐑛𐑧𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑤 𐑚𐑦𐑟𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑥. 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑟𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑓𐑧𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑞 ·𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑛𐑹'𐑟 𐑒𐑮𐑭𐑓𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩 𐑔𐑢𐑨𐑒, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑷𐑤 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑕 𐑜𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑰 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑓 𐑞 𐑯𐑽𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑐𐑹𐑑 𐑑 𐑣𐑰𐑝 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑯 𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑺. 𐑲 𐑨𐑥 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑵𐑐𐑼𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑕, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑲 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑼 𐑞 ·𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑛𐑹'𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑝𐑿 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑨𐑟 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑝𐑦𐑛𐑧𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑤. 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 ·𐑕𐑷𐑤 𐑝 ·𐑑𐑸𐑕𐑩𐑕 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑝𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑳𐑯𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑰𐑓 𐑚𐑲 𐑩 𐑕𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑤𐑼 𐑓𐑮𐑲𐑑? 𐑲 𐑑𐑧𐑤 𐑿, 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑯𐑴 𐑯𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑕.

𐑲 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑯𐑬 𐑮𐑦𐑓𐑻 𐑿 𐑑 ·𐑤𐑨𐑙𐑟𐑛𐑹𐑓'𐑕 ·𐑝𐑶𐑦𐑡𐑩𐑟 𐑓 𐑩 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑻𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑐𐑶𐑯𐑑, 𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑽𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑩𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑞 𐑮𐑲𐑑𐑼 𐑣𐑽𐑪𐑝. 𐑤𐑨𐑙𐑟𐑛𐑹𐑓, 𐑿 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑯𐑴 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑢𐑱, 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩𐑑𐑨𐑗𐑑 𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑮𐑳𐑖𐑩𐑯 ·𐑨𐑛𐑥𐑼𐑩𐑤 ·𐑒𐑮𐑵𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑯'𐑟 𐑓𐑱𐑥𐑩𐑕 ·𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑳𐑝𐑼𐑦 ·𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑦𐑛𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑦𐑜𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑗𐑼𐑦. 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 ·𐑤𐑨𐑙𐑟𐑛𐑹𐑓 𐑞𐑳𐑕 𐑚𐑦𐑜𐑦𐑯𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑰𐑯𐑔 𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼:

“𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑔𐑻𐑑𐑰𐑯𐑔 𐑝 𐑥𐑱 𐑬𐑼 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑦 𐑑 𐑕𐑱𐑤, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑯𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑 𐑛𐑱 𐑢𐑰 𐑢𐑻 𐑬𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑴𐑐𐑩𐑯 𐑕𐑰, 𐑪𐑯 𐑬𐑼 𐑢𐑱 𐑑 ·𐑪𐑒𐑪𐑗. 𐑞 𐑢𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑒𐑤𐑽 𐑯 𐑓𐑲𐑯, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑕𐑴 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑪𐑤𐑼𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑰 𐑢𐑻 𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑲𐑡𐑛 𐑑 𐑒𐑰𐑐 𐑪𐑯 𐑬𐑼 𐑓𐑻 𐑒𐑤𐑴𐑞𐑦𐑙. 𐑓 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑛𐑱𐑟 𐑢𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛; 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑞 𐑯𐑲𐑯𐑑𐑰𐑯𐑔 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑩 𐑚𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑒 𐑜𐑱𐑤 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑯𐑹𐑔𐑢𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑨𐑙 𐑳𐑐. 𐑩𐑯 𐑳𐑯𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑤𐑸𐑡 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑞 𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦 𐑝 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑤𐑸𐑡𐑼 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑦𐑑𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓, 𐑤𐑱 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑻𐑓𐑦𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑐𐑼𐑕𐑰𐑝𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑪𐑯 𐑚𐑹𐑛 𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑞 𐑥𐑴𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑓𐑫𐑤 𐑕𐑱𐑤, 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑕𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑪𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑝𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥. 𐑢𐑰 𐑢𐑻 𐑞𐑳𐑕 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑛𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑼, 𐑨𐑟 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑡𐑲𐑜𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑒𐑮𐑰𐑗𐑼, 𐑕𐑧𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑳𐑐 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑚𐑨𐑒, 𐑮𐑱𐑟𐑛 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑓𐑰𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑰𐑕𐑑 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼. 𐑞 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑕 𐑮𐑰𐑤𐑛, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑓𐑧𐑤 𐑷𐑤𐑑𐑩𐑜𐑧𐑞𐑼, 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑢𐑰 𐑣𐑵 𐑢𐑻 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑴 𐑷𐑤 𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑨𐑙 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑒, 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑒𐑤𐑵𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑒 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑮𐑪𐑒; 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑛 𐑝 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑰 𐑕𐑷 𐑞 𐑥𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑼 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑪𐑓 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑳𐑑𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑜𐑮𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑯 𐑕𐑩𐑤𐑧𐑥𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑦. 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 ·𐑛'𐑢𐑫𐑤𐑓 𐑩𐑐𐑤𐑲𐑛 𐑦𐑥𐑰𐑛𐑾𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑑 𐑞 𐑐𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑕 𐑑 𐑦𐑜𐑟𐑨𐑥𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑹 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑞 𐑝𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑤 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑰𐑝𐑛 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑛𐑨𐑥𐑦𐑡 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑖𐑪𐑒, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑰 𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑦𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑱𐑐𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑲𐑼𐑤𐑦 𐑳𐑯𐑦𐑯𐑡𐑼𐑛.”

𐑯𐑬, 𐑞 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 ·𐑛'𐑢𐑫𐑤𐑓 𐑣𐑽 𐑩𐑤𐑵𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑭𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑦𐑯 𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑕𐑗𐑩𐑯, 𐑦𐑟 𐑩 ·𐑯𐑿 ·𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛𐑼, 𐑣𐑵, 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑩 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑤𐑲𐑓 𐑝 𐑳𐑯𐑿𐑠𐑵𐑩𐑤 𐑩𐑛𐑝𐑧𐑯𐑗𐑼𐑟 𐑨𐑟 𐑩 𐑕𐑰-𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯, 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑛𐑱 𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑲𐑛𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑝𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑡 𐑝 ·𐑛𐑹𐑗𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑼 𐑯𐑽 ·𐑚𐑪𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯. 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑞 𐑪𐑯𐑼 𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑯𐑧𐑓𐑿 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟. 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑐𐑼𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑼𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑕𐑗𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑐𐑨𐑕𐑦𐑡 𐑦𐑯 ·𐑤𐑨𐑙𐑟𐑛𐑹𐑓. 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑖𐑦𐑱𐑑𐑕 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑢𐑻𐑛. 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐, 𐑣𐑬𐑧𐑝𐑼, 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑚𐑲 𐑯𐑴 𐑥𐑰𐑯𐑟 𐑩 𐑤𐑸𐑡 𐑢𐑳𐑯: 𐑩 ·𐑮𐑳𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑒𐑮𐑭𐑓𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑑 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑲𐑚𐑽𐑾𐑯 𐑒𐑴𐑕𐑑, 𐑯 𐑐𐑻𐑗𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑥𐑲 𐑳𐑙𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑚𐑸𐑑𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑢𐑱 𐑞 𐑝𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑣𐑴𐑥.

𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑳𐑐 𐑯 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑥𐑨𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑫𐑒 𐑝 𐑴𐑤𐑛-𐑓𐑨𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑩𐑛𐑝𐑧𐑯𐑗𐑼, 𐑕𐑴 𐑓𐑫𐑤, 𐑑𐑵, 𐑝 𐑪𐑯𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑟—𐑞 𐑝𐑶𐑦𐑡 𐑝 ·𐑤𐑲𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑤 ·𐑢𐑱𐑓𐑼, 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑱𐑯𐑗𐑩𐑯𐑑 ·𐑛𐑨𐑥𐑐𐑽'𐑟 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑗𐑳𐑥𐑟—𐑲 𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑩 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑥𐑨𐑑𐑼 𐑕𐑧𐑑 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑕𐑴 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑡𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑒𐑢𐑴𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 ·𐑤𐑨𐑙𐑟𐑛𐑹𐑓, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑲 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑓𐑹𐑚𐑺 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑑 𐑣𐑽 𐑓 𐑩 𐑒𐑼𐑪𐑚𐑼𐑩𐑑𐑦𐑝 𐑦𐑜𐑟𐑭𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑤, 𐑦𐑓 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑚𐑰 𐑯𐑰𐑛𐑩𐑛.

·𐑤𐑲𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑤, 𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑟, 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑱 𐑑 “𐑡𐑪𐑯 ·𐑓𐑻𐑛𐑦𐑯𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑴,” 𐑨𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑟 𐑞 𐑥𐑪𐑛𐑼𐑯 ·𐑣𐑢𐑭𐑯 ·𐑓𐑧𐑮𐑯𐑭𐑯𐑛𐑧𐑕. “𐑦𐑯 𐑬𐑼 𐑢𐑱 𐑞𐑦𐑞𐑼,” 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑧𐑟, “𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑓𐑹 𐑴'𐑒𐑤𐑪𐑒 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑥𐑹𐑯𐑦𐑙, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑢𐑰 𐑢𐑻 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑛 𐑯 𐑓𐑦𐑓𐑑𐑦 𐑤𐑰𐑜𐑟 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 ·𐑥𐑱𐑯 𐑝 ·𐑩𐑥𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑩, 𐑬𐑼 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑓𐑧𐑤𐑑 𐑩 𐑑𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑖𐑪𐑒, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑐𐑫𐑑 𐑬𐑼 𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑯𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑱 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑣𐑸𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑑𐑧𐑤 𐑢𐑺 𐑞𐑱 𐑢𐑻 𐑹 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑑 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑚𐑦𐑜𐑨𐑯 𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑺 𐑓 𐑛𐑧𐑔. 𐑯, 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑰𐑛, 𐑞 𐑖𐑪𐑒 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑴 𐑕𐑳𐑛𐑩𐑯 𐑯 𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑑, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑰 𐑑𐑫𐑒 𐑦𐑑 𐑓 𐑜𐑮𐑭𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑒 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑩 𐑮𐑪𐑒; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑞 𐑩𐑥𐑱𐑟𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑴𐑝𐑼, 𐑢𐑰 𐑒𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑞 𐑤𐑧𐑛, 𐑯 𐑕𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑯𐑴 𐑜𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛. * * * * * 𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑖𐑪𐑒 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑞 𐑜𐑳𐑯𐑟 𐑤𐑰𐑐 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑒𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑡𐑩𐑟, 𐑯 𐑕𐑧𐑝𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑞 𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑢𐑻 𐑖𐑱𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑞𐑺 𐑣𐑨𐑥𐑩𐑒𐑕. 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 ·𐑛𐑱𐑝𐑦𐑕, 𐑣𐑵 𐑤𐑱 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑪𐑯 𐑩 𐑜𐑳𐑯, 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑔𐑮𐑴𐑯 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑨𐑚𐑦𐑯!” ·𐑤𐑲𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑜𐑴𐑟 𐑪𐑯 𐑑 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑿𐑑 𐑞 𐑖𐑪𐑒 𐑑 𐑩𐑯 𐑻𐑔𐑒𐑢𐑱𐑒, 𐑯 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑟 𐑑 𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑖𐑦𐑱𐑑 𐑞 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑿𐑑𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑚𐑲 𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑩 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑻𐑔𐑒𐑢𐑱𐑒, 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑢𐑺 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑑𐑲𐑥, 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑨𐑒𐑗𐑵𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑵 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑗𐑦𐑓 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑐𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑖 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑲 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑦𐑓, 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑛𐑸𐑒𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑻𐑤𐑦 𐑬𐑼 𐑝 𐑞 𐑥𐑹𐑯𐑦𐑙, 𐑞 𐑖𐑪𐑒 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑷𐑤 𐑒𐑷𐑟𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑩𐑯 𐑳𐑯𐑕𐑰𐑯 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑝𐑻𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑣𐑳𐑤 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑚𐑦𐑯𐑰𐑔.

𐑲 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑴𐑕𐑰𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑕𐑧𐑝𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑥𐑹 𐑦𐑜𐑟𐑭𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑤𐑟, 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑢𐑱 𐑹 𐑩𐑯𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑯𐑴𐑯 𐑑 𐑥𐑰, 𐑝 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑐𐑬𐑼 𐑯 𐑥𐑨𐑤𐑦𐑕 𐑨𐑑 𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 𐑢𐑱𐑤. 𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑹 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕, 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑯𐑴𐑯, 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑑 𐑗𐑱𐑕 𐑞 𐑩𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕 𐑚𐑨𐑒 𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑕, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑑 𐑐𐑼𐑕𐑿 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑦𐑑𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓, 𐑯 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑣𐑻𐑤𐑛 𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑛𐑧𐑒𐑕. 𐑞 ·𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑤𐑦𐑖 𐑖𐑦𐑐 ·𐑐𐑳𐑕𐑦 ·𐑣𐑷𐑤 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑑𐑧𐑤 𐑩 𐑕𐑑𐑹𐑦 𐑪𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑧𐑛; 𐑯, 𐑨𐑟 𐑓 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑧𐑙𐑔, 𐑤𐑧𐑑 𐑥𐑰 𐑕𐑱, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑦𐑜𐑟𐑭𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑢𐑺 𐑞 𐑤𐑲𐑯𐑟 𐑩𐑑𐑨𐑗𐑑 𐑑 𐑩 𐑮𐑳𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑣𐑨𐑝, 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑒𐑭𐑥, 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑕𐑓𐑻𐑛 𐑑 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐, 𐑯 𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑛 𐑞𐑺; 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑑𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑻 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑣𐑳𐑤 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑞 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼, 𐑨𐑟 𐑩 𐑣𐑹𐑕 𐑢𐑷𐑒𐑕 𐑪𐑓 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑒𐑸𐑑. 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯, 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑪𐑓𐑩𐑯 𐑩𐑚𐑟𐑻𐑝𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑, 𐑦𐑓 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑕 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑒, 𐑦𐑟 𐑩𐑤𐑬𐑛 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑑 𐑮𐑨𐑤𐑦, 𐑣𐑰 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑨𐑒𐑑𐑕, 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑴 𐑪𐑓𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑚𐑤𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑮𐑱𐑡, 𐑨𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑢𐑦𐑤𐑓𐑩𐑤, 𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑚𐑼𐑩𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑟𐑲𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑼𐑕𐑿𐑼𐑟; 𐑯𐑹 𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑝𐑱𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑧𐑤𐑩𐑒𐑢𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑨𐑮𐑩𐑒𐑑𐑼, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑑𐑨𐑒𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑓𐑮𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑴𐑐𐑩𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑬𐑔, 𐑯 𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑱𐑯 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑛𐑮𐑧𐑛 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑨𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑓 𐑕𐑧𐑝𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑧𐑒𐑿𐑑𐑦𐑝 𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑕. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑲 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑥𐑹 𐑯 𐑩 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑒𐑤𐑵𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑤𐑳𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯; 𐑩 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑸𐑒𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑯 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑦𐑜𐑯𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯, 𐑚𐑲 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑿 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑓𐑱𐑤 𐑑 𐑕𐑰, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑟 𐑞 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑥𐑸𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑦𐑝𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑚𐑫𐑒 𐑒𐑼𐑪𐑚𐑼𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑯 𐑓𐑨𐑒𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑛𐑱, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑥𐑸𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑟 (𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑷𐑤 𐑥𐑸𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑟) 𐑸 𐑥𐑽 𐑮𐑧𐑐𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑱𐑡𐑩𐑟; 𐑕𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑓 𐑞 𐑥𐑦𐑤𐑾𐑯𐑔 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑢𐑰 𐑕𐑱 𐑭𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 ·𐑕𐑪𐑤𐑩𐑥𐑩𐑯—·𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑤𐑦 𐑞𐑺 𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑳𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑯𐑿 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑯.

𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑔 ·𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑗𐑩𐑯 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑗𐑼𐑦 𐑤𐑦𐑝𐑛 ·𐑐𐑮𐑴𐑒𐑴𐑐𐑾𐑕, 𐑩 ·𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑗𐑩𐑯 𐑥𐑨𐑡𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑝 ·𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑴𐑐𐑩𐑤, 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑛𐑱𐑟 𐑢𐑧𐑯 ·𐑡𐑳𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑾𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑟 ·𐑧𐑥𐑐𐑼𐑼 𐑯 ·𐑚𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑕𐑸𐑾𐑕 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑤. 𐑨𐑟 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑯𐑴, 𐑣𐑰 𐑮𐑴𐑑 𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑦 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑴𐑯 𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟, 𐑩 𐑢𐑻𐑒 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑢𐑱 𐑝 𐑳𐑯𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑝𐑨𐑤𐑿. 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑚𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑷𐑔𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑟, 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑷𐑤𐑢𐑱𐑟 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑼𐑛 𐑩 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑕𐑑𐑢𐑻𐑞𐑦 𐑯 𐑳𐑯𐑦𐑜𐑟𐑨𐑡𐑼𐑱𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑹𐑾𐑯, 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑧𐑐𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑹 𐑑𐑵 𐑐𐑼𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑼𐑟, 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑩𐑓𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑥𐑨𐑑𐑼 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑛.

𐑯𐑬, 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑣𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑦 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟, ·𐑐𐑮𐑴𐑒𐑴𐑐𐑾𐑕 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑, 𐑛𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑑𐑻𐑥 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑮𐑰𐑓𐑧𐑒𐑗𐑼 𐑨𐑑 ·𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑴𐑐𐑩𐑤, 𐑩 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑕𐑰-𐑥𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑼 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑗𐑼𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑯𐑱𐑚𐑼𐑦𐑙 ·𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑐𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑕, 𐑹 ·𐑕𐑰 𐑝 ·𐑥𐑸𐑥𐑼𐑩, 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑣𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑶𐑛 𐑝𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼𐑟 𐑓 𐑩 𐑐𐑽𐑾𐑛 𐑝 𐑥𐑹 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑓𐑦𐑓𐑑𐑦 𐑘𐑽𐑟. 𐑩 𐑓𐑨𐑒𐑑 𐑞𐑳𐑕 𐑕𐑧𐑑 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑤 𐑣𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑦 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑰𐑟𐑦𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑰 𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑕𐑧𐑛. 𐑯𐑹 𐑦𐑟 𐑞𐑺 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑮𐑰𐑟𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑑 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑚𐑰. 𐑝 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑲𐑕 𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑖𐑰𐑟 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑕𐑰-𐑥𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑼 𐑢𐑪𐑟, 𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑛. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑶𐑛 𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑕, 𐑨𐑟 𐑢𐑧𐑤 𐑨𐑟 𐑓 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑮𐑰𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑟, 𐑣𐑰 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑩 𐑢𐑱𐑤; 𐑯 𐑲 𐑨𐑥 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑪𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑤𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑑 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒 𐑩 𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 𐑢𐑱𐑤. 𐑯 𐑲 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑑𐑧𐑤 𐑿 𐑢𐑲. 𐑓 𐑩 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑲 𐑓𐑨𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑷𐑤𐑢𐑱𐑟 𐑳𐑯𐑯𐑴𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑥𐑧𐑛𐑦𐑑𐑼𐑱𐑯𐑾𐑯 𐑯 𐑞 𐑛𐑰𐑐 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼𐑟 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑦𐑑. 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑯𐑬 𐑲 𐑨𐑥 𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑕𐑰𐑟 𐑸 𐑯𐑪𐑑, 𐑯 𐑐𐑼𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑕 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑚𐑰, 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑑𐑿𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑟, 𐑩 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕 𐑓 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑩𐑚𐑦𐑗𐑵𐑩𐑤 𐑜𐑮𐑦𐑜𐑺𐑾𐑕 𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑹𐑑. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑓𐑻𐑞𐑼 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑜𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑮𐑰𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑮𐑵𐑝𐑛 𐑑 𐑥𐑰, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑪𐑛𐑼𐑯 𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑞𐑺 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑲𐑕𐑩𐑤𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑥𐑧𐑛𐑦𐑑𐑼𐑱𐑯𐑾𐑯. 𐑲 𐑨𐑥 𐑑𐑴𐑤𐑛, 𐑪𐑯 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑷𐑔𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑦, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑚𐑸𐑚𐑸𐑦 𐑒𐑴𐑕𐑑, 𐑩 ·𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑛𐑹 ·𐑛𐑱𐑝𐑦𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑚𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑖 𐑯𐑱𐑝𐑦 𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑞 𐑕𐑒𐑧𐑤𐑩𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑩 𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 𐑢𐑱𐑤. 𐑯𐑬, 𐑨𐑟 𐑩 𐑝𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑢𐑹 𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑭𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑞 ·𐑛𐑸𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑧𐑤𐑟, 𐑣𐑧𐑯𐑕 𐑩 𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑒𐑫𐑛, 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑮𐑵𐑑, 𐑐𐑭𐑕 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑥𐑧𐑛𐑦𐑑𐑼𐑱𐑯𐑾𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑐𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑕.

𐑦𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑐𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑕, 𐑨𐑟 𐑓𐑸 𐑨𐑟 𐑲 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑤𐑻𐑯, 𐑯𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑽 𐑕𐑳𐑚𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑛 ·𐑚𐑮𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛, 𐑞 𐑭𐑤𐑦𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑮𐑲𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑤. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑮𐑰𐑟𐑩𐑯 𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑰𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑓𐑵𐑛 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 𐑢𐑱𐑤—𐑕𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑛 𐑹 𐑒𐑳𐑑𐑩𐑤-𐑓𐑦𐑖—𐑤𐑻𐑒𐑕 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑚𐑪𐑑𐑩𐑥 𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑰, 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑪𐑟 𐑤𐑸𐑡 𐑒𐑮𐑰𐑗𐑼𐑟, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑯𐑴 𐑥𐑰𐑯𐑟 𐑞 𐑤𐑸𐑡𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑹𐑑, 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑕𐑻𐑓𐑦𐑕. 𐑦𐑓, 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑿 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑐𐑼𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑫𐑑 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑑𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑑𐑩𐑜𐑧𐑞𐑼, 𐑯 𐑮𐑰𐑟𐑩𐑯 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑩 𐑚𐑦𐑑, 𐑿 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑒𐑤𐑽𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑼𐑕𐑰𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑, 𐑩𐑒𐑹𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑣𐑿𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑮𐑰𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑙, ·𐑐𐑮𐑴𐑒𐑴𐑐𐑾𐑕'𐑩𐑟 𐑕𐑰-𐑥𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑼, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑓 𐑣𐑭𐑓 𐑩 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑗𐑼𐑦 𐑕𐑑𐑴𐑝 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑕 𐑝 𐑩 ·𐑮𐑴𐑥𐑩𐑯 ·𐑧𐑥𐑐𐑼𐑼, 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑚𐑩𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑩 𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 𐑢𐑱𐑤.

·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 46. 𐑕𐑼𐑥𐑲𐑟𐑩𐑟.

𐑞𐑴, 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑿𐑥𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑣𐑪𐑑 𐑓𐑲𐑼 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑻𐑐𐑩𐑕, ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑦𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑔𐑷𐑑𐑕 𐑯 𐑨𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑝𐑿 𐑞 𐑳𐑤𐑑𐑦𐑥𐑩𐑑 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑗𐑼 𐑝 ·𐑥𐑪𐑚𐑦 ·𐑛𐑦𐑒; 𐑞𐑴 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑦 𐑑 𐑕𐑨𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑓𐑲𐑕 𐑷𐑤 𐑥𐑹𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑩𐑕𐑑𐑕 𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑐𐑭𐑖𐑩𐑯; 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼𐑞𐑩𐑤𐑧𐑕 𐑦𐑑 𐑥𐑱 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑚𐑲 𐑯𐑱𐑗𐑼 𐑯 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑣𐑩𐑚𐑦𐑗𐑵𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑓𐑸 𐑑𐑵 𐑢𐑧𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑑 𐑩 𐑓𐑲𐑼𐑦 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑥𐑩𐑯'𐑟 𐑢𐑱𐑟, 𐑷𐑤𐑑𐑩𐑜𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑑 𐑩𐑚𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑯 𐑞 𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑨𐑑𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑝𐑶𐑦𐑡. 𐑹 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑰𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑓 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑻 𐑳𐑞𐑼𐑢𐑲𐑟, 𐑞𐑺 𐑢𐑻 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑥𐑴𐑑𐑦𐑝𐑟 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑥𐑹 𐑦𐑯𐑓𐑤𐑵𐑧𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑥. 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑚𐑰 𐑮𐑦𐑓𐑲𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑑𐑵 𐑥𐑳𐑗, 𐑐𐑼𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑕, 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑪𐑯𐑩𐑥𐑱𐑯𐑾, 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑯𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑝𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑝𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑑𐑩𐑢𐑹𐑛𐑟 𐑞 ·𐑢𐑲𐑑 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑐𐑪𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑑𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑛𐑦𐑜𐑮𐑰 𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟, 𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑥𐑹 𐑥𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑤𐑵 𐑚𐑲 𐑕𐑴 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑞 𐑥𐑹 𐑣𐑰 𐑥𐑳𐑤𐑑𐑦𐑐𐑤𐑲𐑛 𐑞 𐑗𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑰𐑗 𐑕𐑳𐑚𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑢𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑛 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑐𐑮𐑵𐑝 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑞 𐑣𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑓 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩𐑯 𐑣𐑲𐑐𐑪𐑔𐑦𐑕𐑦𐑕 𐑚𐑰 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑰𐑛 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑧𐑐𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤, 𐑞𐑺 𐑢𐑻 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑩𐑛𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑼𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑗, 𐑞𐑴 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑴 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑩𐑒𐑹𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑢𐑲𐑤𐑛𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑮𐑵𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑐𐑭𐑖𐑩𐑯, 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑢𐑻 𐑚𐑲 𐑯𐑴 𐑥𐑰𐑯𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑱𐑐𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑕𐑢𐑱𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑥.

𐑑 𐑩𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑦𐑖 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑪𐑚𐑡𐑧𐑒𐑑 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑿𐑟 𐑑𐑵𐑤𐑟; 𐑯 𐑝 𐑷𐑤 𐑑𐑵𐑤𐑟 𐑿𐑟𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑖𐑨𐑛𐑴 𐑝 𐑞 𐑥𐑵𐑯, 𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑸 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑨𐑐𐑑 𐑑 𐑜𐑧𐑑 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑹𐑛𐑼. 𐑣𐑰 𐑯𐑿, 𐑓 𐑦𐑜𐑟𐑭𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑤, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑬𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑥𐑨𐑜𐑯𐑧𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑩𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑕 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑴𐑝𐑼 ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒, 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑩𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑒𐑳𐑝𐑼 𐑞 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑰𐑑 𐑕𐑐𐑦𐑮𐑦𐑗𐑵𐑩𐑤 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑥𐑹 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑥𐑽 𐑒𐑹𐑐𐑹𐑾𐑤 𐑕𐑵𐑐𐑽𐑦𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑪𐑤𐑝𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑧𐑒𐑗𐑵𐑩𐑤 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑖𐑦𐑐; 𐑓 𐑑 𐑞 𐑐𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑐𐑦𐑮𐑦𐑗𐑵𐑩𐑤, 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑧𐑒𐑗𐑵𐑩𐑤 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑕𐑹𐑑 𐑝 𐑒𐑹𐑐𐑹𐑾𐑤 𐑮𐑦𐑤𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯. 𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒'𐑕 𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦 𐑯 ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒'𐑕 𐑒𐑴𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑢𐑻 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚'𐑟, 𐑕𐑴 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑨𐑟 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑒𐑧𐑐𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑨𐑜𐑯𐑩𐑑 𐑨𐑑 ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒'𐑕 𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑯; 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑣𐑰 𐑯𐑿 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑓 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑞 𐑗𐑰𐑓 𐑥𐑱𐑑, 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑴𐑤, 𐑩𐑚𐑣𐑹𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯'𐑟 𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑕𐑑, 𐑯 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑣𐑰, 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑡𐑶𐑓𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑦𐑑, 𐑹 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑳𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑦𐑑. 𐑦𐑑 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑩 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑝𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑦𐑤𐑨𐑐𐑕 𐑺 𐑞 ·𐑢𐑲𐑑 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑰𐑯. 𐑛𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑝𐑩𐑤 ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑚𐑰 𐑨𐑐𐑑 𐑑 𐑓𐑷𐑤 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑴𐑐𐑩𐑯 𐑮𐑦𐑤𐑨𐑐𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑝 𐑮𐑦𐑚𐑧𐑤𐑘𐑩𐑯 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯'𐑟 𐑤𐑰𐑛𐑼𐑖𐑦𐑐, 𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑧𐑕 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑹𐑛𐑦𐑯𐑼𐑦, 𐑐𐑮𐑵𐑛𐑧𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑤, 𐑕𐑻𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑯𐑓𐑤𐑵𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑚𐑮𐑷𐑑 𐑑 𐑚𐑺 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥. 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑞𐑨𐑑, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑝 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑙 ·𐑥𐑪𐑚𐑦 ·𐑛𐑦𐑒 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑴𐑢𐑱𐑟 𐑥𐑹 𐑕𐑦𐑜𐑯𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑥𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑓𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑵𐑐𐑻𐑤𐑩𐑑𐑦𐑝 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑕 𐑯 𐑖𐑮𐑵𐑛𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑓𐑹𐑕𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑨𐑑, 𐑓 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑑, 𐑞 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑑 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑢𐑱 𐑚𐑰 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑑 𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡 𐑦𐑥𐑨𐑡𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑑𐑦𐑝 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑲𐑩𐑕𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑯𐑨𐑗𐑼𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑑; 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑓𐑫𐑤 𐑑𐑧𐑮𐑼 𐑝 𐑞 𐑝𐑶𐑦𐑡 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑒𐑧𐑐𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑛𐑮𐑷𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑩𐑚𐑕𐑒𐑘𐑫𐑼 𐑚𐑨𐑒𐑜𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 (𐑓 𐑓𐑿 𐑥𐑧𐑯'𐑟 𐑒𐑳𐑮𐑦𐑡 𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑮𐑵𐑓 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑴𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑥𐑧𐑛𐑦𐑑𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑳𐑯𐑮𐑦𐑤𐑰𐑝𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑨𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯); 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑞𐑱 𐑕𐑑𐑫𐑛 𐑞𐑺 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑯𐑲𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑗𐑩𐑟, 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑪𐑓𐑦𐑕𐑼𐑟 𐑯 𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑯𐑽𐑼 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑑 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒 𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑯 ·𐑥𐑪𐑚𐑦 ·𐑛𐑦𐑒. 𐑓 𐑣𐑬𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑰𐑜𐑼𐑤𐑦 𐑯 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑧𐑗𐑵𐑩𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑞 𐑕𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑡 𐑒𐑮𐑵 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑣𐑱𐑤𐑛 𐑞 𐑩𐑯𐑬𐑯𐑕𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑕𐑑; 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑼𐑟 𐑝 𐑷𐑤 𐑕𐑹𐑑𐑕 𐑸 𐑥𐑹 𐑹 𐑤𐑧𐑕 𐑒𐑩𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑕 𐑯 𐑳𐑯𐑮𐑦𐑤𐑲𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤—𐑞𐑱 𐑤𐑦𐑝 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑝𐑺𐑦𐑦𐑙 𐑬𐑑𐑼 𐑢𐑧𐑞𐑼, 𐑯 𐑞𐑱 𐑦𐑯𐑣𐑱𐑤 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑓𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑯𐑩𐑕—𐑯 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑱𐑯𐑛 𐑓 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑪𐑚𐑡𐑧𐑒𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑴𐑑 𐑯 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑙𐑒 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑐𐑼𐑕𐑿𐑑, 𐑣𐑬𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑼𐑦 𐑝 𐑤𐑲𐑓 𐑯 𐑐𐑭𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑧𐑯𐑛, 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑩𐑚𐑳𐑝 𐑷𐑤 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑟𐑦𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑑𐑧𐑥𐑐𐑼𐑼𐑦 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑩𐑕𐑑𐑕 𐑯 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑶𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑝𐑰𐑯 𐑯 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑔𐑦𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑩𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑓 𐑞 𐑓𐑲𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑛𐑨𐑖.

𐑯𐑹 𐑢𐑪𐑟 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑳𐑯𐑥𐑲𐑯𐑛𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑩𐑯𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑔𐑦𐑙. 𐑦𐑯 𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑝 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑪𐑙 𐑦𐑥𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑥𐑨𐑯𐑒𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑛𐑱𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑚𐑱𐑕 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑼𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑸 𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑯𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑑. 𐑞 𐑐𐑻𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑑𐑿𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑥𐑨𐑯𐑿𐑓𐑨𐑒𐑗𐑼𐑛 𐑥𐑨𐑯, 𐑔𐑷𐑑 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚, 𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑹𐑛𐑦𐑛𐑯𐑩𐑕. 𐑜𐑮𐑭𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑢𐑲𐑑 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑓𐑫𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑲𐑑𐑕 𐑞 𐑣𐑸𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑥𐑲 𐑕𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑡 𐑒𐑮𐑵, 𐑯 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑦𐑙 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑞𐑺 𐑕𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑡𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑚𐑮𐑰𐑛𐑟 𐑩 𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑕 𐑯𐑲𐑑-𐑻𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑟𐑩𐑥 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑥, 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤, 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑓 𐑞 𐑤𐑳𐑝 𐑝 𐑦𐑑 𐑞𐑱 𐑜𐑦𐑝 𐑗𐑱𐑕 𐑑 ·𐑥𐑪𐑚𐑦 ·𐑛𐑦𐑒, 𐑞𐑱 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑷𐑤𐑕𐑴 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑓𐑵𐑛 𐑓 𐑞𐑺 𐑥𐑹 𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑯, 𐑛𐑱𐑤𐑦 𐑨𐑐𐑩𐑑𐑲𐑑𐑕. 𐑓 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑞 𐑣𐑲 𐑤𐑦𐑓𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑯 𐑖𐑦𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑮𐑦𐑒 ·𐑒𐑮𐑵𐑕𐑱𐑛𐑼𐑟 𐑝 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑑 𐑑𐑮𐑩𐑝𐑻𐑕 𐑑𐑵 𐑔𐑬𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑥𐑲𐑤𐑟 𐑝 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑑 𐑓𐑲𐑑 𐑓 𐑞𐑺 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑧𐑐𐑩𐑤𐑒𐑼, 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑻𐑜𐑤𐑼𐑦𐑟, 𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑐𐑪𐑒𐑩𐑑𐑕, 𐑯 𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑐𐑲𐑩𐑕 𐑐𐑻𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑟𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑢𐑱. 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑞𐑱 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑛 𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑓𐑲𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑯 𐑮𐑴𐑥𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑪𐑚𐑡𐑧𐑒𐑑—𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑓𐑲𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑯 𐑮𐑴𐑥𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑪𐑚𐑡𐑧𐑒𐑑, 𐑑𐑵 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑦𐑯 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑜𐑳𐑕𐑑. 𐑲 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑐 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑥𐑧𐑯, 𐑔𐑷𐑑 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚, 𐑝 𐑷𐑤 𐑣𐑴𐑐𐑕 𐑝 𐑒𐑨𐑖—𐑲, 𐑒𐑨𐑖. 𐑞𐑱 𐑥𐑱 𐑕𐑒𐑹𐑯 𐑒𐑨𐑖 𐑯𐑬; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑤𐑧𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑥𐑳𐑯𐑔𐑕 𐑜𐑴 𐑚𐑲, 𐑯 𐑯𐑴 𐑐𐑼𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑝 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑥𐑦𐑕 𐑝 𐑦𐑑 𐑑 𐑞𐑧𐑥, 𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑒𐑢𐑲𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑒𐑨𐑖 𐑷𐑤 𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑕 𐑥𐑿𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑥, 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑒𐑨𐑖 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑕𐑵𐑯 𐑒𐑨𐑖𐑽 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚.

𐑯𐑹 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞𐑺 𐑢𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑩𐑯𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑷𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑼𐑦 𐑥𐑴𐑑𐑦𐑝 𐑥𐑹 𐑮𐑦𐑤𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑑 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑐𐑻𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑤𐑦. 𐑣𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑳𐑤𐑕𐑦𐑝𐑤𐑦, 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑚𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤, 𐑯 𐑐𐑼𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑕 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑥𐑩𐑗𐑫𐑼𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑦𐑝𐑰𐑤𐑛 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑲𐑥 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑲𐑝𐑩𐑑 𐑐𐑻𐑐𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛'𐑟 𐑝𐑶𐑦𐑡, ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑬 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑲𐑼𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑕 𐑞𐑨𐑑, 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑴 𐑛𐑵𐑦𐑙, 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑤𐑱𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑴𐑐𐑩𐑯 𐑑 𐑞 𐑳𐑯𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑼𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑗𐑸𐑡 𐑝 𐑿𐑟𐑻𐑐𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯; 𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑐𐑻𐑓𐑦𐑒𐑑 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑿𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑦, 𐑚𐑴𐑔 𐑥𐑪𐑮𐑩𐑤 𐑯 𐑤𐑰𐑜𐑩𐑤, 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑮𐑵 𐑦𐑓 𐑕𐑴 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑴𐑟𐑛, 𐑯 𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑐𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑, 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑮𐑦𐑓𐑿𐑟 𐑷𐑤 𐑓𐑻𐑞𐑼 𐑴𐑚𐑰𐑛𐑾𐑯𐑕 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑯 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑞 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑭𐑯𐑛. 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑺𐑤𐑦 𐑣𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑿𐑑𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑿𐑟𐑻𐑐𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑐𐑪𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑢𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑝 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩 𐑕𐑩𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑜𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛, ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑝 𐑒𐑹𐑕 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑕 𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑑𐑧𐑒𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓. 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑑𐑧𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑴𐑯 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑛𐑪𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑱𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑯 𐑯 𐑣𐑸𐑑 𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛, 𐑚𐑨𐑒𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑩 𐑣𐑰𐑛𐑓𐑩𐑤, 𐑒𐑤𐑴𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑨𐑤𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑱𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑑 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑑 𐑨𐑑𐑥𐑩𐑕𐑓𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑒 𐑦𐑯𐑓𐑤𐑵𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑐𐑪𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑓 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑮𐑵 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑡𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑑.

𐑓 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑮𐑰𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑯 𐑳𐑞𐑼𐑟 𐑐𐑼𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑕 𐑑𐑵 𐑨𐑯𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑝𐑻𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑦𐑝𐑧𐑤𐑩𐑐𐑑 𐑣𐑽, ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑷 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑛𐑦𐑜𐑮𐑰 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑿 𐑑𐑮𐑵 𐑑 𐑞 𐑯𐑨𐑗𐑼𐑩𐑤, 𐑯𐑪𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑐𐑻𐑐𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛'𐑟 𐑝𐑶𐑦𐑡; 𐑩𐑚𐑟𐑻𐑝 𐑷𐑤 𐑒𐑳𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑥𐑼𐑦 𐑿𐑕𐑦𐑡𐑩𐑟; 𐑯 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑞𐑨𐑑, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑓𐑹𐑕 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑑 𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑯𐑕 𐑷𐑤 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑧𐑤 𐑯𐑴𐑯 𐑐𐑨𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑐𐑼𐑕𐑿𐑑 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑓𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑯.

𐑚𐑰 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑥𐑱, 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑝𐑶𐑕 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑬 𐑪𐑓𐑩𐑯 𐑣𐑻𐑛 𐑣𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑-𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑟 𐑯 𐑨𐑛𐑥𐑪𐑯𐑦𐑖𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑑 𐑒𐑰𐑐 𐑩 𐑚𐑮𐑲𐑑 𐑤𐑫𐑒-𐑬𐑑, 𐑯 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑴𐑥𐑦𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑹𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑩 𐑐𐑹𐑐𐑩𐑕. 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑝𐑦𐑡𐑦𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑢𐑹𐑛.

·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 47. 𐑞 ·𐑥𐑨𐑑-·𐑥𐑱𐑒𐑼.

𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩 𐑒𐑤𐑬𐑛𐑦, 𐑕𐑳𐑤𐑑𐑮𐑦 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼𐑯𐑵𐑯; 𐑞 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑢𐑻 𐑤𐑱𐑟𐑦𐑤𐑦 𐑤𐑬𐑯𐑡𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑒𐑕, 𐑹 𐑝𐑱𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑜𐑱𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑤𐑧𐑛-𐑒𐑳𐑤𐑼𐑛 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼𐑟. ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜 𐑯 𐑲 𐑢𐑻 𐑥𐑲𐑤𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑶𐑛 𐑢𐑰𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑛 𐑩 𐑕𐑹𐑛-𐑥𐑨𐑑, 𐑓 𐑩𐑯 𐑩𐑛𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑤𐑨𐑖𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑬𐑼 𐑚𐑴𐑑. 𐑕𐑴 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑯 𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑛𐑿𐑛 𐑯 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑣𐑬 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑤𐑿𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑕𐑰𐑯, 𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑮𐑧𐑝𐑼𐑦 𐑤𐑻𐑒𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑺, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑰𐑗 𐑕𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑼 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑪𐑤𐑝𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑴𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑦𐑟𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓.

𐑲 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞 𐑩𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑹 𐑐𐑱𐑡 𐑝 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜, 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑚𐑦𐑟𐑦 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑥𐑨𐑑. 𐑨𐑟 𐑲 𐑒𐑧𐑐𐑑 𐑐𐑭𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑯 𐑮𐑰𐑐𐑭𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑓𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑹 𐑢𐑵𐑓 𐑝 𐑥𐑸𐑤𐑲𐑯 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑢𐑰𐑯 𐑞 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑘𐑸𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑹𐑐, 𐑿𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑲 𐑴𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑓 𐑞 𐑖𐑳𐑑𐑩𐑤, 𐑯 𐑨𐑟 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜, 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑲𐑛𐑢𐑱𐑟, 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑯 𐑩𐑯𐑪𐑯 𐑕𐑤𐑦𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑧𐑝𐑦 𐑴𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑕𐑹𐑛 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑢𐑰𐑯 𐑞 𐑔𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑟, 𐑯 𐑲𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑪𐑓 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼, 𐑒𐑺𐑤𐑩𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑯 𐑳𐑯𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑮𐑴𐑝 𐑣𐑴𐑥 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑘𐑸𐑯: 𐑲 𐑕𐑱 𐑕𐑴 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡 𐑩 𐑛𐑮𐑰𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑞𐑺 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑮𐑱𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑞 𐑕𐑰, 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑮𐑴𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑥𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑛𐑳𐑤 𐑕𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑹𐑛, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑓 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑻 𐑞 ·𐑤𐑵𐑥 𐑝 ·𐑑𐑲𐑥, 𐑯 𐑲 𐑥𐑲𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑢𐑻 𐑩 𐑖𐑳𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑥𐑦𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑦 𐑢𐑰𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑯 𐑢𐑰𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑢𐑱 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑓𐑱𐑑𐑕. 𐑞𐑺 𐑤𐑱 𐑞 𐑓𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑑 𐑔𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑹𐑐 𐑕𐑳𐑚𐑡𐑧𐑒𐑑 𐑑 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑕𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑩𐑤, 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑙, 𐑳𐑯𐑗𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑦𐑙 𐑝𐑲𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯, 𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑝𐑲𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑥𐑽𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑯𐑳𐑓 𐑑 𐑩𐑛𐑥𐑦𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑪𐑕𐑢𐑲𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑚𐑤𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑔𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑴𐑯. 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑹𐑐 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑯𐑦𐑕𐑧𐑕𐑦𐑑𐑦; 𐑯 𐑣𐑽, 𐑔𐑷𐑑 𐑲, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑥𐑲 𐑴𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑲 𐑐𐑤𐑲 𐑥𐑲 𐑴𐑯 𐑖𐑳𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑯 𐑢𐑰𐑝 𐑥𐑲 𐑴𐑯 𐑛𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑦 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑳𐑯𐑷𐑤𐑑𐑼𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑔𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑟. 𐑥𐑰𐑯𐑑𐑲𐑥, ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜'𐑟 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑳𐑤𐑕𐑦𐑝, 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑓𐑼𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑕𐑹𐑛, 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑢𐑵𐑓 𐑕𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦, 𐑹 𐑒𐑮𐑫𐑒𐑩𐑛𐑤𐑦, 𐑹 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑪𐑙𐑤𐑦, 𐑹 𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑤𐑦, 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑒𐑱𐑕 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑚𐑰; 𐑯 𐑚𐑲 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑛𐑦𐑓𐑼𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑒𐑤𐑵𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑤𐑴 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑛𐑿𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑒𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑪𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑲𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑨𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑰𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑓𐑨𐑚𐑮𐑦𐑒; 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑕𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑡'𐑩𐑟 𐑕𐑹𐑛, 𐑔𐑷𐑑 𐑲, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑞𐑳𐑕 𐑓𐑲𐑯𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑖𐑱𐑐𐑕 𐑯 𐑓𐑨𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑚𐑴𐑔 𐑢𐑹𐑐 𐑯 𐑢𐑵𐑓; 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑰𐑟𐑦, 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑓𐑼𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑕𐑹𐑛 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑗𐑭𐑯𐑕—𐑲, 𐑗𐑭𐑯𐑕, 𐑓𐑮𐑰 𐑢𐑦𐑤, 𐑯 𐑯𐑦𐑕𐑧𐑕𐑦𐑑𐑦—𐑯𐑴𐑢𐑲𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑨𐑑𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤—𐑷𐑤 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑢𐑰𐑝𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑢𐑻𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑑𐑩𐑜𐑧𐑞𐑼. 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑢𐑹𐑐 𐑝 𐑯𐑦𐑕𐑧𐑕𐑦𐑑𐑦, 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑕𐑢𐑻𐑝𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑳𐑤𐑑𐑦𐑥𐑩𐑑 𐑒𐑹𐑕—𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑷𐑤𐑑𐑼𐑯𐑱𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑝𐑲𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯, 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑰𐑛, 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑; 𐑓𐑮𐑰 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑓𐑮𐑰 𐑑 𐑐𐑤𐑲 𐑣𐑻 𐑖𐑳𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑢𐑰𐑯 𐑜𐑦𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑔𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑟; 𐑯 𐑗𐑭𐑯𐑕, 𐑞𐑴 𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑐𐑤𐑱 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑮𐑲𐑑 𐑤𐑲𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑯𐑦𐑕𐑧𐑕𐑦𐑑𐑦, 𐑯 𐑕𐑲𐑛𐑢𐑱𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑥𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑛𐑦𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑓𐑮𐑰 𐑢𐑦𐑤, 𐑞𐑴 𐑞𐑳𐑕 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑚𐑛 𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑚𐑴𐑔, 𐑗𐑭𐑯𐑕 𐑚𐑲 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑟 𐑮𐑵𐑤𐑟 𐑲𐑞𐑼, 𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑓𐑰𐑗𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑤𐑴 𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑝𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑕.

𐑞𐑳𐑕 𐑢𐑰 𐑢𐑻 𐑢𐑰𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑯 𐑢𐑰𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑢𐑱 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑲 𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑨𐑑 𐑩 𐑕𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑕𐑴 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡, 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑛𐑮𐑷𐑯, 𐑯 𐑥𐑿𐑟𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑦 𐑢𐑲𐑤𐑛 𐑯 𐑳𐑯𐑻𐑔𐑤𐑦, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑚𐑷𐑤 𐑝 𐑓𐑮𐑰 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑛𐑮𐑪𐑐𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑥𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛, 𐑯 𐑲 𐑕𐑑𐑫𐑛 𐑜𐑱𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑳𐑐 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑒𐑤𐑬𐑛𐑟 𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑕 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑝𐑶𐑕 𐑛𐑮𐑪𐑐𐑑 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑢𐑦𐑙. 𐑣𐑲 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑓𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑪𐑕-𐑑𐑮𐑰𐑟 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑨𐑛 ·𐑜𐑱-·𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑼, ·𐑑𐑨𐑖𐑑𐑱𐑜𐑴. 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑮𐑰𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑰𐑜𐑼𐑤𐑦 𐑓𐑹𐑢𐑼𐑛, 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑧𐑗𐑑 𐑬𐑑 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑢𐑪𐑯𐑛, 𐑯 𐑨𐑑 𐑚𐑮𐑰𐑓 𐑕𐑳𐑛𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑿𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑟. 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑖𐑫𐑼 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑕𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑥𐑴𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑐𐑼𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑕 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑻𐑛 𐑷𐑤 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑞 𐑕𐑰𐑟, 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑛𐑟 𐑝 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑥𐑧𐑯'𐑟 𐑤𐑫𐑒-𐑬𐑑𐑕 𐑐𐑻𐑗𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑣𐑲 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑺; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑓𐑿 𐑝 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑤𐑳𐑙𐑟 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑩𐑒𐑳𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑥𐑛 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑒𐑮𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑛𐑦𐑮𐑲𐑝𐑛 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩 𐑥𐑸𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑒𐑱𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑨𐑟 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 ·𐑑𐑨𐑖𐑑𐑱𐑜𐑴 𐑞 ·𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑾𐑯'𐑟.

𐑨𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑑𐑫𐑛 𐑣𐑪𐑝𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑿 𐑣𐑭𐑓 𐑕𐑩𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑺, 𐑕𐑴 𐑢𐑲𐑤𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑯 𐑰𐑜𐑼𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑽𐑦𐑙 𐑑𐑩𐑢𐑹𐑛𐑟 𐑞 𐑣𐑼𐑲𐑟𐑩𐑯, 𐑿 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑔𐑷𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑓𐑩𐑑 𐑹 𐑕𐑰𐑼 𐑚𐑦𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑖𐑨𐑛𐑴𐑟 𐑝 ·𐑓𐑱𐑑, 𐑯 𐑚𐑲 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑢𐑲𐑤𐑛 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑟 𐑩𐑯𐑬𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑺 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑦𐑙.

“𐑞𐑺 𐑖𐑰 𐑚𐑤𐑴𐑟! 𐑞𐑺! 𐑞𐑺! 𐑞𐑺! 𐑖𐑰 𐑚𐑤𐑴𐑟! 𐑖𐑰 𐑚𐑤𐑴𐑟!”

“𐑢𐑺-𐑩𐑢𐑱?”

“𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑤𐑰-𐑚𐑰𐑥, 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑑𐑵 𐑥𐑲𐑤𐑟 𐑪𐑓! 𐑩 𐑕𐑒𐑵𐑤 𐑝 𐑞𐑧𐑥!”

𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑷𐑤 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯.

𐑞 ·𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑚𐑤𐑴𐑟 𐑨𐑟 𐑩 𐑒𐑤𐑪𐑒 𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑕, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑰𐑝𐑦𐑱𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑯 𐑮𐑦𐑤𐑲𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑿𐑯𐑦𐑓𐑹𐑥𐑦𐑑𐑦. 𐑯 𐑞𐑺𐑚𐑲 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑢𐑦𐑖 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑓𐑦𐑖 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑚𐑟 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑡𐑰𐑯𐑩𐑕.

“𐑞𐑺 𐑜𐑴 𐑓𐑤𐑵𐑒𐑕!” 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑬 𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑲 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 ·𐑑𐑨𐑖𐑑𐑱𐑜𐑴; 𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑩𐑐𐑽𐑛.

“𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑒, 𐑕𐑑𐑿𐑼𐑛!” 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚. “𐑑𐑲𐑥! 𐑑𐑲𐑥!”

𐑛𐑴-·𐑚𐑶 𐑣𐑳𐑮𐑦𐑛 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑴, 𐑜𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑢𐑪𐑗, 𐑯 𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑹𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑞 𐑦𐑜𐑟𐑨𐑒𐑑 𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑑 𐑑 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚.

𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑬 𐑒𐑧𐑐𐑑 𐑩𐑢𐑱 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛, 𐑯 𐑖𐑰 𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑴𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑦𐑑. ·𐑑𐑨𐑖𐑑𐑱𐑜𐑴 𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑹𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑜𐑪𐑯 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑤𐑰𐑢𐑼𐑛, 𐑢𐑰 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑓𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑑 𐑑 𐑕𐑰 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯 𐑛𐑦𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑯 𐑩𐑛𐑝𐑭𐑯𐑕 𐑝 𐑬𐑼 𐑚𐑬𐑟. 𐑓 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑿𐑤𐑼 𐑒𐑮𐑭𐑓𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑢𐑧𐑯, 𐑕𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑛𐑦𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯, 𐑣𐑰 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼𐑞𐑩𐑤𐑧𐑕, 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑰𐑤𐑛 𐑚𐑦𐑯𐑰𐑔 𐑞 𐑕𐑻𐑓𐑦𐑕, 𐑥𐑦𐑤𐑟 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛, 𐑯 𐑕𐑢𐑦𐑓𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑢𐑦𐑥𐑟 𐑪𐑓 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑪𐑐𐑩𐑟𐑦𐑑 𐑒𐑢𐑹𐑑𐑼—𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑰𐑑𐑓𐑩𐑤𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑯𐑬 𐑚𐑰 𐑦𐑯 𐑨𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯; 𐑓 𐑞𐑺 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑴 𐑮𐑰𐑟𐑩𐑯 𐑑 𐑕𐑩𐑐𐑴𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑓𐑦𐑖 𐑕𐑰𐑯 𐑚𐑲 ·𐑑𐑨𐑖𐑑𐑱𐑜𐑴 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑢𐑱 𐑩𐑤𐑸𐑥𐑛, 𐑹 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑰𐑛 𐑯𐑿 𐑨𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑝 𐑬𐑼 𐑝𐑦𐑕𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑦. 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑕𐑦𐑤𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑓 𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑒𐑰𐑐𐑼𐑟—𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑟, 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑩𐑐𐑶𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑑 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕, 𐑚𐑲 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑮𐑦𐑤𐑰𐑝𐑛 𐑞 ·𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑾𐑯 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑥𐑱𐑯-𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑧𐑛. 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑼𐑟 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑓𐑹 𐑯 𐑥𐑦𐑟𐑩𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑛𐑬𐑯; 𐑞 𐑤𐑲𐑯 𐑑𐑳𐑚𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑓𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕𐑩𐑟; 𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑔𐑮𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑬𐑑; 𐑞 ·𐑥𐑱𐑯𐑘𐑸𐑛 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑚𐑨𐑒𐑑, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕 𐑕𐑢𐑳𐑙 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑞 𐑕𐑰 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑕𐑨𐑥𐑓𐑲𐑼 𐑚𐑭𐑕𐑒𐑩𐑑𐑕 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑣𐑲 𐑒𐑤𐑦𐑓𐑕. 𐑬𐑑𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑝 𐑞 𐑚𐑫𐑤𐑢𐑼𐑒𐑕 𐑞𐑺 𐑰𐑜𐑼 𐑒𐑮𐑵𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑒𐑤𐑳𐑙 𐑑 𐑞 𐑮𐑱𐑤, 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑓𐑫𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑶𐑟𐑛 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑜𐑳𐑯𐑩𐑤. 𐑕𐑴 𐑤𐑫𐑒 𐑞 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑤𐑲𐑯 𐑝 𐑥𐑨𐑯-𐑝-𐑢𐑹'𐑟 𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑑 𐑔𐑮𐑴 𐑞𐑧𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑝𐑟 𐑪𐑯 𐑚𐑹𐑛 𐑩𐑯 𐑧𐑯𐑩𐑥𐑦'𐑟 𐑖𐑦𐑐.

𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑩 𐑕𐑳𐑛𐑩𐑯 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑒𐑤𐑩𐑥𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑣𐑻𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑑𐑫𐑒 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑲 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤. 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑜𐑤𐑺𐑛 𐑨𐑑 𐑛𐑸𐑒 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚, 𐑣𐑵 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑼𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑓𐑲𐑝 𐑛𐑳𐑕𐑒𐑦 𐑓𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑥𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑖 𐑓𐑹𐑥𐑛 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑺.

·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 48. 𐑞 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 ·𐑤𐑴𐑼𐑦𐑙.

𐑞 𐑓𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑥𐑟, 𐑓 𐑕𐑴 𐑞𐑱 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛, 𐑢𐑻 𐑓𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑝 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑒, 𐑯, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑯𐑶𐑟𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑕𐑩𐑤𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑦, 𐑢𐑻 𐑒𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑤𐑵𐑕 𐑞 𐑑𐑨𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑯 𐑚𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑕𐑢𐑳𐑙 𐑞𐑺. 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑚𐑴𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑷𐑤𐑢𐑱𐑟 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑛𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑺 𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕, 𐑞𐑴 𐑑𐑧𐑒𐑯𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑛 𐑞 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯'𐑟, 𐑪𐑯 𐑩𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑣𐑨𐑙𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑼𐑛 𐑒𐑢𐑹𐑑𐑼. 𐑞 𐑓𐑦𐑜𐑼 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑯𐑬 𐑕𐑑𐑫𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑚𐑬𐑟 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑑𐑷𐑤 𐑯 𐑕𐑢𐑸𐑑, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑑𐑵𐑔 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑮𐑴𐑑𐑮𐑵𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑕𐑑𐑰𐑤-𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑤𐑦𐑐𐑕. 𐑩 𐑮𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑤𐑛 ·𐑗𐑲𐑯𐑰𐑟 𐑡𐑨𐑒𐑩𐑑 𐑝 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑒 𐑒𐑪𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑓𐑿𐑯𐑽𐑾𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑢𐑲𐑛 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑒 𐑑𐑮𐑴𐑟𐑼𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑛𐑸𐑒 𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑓. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑦𐑚𐑪𐑯𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩 𐑜𐑤𐑦𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑐𐑤𐑨𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑑𐑻𐑚𐑩𐑯, 𐑞 𐑤𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑺 𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑯 𐑒𐑶𐑤𐑛 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑯 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑧𐑛. 𐑤𐑧𐑕 𐑕𐑢𐑸𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑨𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑, 𐑞 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑨𐑯𐑘𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑓𐑦𐑜𐑼 𐑢𐑻 𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑝𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑛, 𐑑𐑲𐑜𐑼-𐑘𐑧𐑤𐑴 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑧𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑽 𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑝 𐑞 𐑨𐑚𐑼𐑦𐑡𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑯𐑱𐑑𐑦𐑝𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑤𐑩𐑟;—𐑩 𐑮𐑱𐑕 𐑯𐑴𐑑𐑹𐑾𐑕 𐑓 𐑩 𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑛𐑲𐑩𐑚𐑪𐑤𐑦𐑟𐑩𐑥 𐑝 𐑕𐑳𐑚𐑑𐑦𐑤𐑑𐑦, 𐑯 𐑚𐑲 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑪𐑯𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑥𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑯𐑼𐑟 𐑕𐑩𐑐𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑞 𐑐𐑱𐑛 𐑕𐑐𐑲𐑟 𐑯 𐑕𐑰𐑒𐑮𐑩𐑑 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑓𐑦𐑛𐑧𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑤 𐑱𐑡𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼 𐑝 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑤, 𐑞𐑺 𐑤𐑹𐑛, 𐑣𐑵𐑟 𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑙-𐑮𐑵𐑥 𐑞𐑱 𐑕𐑩𐑐𐑴𐑟 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑧𐑤𐑕𐑢𐑺.

𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑞 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑖𐑦𐑐'𐑕 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑦 𐑢𐑻 𐑜𐑱𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑼𐑟, ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 𐑬𐑑 𐑑 𐑞 𐑢𐑲𐑑-𐑑𐑻𐑚𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑣𐑧𐑛, “𐑷𐑤 𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑦 𐑞𐑺, ·𐑓𐑧𐑛𐑩𐑤𐑩?”

“𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑦,” 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞 𐑣𐑭𐑓-𐑣𐑦𐑕𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑤𐑲.

“𐑤𐑴𐑼 𐑩𐑢𐑱 𐑞𐑧𐑯; 𐑛'𐑘𐑰 𐑣𐑽?” 𐑖𐑬𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑒𐑮𐑪𐑕 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑒. “𐑤𐑴𐑼 𐑩𐑢𐑱 𐑞𐑺, 𐑲 𐑕𐑱.”

𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞 𐑔𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑝𐑶𐑕, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑐𐑲𐑑 𐑝 𐑞𐑺 𐑩𐑥𐑱𐑟𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑞 𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑨𐑙 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑞 𐑮𐑱𐑤; 𐑞 𐑖𐑰𐑝𐑟 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑤𐑪𐑒𐑕; 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑢𐑪𐑤𐑴, 𐑞 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕 𐑛𐑮𐑪𐑐𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑕𐑰; 𐑢𐑲𐑤, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑛𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑩𐑕, 𐑪𐑓-𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑛𐑺𐑦𐑙, 𐑳𐑯𐑯𐑴𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑝𐑴𐑒𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯, 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑼𐑟, 𐑜𐑴𐑑-𐑤𐑲𐑒, 𐑤𐑰𐑐𐑑 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑞 𐑮𐑴𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑖𐑦𐑐'𐑕 𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑑𐑪𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑴.

𐑣𐑸𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑞𐑱 𐑐𐑫𐑤𐑛 𐑬𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐'𐑕 𐑤𐑰, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑩 𐑓𐑹𐑔 𐑒𐑰𐑤, 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑢𐑼𐑛 𐑕𐑲𐑛, 𐑐𐑫𐑤𐑛 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑻𐑯, 𐑯 𐑖𐑴𐑛 𐑞 𐑓𐑲𐑝 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑼𐑟 𐑮𐑴𐑦𐑙 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚, 𐑣𐑵, 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑻𐑯, 𐑤𐑬𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑣𐑱𐑤𐑛 ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒, ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚, 𐑯 ·𐑓𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑒, 𐑑 𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑛 𐑞𐑧𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑝𐑟 𐑢𐑲𐑛𐑤𐑦, 𐑕𐑴 𐑨𐑟 𐑑 𐑒𐑳𐑝𐑼 𐑩 𐑤𐑸𐑡 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑨𐑯𐑕 𐑝 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑺 𐑲𐑟 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯 𐑮𐑦𐑝𐑩𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑢𐑸𐑑 ·𐑓𐑧𐑛𐑩𐑤𐑩 𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑮𐑵, 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑥𐑱𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕 𐑴𐑚𐑱𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑞 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑭𐑯𐑛.

“𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚?—” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒.

“𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑛 𐑘𐑹𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑝𐑟,” 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚; “𐑜𐑦𐑝 𐑢𐑱, 𐑷𐑤 𐑓𐑹 𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕. 𐑞𐑬, ·𐑓𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑒, 𐑐𐑫𐑤 𐑬𐑑 𐑥𐑹 𐑑 𐑤𐑰𐑢𐑼𐑛!”

“𐑲, 𐑲, 𐑕𐑻,” 𐑗𐑽𐑦𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 ·𐑒𐑦𐑙-·𐑐𐑴𐑕𐑑, 𐑕𐑢𐑰𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑽𐑦𐑙 𐑹. “𐑤𐑱 𐑚𐑨𐑒!” 𐑩𐑛𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑮𐑵. “𐑞𐑺!—𐑞𐑺!—𐑞𐑺 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯! 𐑞𐑺 𐑖𐑰 𐑚𐑤𐑴𐑟 𐑮𐑲𐑑 𐑩𐑣𐑧𐑛, 𐑚𐑶𐑟!—𐑤𐑱 𐑚𐑨𐑒!”

“𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑣𐑰𐑛 𐑘𐑪𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑘𐑧𐑤𐑴 𐑚𐑶𐑟, ·𐑸𐑒𐑦.”

“𐑴, 𐑲 𐑛𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑥𐑲𐑯𐑛 '𐑩𐑥, 𐑕𐑻,” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 ·𐑸𐑒𐑦; “𐑲 𐑯𐑿 𐑦𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑯𐑬. 𐑛𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑲 𐑣𐑽 '𐑩𐑥 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛? 𐑯 𐑛𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑲 𐑑𐑧𐑤 ·𐑒𐑱𐑚𐑩𐑒𐑴 𐑣𐑽 𐑝 𐑦𐑑? 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑱 𐑘𐑰, ·𐑒𐑱𐑚𐑩𐑒𐑴? 𐑞𐑱 𐑸 𐑕𐑑𐑴𐑩𐑢𐑱𐑟, ·𐑥𐑼 ·𐑓𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑒.”

“𐑐𐑫𐑤, 𐑐𐑫𐑤, 𐑥𐑲 𐑓𐑲𐑯 𐑣𐑸𐑑𐑕-𐑩𐑤𐑲𐑝; 𐑐𐑫𐑤, 𐑥𐑲 𐑗𐑦𐑤𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑯; 𐑐𐑫𐑤, 𐑥𐑲 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑟,” 𐑛𐑮𐑷𐑤𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑯 𐑕𐑵𐑞𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑲𐑛 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑮𐑵, 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑝 𐑣𐑵𐑥 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑖𐑴𐑛 𐑕𐑲𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑳𐑯𐑰𐑟𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑕. “𐑢𐑲 𐑛𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑿 𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑒 𐑘𐑹 𐑚𐑨𐑒𐑚𐑴𐑯𐑟, 𐑥𐑲 𐑚𐑶𐑟? 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑿 𐑕𐑑𐑺 𐑨𐑑? 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑘𐑪𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑚𐑴𐑑? 𐑑𐑳𐑑! 𐑞𐑱 𐑸 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑓𐑲𐑝 𐑥𐑹 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑑 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑐 𐑳𐑕—𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑥𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑢𐑺—𐑞 𐑥𐑹 𐑞 𐑥𐑧𐑮𐑽. 𐑐𐑫𐑤, 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑛𐑵 𐑐𐑫𐑤; 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑥𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑞 𐑚𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑑𐑴𐑯—𐑛𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑸 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑓𐑧𐑤𐑴𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑳𐑓. 𐑕𐑴, 𐑕𐑴; 𐑞𐑺 𐑿 𐑸 𐑯𐑬; 𐑞𐑨𐑑'𐑕 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑴𐑒 𐑓 𐑩 𐑔𐑬𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑐𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑟; 𐑞𐑨𐑑'𐑕 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑴𐑒 𐑑 𐑕𐑢𐑰𐑐 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑕! 𐑣𐑼𐑭 𐑓 𐑞 𐑜𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑒𐑳𐑐 𐑝 𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 𐑶𐑤, 𐑥𐑲 𐑣𐑽𐑴𐑟! 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑗𐑽𐑟, 𐑥𐑧𐑯—𐑷𐑤 𐑣𐑸𐑑𐑕 𐑩𐑤𐑲𐑝! 𐑰𐑟𐑦, 𐑰𐑟𐑦; 𐑛𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑣𐑳𐑮𐑦—𐑛𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑣𐑳𐑮𐑦. 𐑢𐑲 𐑛𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑿 𐑕𐑯𐑨𐑐 𐑘𐑹 𐑹𐑟, 𐑿 𐑮𐑭𐑕𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑟? 𐑚𐑲𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑔𐑦𐑙, 𐑿 𐑛𐑪𐑜𐑟! 𐑕𐑴, 𐑕𐑴, 𐑕𐑴, 𐑞𐑧𐑯:—𐑕𐑪𐑓𐑑𐑤𐑦, 𐑕𐑪𐑓𐑑𐑤𐑦! 𐑞𐑨𐑑'𐑕 𐑦𐑑—𐑞𐑨𐑑'𐑕 𐑦𐑑! 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑪𐑙. 𐑜𐑦𐑝 𐑢𐑱 𐑞𐑺, 𐑜𐑦𐑝 𐑢𐑱! 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑤 𐑓𐑧𐑗 𐑘𐑰, 𐑘𐑰 𐑮𐑨𐑜𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑓𐑦𐑯 𐑮𐑨𐑐𐑕𐑒𐑨𐑤𐑾𐑯𐑟; 𐑘𐑰 𐑸 𐑷𐑤 𐑩𐑕𐑤𐑰𐑐. 𐑕𐑑𐑪𐑐 𐑕𐑯𐑹𐑦𐑙, 𐑘𐑰 𐑕𐑤𐑰𐑐𐑼𐑟, 𐑯 𐑐𐑫𐑤. 𐑐𐑫𐑤, 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑘𐑰? 𐑐𐑫𐑤, 𐑒𐑭𐑯𐑑 𐑘𐑰? 𐑐𐑫𐑤, 𐑢𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑘𐑰? 𐑢𐑲 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑯𐑱𐑥 𐑝 𐑜𐑳𐑡𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑯 𐑡𐑦𐑯𐑡𐑼-𐑒𐑱𐑒𐑕 𐑛𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑘𐑰 𐑐𐑫𐑤?—𐑐𐑫𐑤 𐑯 𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑒 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑔𐑦𐑙! 𐑐𐑫𐑤, 𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑑 𐑘𐑹 𐑲𐑟 𐑬𐑑! 𐑣𐑽!” 𐑢𐑦𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑬𐑑 𐑞 𐑖𐑸𐑐 𐑯𐑲𐑓 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑜𐑻𐑛𐑩𐑤; “𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑥𐑳𐑞𐑼'𐑟 𐑕𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑘𐑰 𐑛𐑮𐑷 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑲𐑓, 𐑯 𐑐𐑫𐑤 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑚𐑤𐑱𐑛 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑢𐑰𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑑𐑰𐑔. 𐑞𐑨𐑑'𐑕 𐑦𐑑—𐑞𐑨𐑑'𐑕 𐑦𐑑. 𐑯𐑬 𐑘𐑰 𐑛𐑵 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑔𐑦𐑙; 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑕 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑦𐑑, 𐑥𐑲 𐑕𐑑𐑰𐑤-𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑕. 𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑑 𐑣𐑻—𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑑 𐑣𐑻, 𐑥𐑲 𐑕𐑦𐑤𐑝𐑼-𐑕𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑟! 𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑑 𐑣𐑻, 𐑥𐑸𐑤𐑦𐑙-𐑕𐑐𐑲𐑒𐑕!”

𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚'𐑟 𐑦𐑜𐑟𐑹𐑛𐑾𐑥 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑮𐑵 𐑦𐑟 𐑜𐑦𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑣𐑽 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑸𐑡, 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑪𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑮𐑭𐑞𐑼 𐑩 𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑽 𐑢𐑱 𐑝 𐑑𐑷𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑦𐑯 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑤, 𐑯 𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑳𐑤𐑒𐑱𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑮𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑡𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑮𐑴𐑦𐑙. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑿 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑩𐑐𐑴𐑟 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑻𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑲𐑟𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑓𐑤𐑵 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑛𐑬𐑯𐑮𐑲𐑑 𐑐𐑭𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑪𐑙𐑜𐑮𐑦𐑜𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯. 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑷𐑤; 𐑯 𐑞𐑺𐑦𐑯 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑗𐑰𐑓 𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑦𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑦. 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑕𐑱 𐑞 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑑𐑼𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑒 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑮𐑵, 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑑𐑴𐑯 𐑕𐑴 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑝 𐑓𐑳𐑯 𐑯 𐑓𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑦, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑦 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑕𐑴 𐑒𐑨𐑤𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑥𐑽𐑤𐑦 𐑨𐑟 𐑩 𐑕𐑐𐑲𐑕 𐑑 𐑞 𐑓𐑳𐑯, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑯𐑴 𐑹𐑟𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑣𐑽 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑒𐑢𐑽 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑩𐑒𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑 𐑐𐑫𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑓 𐑛𐑽 𐑤𐑲𐑓, 𐑯 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑐𐑫𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑓 𐑞 𐑥𐑽 𐑡𐑴𐑒 𐑝 𐑞 𐑔𐑦𐑙. 𐑚𐑦𐑕𐑲𐑛𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑑 𐑕𐑴 𐑰𐑟𐑦 𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓, 𐑕𐑴 𐑤𐑬𐑯𐑡𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑥𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑡𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑽𐑦𐑙-𐑹, 𐑯 𐑕𐑴 𐑚𐑮𐑷𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑜𐑱𐑐𐑑—𐑴𐑐𐑩𐑯-𐑥𐑬𐑞𐑛 𐑨𐑑 𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟—𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑥𐑽 𐑕𐑲𐑑 𐑝 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩 𐑘𐑷𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑭𐑯𐑛𐑼, 𐑚𐑲 𐑖𐑽 𐑓𐑹𐑕 𐑝 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑭𐑕𐑑, 𐑨𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑗𐑸𐑥 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑵. 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯, ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑪𐑛 𐑕𐑹𐑑 𐑝 𐑣𐑿𐑥𐑼𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑕, 𐑣𐑵𐑟 𐑡𐑪𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑕𐑴 𐑒𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑾𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑨𐑥𐑚𐑦𐑜𐑿𐑩𐑕, 𐑨𐑟 𐑑 𐑐𐑫𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑦𐑯𐑓𐑽𐑽𐑟 𐑪𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑜𐑸𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑥𐑨𐑑𐑼 𐑝 𐑴𐑚𐑱𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑧𐑥.

𐑦𐑯 𐑴𐑚𐑰𐑛𐑾𐑯𐑕 𐑑 𐑩 𐑕𐑲𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚, ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑬 𐑐𐑫𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑴𐑚𐑤𐑰𐑒𐑤𐑦 𐑩𐑒𐑮𐑪𐑕 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚'𐑟 𐑚𐑬; 𐑯 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑓 𐑩 𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑑 𐑹 𐑕𐑴 𐑞 𐑑𐑵 𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕 𐑢𐑻 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑯𐑽 𐑑 𐑰𐑗 𐑳𐑞𐑼, ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚 𐑣𐑱𐑤𐑛 𐑞 𐑥𐑱𐑑.

“·𐑥𐑼 ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒! 𐑤𐑸𐑚𐑼𐑛 𐑚𐑴𐑑 𐑞𐑺, 𐑩𐑣𐑶! 𐑩 𐑢𐑻𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑘𐑰, 𐑕𐑻, 𐑦𐑓 𐑘𐑰 𐑐𐑤𐑰𐑟!”

“𐑣𐑩𐑤𐑴!” 𐑮𐑩𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑛 ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒, 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑩 𐑕𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑯𐑗 𐑨𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑐𐑴𐑒; 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑻𐑯𐑩𐑕𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑼𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑻𐑡𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑮𐑵; 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑱𐑕 𐑕𐑧𐑑 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑓𐑤𐑦𐑯𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚'𐑟.

“𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒 𐑘𐑰 𐑝 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑘𐑧𐑤𐑴 𐑚𐑶𐑟, 𐑕𐑻!”

“𐑕𐑥𐑳𐑜𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑪𐑯 𐑚𐑹𐑛, 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑣𐑬, 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑛. (𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑪𐑙, 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑪𐑙, 𐑚𐑶𐑟!)” 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑢𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑼 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑮𐑵, 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑬𐑑 𐑤𐑬𐑛 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯: “𐑩 𐑕𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑦𐑟𐑯𐑩𐑕, ·𐑥𐑼 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚! (𐑕𐑰𐑞 𐑣𐑻, 𐑕𐑰𐑞 𐑣𐑻, 𐑥𐑲 𐑤𐑨𐑛𐑟!) 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑥𐑲𐑯𐑛, ·𐑥𐑼 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚, 𐑷𐑤 𐑓 𐑞 𐑚𐑧𐑕𐑑. 𐑤𐑧𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑘𐑹 𐑒𐑮𐑵 𐑐𐑫𐑤 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑪𐑙, 𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑤. (𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑙, 𐑥𐑲 𐑥𐑧𐑯, 𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑙!) 𐑞𐑺'𐑟 𐑣𐑪𐑜𐑟𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑟 𐑝 𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 𐑩𐑣𐑧𐑛, ·𐑥𐑼 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚, 𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑'𐑕 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑘𐑰 𐑒𐑱𐑥 𐑓. (𐑐𐑫𐑤, 𐑥𐑲 𐑚𐑶𐑟!) 𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥, 𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥'𐑟 𐑞 𐑐𐑤𐑱! 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑰𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑛𐑿𐑑𐑦; 𐑛𐑿𐑑𐑦 𐑯 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑓𐑦𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛.”

“𐑲, 𐑲, 𐑲 𐑔𐑷𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑥𐑳𐑗,” 𐑕𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑤𐑩𐑒𐑢𐑲𐑟𐑛 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕 𐑛𐑲𐑝𐑻𐑡𐑛, “𐑨𐑟 𐑕𐑵𐑯 𐑨𐑟 𐑲 𐑒𐑤𐑨𐑐𐑑 𐑲 𐑪𐑯 '𐑩𐑥, 𐑲 𐑔𐑷𐑑 𐑕𐑴. 𐑲, 𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑'𐑕 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑓, 𐑕𐑴 𐑪𐑓𐑩𐑯, 𐑨𐑟 ·𐑛𐑴-·𐑚𐑶 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑕𐑩𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑛. 𐑞𐑱 𐑢𐑻 𐑣𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑯 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑞𐑺. 𐑞 ·𐑢𐑲𐑑 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤'𐑟 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑚𐑪𐑑𐑩𐑥 𐑝 𐑦𐑑. 𐑢𐑧𐑤, 𐑢𐑧𐑤, 𐑕𐑴 𐑚𐑰 𐑦𐑑! 𐑒𐑭𐑯𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑐𐑑! 𐑷𐑤 𐑮𐑲𐑑! 𐑜𐑦𐑝 𐑢𐑱, 𐑥𐑧𐑯! 𐑦𐑑 𐑱𐑯𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑢𐑲𐑑 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑑-𐑛𐑱! 𐑜𐑦𐑝 𐑢𐑱!”

𐑯𐑬 𐑞 𐑨𐑛𐑝𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑬𐑑𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑖 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑼𐑟 𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩 𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑤𐑴𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑒, 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑳𐑯𐑮𐑰𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑩𐑢𐑱𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑩 𐑕𐑹𐑑 𐑝 𐑕𐑵𐑐𐑼𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑕 𐑩𐑥𐑱𐑟𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑝 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐'𐑕 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑦; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 ·𐑸𐑒𐑦'𐑟 𐑓𐑨𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑛 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑳𐑝𐑼𐑦 𐑣𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑐𐑮𐑰𐑝𐑾𐑕 𐑜𐑪𐑑 𐑩𐑚𐑮𐑷𐑛 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑞𐑧𐑥, 𐑞𐑴 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑰𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑒𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑕𐑥𐑷𐑤 𐑥𐑧𐑠𐑼 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑺𐑛 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑓 𐑞 𐑦𐑝𐑧𐑯𐑑. 𐑦𐑑 𐑑𐑫𐑒 𐑪𐑓 𐑞 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑰𐑥 𐑧𐑡 𐑝 𐑞𐑺 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼; 𐑯 𐑕𐑴 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑯 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚'𐑟 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑓𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑢𐑱 𐑝 𐑩𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑓 𐑞𐑺 𐑩𐑐𐑽𐑩𐑯𐑕, 𐑞𐑱 𐑢𐑻 𐑓 𐑞 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑓𐑮𐑰𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑕𐑵𐑐𐑼𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑕 𐑕𐑼𐑥𐑲𐑟𐑦𐑙𐑟; 𐑞𐑴 𐑞 𐑩𐑓𐑺 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑤𐑧𐑓𐑑 𐑩𐑚𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑮𐑵𐑥 𐑓 𐑷𐑤 𐑥𐑨𐑯𐑼 𐑝 𐑢𐑲𐑤𐑛 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑡𐑧𐑒𐑗𐑼𐑟 𐑨𐑟 𐑑 𐑛𐑸𐑒 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚'𐑟 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑲𐑕 𐑱𐑡𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑥𐑨𐑑𐑼 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑚𐑦𐑜𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑙. 𐑓 𐑥𐑰, 𐑲 𐑕𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑛 𐑞 𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑽𐑾𐑕 𐑖𐑨𐑛𐑴𐑟 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑕𐑰𐑯 𐑒𐑮𐑰𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑪𐑯 𐑚𐑹𐑛 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛 𐑛𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑛𐑦𐑥 ·𐑯𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑑 𐑛𐑷𐑯, 𐑨𐑟 𐑢𐑧𐑤 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑧𐑯𐑦𐑜𐑥𐑨𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑣𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑳𐑯𐑩𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 ·𐑦𐑤𐑲𐑡𐑩.

𐑥𐑰𐑯𐑑𐑲𐑥, ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚, 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑣𐑽𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑪𐑓𐑦𐑕𐑼𐑟, 𐑣𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑲𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑞 𐑓𐑻𐑞𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑢𐑼𐑛, 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑝 𐑞 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕; 𐑩 𐑕𐑻𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑕 𐑚𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑬 𐑐𐑴𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑩 𐑒𐑮𐑵 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑐𐑫𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑥. 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑑𐑲𐑜𐑼 𐑘𐑧𐑤𐑴 𐑒𐑮𐑰𐑗𐑼𐑟 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑷𐑤 𐑕𐑑𐑰𐑤 𐑯 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑚𐑴𐑯; 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑓𐑲𐑝 𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑐-𐑣𐑨𐑥𐑼𐑟 𐑞𐑱 𐑮𐑴𐑟 𐑯 𐑓𐑧𐑤 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑮𐑧𐑜𐑿𐑤𐑼 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑴𐑒𐑕 𐑝 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑧𐑙𐑔, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑐𐑽𐑦𐑪𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑞 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑣𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑚𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑶𐑤𐑼 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑩 ·𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑦𐑕𐑦𐑐𐑦 𐑕𐑑𐑰𐑥𐑼. 𐑨𐑟 𐑓 ·𐑓𐑧𐑛𐑩𐑤𐑩, 𐑣𐑵 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑰𐑯 𐑐𐑫𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑽 𐑹, 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑔𐑮𐑴𐑯 𐑩𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑒 𐑡𐑨𐑒𐑩𐑑, 𐑯 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑱𐑒𐑩𐑛 𐑗𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑣𐑴𐑤 𐑐𐑸𐑑 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦 𐑩𐑚𐑳𐑝 𐑞 𐑜𐑳𐑯𐑩𐑤, 𐑒𐑤𐑽𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑳𐑑 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑞 𐑷𐑤𐑑𐑼𐑯𐑱𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑛𐑦𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼𐑦 𐑣𐑼𐑲𐑟𐑩𐑯; 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑝 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑸𐑥, 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑓𐑧𐑯𐑕𐑼'𐑟, 𐑔𐑮𐑴𐑯 𐑣𐑭𐑓 𐑚𐑨𐑒𐑢𐑼𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑺, 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑓 𐑑 𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑚𐑨𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦 𐑑 𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑐; ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑰𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑦 𐑥𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑡𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑽𐑦𐑙 𐑹 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑔𐑬𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑚𐑴𐑑 𐑤𐑴𐑼𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑺 𐑞 ·𐑢𐑲𐑑 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑑𐑹𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥. 𐑷𐑤 𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑕 𐑞 𐑬𐑑𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑧𐑗𐑑 𐑸𐑥 𐑜𐑱𐑝 𐑩 𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑽 𐑥𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑱𐑯𐑛 𐑓𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑑, 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑'𐑕 𐑓𐑲𐑝 𐑹𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑕𐑰𐑯 𐑕𐑦𐑥𐑩𐑤𐑑𐑱𐑯𐑾𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑑. 𐑚𐑴𐑑 𐑯 𐑒𐑮𐑵 𐑕𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑰. 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑞 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑛 𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑮𐑽 𐑐𐑷𐑟𐑛 𐑪𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑢𐑱. 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑦𐑮𐑧𐑜𐑿𐑤𐑼𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑧𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑚𐑤𐑵, 𐑞𐑳𐑕 𐑜𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑯𐑴 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑻𐑯𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑑𐑴𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑥𐑵𐑝𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑, 𐑞𐑴 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑤𐑴𐑟𐑼 𐑝𐑦𐑕𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑦 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑩𐑚𐑟𐑻𐑝𐑛 𐑦𐑑.

“𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑤𐑫𐑒 𐑬𐑑 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑹𐑟!” 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒. “𐑞𐑬, ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜, 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑳𐑐!”

𐑯𐑦𐑥𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑙𐑦𐑙 𐑳𐑐 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑨𐑙𐑜𐑿𐑤𐑼 𐑮𐑱𐑟𐑛 𐑚𐑪𐑒𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑬, 𐑞 𐑕𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑡 𐑕𐑑𐑫𐑛 𐑦𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑑 𐑞𐑺, 𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑰𐑜𐑼 𐑲𐑟 𐑜𐑱𐑟𐑛 𐑪𐑓 𐑑𐑩𐑢𐑹𐑛𐑟 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑪𐑑 𐑢𐑺 𐑞 𐑗𐑱𐑕 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛. 𐑤𐑲𐑒𐑢𐑲𐑟 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑰𐑥 𐑕𐑑𐑻𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑 𐑢𐑺 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑷𐑤𐑕𐑴 𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑨𐑙𐑜𐑿𐑤𐑼𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑤𐑨𐑑𐑓𐑹𐑥𐑛 𐑤𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑜𐑳𐑯𐑩𐑤, ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑰𐑯 𐑒𐑵𐑤𐑦 𐑯 𐑩𐑛𐑮𐑶𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑨𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑑 𐑞 𐑡𐑻𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑑𐑪𐑕𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑗𐑦𐑐 𐑝 𐑩 𐑒𐑮𐑭𐑓𐑑, 𐑯 𐑕𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑲𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑝𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑤𐑵 𐑲 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑰.

𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑓𐑸 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑 ·𐑓𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑒'𐑕 𐑚𐑴𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑷𐑤𐑕𐑴 𐑤𐑲𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑮𐑧𐑔𐑤𐑩𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤; 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑭𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑤𐑩𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑑𐑪𐑐 𐑝 𐑞 𐑤𐑪𐑜𐑼𐑣𐑧𐑛, 𐑩 𐑕𐑑𐑬𐑑 𐑕𐑹𐑑 𐑝 𐑐𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑮𐑵𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑒𐑰𐑤, 𐑯 𐑮𐑲𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑑𐑵 𐑓𐑰𐑑 𐑩𐑚𐑳𐑝 𐑞 𐑤𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑻𐑯 𐑐𐑤𐑨𐑑𐑓𐑹𐑥. 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑿𐑟𐑛 𐑓 𐑒𐑨𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑤𐑲𐑯. 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑑𐑪𐑐 𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑥𐑹 𐑕𐑐𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑕 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑞 𐑐𐑭𐑥 𐑝 𐑩 𐑥𐑨𐑯'𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛, 𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩 𐑚𐑱𐑕 𐑨𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑, ·𐑓𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑒 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑐𐑻𐑗𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑-𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑝 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑕𐑳𐑙𐑒 𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑣𐑻 𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑒𐑕. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 ·𐑒𐑦𐑙-·𐑐𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑥𐑷𐑤 𐑯 𐑖𐑹𐑑, 𐑯 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 ·𐑒𐑦𐑙-·𐑐𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑓𐑫𐑤 𐑝 𐑩 𐑤𐑸𐑡 𐑯 𐑑𐑷𐑤 𐑨𐑥𐑚𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯, 𐑕𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑤𐑪𐑜𐑼𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛-𐑐𐑶𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑯𐑴 𐑥𐑰𐑯𐑟 𐑕𐑨𐑑𐑦𐑕𐑓𐑲 ·𐑒𐑦𐑙-·𐑐𐑴𐑕𐑑.

“𐑲 𐑒𐑭𐑯𐑑 𐑕𐑰 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑕𐑰𐑟 𐑪𐑓; 𐑑𐑦𐑐 𐑳𐑕 𐑳𐑐 𐑩𐑯 𐑹 𐑞𐑺, 𐑯 𐑤𐑧𐑑 𐑥𐑰 𐑪𐑯 𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑.”

𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕, ·𐑛𐑨𐑜𐑵, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑲𐑞𐑼 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑜𐑳𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑛𐑦 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑱, 𐑕𐑢𐑦𐑓𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑤𐑦𐑛 𐑭𐑓𐑑, 𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑦𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑝𐑪𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑽𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑤𐑪𐑓𐑑𐑦 𐑖𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑼𐑟 𐑓 𐑩 𐑐𐑧𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑤.

“𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑩 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑-𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑨𐑟 𐑧𐑯𐑦, 𐑕𐑻. 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑿 𐑥𐑬𐑯𐑑?”

“𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑲 𐑢𐑦𐑤, 𐑯 𐑔𐑨𐑙𐑒 𐑘𐑰 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑥𐑳𐑗, 𐑥𐑲 𐑓𐑲𐑯 𐑓𐑧𐑤𐑴; 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑲 𐑢𐑦𐑖 𐑿 𐑓𐑦𐑓𐑑𐑦 𐑓𐑰𐑑 𐑑𐑷𐑤𐑼.”

𐑢𐑺𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑐𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑰𐑑 𐑓𐑻𐑥𐑤𐑦 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑑𐑵 𐑪𐑐𐑩𐑟𐑦𐑑 𐑐𐑤𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑, 𐑞 𐑡𐑲𐑜𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑯𐑰𐑜𐑮𐑴, 𐑕𐑑𐑵𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤, 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑤𐑨𐑑 𐑐𐑭𐑥 𐑑 ·𐑓𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑒'𐑕 𐑓𐑫𐑑, 𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑐𐑫𐑑𐑦𐑙 ·𐑓𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑒'𐑕 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑻𐑕-𐑐𐑤𐑵𐑥𐑛 𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑯 𐑚𐑦𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑙 𐑨𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑑𐑪𐑕, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑛𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑩𐑕 𐑓𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑞 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑣𐑲 𐑯 𐑛𐑮𐑲 𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑖𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑼𐑟. 𐑯 𐑣𐑽 𐑢𐑪𐑟 ·𐑓𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑒 𐑯𐑬 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙, ·𐑛𐑨𐑜𐑵 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑤𐑦𐑓𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑸𐑥 𐑓𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑖𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑚𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑚𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑑 𐑤𐑰𐑯 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑛𐑦 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑚𐑲.

𐑨𐑑 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑩 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡 𐑕𐑲𐑑 𐑑 𐑞 𐑑𐑲𐑮𐑴 𐑑 𐑕𐑰 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑕 𐑣𐑨𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑿𐑛 𐑝 𐑳𐑯𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑕 𐑕𐑒𐑦𐑤 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑥𐑱𐑯𐑑𐑱𐑯 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑑 𐑐𐑪𐑕𐑗𐑼 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑴𐑑, 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑐𐑦𐑗𐑑 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑮𐑲𐑩𐑑𐑩𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑼𐑝𐑻𐑕 𐑯 𐑒𐑮𐑪𐑕-𐑮𐑳𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑰𐑟. 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑥𐑹 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡 𐑑 𐑕𐑰 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑜𐑦𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑻𐑗𐑑 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑤𐑪𐑜𐑼𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑦𐑑𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓, 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑕𐑻𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑲𐑑 𐑝 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 ·𐑓𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑒 𐑥𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑡𐑲𐑜𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑒 ·𐑛𐑨𐑜𐑵 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑥𐑹 𐑒𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑾𐑕; 𐑓 𐑕𐑩𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑒𐑵𐑤, 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑓𐑼𐑩𐑯𐑑, 𐑰𐑟𐑦, 𐑳𐑯𐑔𐑷𐑑 𐑝, 𐑚𐑸𐑚𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑒 𐑥𐑨𐑡𐑩𐑕𐑑𐑦, 𐑞 𐑯𐑴𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑯𐑰𐑜𐑮𐑴 𐑑 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑮𐑴𐑤 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑰 𐑣𐑸𐑥𐑴𐑯𐑾𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑲𐑯 𐑓𐑹𐑥. 𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑮𐑷𐑛 𐑚𐑨𐑒, 𐑓𐑤𐑨𐑒𐑕𐑩𐑯-𐑣𐑺𐑛 ·𐑓𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑒 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑩 𐑕𐑯𐑴-𐑓𐑤𐑱𐑒. 𐑞 𐑚𐑺𐑼 𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑑 𐑯𐑴𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑼 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑞 𐑮𐑲𐑛𐑼. 𐑞𐑴 𐑑𐑮𐑵𐑤𐑦 𐑝𐑦𐑝𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑕, 𐑑𐑿𐑥𐑳𐑤𐑗𐑵𐑩𐑕, 𐑪𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑕 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 ·𐑓𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑒 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑯𐑬 𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑥𐑐 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑕; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑨𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑣𐑰𐑝 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑣𐑰 𐑞𐑺𐑚𐑲 𐑜𐑦𐑝 𐑑 𐑞 𐑯𐑰𐑜𐑮𐑴'𐑟 𐑤𐑹𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑗𐑧𐑕𐑑. 𐑕𐑴 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑲 𐑕𐑰𐑯 ·𐑐𐑭𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑯 ·𐑝𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑥𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑤𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑨𐑜𐑯𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑥𐑩𐑕 𐑻𐑔, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞 𐑻𐑔 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑷𐑤𐑑𐑼 𐑣𐑻 𐑑𐑲𐑛𐑟 𐑯 𐑣𐑻 𐑕𐑰𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑓 𐑞𐑨𐑑.

𐑥𐑰𐑯𐑢𐑲𐑤 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚, 𐑞 𐑔𐑻𐑛 𐑥𐑱𐑑, 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑛 𐑯𐑴 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑓𐑸-𐑜𐑱𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑕𐑦𐑑𐑿𐑛𐑟. 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑞𐑺 𐑮𐑧𐑜𐑿𐑤𐑼 𐑕𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙𐑟, 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑩 𐑑𐑧𐑥𐑐𐑼𐑼𐑦 𐑛𐑲𐑝 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑥𐑽 𐑓𐑮𐑲𐑑; 𐑯 𐑦𐑓 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑻 𐑞 𐑒𐑱𐑕, ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚, 𐑨𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑒𐑱𐑕𐑩𐑟, 𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑟, 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑪𐑤𐑝𐑛 𐑑 𐑕𐑪𐑤𐑦𐑕 𐑞 𐑤𐑨𐑙𐑜𐑢𐑦𐑖𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑝𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑲𐑐. 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑛𐑮𐑵 𐑦𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑑𐑚𐑨𐑯𐑛, 𐑢𐑺 𐑣𐑰 𐑷𐑤𐑢𐑱𐑟 𐑢𐑹 𐑦𐑑 𐑩𐑕𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑑 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑓𐑧𐑞𐑼. 𐑣𐑰 𐑤𐑴𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑑, 𐑯 𐑮𐑨𐑥𐑛 𐑣𐑴𐑥 𐑞 𐑤𐑴𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑔𐑳𐑥-𐑧𐑯𐑛; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑣𐑸𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑣𐑰 𐑦𐑜𐑯𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑨𐑗 𐑩𐑒𐑮𐑪𐑕 𐑞 𐑮𐑳𐑓 𐑕𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑐𐑱𐑐𐑼 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 ·𐑑𐑨𐑖𐑑𐑱𐑜𐑴, 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑽, 𐑣𐑵𐑟 𐑲𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑕𐑧𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑢𐑼𐑛 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑑𐑵 𐑓𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑟, 𐑕𐑳𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑮𐑪𐑐𐑑 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑤𐑲𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑑 𐑨𐑑𐑦𐑑𐑿𐑛 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑰𐑑, 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑦𐑙 𐑬𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑒 𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑯𐑟𐑦 𐑝 𐑣𐑳𐑮𐑦, “𐑛𐑬𐑯, 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑷𐑤, 𐑯 𐑜𐑦𐑝 𐑢𐑱!—𐑞𐑺 𐑞𐑱 𐑸!”

𐑑 𐑩 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟𐑥𐑩𐑯, 𐑯𐑴 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑯𐑹 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑕𐑲𐑯 𐑝 𐑩 𐑣𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑙, 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑝𐑦𐑟𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑴𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑; 𐑯𐑳𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑩 𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑚𐑦𐑑 𐑝 𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑯𐑦𐑖 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼, 𐑯 𐑔𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑒𐑨𐑑𐑼𐑛 𐑐𐑳𐑓𐑕 𐑝 𐑝𐑱𐑐𐑼 𐑣𐑪𐑝𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑦𐑑, 𐑯 𐑕𐑩𐑓𐑿𐑟𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑤𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑪𐑓 𐑑 𐑤𐑰𐑢𐑼𐑛, 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑞 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑓𐑿𐑟𐑛 𐑕𐑒𐑳𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑮𐑴𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑴𐑟. 𐑞 𐑺 𐑼𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑕𐑳𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑝𐑲𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑯 𐑑𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑩𐑤𐑛, 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑻, 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑞 𐑺 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑣𐑰𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑲𐑼𐑯. 𐑚𐑦𐑯𐑰𐑔 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑨𐑑𐑥𐑩𐑕𐑓𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑒 𐑢𐑱𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑯 𐑒𐑻𐑤𐑦𐑙, 𐑯 𐑐𐑸𐑖𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑦𐑯𐑰𐑔 𐑩 𐑔𐑦𐑯 𐑤𐑱𐑼 𐑝 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼, 𐑷𐑤𐑕𐑴, 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑕𐑢𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑙. 𐑕𐑰𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑩𐑛𐑝𐑭𐑯𐑕 𐑝 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟, 𐑞 𐑐𐑳𐑓𐑕 𐑝 𐑝𐑱𐑐𐑼 𐑞𐑱 𐑕𐑐𐑬𐑑𐑩𐑛, 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑞𐑺 𐑓𐑹𐑮𐑳𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑒𐑫𐑮𐑽𐑟 𐑯 𐑛𐑦𐑑𐑨𐑗𐑑 𐑓𐑤𐑲𐑦𐑙 𐑬𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑛𐑼𐑟.

𐑷𐑤 𐑓𐑹 𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕 𐑢𐑻 𐑯𐑬 𐑦𐑯 𐑒𐑰𐑯 𐑐𐑼𐑕𐑿𐑑 𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑕𐑐𐑪𐑑 𐑝 𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼 𐑯 𐑺. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑚𐑨𐑛 𐑓𐑺 𐑑 𐑬𐑑𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑐 𐑞𐑧𐑥; 𐑦𐑑 𐑓𐑤𐑵 𐑪𐑯 𐑯 𐑪𐑯, 𐑨𐑟 𐑩 𐑥𐑨𐑕 𐑝 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑚𐑤𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑳𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑚𐑹𐑯 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑩 𐑮𐑨𐑐𐑦𐑛 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑰𐑥 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑤𐑟.

“𐑐𐑫𐑤, 𐑐𐑫𐑤, 𐑥𐑲 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑚𐑶𐑟,” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒, 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑤𐑴𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑐𐑪𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑼 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑧𐑯; 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑞 𐑖𐑸𐑐 𐑓𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑑 𐑜𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑕 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑲𐑟 𐑛𐑸𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑩𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑝 𐑞 𐑚𐑬, 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑨𐑟 𐑑𐑵 𐑝𐑦𐑟𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑯𐑰𐑛𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑑𐑵 𐑳𐑯𐑻𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑕𐑩𐑟. 𐑣𐑰 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑱 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑮𐑵, 𐑞𐑴, 𐑯𐑹 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑮𐑵 𐑕𐑱 𐑧𐑯𐑦𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥. 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑞 𐑕𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑽𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑽 𐑢𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑼𐑟, 𐑯𐑬 𐑣𐑸𐑖 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑭𐑯𐑛, 𐑯𐑬 𐑕𐑪𐑓𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑰𐑑𐑦.

𐑣𐑬 𐑛𐑦𐑓𐑼𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑞 𐑤𐑬𐑛 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 ·𐑒𐑦𐑙-·𐑐𐑴𐑕𐑑. “𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑬𐑑 𐑯 𐑕𐑱 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑔𐑦𐑙, 𐑥𐑲 𐑣𐑸𐑑𐑦𐑟. 𐑮𐑹 𐑯 𐑐𐑫𐑤, 𐑥𐑲 𐑔𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑚𐑴𐑤𐑑𐑕! 𐑚𐑰𐑗 𐑥𐑰, 𐑚𐑰𐑗 𐑥𐑰 𐑪𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑒 𐑚𐑨𐑒𐑕, 𐑚𐑶𐑟; 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑵 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑓 𐑥𐑰, 𐑯 𐑲'𐑤 𐑕𐑲𐑯 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑑 𐑿 𐑥𐑲 ·𐑥𐑸𐑔𐑩'𐑟 ·𐑝𐑦𐑯𐑘𐑼𐑛 𐑐𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑑𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯, 𐑚𐑶𐑟; 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑤𐑵𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑲𐑓 𐑯 𐑗𐑦𐑤𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑯, 𐑚𐑶𐑟. 𐑤𐑱 𐑥𐑰 𐑪𐑯—𐑤𐑱 𐑥𐑰 𐑪𐑯! 𐑴 ·𐑤𐑹𐑛, ·𐑤𐑹𐑛! 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑲 𐑖𐑨𐑤 𐑜𐑴 𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑒, 𐑕𐑑𐑺𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑨𐑛! 𐑕𐑰! 𐑕𐑰 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼!” 𐑯 𐑕𐑴 𐑖𐑬𐑑𐑦𐑙, 𐑣𐑰 𐑐𐑫𐑤𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑧𐑛, 𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑥𐑐𐑑 𐑳𐑐 𐑯 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑪𐑯 𐑦𐑑; 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑑 𐑳𐑐, 𐑓𐑤𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑑 𐑓𐑸 𐑪𐑓 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑰; 𐑯 𐑓𐑲𐑯𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑓𐑧𐑤 𐑑 𐑮𐑽𐑦𐑙 𐑯 𐑐𐑤𐑳𐑯𐑡𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑'𐑕 𐑕𐑑𐑻𐑯 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑒𐑮𐑱𐑟𐑛 𐑒𐑴𐑤𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑺𐑦.

“𐑤𐑫𐑒 𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑗𐑨𐑐 𐑯𐑬,” 𐑓𐑦𐑤𐑩𐑕𐑪𐑓𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑮𐑷𐑤𐑛 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚, 𐑣𐑵, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑳𐑯𐑤𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑖𐑹𐑑 𐑐𐑲𐑐, 𐑥𐑦𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑱𐑯𐑛 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑢𐑰𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑑𐑰𐑔, 𐑨𐑑 𐑩 𐑖𐑹𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕, 𐑓𐑪𐑤𐑴𐑛 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼—“𐑣𐑰'𐑟 𐑜𐑪𐑑 𐑓𐑦𐑑𐑕, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 ·𐑓𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑒 𐑣𐑨𐑟. 𐑓𐑦𐑑𐑕? 𐑘𐑧𐑕, 𐑜𐑦𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑓𐑦𐑑𐑕—𐑞𐑨𐑑'𐑕 𐑞 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑢𐑻𐑛—𐑐𐑦𐑗 𐑓𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 '𐑩𐑥. 𐑥𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑤𐑦, 𐑥𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑤𐑦, 𐑣𐑸𐑑𐑕-𐑩𐑤𐑲𐑝. 𐑐𐑫𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑓 𐑕𐑳𐑐𐑼, 𐑿 𐑯𐑴;—𐑥𐑧𐑮𐑦'𐑟 𐑞 𐑢𐑻𐑛. 𐑐𐑫𐑤, 𐑚𐑱𐑚𐑟—𐑐𐑫𐑤, 𐑕𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙𐑟—𐑐𐑫𐑤, 𐑷𐑤. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑤 𐑸 𐑿 𐑣𐑳𐑮𐑦𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑? 𐑕𐑪𐑓𐑑𐑤𐑦, 𐑕𐑪𐑓𐑑𐑤𐑦, 𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑦, 𐑥𐑲 𐑥𐑧𐑯. 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑫𐑤, 𐑯 𐑒𐑰𐑐 𐑐𐑫𐑤𐑦𐑙; 𐑯𐑳𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑹. 𐑒𐑮𐑨𐑒 𐑷𐑤 𐑘𐑹 𐑚𐑨𐑒𐑚𐑴𐑯𐑟, 𐑯 𐑚𐑲𐑑 𐑘𐑹 𐑯𐑲𐑝𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑑𐑵—𐑞𐑨𐑑'𐑕 𐑷𐑤. 𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑦𐑑 𐑰𐑟𐑦—𐑢𐑲 𐑛𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑘𐑰 𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑦𐑑 𐑰𐑟𐑦, 𐑲 𐑕𐑱, 𐑯 𐑚𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑘𐑹 𐑤𐑦𐑝𐑼𐑟 𐑯 𐑤𐑳𐑙𐑟!”

𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑵𐑑𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑑𐑲𐑜𐑼-𐑘𐑧𐑤𐑴 𐑒𐑮𐑵 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟—𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑢𐑻𐑛𐑟 𐑚𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑴𐑥𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑣𐑽; 𐑓 𐑿 𐑤𐑦𐑝 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑞 𐑚𐑤𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑛 𐑤𐑲𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑰𐑝𐑨𐑯𐑡𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛. 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑓𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑤 𐑖𐑸𐑒𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑷𐑛𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑕 𐑕𐑰𐑟 𐑥𐑱 𐑜𐑦𐑝 𐑽 𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑢𐑻𐑛𐑟, 𐑢𐑧𐑯, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑑𐑹𐑯𐑱𐑛𐑴 𐑚𐑮𐑬, 𐑯 𐑲𐑟 𐑝 𐑮𐑧𐑛 𐑥𐑻𐑛𐑼, 𐑯 𐑓𐑴𐑥-𐑜𐑤𐑵𐑛 𐑤𐑦𐑐𐑕, ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑤𐑰𐑐𐑑 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑮𐑱.

𐑥𐑰𐑯𐑢𐑲𐑤, 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕 𐑑𐑹 𐑪𐑯. 𐑞 𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑰𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑕𐑐𐑩𐑕𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑒 𐑩𐑤𐑵𐑠𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑝 ·𐑓𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑒 𐑑 “𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑤,” 𐑨𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑛 𐑞 𐑓𐑦𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑕 𐑥𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑼 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑣𐑰 𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑺𐑛 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑲𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑴𐑑'𐑕 𐑚𐑬 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑑𐑱𐑤—𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑩𐑤𐑵𐑠𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑨𐑑 𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑕𐑴 𐑝𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑛 𐑯 𐑤𐑲𐑓-𐑤𐑲𐑒, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑱 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑒𐑷𐑟 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑹 𐑑𐑵 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑑 𐑕𐑯𐑨𐑗 𐑩 𐑓𐑽𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑤𐑫𐑒 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑞 𐑖𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑼. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑮𐑵𐑤; 𐑓 𐑞 𐑹𐑟𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑐𐑫𐑑 𐑬𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑲𐑟, 𐑯 𐑮𐑨𐑥 𐑩 𐑕𐑒𐑿𐑼 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑞𐑺 𐑯𐑧𐑒𐑕; 𐑿𐑕𐑦𐑡 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑯𐑬𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑱 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑯𐑴 𐑹𐑜𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑽𐑟, 𐑯 𐑯𐑴 𐑤𐑦𐑥𐑟 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑸𐑥𐑟, 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑥𐑴𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑕.

𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩 𐑕𐑲𐑑 𐑓𐑫𐑤 𐑝 𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑒 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑯 𐑷! 𐑞 𐑝𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑢𐑧𐑤𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑪𐑥𐑯𐑦𐑐𐑩𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑕𐑰; 𐑞 𐑕𐑻𐑡𐑦𐑙, 𐑣𐑪𐑤𐑴 𐑮𐑹 𐑞𐑱 𐑥𐑱𐑛, 𐑨𐑟 𐑞𐑱 𐑮𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑞 𐑱𐑑 𐑜𐑳𐑯𐑩𐑤𐑟, 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑡𐑲𐑜𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑚𐑴𐑤𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑚𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑚𐑴𐑤𐑦𐑙-𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑯; 𐑞 𐑚𐑮𐑰𐑓 𐑕𐑩𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑨𐑜𐑩𐑯𐑦 𐑝 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑, 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑑𐑦𐑐 𐑓 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑯𐑲𐑓-𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑧𐑡 𐑝 𐑞 𐑖𐑸𐑐𐑼 𐑢𐑱𐑝𐑟, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑔𐑮𐑧𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑒𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑑𐑵; 𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑛𐑩𐑯 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑛𐑦𐑐 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼𐑦 𐑜𐑤𐑧𐑯𐑟 𐑯 𐑣𐑪𐑤𐑴𐑟; 𐑞 𐑒𐑰𐑯 𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑯 𐑜𐑴𐑛𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑑 𐑜𐑱𐑯 𐑞 𐑑𐑪𐑐 𐑝 𐑞 𐑪𐑐𐑩𐑟𐑦𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑤; 𐑞 𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑤𐑪𐑙, 𐑕𐑤𐑧𐑛-𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑕𐑤𐑲𐑛 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑕𐑲𐑛;—𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑰𐑟, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑟𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑯 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑽𐑟, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑖𐑳𐑛𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑜𐑭𐑕𐑐𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑹𐑟𐑥𐑧𐑯, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑕 𐑕𐑲𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑲𐑝𐑼𐑦 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛 𐑚𐑺𐑦𐑙 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑻 𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑬𐑑𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑧𐑗𐑑 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑟, 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑢𐑲𐑤𐑛 𐑣𐑧𐑯 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑣𐑻 𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑰𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑮𐑵𐑛;—𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑔𐑮𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑙.

𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑞 𐑮𐑷 𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑮𐑵𐑑, 𐑥𐑸𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑚𐑫𐑟𐑩𐑥 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑲𐑓 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑓𐑰𐑝𐑼 𐑣𐑰𐑑 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑨𐑑𐑩𐑤; 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑛 𐑥𐑨𐑯'𐑟 𐑜𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑳𐑯𐑯𐑴𐑯 𐑓𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑥 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛;—𐑯𐑲𐑞𐑼 𐑝 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑓𐑰𐑤 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑼 𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑪𐑙𐑜𐑼 𐑦𐑥𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑛𐑳𐑟, 𐑣𐑵 𐑓 𐑞 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑓𐑲𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑐𐑫𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑗𐑸𐑥𐑛, 𐑗𐑻𐑯𐑛 𐑕𐑻𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑞 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 𐑢𐑱𐑤.

𐑞 𐑛𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑗𐑱𐑕 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑬 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑹 𐑯 𐑥𐑹 𐑝𐑦𐑟𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤, 𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑮𐑰𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑛𐑸𐑒𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑛𐑳𐑯 𐑒𐑤𐑬𐑛-𐑖𐑨𐑛𐑴𐑟 𐑓𐑤𐑳𐑙 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑰. 𐑞 𐑡𐑧𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑝𐑱𐑐𐑼 𐑯𐑴 𐑤𐑪𐑙𐑜𐑼 𐑚𐑤𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑑𐑦𐑤𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦𐑢𐑺 𐑑 𐑮𐑲𐑑 𐑯 𐑤𐑧𐑓𐑑; 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑕𐑧𐑐𐑼𐑱𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑺 𐑢𐑱𐑒𐑕. 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕 𐑢𐑻 𐑐𐑫𐑤𐑛 𐑥𐑹 𐑩𐑐𐑸𐑑; ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒 𐑜𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑗𐑱𐑕 𐑑 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑮𐑳𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑛𐑧𐑛 𐑑 𐑤𐑰𐑢𐑼𐑛. 𐑬𐑼 𐑕𐑱𐑤 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑬 𐑕𐑧𐑑, 𐑯, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑮𐑲𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛, 𐑢𐑰 𐑮𐑳𐑖𐑑 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑙; 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑 𐑜𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑥𐑨𐑛𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑞 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑤𐑰 𐑹𐑟 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑕𐑒𐑺𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑰 𐑢𐑻𐑒𐑑 𐑮𐑨𐑐𐑦𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑯𐑳𐑓 𐑑 𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑱𐑐 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑑𐑹𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑮𐑴-𐑤𐑪𐑒𐑕.

𐑕𐑵𐑯 𐑢𐑰 𐑢𐑻 𐑮𐑳𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑩 𐑕𐑩𐑓𐑿𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑲𐑛 𐑝𐑱𐑤 𐑝 𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑑; 𐑯𐑲𐑞𐑼 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑯𐑹 𐑚𐑴𐑑 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑕𐑰𐑯.

“𐑜𐑦𐑝 𐑢𐑱, 𐑥𐑧𐑯,” 𐑢𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑼𐑛 ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒, 𐑛𐑮𐑷𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑓𐑻𐑞𐑼 𐑭𐑓𐑑 𐑞 𐑖𐑰𐑑 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑱𐑤; “𐑞𐑺 𐑦𐑟 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑑 𐑒𐑦𐑤 𐑩 𐑓𐑦𐑖 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑞 𐑕𐑒𐑢𐑷𐑤 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑟. 𐑞𐑺'𐑟 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯!—𐑒𐑤𐑴𐑕 𐑑! 𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑙!”

𐑕𐑵𐑯 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼, 𐑑𐑵 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑒 𐑕𐑩𐑒𐑕𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑪𐑯 𐑰𐑗 𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑝 𐑳𐑕 𐑛𐑦𐑯𐑴𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑜𐑪𐑑 𐑓𐑭𐑕𐑑; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑣𐑸𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑢𐑻 𐑞𐑱 𐑴𐑝𐑼𐑣𐑻𐑛, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑤𐑲𐑑𐑯𐑦𐑙-𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑣𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑼 ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒 𐑕𐑧𐑛: “𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑳𐑐!” 𐑯 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜, 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛, 𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑨𐑙 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑰𐑑.

𐑞𐑴 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑹𐑟𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑓𐑱𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑤𐑲𐑓 𐑯 𐑛𐑧𐑔 𐑐𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑤 𐑕𐑴 𐑒𐑤𐑴𐑕 𐑑 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑩𐑣𐑧𐑛, 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞𐑺 𐑲𐑟 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑕 𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑥𐑱𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑻𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑, 𐑞𐑱 𐑯𐑿 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑒𐑳𐑥; 𐑞𐑱 𐑣𐑻𐑛, 𐑑𐑵, 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑹𐑥𐑩𐑕 𐑢𐑪𐑤𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑨𐑟 𐑝 𐑓𐑦𐑓𐑑𐑦 𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑓𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑕𐑑𐑻𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑼. 𐑥𐑰𐑯𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑚𐑵𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑞 𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑑, 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑝𐑟 𐑒𐑻𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑼𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑳𐑕 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑞 𐑦𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑒𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑦𐑯𐑮𐑱𐑡𐑛 𐑕𐑻𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕.

“𐑞𐑨𐑑'𐑕 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑳𐑥𐑐. 𐑞𐑺, 𐑞𐑺, 𐑜𐑦𐑝 𐑦𐑑 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥!” 𐑢𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑼𐑛 ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒.

𐑩 𐑖𐑹𐑑 𐑮𐑳𐑖𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑤𐑰𐑐𐑑 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑; 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞 𐑛𐑸𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑲𐑼𐑯 𐑝 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜. 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑢𐑧𐑤𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑒𐑱𐑥 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑦𐑟𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑐𐑫𐑖 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑩𐑕𐑑𐑻𐑯, 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑓𐑹𐑢𐑼𐑛 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑪𐑯 𐑩 𐑤𐑧𐑡; 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑤 𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑨𐑐𐑕𐑑 𐑯 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑤𐑴𐑛𐑩𐑛; 𐑩 𐑜𐑳𐑖 𐑝 𐑕𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑝𐑱𐑐𐑼 𐑖𐑪𐑑 𐑳𐑐 𐑯𐑽 𐑚𐑲; 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑮𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑯 𐑑𐑳𐑥𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩𐑯 𐑻𐑔𐑒𐑢𐑱𐑒 𐑚𐑦𐑯𐑰𐑔 𐑳𐑕. 𐑞 𐑣𐑴𐑤 𐑒𐑮𐑵 𐑢𐑻 𐑣𐑭𐑓 𐑕𐑳𐑓𐑩𐑒𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑨𐑟 𐑞𐑱 𐑢𐑻 𐑑𐑪𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑑𐑼-𐑕𐑒𐑧𐑤𐑑𐑼 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑒𐑻𐑛𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑒𐑮𐑰𐑥 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑒𐑢𐑷𐑤. 𐑕𐑒𐑢𐑷𐑤, 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑯 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑷𐑤 𐑚𐑤𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑑𐑩𐑜𐑧𐑞𐑼; 𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑥𐑽𐑤𐑦 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑟𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑲𐑼𐑯, 𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑱𐑐𐑑.

𐑞𐑴 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑰𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑢𐑪𐑥𐑐𐑑, 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑽𐑤𐑦 𐑳𐑯𐑣𐑸𐑥𐑛. 𐑕𐑢𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑰 𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑑 𐑳𐑐 𐑞 𐑓𐑤𐑴𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑹𐑟, 𐑯 𐑤𐑨𐑖𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑩𐑒𐑮𐑪𐑕 𐑞 𐑜𐑳𐑯𐑩𐑤, 𐑑𐑳𐑥𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑚𐑨𐑒 𐑑 𐑬𐑼 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕𐑩𐑟. 𐑞𐑺 𐑢𐑰 𐑕𐑨𐑑 𐑳𐑐 𐑑 𐑬𐑼 𐑯𐑰𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑰, 𐑞 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼 𐑒𐑳𐑝𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑮𐑦𐑚 𐑯 𐑐𐑤𐑨𐑙𐑒, 𐑕𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑑 𐑬𐑼 𐑛𐑬𐑯𐑢𐑼𐑛 𐑜𐑱𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑲𐑟 𐑞 𐑕𐑩𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑒𐑮𐑭𐑓𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑩 𐑒𐑪𐑮𐑩𐑤 𐑚𐑴𐑑 𐑜𐑮𐑴𐑯 𐑳𐑐 𐑑 𐑳𐑕 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑚𐑪𐑑𐑩𐑥 𐑝 𐑞 𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯.

𐑞 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑮𐑰𐑕𐑑 𐑑 𐑩 𐑣𐑬𐑤; 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑝𐑟 𐑛𐑨𐑖𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑚𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑼𐑟 𐑑𐑩𐑜𐑧𐑞𐑼; 𐑞 𐑣𐑴𐑤 𐑕𐑒𐑢𐑷𐑤 𐑮𐑹𐑛, 𐑓𐑹𐑒𐑑, 𐑯 𐑒𐑮𐑨𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑼𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑳𐑕 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑓𐑲𐑼 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑺𐑦, 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑗, 𐑳𐑯𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑿𐑥𐑛, 𐑢𐑰 𐑢𐑻 𐑚𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑙; 𐑦𐑥𐑹𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑡𐑷𐑟 𐑝 𐑛𐑧𐑔! 𐑦𐑯 𐑝𐑱𐑯 𐑢𐑰 𐑣𐑱𐑤𐑛 𐑞 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕; 𐑨𐑟 𐑢𐑧𐑤 𐑮𐑹 𐑑 𐑞 𐑤𐑲𐑝 𐑒𐑴𐑤𐑟 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑞 𐑗𐑦𐑥𐑯𐑦 𐑝 𐑩 𐑓𐑤𐑱𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑕 𐑨𐑟 𐑣𐑱𐑤 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑹𐑥. 𐑥𐑰𐑯𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑞 𐑛𐑮𐑲𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑒𐑳𐑛, 𐑮𐑨𐑒, 𐑯 𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑑, 𐑜𐑮𐑵 𐑛𐑸𐑒𐑼 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑖𐑨𐑛𐑴𐑟 𐑝 𐑯𐑲𐑑; 𐑯𐑴 𐑕𐑲𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑚𐑰 𐑕𐑰𐑯. 𐑞 𐑮𐑲𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑰 𐑓𐑼𐑚𐑨𐑛 𐑷𐑤 𐑩𐑑𐑧𐑥𐑐𐑑𐑕 𐑑 𐑚𐑱𐑤 𐑬𐑑 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑. 𐑞 𐑹𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑿𐑕𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑨𐑟 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑐𐑧𐑤𐑼𐑟, 𐑐𐑼𐑓𐑹𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑯𐑬 𐑞 𐑪𐑓𐑦𐑕 𐑝 𐑤𐑲𐑓-𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑻𐑝𐑼𐑟. 𐑕𐑴, 𐑒𐑳𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑤𐑨𐑖𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼𐑐𐑮𐑵𐑓 𐑥𐑨𐑗 𐑒𐑧𐑜, 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑓𐑱𐑤𐑘𐑼𐑟 ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑝𐑛 𐑑 𐑦𐑜𐑯𐑲𐑑 𐑞 𐑤𐑨𐑥𐑐 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑯; 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑧𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑑 𐑪𐑯 𐑩 𐑢𐑱𐑓 𐑐𐑴𐑤, 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑑 𐑑 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑛-𐑚𐑺𐑼 𐑝 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑓𐑼𐑤𐑹𐑯 𐑣𐑴𐑐. 𐑞𐑺, 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑨𐑑, 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑳𐑐 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑥𐑚𐑩𐑕𐑰𐑤 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑣𐑸𐑑 𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑲𐑑𐑦 𐑓𐑼𐑤𐑹𐑯𐑯𐑩𐑕. 𐑞𐑺, 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑨𐑑, 𐑞 𐑕𐑲𐑯 𐑯 𐑕𐑦𐑥𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑩 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑 𐑓𐑱𐑔, 𐑣𐑴𐑐𐑤𐑩𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑳𐑐 𐑣𐑴𐑐 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑥𐑦𐑛𐑕𐑑 𐑝 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑺.

𐑢𐑧𐑑, 𐑛𐑮𐑧𐑯𐑗𐑑 𐑔𐑮𐑵, 𐑯 𐑖𐑦𐑝𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑒𐑴𐑤𐑛, 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑺𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑹 𐑚𐑴𐑑, 𐑢𐑰 𐑤𐑦𐑓𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑳𐑐 𐑬𐑼 𐑲𐑟 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑛𐑷𐑯 𐑒𐑱𐑥 𐑪𐑯. 𐑞 𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑛 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑞 𐑕𐑰, 𐑞 𐑧𐑥𐑐𐑑𐑦 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑯 𐑤𐑱 𐑒𐑮𐑳𐑖𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑪𐑑𐑩𐑥 𐑝 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑. 𐑕𐑳𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑦 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜 𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑰𐑑, 𐑣𐑪𐑤𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑽. 𐑢𐑰 𐑷𐑤 𐑣𐑻𐑛 𐑩 𐑓𐑱𐑯𐑑 𐑒𐑮𐑰𐑒𐑦𐑙, 𐑨𐑟 𐑝 𐑮𐑴𐑐𐑕 𐑯 𐑘𐑸𐑛𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑞𐑼𐑑𐑵 𐑥𐑳𐑓𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑹𐑥. 𐑞 𐑕𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑒𐑱𐑥 𐑯𐑽𐑼 𐑯 𐑯𐑽𐑼; 𐑞 𐑔𐑦𐑒 𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑕 𐑢𐑻 𐑛𐑦𐑥𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑸𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑩 𐑣𐑿𐑡, 𐑝𐑱𐑜 𐑓𐑹𐑥. 𐑩𐑓𐑮𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑛, 𐑢𐑰 𐑷𐑤 𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑨𐑙 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑕𐑰 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑤𐑵𐑥𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑝𐑿, 𐑚𐑺𐑦𐑙 𐑮𐑲𐑑 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑳𐑕 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑝 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑥𐑹 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑤𐑧𐑙𐑔.

𐑓𐑤𐑴𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑝𐑟 𐑢𐑰 𐑕𐑷 𐑞 𐑩𐑚𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑚𐑴𐑑, 𐑨𐑟 𐑓 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑑𐑪𐑕𐑑 𐑯 𐑜𐑱𐑐𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑯𐑰𐑔 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐'𐑕 𐑚𐑬𐑟 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑗𐑦𐑐 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑚𐑱𐑕 𐑝 𐑩 𐑒𐑨𐑑𐑼𐑨𐑒𐑑; 𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑞 𐑝𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑳𐑤 𐑮𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑦𐑑, 𐑯 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑰𐑯 𐑯𐑴 𐑥𐑹 𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑦𐑑 𐑒𐑱𐑥 𐑳𐑐 𐑢𐑧𐑤𐑑𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑕𐑑𐑻𐑯. 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯 𐑢𐑰 𐑕𐑢𐑨𐑥 𐑓 𐑦𐑑, 𐑢𐑻 𐑛𐑨𐑖𐑑 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑕𐑰𐑟, 𐑯 𐑢𐑻 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑳𐑐 𐑯 𐑕𐑱𐑓𐑤𐑦 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑪𐑯 𐑚𐑹𐑛. 𐑺 𐑞 𐑕𐑒𐑢𐑷𐑤 𐑒𐑱𐑥 𐑒𐑤𐑴𐑕 𐑑, 𐑞 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑒𐑳𐑑 𐑤𐑵𐑕 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞𐑺 𐑓𐑦𐑖 𐑯 𐑮𐑩𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑛 𐑑 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑦𐑯 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑑𐑲𐑥. 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑜𐑦𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑳𐑕 𐑳𐑐, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑒𐑮𐑵𐑟𐑦𐑙, 𐑦𐑓 𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑑 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑤𐑲𐑑 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑑𐑴𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑬𐑼 𐑐𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑖𐑦𐑙,—𐑩𐑯 𐑹 𐑹 𐑩 𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑕 𐑐𐑴𐑤.

·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 49. 𐑞 ·𐑣𐑲𐑰𐑯𐑩.

𐑞𐑺 𐑸 𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑒𐑢𐑽 𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑯 𐑩𐑒𐑱𐑠𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡 𐑥𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑑 𐑩𐑓𐑺 𐑢𐑰 𐑒𐑷𐑤 𐑤𐑲𐑓 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑩 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑕 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑣𐑴𐑤 𐑿𐑯𐑦𐑝𐑻𐑕 𐑓 𐑩 𐑝𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑨𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑡𐑴𐑒, 𐑞𐑴 𐑞 𐑢𐑦𐑑 𐑞𐑺𐑪𐑝 𐑣𐑰 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑥𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑻𐑯𐑟, 𐑯 𐑥𐑹 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑕 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑡𐑴𐑒 𐑦𐑟 𐑨𐑑 𐑯𐑴𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦'𐑟 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑕 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑴𐑯. 𐑣𐑬𐑧𐑝𐑼, 𐑯𐑳𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑦𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑕, 𐑯 𐑯𐑳𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑟 𐑢𐑻𐑔 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑿𐑑𐑦𐑙. 𐑣𐑰 𐑚𐑴𐑤𐑑𐑕 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑦𐑝𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑕, 𐑷𐑤 𐑒𐑮𐑰𐑛𐑟, 𐑯 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑰𐑓𐑕, 𐑯 𐑐𐑼𐑕𐑢𐑱𐑠𐑩𐑯𐑟, 𐑷𐑤 𐑣𐑸𐑛 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑝𐑦𐑟𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑦𐑟𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤, 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑥𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑣𐑬 𐑯𐑪𐑚𐑦; 𐑨𐑟 𐑩𐑯 𐑪𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑗 𐑝 𐑐𐑴𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑛𐑲𐑡𐑧𐑕𐑗𐑩𐑯 𐑜𐑪𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑚𐑫𐑤𐑩𐑑𐑕 𐑯 𐑜𐑳𐑯 𐑓𐑤𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑕. 𐑯 𐑨𐑟 𐑓 𐑕𐑥𐑷𐑤 𐑛𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑒𐑳𐑤𐑑𐑦𐑟 𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑮𐑦𐑦𐑙𐑟, 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑕𐑳𐑛𐑩𐑯 𐑛𐑦𐑟𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑼, 𐑐𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑤 𐑝 𐑤𐑲𐑓 𐑯 𐑤𐑦𐑥; 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑰𐑟, 𐑯 𐑛𐑧𐑔 𐑦𐑑𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓, 𐑕𐑰𐑥 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑤𐑲, 𐑜𐑫𐑛-𐑯𐑱𐑗𐑼𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑑𐑕, 𐑯 𐑡𐑪𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑳𐑯𐑗𐑩𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑚𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑴𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑳𐑯𐑕𐑰𐑯 𐑯 𐑳𐑯𐑩𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑡𐑴𐑒𐑼. 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑪𐑛 𐑕𐑹𐑑 𐑝 𐑢𐑱𐑢𐑼𐑛 𐑥𐑵𐑛 𐑲 𐑨𐑥 𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑝, 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑟 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑩 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑝 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑰𐑥 𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑚𐑿𐑤𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯; 𐑦𐑑 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑥𐑦𐑛𐑕𐑑 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑻𐑯𐑩𐑕𐑑𐑯𐑩𐑕, 𐑕𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑡𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑩 𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑥𐑴𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑕, 𐑯𐑬 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑟 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑩 𐑐𐑸𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑡𐑴𐑒. 𐑞𐑺 𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑳𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑞 𐑐𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑤𐑟 𐑝 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑚𐑮𐑰𐑛 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑓𐑮𐑰 𐑯 𐑰𐑟𐑦 𐑕𐑹𐑑 𐑝 𐑡𐑰𐑯𐑾𐑤, 𐑛𐑧𐑕𐑐𐑼𐑭𐑛𐑴 𐑓𐑦𐑤𐑪𐑕𐑩𐑓𐑦; 𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑦𐑑 𐑲 𐑯𐑬 𐑮𐑦𐑜𐑸𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑣𐑴𐑤 𐑝𐑶𐑦𐑡 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 ·𐑢𐑲𐑑 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑪𐑚𐑡𐑧𐑒𐑑.

“·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜,” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑲, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑞𐑱 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑛𐑮𐑨𐑜𐑛 𐑥𐑰, 𐑞 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑥𐑨𐑯, 𐑑 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑒, 𐑯 𐑲 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑖𐑱𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑲𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑲 𐑡𐑨𐑒𐑩𐑑 𐑑 𐑓𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑪𐑓 𐑞 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼; “·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜, 𐑥𐑲 𐑓𐑲𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑯𐑛, 𐑛𐑳𐑟 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑕𐑹𐑑 𐑝 𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑪𐑓𐑩𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑩𐑯?” 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑦𐑥𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯, 𐑞𐑴 𐑕𐑴𐑒𐑑 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑡𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑥𐑰, 𐑣𐑰 𐑜𐑱𐑝 𐑥𐑰 𐑑 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑪𐑓𐑩𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑩𐑯.

“·𐑥𐑼 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚,” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑲, 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑻𐑞𐑦, 𐑣𐑵, 𐑚𐑳𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑳𐑐 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑶𐑤-𐑡𐑨𐑒𐑩𐑑, 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑬 𐑒𐑭𐑥𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑥𐑴𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑲𐑐 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑮𐑱𐑯; “·𐑥𐑼 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚, 𐑲 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑣𐑻𐑛 𐑿 𐑕𐑱 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑝 𐑷𐑤 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑿 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑥𐑧𐑑, 𐑬𐑼 𐑗𐑰𐑓 𐑥𐑱𐑑, ·𐑥𐑼 ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒, 𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑲 𐑓𐑸 𐑞 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑒𐑺𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑯 𐑐𐑮𐑵𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑑. 𐑲 𐑕𐑩𐑐𐑴𐑟 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑜𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑐𐑤𐑳𐑥𐑐 𐑪𐑯 𐑩 𐑓𐑤𐑲𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑘𐑹 𐑕𐑱𐑤 𐑕𐑧𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑓𐑪𐑜𐑦 𐑕𐑒𐑢𐑷𐑤 𐑦𐑟 𐑞 𐑣𐑲𐑑 𐑝 𐑩 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑥𐑩𐑯'𐑟 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑯?”

“𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑯. 𐑲'𐑝 𐑤𐑴𐑼𐑛 𐑓 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑩 𐑤𐑰𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑜𐑱𐑤 𐑪𐑓 ·𐑒𐑱𐑐 ·𐑣𐑹𐑯.”

“·𐑥𐑼 ·𐑓𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑒,” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑲, 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 ·𐑒𐑦𐑙-·𐑐𐑴𐑕𐑑, 𐑣𐑵 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑒𐑤𐑴𐑕 𐑚𐑲; “𐑿 𐑸 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑽𐑾𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑟, 𐑯 𐑲 𐑨𐑥 𐑯𐑪𐑑. 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑿 𐑑𐑧𐑤 𐑥𐑰 𐑢𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑩𐑯 𐑳𐑯𐑷𐑤𐑑𐑼𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑤𐑷 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑼𐑦, ·𐑥𐑼 ·𐑓𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑒, 𐑓 𐑩𐑯 𐑹𐑟𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑑 𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑒 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑴𐑯 𐑚𐑨𐑒 𐑐𐑫𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑚𐑨𐑒-𐑓𐑹𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑛𐑧𐑔'𐑕 𐑡𐑷𐑟?”

“𐑒𐑭𐑯𐑑 𐑿 𐑑𐑢𐑦𐑕𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑥𐑷𐑤𐑼?” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 ·𐑓𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑒. “𐑘𐑧𐑕, 𐑞𐑨𐑑'𐑕 𐑞 𐑤𐑷. 𐑲 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑑 𐑕𐑰 𐑩 𐑚𐑴𐑑'𐑕 𐑒𐑮𐑵 𐑚𐑨𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼 𐑳𐑐 𐑑 𐑩 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑓𐑱𐑕 𐑓𐑹𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑. 𐑣𐑭, 𐑣𐑭! 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑜𐑦𐑝 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑕𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑑 𐑓 𐑕𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑑, 𐑥𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑!”

𐑣𐑽 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑸𐑖𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑦𐑑𐑯𐑩𐑕𐑩𐑟, 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑩 𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑚𐑼𐑩𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑑𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑲𐑼 𐑒𐑱𐑕. 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑼𐑦𐑙, 𐑞𐑺𐑓𐑹, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑒𐑢𐑷𐑤𐑟 𐑯 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑕𐑲𐑟𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼 𐑯 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑢𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑝𐑫𐑨𐑒𐑕 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑛𐑰𐑐, 𐑢𐑻 𐑥𐑨𐑑𐑼𐑟 𐑝 𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑩𐑒𐑳𐑮𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑒𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑝 𐑤𐑲𐑓; 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑵𐑐𐑻𐑤𐑩𐑑𐑦𐑝𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑜𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑪𐑯 𐑑 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑲 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑲𐑯 𐑥𐑲 𐑤𐑲𐑓 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑣𐑵 𐑕𐑑𐑽𐑛 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑—𐑪𐑓𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑩 𐑓𐑧𐑤𐑴 𐑣𐑵 𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑥𐑴𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑧𐑗𐑵𐑩𐑕𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑐𐑶𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑕𐑒𐑳𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑭𐑓𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑴𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑥𐑐𐑦𐑙𐑟; 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑐𐑼𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑼 𐑛𐑦𐑟𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑼 𐑑 𐑬𐑼 𐑴𐑯 𐑐𐑼𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑼 𐑚𐑴𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑗𐑰𐑓𐑤𐑦 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑿𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑑 ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒'𐑕 𐑛𐑮𐑲𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑪𐑯 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑑𐑰𐑔 𐑝 𐑩 𐑕𐑒𐑢𐑷𐑤, 𐑯 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑨𐑑 ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒, 𐑯𐑪𐑑𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙, 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑓𐑱𐑥𐑩𐑕 𐑓 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑣𐑰𐑛𐑓𐑩𐑤𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑼𐑦; 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑲 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑪𐑙𐑛 𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑳𐑯𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑮𐑵𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑑 ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒'𐑕 𐑚𐑴𐑑; 𐑯 𐑓𐑲𐑯𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑩 𐑛𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑤'𐑟 𐑗𐑱𐑕 𐑲 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑦𐑒𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛, 𐑑𐑳𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑞 ·𐑢𐑲𐑑 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤: 𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑷𐑤 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑑𐑩𐑜𐑧𐑞𐑼, 𐑲 𐑕𐑱, 𐑲 𐑔𐑷𐑑 𐑲 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑢𐑧𐑤 𐑜𐑴 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑴 𐑯 𐑥𐑱𐑒 𐑩 𐑮𐑳𐑓 𐑛𐑮𐑭𐑓𐑑 𐑝 𐑥𐑲 𐑢𐑦𐑤. “·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜,” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑲, “𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑙, 𐑿 𐑖𐑨𐑤 𐑚𐑰 𐑥𐑲 𐑤𐑷𐑘𐑼, 𐑦𐑜𐑟𐑧𐑒𐑿𐑑𐑼, 𐑯 𐑤𐑧𐑜𐑩𐑑𐑰.”

𐑦𐑑 𐑥𐑱 𐑕𐑰𐑥 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑝 𐑷𐑤 𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑼𐑟 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑚𐑰 𐑑𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑤𐑟 𐑯 𐑑𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑸 𐑯𐑴 𐑐𐑰𐑐𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛 𐑥𐑹 𐑓𐑪𐑯𐑛 𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑛𐑲𐑝𐑻𐑖𐑩𐑯. 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞 𐑓𐑹𐑔 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑲 𐑯𐑷𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑤𐑲𐑓 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑛𐑳𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑔𐑦𐑙. 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑞 𐑕𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑦 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑒𐑤𐑵𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑩𐑒𐑱𐑠𐑩𐑯, 𐑲 𐑓𐑧𐑤𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑰𐑟𐑽; 𐑩 𐑕𐑑𐑴𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑮𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑩𐑢𐑱 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑥𐑲 𐑣𐑸𐑑. 𐑚𐑦𐑕𐑲𐑛𐑟, 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑛𐑱𐑟 𐑲 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑯𐑬 𐑤𐑦𐑝 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑚𐑰 𐑨𐑟 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑛𐑱𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 ·𐑤𐑨𐑟𐑼𐑩𐑕 𐑤𐑦𐑝𐑛 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑮𐑧𐑟𐑼𐑧𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯; 𐑩 𐑕𐑳𐑐𐑤𐑦𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑦 𐑒𐑤𐑰𐑯 𐑜𐑱𐑯 𐑝 𐑕𐑴 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑥𐑳𐑯𐑔𐑕 𐑹 𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑕 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑒𐑱𐑕 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑚𐑰. 𐑲 𐑕𐑼𐑝𐑲𐑝𐑛 𐑥𐑲𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓; 𐑥𐑲 𐑛𐑧𐑔 𐑯 𐑚𐑧𐑮𐑾𐑤 𐑢𐑻 𐑤𐑪𐑒𐑑 𐑳𐑐 𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑲 𐑗𐑧𐑕𐑑. 𐑲 𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑑 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑥𐑰 𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑤𐑦 𐑯 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛𐑤𐑦, 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑒𐑢𐑲𐑩𐑑 𐑜𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑒𐑤𐑰𐑯 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑕𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑞 𐑚𐑸𐑟 𐑝 𐑩 𐑕𐑯𐑳𐑜 𐑓𐑨𐑥𐑤𐑦 𐑝𐑷𐑤𐑑.

𐑯𐑬 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑔𐑷𐑑 𐑲, 𐑳𐑯𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑴𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑳𐑐 𐑞 𐑕𐑤𐑰𐑝𐑟 𐑝 𐑥𐑲 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑒, 𐑣𐑽 𐑜𐑴𐑟 𐑓 𐑩 𐑒𐑵𐑤, 𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑛𐑲𐑝 𐑨𐑑 𐑛𐑧𐑔 𐑯 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑤 𐑓𐑧𐑗 𐑞 𐑣𐑲𐑯𐑛𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑.

·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 50. 𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚'𐑟 ·𐑚𐑴𐑑 𐑯 ·𐑒𐑮𐑵. 𐑓𐑧𐑛𐑩𐑤𐑩.

“𐑣𐑵 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑔𐑷𐑑 𐑦𐑑, ·𐑓𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑒!” 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚; “𐑦𐑓 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑤𐑧𐑜 𐑿 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑒𐑨𐑗 𐑥𐑰 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑚𐑴𐑑, 𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑧𐑕 𐑥𐑱𐑚𐑰 𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑪𐑐 𐑞 𐑐𐑤𐑳𐑜-𐑣𐑴𐑤 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑥𐑲 𐑑𐑦𐑥𐑚𐑼 𐑑𐑴. 𐑴! 𐑣𐑰'𐑟 𐑩 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑥𐑨𐑯!”

“𐑲 𐑛𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒 𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑴 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡, 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑷𐑤, 𐑪𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑩𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑,” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 ·𐑓𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑒. “𐑦𐑓 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑤𐑧𐑜 𐑢𐑻 𐑪𐑓 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑐, 𐑯𐑬, 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑚𐑰 𐑩 𐑛𐑦𐑓𐑼𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑔𐑦𐑙. 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑱𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑣𐑦𐑥; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑯𐑰, 𐑯 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑐𐑸𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑤𐑧𐑓𐑑, 𐑿 𐑯𐑴.”

“𐑲 𐑛𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑯𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑, 𐑥𐑲 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑥𐑨𐑯; 𐑲 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑕𐑷 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑯𐑰𐑤.”

𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑢𐑱𐑤-𐑢𐑲𐑟 𐑐𐑰𐑐𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑪𐑓𐑩𐑯 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑸𐑜𐑿𐑛 𐑢𐑧𐑞𐑼, 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑐𐑨𐑮𐑩𐑥𐑬𐑯𐑑 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑹𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑤𐑲𐑓 𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑩𐑒𐑕𐑧𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑝𐑶𐑦𐑡, 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑮𐑲𐑑 𐑓 𐑩 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 𐑑 𐑡𐑧𐑐𐑼𐑛𐑲𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑲𐑓 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑨𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑝 𐑐𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑤𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑗𐑱𐑕. 𐑕𐑴 ·𐑑𐑨𐑥𐑼𐑤𐑱𐑯'𐑟 𐑕𐑴𐑤𐑡𐑼𐑟 𐑪𐑓𐑩𐑯 𐑸𐑜𐑿𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑑𐑺𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑲𐑟, 𐑢𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑨𐑤𐑿𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑤𐑲𐑓 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑷𐑑 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑒𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑔𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑓𐑲𐑑.

𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑞 𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑕𐑗𐑩𐑯 𐑩𐑕𐑿𐑥𐑛 𐑩 𐑥𐑪𐑛𐑦𐑓𐑲𐑛 𐑨𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑. 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑑𐑵 𐑤𐑧𐑜𐑟 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑩 𐑣𐑪𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑝 𐑛𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑼; 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑐𐑼𐑕𐑿𐑑 𐑝 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑦𐑟 𐑷𐑤𐑢𐑱𐑟 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑯 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑹𐑛𐑦𐑯𐑼𐑦 𐑛𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑒𐑳𐑤𐑑𐑦𐑟; 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑡𐑵𐑩𐑤 𐑥𐑴𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑, 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑰𐑛, 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑮𐑲𐑟𐑩𐑟 𐑩 𐑐𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑤; 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑕𐑻𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑲𐑟 𐑓 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑥𐑱𐑥𐑛 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑑 𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑼 𐑩 𐑢𐑱𐑤-𐑚𐑴𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑑? 𐑨𐑟 𐑩 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑔𐑦𐑙, 𐑞 𐑡𐑶𐑯𐑑-𐑴𐑯𐑼𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑔𐑷𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑑.

𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑢𐑧𐑤 𐑯𐑿 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑷𐑤𐑞𐑴 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑴𐑥 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑚𐑴𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑨𐑮𐑩𐑑𐑦𐑝𐑤𐑦 𐑣𐑸𐑥𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑝𐑦𐑕𐑦𐑕𐑦𐑑𐑿𐑛𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑗𐑱𐑕, 𐑓 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑒 𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑯𐑽 𐑞 𐑕𐑰𐑯 𐑝 𐑨𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑯 𐑜𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑹𐑛𐑼𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑐𐑻𐑕𐑩𐑯, 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑓 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑩 𐑚𐑴𐑑 𐑨𐑒𐑗𐑵𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑩𐑐𐑹𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑨𐑟 𐑩 𐑮𐑧𐑜𐑿𐑤𐑼 𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑟𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑑—𐑩𐑚𐑳𐑝 𐑷𐑤 𐑓 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑕𐑩𐑐𐑤𐑲𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑓𐑲𐑝 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑩 𐑥𐑧𐑯, 𐑨𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑚𐑴𐑑'𐑕 𐑒𐑮𐑵, 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑧𐑤 𐑯𐑿 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑕 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑰𐑑𐑕 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑛 𐑞 𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑴𐑯𐑼𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛. 𐑞𐑺𐑓𐑹 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑕𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑩 𐑚𐑴𐑑'𐑕 𐑒𐑮𐑵 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞𐑧𐑥, 𐑯𐑹 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑣𐑰 𐑦𐑯 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑢𐑱 𐑣𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑛𐑦𐑟𐑲𐑼𐑟 𐑪𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑧𐑛. 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼𐑞𐑩𐑤𐑧𐑕 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑐𐑮𐑲𐑝𐑩𐑑 𐑥𐑧𐑠𐑼𐑟 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑴𐑯 𐑑𐑳𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑨𐑑𐑼. 𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑤 ·𐑒𐑱𐑚𐑩𐑒𐑴'𐑟 𐑐𐑳𐑚𐑤𐑦𐑖𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑳𐑝𐑼𐑦, 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑼𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑓𐑹𐑕𐑰𐑯 𐑦𐑑, 𐑞𐑴 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑖𐑫𐑼 𐑢𐑧𐑯, 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑐𐑹𐑑, 𐑷𐑤 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑒𐑤𐑵𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑞 𐑒𐑳𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑥𐑼𐑦 𐑚𐑦𐑟𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑓𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕 𐑓 𐑕𐑻𐑝𐑦𐑕; 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑞𐑦𐑕 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑬 𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑚𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑻𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑥𐑨𐑑𐑼 𐑝 𐑥𐑱𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑔𐑴𐑤-𐑐𐑦𐑯𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑴𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑓 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑔𐑷𐑑 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑺 𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕, 𐑯 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑕𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑕𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑳𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑕𐑥𐑷𐑤 𐑢𐑫𐑛𐑩𐑯 𐑕𐑒𐑿𐑼𐑟, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑞 𐑤𐑲𐑯 𐑦𐑟 𐑮𐑳𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑬𐑑 𐑸 𐑐𐑦𐑯𐑛 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑵𐑝 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑬: 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩𐑚𐑟𐑻𐑝𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑯 𐑐𐑼𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑼𐑤𐑦 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑕𐑦𐑑𐑿𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑯 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑩 𐑒𐑴𐑑 𐑝 𐑖𐑰𐑞𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑪𐑑𐑩𐑥 𐑝 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑, 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑓 𐑑 𐑥𐑱𐑒 𐑦𐑑 𐑚𐑧𐑑𐑼 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑞 𐑐𐑶𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑖𐑼 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑲𐑝𐑼𐑦 𐑤𐑦𐑥; 𐑯 𐑷𐑤𐑕𐑴 𐑞 𐑨𐑙𐑟𐑲𐑩𐑑𐑦 𐑣𐑰 𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑦𐑜𐑟𐑨𐑒𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑖𐑱𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑔𐑲 𐑚𐑹𐑛, 𐑹 𐑒𐑤𐑳𐑥𐑟𐑦 𐑒𐑤𐑰𐑑, 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑛, 𐑞 𐑣𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑐𐑰𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑'𐑕 𐑚𐑬 𐑓 𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑯𐑰 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑛𐑸𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑹 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑚𐑦𐑙 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤; 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩𐑚𐑟𐑻𐑝𐑛 𐑣𐑬 𐑪𐑓𐑩𐑯 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑑𐑫𐑛 𐑳𐑐 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑚𐑴𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑪𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑼𐑦 𐑯𐑰 𐑓𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑧𐑥𐑦-𐑕𐑻𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑼 𐑛𐑦𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑒𐑤𐑰𐑑, 𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑒𐑸𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑼'𐑟 𐑗𐑦𐑟𐑩𐑤 𐑜𐑬𐑡𐑛 𐑬𐑑 𐑩 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑣𐑽 𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑑 𐑩 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑞𐑺; 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑟, 𐑲 𐑕𐑱, 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑩𐑢𐑱𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑯 𐑒𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑦𐑪𐑕𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑑𐑲𐑥. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦 𐑕𐑩𐑐𐑴𐑟𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑐𐑼𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑼 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑐𐑼𐑱𐑑𐑦𐑝 𐑣𐑰𐑛𐑓𐑩𐑤𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑦𐑯 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑰 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑝𐑿 𐑑 𐑞 𐑳𐑤𐑑𐑦𐑥𐑩𐑑 𐑗𐑱𐑕 𐑝 ·𐑥𐑪𐑚𐑦 ·𐑛𐑦𐑒; 𐑓 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑷𐑤𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑦 𐑮𐑦𐑝𐑰𐑤𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑑 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑹𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑥𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑼 𐑦𐑯 𐑐𐑻𐑕𐑩𐑯. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩 𐑕𐑳𐑐𐑩𐑟𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑯𐑴 𐑥𐑰𐑯𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑪𐑤𐑝 𐑞 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑴𐑑𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑩𐑕𐑐𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑨𐑟 𐑑 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑚𐑴𐑑'𐑕 𐑒𐑮𐑵 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑕𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑚𐑴𐑑.

𐑯𐑬, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑹𐑛𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑑 𐑓𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑥𐑟, 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑱𐑯𐑛 𐑕𐑵𐑯 𐑢𐑱𐑯𐑛 𐑩𐑢𐑱; 𐑓 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑼 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑟 𐑕𐑵𐑯 𐑢𐑱𐑯. 𐑚𐑦𐑕𐑲𐑛𐑟, 𐑯𐑬 𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑳𐑯𐑩𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑪𐑛𐑟 𐑯 𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑝 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡 𐑯𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑳𐑐 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑳𐑯𐑯𐑴𐑯 𐑯𐑫𐑒𐑕 𐑯 𐑨𐑖-𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑻𐑔 𐑑 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑓𐑤𐑴𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑬𐑑𐑤𐑷𐑟 𐑝 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑼𐑟; 𐑯 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑕 𐑞𐑧𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑝𐑟 𐑪𐑓𐑩𐑯 𐑐𐑦𐑒 𐑳𐑐 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑒𐑢𐑽 𐑒𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑢𐑱 𐑒𐑮𐑰𐑗𐑼𐑟 𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑑𐑪𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑞 𐑴𐑐𐑩𐑯 𐑕𐑰 𐑪𐑯 𐑐𐑤𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑕, 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑮𐑧𐑒, 𐑹𐑟, 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕, 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑵𐑟, 𐑚𐑤𐑴𐑯-𐑪𐑓 ·𐑡𐑨𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑰𐑟 𐑡𐑳𐑙𐑒𐑕, 𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑑; 𐑞𐑨𐑑 ·𐑚𐑰𐑧𐑤𐑟𐑦𐑚𐑳𐑚 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑒𐑤𐑲𐑥 𐑳𐑐 𐑞 𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑐 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑒𐑨𐑚𐑦𐑯 𐑑 𐑗𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯, 𐑯 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑱𐑑 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑳𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑛𐑿𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑲𐑑𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑴𐑒𐑕𐑩𐑤.

𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑥𐑱, 𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑞 𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑹𐑛𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑑 𐑓𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑥𐑟 𐑕𐑵𐑯 𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑞𐑺 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑵, 𐑞𐑴 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑻 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑣𐑬 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞𐑧𐑥, 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑺-𐑑𐑻𐑚𐑩𐑯𐑛 ·𐑓𐑧𐑛𐑩𐑤𐑩 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑱𐑯𐑛 𐑩 𐑥𐑳𐑓𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑦 𐑑 𐑞 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑. 𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑕 𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑱𐑥 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑥𐑨𐑯𐑼𐑤𐑦 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑞𐑦𐑕, 𐑚𐑲 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑹𐑑 𐑝 𐑳𐑯𐑩𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑑𐑲 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑵𐑯 𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑤𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚'𐑟 𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑽 𐑓𐑹𐑗𐑵𐑯𐑟; 𐑯𐑱, 𐑕𐑴 𐑓𐑸 𐑨𐑟 𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑕𐑹𐑑 𐑝 𐑩 𐑣𐑭𐑓-𐑣𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑓𐑤𐑵𐑩𐑯𐑕; ·𐑣𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑯𐑴𐑟, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑷𐑔𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑣𐑦𐑥; 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑯𐑳𐑯 𐑯𐑿. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑩𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑯 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑓𐑼𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑺 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑙 ·𐑓𐑧𐑛𐑩𐑤𐑩. 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩 𐑒𐑮𐑰𐑗𐑼 𐑨𐑟 𐑕𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑤𐑲𐑟𐑛, 𐑛𐑩𐑥𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑐𐑰𐑐𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑑𐑧𐑥𐑐𐑼𐑩𐑑 𐑟𐑴𐑯 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑰 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑛𐑮𐑰𐑥𐑟, 𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑥𐑤𐑦; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑝 𐑣𐑵𐑥 𐑯𐑬 𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑜𐑤𐑲𐑛 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑞 𐑳𐑯𐑗𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑦𐑙 ·𐑱𐑠𐑦𐑨𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑿𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑟, 𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑞 ·𐑹𐑦𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑲𐑤𐑟 𐑑 𐑞 𐑰𐑕𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑯𐑑—𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑿𐑤𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛, 𐑦𐑥𐑩𐑥𐑹𐑾𐑤, 𐑳𐑯𐑷𐑤𐑑𐑼𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑒𐑳𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑟, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑥𐑪𐑛𐑼𐑯 𐑛𐑱𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑻𐑝 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑝 𐑞 𐑜𐑴𐑕𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑨𐑚𐑼𐑦𐑡𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑤𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑻𐑔'𐑕 𐑐𐑮𐑲𐑥𐑩𐑤 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑼𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑞 𐑥𐑧𐑥𐑼𐑦 𐑝 𐑞 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑑 𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑧𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯, 𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕, 𐑳𐑯𐑯𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑕 𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑱𐑥, 𐑲𐑛 𐑰𐑗 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑨𐑟 𐑮𐑾𐑤 𐑓𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑥𐑟, 𐑯 𐑭𐑕𐑒𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑯 𐑯 𐑞 𐑥𐑵𐑯 𐑢𐑲 𐑞𐑱 𐑢𐑻 𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑯 𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑧𐑯𐑛; 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑞𐑴, 𐑩𐑒𐑹𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑑 ·𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑩𐑕𐑦𐑕, 𐑞 𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑰𐑛 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑹𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑛𐑷𐑑𐑼𐑟 𐑝 𐑥𐑧𐑯, 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑷𐑤𐑕𐑴, 𐑨𐑛 𐑞 𐑳𐑯𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑪𐑯𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 ·𐑮𐑨𐑚𐑦𐑯𐑟, 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑳𐑤𐑡𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑱𐑯 𐑩𐑥𐑫𐑼𐑟.

·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 51. 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑐𐑦𐑮𐑦𐑑-·𐑕𐑐𐑬𐑑.

𐑛𐑱𐑟, 𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑕 𐑐𐑭𐑕𐑑, 𐑯 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑰𐑟𐑦 𐑕𐑱𐑤, 𐑞 𐑲𐑝𐑼𐑦 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑕𐑤𐑴𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑢𐑧𐑐𐑑 𐑩𐑒𐑮𐑪𐑕 𐑓𐑹 𐑕𐑧𐑝𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑒𐑮𐑵𐑟𐑦𐑙-𐑜𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑟; 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑪𐑓 𐑞 ·𐑩𐑟𐑹𐑟; 𐑪𐑓 𐑞 ·𐑒𐑱𐑐 𐑛𐑦 ·𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑛𐑧𐑟; 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑑 (𐑕𐑴 𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑛), 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑪𐑓 𐑞 𐑥𐑬𐑔 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑮𐑰𐑴 𐑛𐑦 𐑤𐑭 ·𐑐𐑤𐑭𐑑𐑩; 𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑒𐑨𐑮𐑩𐑤 ·𐑜𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛, 𐑩𐑯 𐑳𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑑, 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼𐑦 𐑤𐑴𐑒𐑨𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑦, 𐑕𐑳𐑞𐑼𐑤𐑦 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 ·𐑕𐑑 ·𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑧𐑯𐑩.

𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑜𐑤𐑲𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑤𐑨𐑑𐑼 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑕𐑼𐑰𐑯 𐑯 𐑥𐑵𐑯𐑤𐑲𐑑 𐑯𐑲𐑑, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑝𐑟 𐑮𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑴𐑤𐑟 𐑝 𐑕𐑦𐑤𐑝𐑼; 𐑯, 𐑚𐑲 𐑞𐑺 𐑕𐑪𐑓𐑑, 𐑕𐑩𐑓𐑿𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑰𐑞𐑦𐑙𐑟, 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑩 𐑕𐑦𐑤𐑝𐑼𐑦 𐑕𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑕, 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑩 𐑕𐑪𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑿𐑛; 𐑪𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩 𐑕𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑯𐑲𐑑 𐑩 𐑕𐑦𐑤𐑝𐑼𐑦 𐑡𐑧𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑰𐑯 𐑓𐑸 𐑦𐑯 𐑩𐑛𐑝𐑭𐑯𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑚𐑳𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑚𐑬. 𐑤𐑦𐑑 𐑳𐑐 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑥𐑵𐑯, 𐑦𐑑 𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑑 𐑕𐑦𐑤𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑾𐑤; 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑐𐑤𐑵𐑥𐑛 𐑯 𐑜𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑜𐑪𐑛 𐑳𐑐𐑮𐑲𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑕𐑰. 𐑓𐑧𐑛𐑩𐑤𐑩 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑡𐑧𐑑. 𐑓 𐑝 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑥𐑵𐑯𐑤𐑲𐑑 𐑯𐑲𐑑𐑕, 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑑 𐑥𐑬𐑯𐑑 𐑑 𐑞 𐑥𐑱𐑯-𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑧𐑛, 𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑩 𐑤𐑫𐑒-𐑬𐑑 𐑞𐑺, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑦𐑠𐑩𐑯 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑓 𐑦𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑛𐑱. 𐑯 𐑘𐑧𐑑, 𐑞𐑴 𐑣𐑻𐑛𐑟 𐑝 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑕𐑰𐑯 𐑚𐑲 𐑯𐑲𐑑, 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑝𐑧𐑯𐑗𐑼 𐑩 𐑤𐑴𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑓 𐑞𐑧𐑥. 𐑿 𐑥𐑱 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑦𐑥𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟, 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑞 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑚𐑦𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑛 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑴𐑤𐑛 ·𐑹𐑦𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑐𐑻𐑗𐑑 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑓𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑳𐑯𐑿𐑠𐑵𐑩𐑤 𐑬𐑼𐑟; 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑑𐑻𐑚𐑩𐑯 𐑯 𐑞 𐑥𐑵𐑯, 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑨𐑯𐑘𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑕𐑒𐑲. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑧𐑯, 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑿𐑯𐑦𐑓𐑹𐑥 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑝𐑩𐑤 𐑞𐑺 𐑓 𐑕𐑧𐑝𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑩𐑒𐑕𐑧𐑕𐑦𐑝 𐑯𐑲𐑑𐑕 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑 𐑳𐑑𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑕𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑬𐑯𐑛; 𐑢𐑧𐑯, 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑕𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑕, 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑳𐑯𐑻𐑔𐑤𐑦 𐑝𐑶𐑕 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑣𐑻𐑛 𐑩𐑯𐑬𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑦𐑤𐑝𐑼𐑦, 𐑥𐑵𐑯-𐑤𐑦𐑑 𐑡𐑧𐑑, 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑲𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑯𐑼 𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑰𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑓 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑢𐑦𐑙𐑛 𐑕𐑐𐑦𐑮𐑦𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑤𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑮𐑦𐑜𐑦𐑙, 𐑯 𐑣𐑱𐑤𐑛 𐑞 𐑥𐑹𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑒𐑮𐑵. “𐑞𐑺 𐑖𐑰 𐑚𐑤𐑴𐑟!” 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑞 𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑥𐑐 𐑝 𐑡𐑳𐑡𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑚𐑤𐑴𐑯, 𐑞𐑱 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑝𐑼𐑛 𐑥𐑹; 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑞𐑱 𐑓𐑧𐑤𐑑 𐑯𐑴 𐑑𐑧𐑮𐑼; 𐑮𐑭𐑞𐑼 𐑐𐑤𐑧𐑠𐑼. 𐑓 𐑞𐑴 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑳𐑯𐑢𐑴𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑬𐑼, 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑕𐑴 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑦𐑝 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑲, 𐑯 𐑕𐑴 𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑽𐑾𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑲𐑑𐑦𐑙, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑕𐑴𐑤 𐑪𐑯 𐑚𐑹𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑝𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑦𐑟𐑲𐑼𐑛 𐑩 𐑤𐑴𐑼𐑦𐑙.

𐑢𐑷𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑒 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑒, 𐑕𐑲𐑛-𐑤𐑳𐑯𐑡𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑛𐑟, ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑭𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑞 𐑑'𐑜𐑨𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑯 𐑮𐑶𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑕𐑧𐑑, 𐑯 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑯𐑕𐑱𐑤 𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑛. 𐑞 𐑚𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑞 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑥. 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑-𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑥𐑨𐑯𐑛, 𐑞 𐑐𐑲𐑤𐑛-𐑳𐑐 𐑒𐑮𐑭𐑓𐑑 𐑮𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑞 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛. 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡, 𐑳𐑐𐑣𐑰𐑝𐑦𐑙, 𐑤𐑦𐑓𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦 𐑝 𐑞 𐑑𐑨𐑓𐑮𐑱𐑤 𐑚𐑮𐑰𐑟 𐑓𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑣𐑪𐑤𐑴𐑟 𐑝 𐑕𐑴 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑟, 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑞 𐑚𐑶𐑩𐑯𐑑, 𐑣𐑪𐑝𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑛𐑧𐑒 𐑑 𐑓𐑰𐑤 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑺 𐑚𐑦𐑯𐑰𐑔 𐑞 𐑓𐑰𐑑; 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑖𐑰 𐑮𐑳𐑖𐑑 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑙, 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑓 𐑑𐑵 𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑨𐑜𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑦𐑯𐑓𐑤𐑵𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑜𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑻—𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑑 𐑥𐑬𐑯𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑑 𐑑 𐑣𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑯, 𐑞 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑑 𐑛𐑮𐑲𐑝 𐑘𐑷𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑣𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑜𐑴𐑤. 𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑿 𐑢𐑪𐑗𐑑 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚'𐑟 𐑓𐑱𐑕 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑯𐑲𐑑, 𐑿 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑔𐑷𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑷𐑤𐑕𐑴 𐑑𐑵 𐑛𐑦𐑓𐑼𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑢𐑹𐑦𐑙. 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑤𐑲𐑝 𐑤𐑧𐑜 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑤𐑲𐑝𐑤𐑦 𐑧𐑒𐑴𐑟 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑒, 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑴𐑒 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑛𐑧𐑛 𐑤𐑦𐑥 𐑕𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑒𐑪𐑓𐑦𐑯-𐑑𐑨𐑐. 𐑪𐑯 𐑤𐑲𐑓 𐑯 𐑛𐑧𐑔 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑢𐑷𐑒𐑑. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞𐑴 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑕𐑴 𐑕𐑢𐑦𐑓𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑛, 𐑯 𐑞𐑴 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑲, 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑨𐑮𐑴𐑟, 𐑞 𐑰𐑜𐑼 𐑜𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑖𐑪𐑑, 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑦𐑤𐑝𐑼𐑦 𐑡𐑧𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑴 𐑥𐑹 𐑕𐑰𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑯𐑲𐑑. 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑼 𐑕𐑢𐑹 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑷 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑕, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑩 𐑕𐑧𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑑𐑲𐑥.

𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑥𐑦𐑛𐑯𐑲𐑑-𐑕𐑐𐑬𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑜𐑮𐑴𐑯 𐑩 𐑓𐑼𐑜𐑪𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑔𐑦𐑙, 𐑢𐑧𐑯, 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑛𐑱𐑟 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼, 𐑤𐑴! 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑕𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑬𐑼, 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯 𐑩𐑯𐑬𐑯𐑕𐑑: 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑷𐑤; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑥𐑱𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑱𐑤 𐑑 𐑴𐑝𐑼𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑦𐑑, 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑕 𐑥𐑹 𐑦𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑩𐑐𐑽𐑛 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑓 𐑦𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑚𐑰𐑯. 𐑯 𐑕𐑴 𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑻𐑝𐑛 𐑳𐑕 𐑯𐑲𐑑 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑯𐑲𐑑, 𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑯𐑴 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑣𐑰𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑑 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑑. 𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑽𐑾𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑡𐑧𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑒𐑤𐑽 𐑥𐑵𐑯𐑤𐑲𐑑, 𐑹 𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑤𐑲𐑑, 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑒𐑱𐑕 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑚𐑰; 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑩𐑐𐑽𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯 𐑓 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑣𐑴𐑤 𐑛𐑱, 𐑹 𐑑𐑵 𐑛𐑱𐑟, 𐑹 𐑔𐑮𐑰; 𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑣𐑬 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑨𐑑 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑑 𐑮𐑧𐑐𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑩𐑛𐑝𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑓𐑻𐑞𐑼 𐑯 𐑓𐑻𐑞𐑼 𐑦𐑯 𐑬𐑼 𐑝𐑨𐑯, 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑕𐑪𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑼𐑦 𐑡𐑧𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑓 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑩𐑤𐑫𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑳𐑕 𐑪𐑯.

𐑯𐑹 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑦𐑥𐑩𐑥𐑹𐑾𐑤 𐑕𐑵𐑐𐑼𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑞𐑺 𐑮𐑱𐑕, 𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑩𐑒𐑹𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑰𐑑𐑼𐑯𐑨𐑗𐑼𐑩𐑤𐑯𐑩𐑕, 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛, 𐑢𐑻 𐑞𐑺 𐑢𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑣𐑵 𐑕𐑢𐑹 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑯 𐑢𐑺𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛; 𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑬𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑴𐑑 𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟, 𐑹 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑬𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑓𐑸 𐑩𐑐𐑸𐑑 𐑤𐑨𐑑𐑦𐑑𐑿𐑛𐑟 𐑯 𐑤𐑪𐑯𐑜𐑦𐑑𐑿𐑛𐑟, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑳𐑯𐑯𐑽𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑐𐑬𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑒𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓-𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑢𐑱𐑤; 𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑤, ·𐑥𐑪𐑚𐑦 ·𐑛𐑦𐑒. 𐑓 𐑩 𐑑𐑲𐑥, 𐑞𐑺 𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑛, 𐑑𐑵, 𐑩 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑕 𐑝 𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑽 𐑛𐑮𐑧𐑛 𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑓𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑨𐑐𐑼𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯, 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑓 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑻 𐑑𐑮𐑧𐑗𐑼𐑩𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑧𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑳𐑕 𐑪𐑯 𐑯 𐑪𐑯, 𐑦𐑯 𐑹𐑛𐑼 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑥𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑼 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑑𐑻𐑯 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑳𐑕, 𐑯 𐑮𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑳𐑕 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑴𐑑𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑯 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑡 𐑕𐑰𐑟.

𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑑𐑧𐑥𐑐𐑼𐑼𐑦 𐑨𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑣𐑧𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟, 𐑕𐑴 𐑝𐑱𐑜 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑕𐑴 𐑷𐑓𐑩𐑤, 𐑛𐑦𐑮𐑲𐑝𐑛 𐑩 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑕 𐑐𐑴𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑼𐑧𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑧𐑞𐑼, 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑗, 𐑚𐑦𐑯𐑰𐑔 𐑷𐑤 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑚𐑤𐑵 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑯𐑩𐑕, 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑔𐑷𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑤𐑻𐑒𐑑 𐑩 𐑛𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑖 𐑗𐑸𐑥, 𐑨𐑟 𐑓 𐑛𐑱𐑟 𐑯 𐑛𐑱𐑟 𐑢𐑰 𐑝𐑶𐑦𐑡𐑛 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑙, 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑕𐑰𐑟 𐑕𐑴 𐑢𐑽𐑦𐑤𐑦, 𐑤𐑴𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑥𐑤𐑦 𐑥𐑲𐑤𐑛, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑕𐑐𐑱𐑕, 𐑦𐑯 𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑳𐑜𐑯𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑑 𐑬𐑼 𐑝𐑧𐑯𐑡𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑧𐑮𐑩𐑯𐑛, 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑝𐑱𐑒𐑱𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑑𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑝 𐑤𐑲𐑓 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑬𐑼 𐑻𐑯-𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑐𐑮𐑬.

𐑚𐑳𐑑, 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑞 𐑰𐑕𐑑𐑢𐑼𐑛, 𐑞 ·𐑒𐑱𐑐 𐑢𐑲𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑚𐑦𐑜𐑨𐑯 𐑣𐑬𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑼𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑳𐑕, 𐑯 𐑢𐑰 𐑮𐑴𐑟 𐑯 𐑓𐑧𐑤 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑤𐑪𐑙, 𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑕𐑰𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑸 𐑞𐑺; 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑞 𐑲𐑝𐑼𐑦-𐑑𐑳𐑕𐑒𐑑 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛 𐑖𐑸𐑐𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑬𐑛 𐑑 𐑞 𐑚𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑, 𐑯 𐑜𐑹𐑛 𐑞 𐑛𐑸𐑒 𐑢𐑱𐑝𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑻 𐑥𐑨𐑛𐑯𐑩𐑕, 𐑑𐑦𐑤, 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑖𐑬𐑼𐑟 𐑝 𐑕𐑦𐑤𐑝𐑼 𐑗𐑦𐑐𐑕, 𐑞 𐑓𐑴𐑥-𐑓𐑤𐑱𐑒𐑕 𐑓𐑤𐑵 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑣𐑻 𐑚𐑫𐑤𐑢𐑼𐑒𐑕; 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑛𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑤𐑩𐑑 𐑝𐑨𐑒𐑿𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑝 𐑤𐑲𐑓 𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑩𐑢𐑱, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑜𐑱𐑝 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕 𐑑 𐑕𐑲𐑑𐑕 𐑥𐑹 𐑛𐑦𐑟𐑥𐑩𐑤 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹.

𐑒𐑤𐑴𐑟 𐑑 𐑬𐑼 𐑚𐑬𐑟, 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡 𐑓𐑹𐑥𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼 𐑛𐑸𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑞𐑼 𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑞𐑼 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑳𐑕; 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑔𐑦𐑒 𐑦𐑯 𐑬𐑼 𐑮𐑽 𐑓𐑤𐑵 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑵𐑑𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑰-𐑮𐑱𐑝𐑩𐑯𐑟. 𐑯 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑥𐑹𐑯𐑦𐑙, 𐑐𐑻𐑗𐑑 𐑪𐑯 𐑬𐑼 𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑟, 𐑮𐑴𐑟 𐑝 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑚𐑻𐑛𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑕𐑰𐑯; 𐑯 𐑕𐑐𐑲𐑑 𐑝 𐑬𐑼 𐑣𐑵𐑑𐑦𐑙𐑟, 𐑓 𐑩 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑪𐑚𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑤𐑳𐑙 𐑑 𐑞 𐑣𐑧𐑥𐑐, 𐑨𐑟 𐑞𐑴 𐑞𐑱 𐑛𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑬𐑼 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑛𐑮𐑦𐑓𐑑𐑦𐑙, 𐑳𐑯𐑦𐑯𐑣𐑨𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑒𐑮𐑭𐑓𐑑; 𐑩 𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑐𐑶𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑑 𐑛𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑤𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯, 𐑯 𐑞𐑺𐑓𐑹 𐑓𐑦𐑑 𐑮𐑵𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙-𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕 𐑓 𐑞𐑺 𐑣𐑴𐑥𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑝𐑟. 𐑯 𐑣𐑰𐑝𐑛 𐑯 𐑣𐑰𐑝𐑛, 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑳𐑯𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑣𐑰𐑝𐑛 𐑞 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑒 𐑕𐑰, 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑓 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑝𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑑𐑲𐑛𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑩 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑕; 𐑯 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑥𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑱𐑯 𐑕𐑴𐑤 𐑢𐑻 𐑦𐑯 𐑨𐑙𐑜𐑢𐑦𐑖 𐑯 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑹𐑕 𐑓 𐑞 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑕𐑦𐑯 𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑓𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑮𐑧𐑛.

𐑒𐑱𐑐 𐑝 𐑜𐑫𐑛 ·𐑣𐑴𐑐, 𐑛𐑵 𐑞𐑱 𐑒𐑷𐑤 𐑘𐑰? 𐑮𐑭𐑞𐑼 ·𐑒𐑱𐑐 ·𐑑𐑹𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑴𐑕𐑴, 𐑨𐑟 𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑛 𐑝 𐑘𐑹; 𐑓 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑩𐑤𐑫𐑼𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑐𐑼𐑓𐑦𐑛𐑾𐑕 𐑕𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑩𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑳𐑕, 𐑢𐑰 𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑬𐑼𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑝𐑟 𐑤𐑷𐑯𐑗𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑑𐑹𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑕𐑰, 𐑢𐑺 𐑜𐑦𐑤𐑑𐑦 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑕𐑓𐑹𐑥𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑓𐑬𐑤𐑟 𐑯 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑓𐑦𐑖, 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑛𐑧𐑥𐑛 𐑑 𐑕𐑢𐑦𐑥 𐑪𐑯 𐑧𐑝𐑼𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑣𐑱𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑹, 𐑹 𐑚𐑰𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑒 𐑺 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑣𐑼𐑲𐑟𐑩𐑯. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑒𐑭𐑥, 𐑕𐑯𐑴-𐑢𐑲𐑑, 𐑯 𐑳𐑯𐑝𐑺𐑦𐑦𐑙; 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑛𐑦𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑓𐑧𐑞𐑼𐑟 𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑒𐑲; 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑚𐑧𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑳𐑕 𐑪𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹, 𐑞 𐑕𐑪𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑼𐑦 𐑡𐑧𐑑 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑨𐑑 𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑚𐑰 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛.

𐑛𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑒𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕, ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚, 𐑞𐑴 𐑩𐑕𐑿𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑓 𐑞 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑞 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑿𐑩𐑤 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑭𐑯𐑛 𐑝 𐑞 𐑛𐑮𐑧𐑯𐑗𐑑 𐑯 𐑛𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑼𐑩𐑕 𐑛𐑧𐑒, 𐑥𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑓𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑞 𐑜𐑤𐑵𐑥𐑾𐑕𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑻𐑝; 𐑯 𐑥𐑹 𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑛𐑩𐑥 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑩𐑛𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑱𐑑𐑕. 𐑦𐑯 𐑑𐑧𐑥𐑐𐑧𐑕𐑗𐑵𐑩𐑕 𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑞𐑰𐑟, 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑚𐑳𐑝 𐑯 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑓𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑛, 𐑯𐑳𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑹 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑚𐑰 𐑛𐑳𐑯 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑐𐑨𐑕𐑦𐑝𐑤𐑦 𐑑 𐑩𐑢𐑱𐑑 𐑞 𐑦𐑖𐑿 𐑝 𐑞 𐑜𐑱𐑤. 𐑞𐑧𐑯 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 𐑯 𐑒𐑮𐑵 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑐𐑮𐑨𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑓𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑕. 𐑕𐑴, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑲𐑝𐑼𐑦 𐑤𐑧𐑜 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑩𐑒𐑳𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑥𐑛 𐑣𐑴𐑤, 𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑓𐑻𐑥𐑤𐑦 𐑜𐑮𐑭𐑕𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑖𐑮𐑬𐑛, ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑓 𐑬𐑼𐑟 𐑯 𐑬𐑼𐑟 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑜𐑱𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑛𐑧𐑛 𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑢𐑼𐑛, 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑩𐑯 𐑩𐑒𐑱𐑠𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑒𐑢𐑷𐑤 𐑝 𐑕𐑤𐑰𐑑 𐑹 𐑕𐑯𐑴 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑷𐑤 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑡𐑰𐑤 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑲𐑤𐑨𐑖𐑩𐑟 𐑑𐑩𐑜𐑧𐑞𐑼. 𐑥𐑰𐑯𐑑𐑲𐑥, 𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑵 𐑛𐑮𐑦𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑓𐑹𐑢𐑼𐑛 𐑐𐑸𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑐𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑕𐑰𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑚𐑻𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑮𐑴𐑒 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑚𐑬𐑟, 𐑕𐑑𐑫𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑤𐑲𐑯 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑞 𐑚𐑫𐑤𐑢𐑼𐑒𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑕𐑑; 𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑧𐑑𐑼 𐑑 𐑜𐑸𐑛 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑞 𐑤𐑰𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑱𐑝𐑟, 𐑰𐑗 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑕𐑤𐑦𐑐𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑩 𐑕𐑹𐑑 𐑝 𐑚𐑴𐑤𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑛 𐑑 𐑞 𐑮𐑱𐑤, 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑢𐑳𐑙 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑤𐑵𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑚𐑧𐑤𐑑. 𐑓𐑿 𐑹 𐑯𐑴 𐑢𐑻𐑛𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑕𐑐𐑴𐑒𐑩𐑯; 𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑖𐑦𐑐, 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑓 𐑥𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑐𐑱𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑼𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑨𐑒𐑕, 𐑛𐑱 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑛𐑱 𐑑𐑹 𐑪𐑯 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑕𐑢𐑦𐑓𐑑 𐑥𐑨𐑛𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑯 𐑜𐑤𐑨𐑛𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑛𐑦𐑥𐑴𐑯𐑦𐑨𐑒 𐑢𐑱𐑝𐑟. 𐑚𐑲 𐑯𐑲𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑥𐑿𐑑𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑣𐑿𐑥𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑞 𐑖𐑮𐑰𐑒𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑝𐑱𐑤𐑛; 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑞 𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑕𐑢𐑳𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑤𐑦𐑯𐑟; 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑢𐑻𐑛𐑤𐑩𐑕 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑕𐑑𐑫𐑛 𐑳𐑐 𐑑 𐑞 𐑚𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑. 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑢𐑽𐑦𐑛 𐑯𐑱𐑗𐑼 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑛𐑦𐑥𐑭𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑴𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑒 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑴𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑥𐑩𐑒. 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑒𐑫𐑛 ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒 𐑓𐑼𐑜𐑧𐑑 𐑞 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑥𐑨𐑯'𐑟 𐑨𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑯𐑲𐑑 𐑜𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑒𐑨𐑚𐑦𐑯 𐑑 𐑥𐑸𐑒 𐑣𐑬 𐑞 𐑚𐑼𐑪𐑥𐑦𐑑𐑼 𐑕𐑑𐑫𐑛, 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑷 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑒𐑤𐑴𐑟𐑛 𐑲𐑟 𐑕𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑤𐑹-𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑵𐑛 𐑗𐑺; 𐑞 𐑮𐑱𐑯 𐑯 𐑣𐑭𐑓-𐑥𐑧𐑤𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑕𐑤𐑰𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑹𐑥 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑦𐑥𐑻𐑡𐑛, 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑕𐑤𐑴𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑳𐑯𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑵𐑝𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑑 𐑯 𐑒𐑴𐑑. 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑑𐑱𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑚𐑦𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑤𐑱 𐑳𐑯𐑮𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑗𐑸𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑑𐑲𐑛𐑟 𐑯 𐑒𐑳𐑮𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑐𐑮𐑰𐑝𐑾𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑕𐑐𐑴𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑝. 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑯 𐑕𐑢𐑳𐑙 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑑𐑲𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑤𐑧𐑯𐑗𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛. 𐑞𐑴 𐑞 𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑦𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑑, 𐑞 𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑔𐑮𐑴𐑯 𐑚𐑨𐑒 𐑕𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑒𐑤𐑴𐑟𐑛 𐑲𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑐𐑶𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑑𐑩𐑢𐑹𐑛𐑟 𐑞 𐑯𐑰𐑛𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑞 𐑑𐑧𐑤-𐑑𐑱𐑤 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑢𐑳𐑙 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑩 𐑚𐑰𐑥 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑰𐑤𐑦𐑙.*

*𐑞 𐑒𐑨𐑚𐑦𐑯-𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑕 𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑛 𐑞 𐑑𐑧𐑤-𐑑𐑱𐑤, 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑪𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑 𐑜𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑞 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑕 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑥, 𐑞 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯, 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑴, 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑓𐑹𐑥 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑝 𐑞 𐑒𐑹𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐.

𐑑𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑥𐑨𐑯! 𐑔𐑷𐑑 ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑖𐑳𐑛𐑼, 𐑕𐑤𐑰𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑜𐑱𐑤, 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑞𐑬 𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑛𐑓𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑲𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑞𐑲 𐑐𐑻𐑐𐑩𐑕.

·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 52. 𐑞 ·𐑨𐑤𐑚𐑩𐑑𐑮𐑪𐑕.

𐑕𐑬𐑔-𐑰𐑕𐑑𐑢𐑼𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 ·𐑒𐑱𐑐, 𐑪𐑓 𐑞 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑 ·𐑒𐑮𐑴𐑟𐑧𐑑𐑕, 𐑩 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑒𐑮𐑵𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑜𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑓 ·𐑮𐑲𐑑 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑥𐑧𐑯, 𐑩 𐑕𐑱𐑤 𐑤𐑵𐑥𐑛 𐑩𐑣𐑧𐑛, 𐑞 ·𐑜𐑪𐑯𐑦 (·𐑨𐑤𐑚𐑩𐑑𐑮𐑪𐑕) 𐑚𐑲 𐑯𐑱𐑥. 𐑨𐑟 𐑖𐑰 𐑕𐑤𐑴𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑮𐑵 𐑯𐑲, 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑥𐑲 𐑤𐑪𐑓𐑑𐑦 𐑐𐑻𐑗 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑓𐑹-𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑-𐑣𐑧𐑛, 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑩 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑝𐑿 𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑲𐑑 𐑕𐑴 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑸𐑒𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑑 𐑩 𐑑𐑲𐑮𐑴 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑸 𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑼𐑦𐑟—𐑩 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑼 𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑰, 𐑯 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑨𐑚𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑣𐑴𐑥.

𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑓 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑝𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑓𐑫𐑤𐑼𐑟, 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑒𐑮𐑭𐑓𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑚𐑤𐑰𐑗𐑑 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑞 𐑕𐑒𐑧𐑤𐑩𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑩 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑷𐑤𐑮𐑩𐑕. 𐑷𐑤 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑣𐑻 𐑕𐑲𐑛𐑟, 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑮𐑩𐑤 𐑩𐑐𐑽𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑕𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑗𐑨𐑯𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑝 𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑮𐑳𐑕𐑑, 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑷𐑤 𐑣𐑻 𐑕𐑐𐑸𐑟 𐑯 𐑣𐑻 𐑮𐑦𐑜𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑻 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑞 𐑔𐑦𐑒 𐑚𐑮𐑭𐑯𐑗𐑩𐑟 𐑝 𐑑𐑮𐑰𐑟 𐑓𐑻𐑛 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑹-𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑕𐑑. 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑣𐑻 𐑤𐑴𐑼 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑕𐑧𐑑. 𐑩 𐑢𐑲𐑤𐑛 𐑕𐑲𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑑 𐑕𐑰 𐑣𐑻 𐑤𐑪𐑙-𐑚𐑽𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑤𐑫𐑒-𐑬𐑑𐑕 𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑-𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑟. 𐑞𐑱 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑒𐑤𐑨𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑒𐑦𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑕𐑑𐑕, 𐑕𐑴 𐑑𐑹𐑯 𐑯 𐑚𐑦𐑐𐑨𐑗𐑑 𐑞 𐑮𐑱𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑕𐑼𐑝𐑲𐑝𐑛 𐑯𐑽𐑤𐑦 𐑓𐑹 𐑘𐑽𐑟 𐑝 𐑒𐑮𐑵𐑟𐑦𐑙. 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑲𐑼𐑯 𐑣𐑵𐑐𐑕 𐑯𐑱𐑤𐑛 𐑑 𐑞 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑, 𐑞𐑱 𐑕𐑢𐑱𐑛 𐑯 𐑕𐑢𐑳𐑙 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑩 𐑓𐑨𐑞𐑩𐑥𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑕𐑰; 𐑯 𐑞𐑴, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑕𐑤𐑴𐑤𐑦 𐑜𐑤𐑲𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑒𐑤𐑴𐑕 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑬𐑼 𐑕𐑑𐑻𐑯, 𐑢𐑰 𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑕 𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑺 𐑒𐑱𐑥 𐑕𐑴 𐑯𐑲 𐑑 𐑰𐑗 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑰 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑤𐑰𐑐𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑-𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑟 𐑝 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑑 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑳𐑞𐑼; 𐑘𐑧𐑑, 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑓𐑼𐑤𐑹𐑯-𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑼𐑥𐑧𐑯, 𐑥𐑲𐑤𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑲𐑦𐑙 𐑳𐑕 𐑨𐑟 𐑞𐑱 𐑐𐑭𐑕𐑑, 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑢𐑻𐑛 𐑑 𐑬𐑼 𐑴𐑯 𐑤𐑫𐑒-𐑬𐑑𐑕, 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑞 𐑒𐑢𐑹𐑑𐑼-𐑛𐑧𐑒 𐑣𐑱𐑤 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑻𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑴.

“𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑩𐑣𐑶! 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑘𐑰 𐑕𐑰𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑢𐑲𐑑 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤?”

𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯, 𐑤𐑰𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑞 𐑐𐑨𐑤𐑦𐑛 𐑚𐑫𐑤𐑢𐑼𐑒𐑕, 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑨𐑒𐑑 𐑝 𐑐𐑫𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑑 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑬𐑔, 𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑣𐑬 𐑓𐑧𐑤 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑕𐑰; 𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛 𐑯𐑬 𐑮𐑲𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑥𐑱𐑯, 𐑣𐑰 𐑦𐑯 𐑝𐑱𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑴𐑝 𐑑 𐑥𐑱𐑒 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑣𐑻𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑 𐑦𐑑. 𐑥𐑰𐑯𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑮𐑰𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑢𐑰𐑯. 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑝𐑺𐑾𐑕 𐑕𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑟 𐑞 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛 𐑢𐑻 𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑺 𐑩𐑚𐑟𐑻𐑝𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑝 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑪𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑥𐑽 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑢𐑲𐑑 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤'𐑟 𐑯𐑱𐑥 𐑑 𐑩𐑯𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑖𐑦𐑐, ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑓 𐑩 𐑥𐑴𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑐𐑷𐑟𐑛; 𐑦𐑑 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑨𐑟 𐑞𐑴 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑤𐑴𐑼𐑛 𐑩 𐑚𐑴𐑑 𐑑 𐑚𐑹𐑛 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑼, 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑞 𐑔𐑮𐑧𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛 𐑓𐑼𐑚𐑨𐑛. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑛𐑝𐑭𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑡 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑢𐑼𐑛 𐑐𐑩𐑟𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯, 𐑣𐑰 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯 𐑕𐑰𐑟𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑑, 𐑯 𐑯𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑲 𐑣𐑻 𐑨𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑼 𐑝𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩 ·𐑯𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑑𐑼 𐑯 𐑖𐑹𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑣𐑴𐑥, 𐑣𐑰 𐑤𐑬𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑣𐑱𐑤𐑛—“𐑩𐑣𐑶 𐑞𐑺! 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑦𐑟 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛, 𐑚𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑞 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛! 𐑑𐑧𐑤 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑑 𐑩𐑛𐑮𐑧𐑕 𐑷𐑤 𐑓𐑿𐑗𐑼 𐑤𐑧𐑑𐑼𐑟 𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑩𐑕𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑒 𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯! 𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑘𐑽𐑟, 𐑦𐑓 𐑲 𐑨𐑥 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑴𐑥, 𐑑𐑧𐑤 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑑 𐑩𐑛𐑮𐑧𐑕 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑑 ——”

𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑴𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑞 𐑑𐑵 𐑢𐑱𐑒𐑕 𐑢𐑻 𐑓𐑺𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑮𐑪𐑕𐑑, 𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦, 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑦𐑯 𐑩𐑒𐑹𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞𐑺 𐑕𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑿𐑤𐑼 𐑢𐑱𐑟, 𐑖𐑴𐑤𐑟 𐑝 𐑕𐑥𐑷𐑤 𐑣𐑸𐑥𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑓𐑦𐑖, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑓 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑛𐑱𐑟 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑐𐑤𐑨𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑢𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑲 𐑬𐑼 𐑕𐑲𐑛, 𐑛𐑸𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑩𐑢𐑱 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑖𐑳𐑛𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑦𐑯𐑟, 𐑯 𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑛 𐑞𐑧𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑝𐑟 𐑓𐑹 𐑯 𐑭𐑓𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑼'𐑟 𐑓𐑤𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑕. 𐑞𐑴 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑒𐑹𐑕 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑿𐑩𐑤 𐑝𐑶𐑦𐑡𐑦𐑙𐑟 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑪𐑓𐑩𐑯 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑯𐑴𐑑𐑦𐑕𐑑 𐑩 𐑕𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑤𐑼 𐑕𐑲𐑑, 𐑘𐑧𐑑, 𐑑 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑥𐑪𐑯𐑩𐑥𐑱𐑯𐑦𐑨𐑒 𐑥𐑨𐑯, 𐑞 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑾𐑕𐑑 𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑓𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑒𐑩𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑨𐑮𐑦 𐑥𐑰𐑯𐑦𐑙𐑟.

“𐑕𐑢𐑦𐑥 𐑩𐑢𐑱 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑥𐑰, 𐑛𐑵 𐑘𐑰?” 𐑥𐑻𐑥𐑼𐑛 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚, 𐑜𐑱𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼. 𐑞𐑺 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑻𐑛𐑟, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞 𐑑𐑴𐑯 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑝𐑱𐑛 𐑥𐑹 𐑝 𐑛𐑰𐑐 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑐𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑕𐑨𐑛𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑱𐑯 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑽𐑟𐑥𐑩𐑯, 𐑣𐑵 𐑞𐑳𐑕 𐑓𐑸 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛 𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑖 𐑣𐑻 𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑢𐑱, 𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 𐑬𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑤𐑲𐑩𐑯 𐑝𐑶𐑕,—“𐑳𐑐 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑥! 𐑒𐑰𐑐 𐑣𐑻 𐑪𐑓 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑞 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛!”

𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑞 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛! 𐑞𐑺 𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑐𐑲𐑼 𐑐𐑮𐑬𐑛 𐑓𐑰𐑤𐑦𐑙𐑟; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑺𐑑𐑵 𐑛𐑳𐑟 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑻𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑯𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑜𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑛𐑳𐑒𐑑? 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑯𐑳𐑥𐑚𐑼𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑐𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑤𐑟 𐑑 𐑞 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑐𐑶𐑯𐑑 𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑕 𐑢𐑰 𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑑𐑩𐑛, 𐑢𐑺 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑰 𐑤𐑧𐑓𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑣𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑘𐑫𐑼, 𐑢𐑻 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑳𐑕.

𐑢𐑻 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛 𐑩𐑯 𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑯, 𐑯 𐑚𐑲 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑰𐑕𐑑𐑢𐑼𐑛 𐑢𐑰 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑓 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑮𐑰𐑗 𐑯𐑿 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟, 𐑯 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑳𐑝𐑼 𐑕𐑲𐑑𐑕 𐑥𐑹 𐑕𐑢𐑰𐑑 𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑧𐑯𐑦 ·𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑩𐑛𐑦𐑟 𐑹 ·𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑝 ·𐑒𐑦𐑙 ·𐑕𐑪𐑤𐑩𐑥𐑩𐑯, 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑢𐑻 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑥𐑦𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑝𐑶𐑦𐑡. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑐𐑼𐑕𐑿𐑑 𐑝 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑓𐑸 𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑰 𐑛𐑮𐑰𐑥 𐑝, 𐑹 𐑦𐑯 𐑑𐑹𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑗𐑱𐑕 𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑛𐑰𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑓𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑥 𐑞𐑨𐑑, 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑹 𐑳𐑞𐑼, 𐑕𐑢𐑦𐑥𐑟 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑷𐑤 𐑣𐑿𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑣𐑸𐑑𐑕; 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑗𐑱𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑜𐑤𐑴𐑚, 𐑞𐑱 𐑲𐑞𐑼 𐑤𐑰𐑛 𐑳𐑕 𐑪𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑚𐑨𐑮𐑩𐑯 𐑥𐑱𐑟𐑩𐑟 𐑹 𐑥𐑦𐑛𐑢𐑱 𐑤𐑰𐑝 𐑳𐑕 𐑢𐑧𐑤𐑥𐑛.

·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 53. 𐑞 ·𐑜𐑨𐑥.

𐑞 𐑪𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑮𐑰𐑟𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑲 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑜𐑴 𐑪𐑯 𐑚𐑹𐑛 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑼 𐑢𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑕𐑐𐑴𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞𐑦𐑕: 𐑞 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛 𐑯 𐑕𐑰 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑴𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑕𐑑𐑹𐑥𐑟. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑞 𐑒𐑱𐑕, 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑷𐑤, 𐑐𐑼𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑕, 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑚𐑹𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑣𐑻—𐑡𐑳𐑡𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑲 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑳𐑚𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑢𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑛𐑳𐑒𐑑 𐑪𐑯 𐑕𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑤𐑼 𐑩𐑒𐑱𐑠𐑩𐑯𐑟—𐑦𐑓 𐑕𐑴 𐑦𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑, 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑴𐑕𐑧𐑕 𐑝 𐑣𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙, 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑩𐑚𐑑𐑱𐑯𐑛 𐑩 𐑯𐑧𐑜𐑩𐑑𐑦𐑝 𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑼 𐑑 𐑞 𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑕𐑗𐑩𐑯 𐑣𐑰 𐑐𐑫𐑑. 𐑓, 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑝𐑧𐑯𐑗𐑵𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑛 𐑬𐑑, 𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑺𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑑 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑹𐑑, 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑓 𐑓𐑲𐑝 𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑕, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑼 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯, 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑧𐑐𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑚𐑿𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑓𐑼𐑥𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑴 𐑩𐑚𐑕𐑹𐑚𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑷𐑑. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑱𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑨𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑢𐑩𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑥𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛, 𐑢𐑻 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑣𐑽 𐑝 𐑞 𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑽 𐑿𐑕𐑦𐑡𐑩𐑟 𐑝 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙-𐑝𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑥𐑰𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑰𐑗 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑦𐑯 𐑓𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑰𐑟, 𐑯 𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑪𐑯 𐑩 𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑒𐑮𐑵𐑟𐑦𐑙-𐑜𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛.

𐑦𐑓 𐑑𐑵 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑼𐑟 𐑒𐑮𐑪𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑲𐑯 ·𐑚𐑨𐑮𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑦𐑯 ·𐑯𐑿 ·𐑘𐑹𐑒 ·𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑑, 𐑹 𐑞 𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑤𐑩𐑑 ·𐑕𐑷𐑤𐑟𐑚𐑼𐑦 ·𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑯 𐑦𐑯 ·𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛; 𐑦𐑓 𐑒𐑨𐑠𐑵𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑰𐑗 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑦𐑯𐑣𐑪𐑕𐑐𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑲𐑤𐑛𐑟, 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑑𐑢𐑱𐑯, 𐑓 𐑞 𐑤𐑲𐑓 𐑝 𐑞𐑧𐑥, 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑢𐑧𐑤 𐑩𐑝𐑶𐑛 𐑩 𐑥𐑿𐑗𐑵𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑨𐑤𐑿𐑑𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯; 𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑪𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑓 𐑩 𐑥𐑴𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑗𐑱𐑯𐑡 𐑞 𐑯𐑿𐑟; 𐑯, 𐑐𐑼𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑕, 𐑕𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑓 𐑩 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑯 𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑼𐑑: 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑣𐑬 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑥𐑹 𐑯𐑨𐑗𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 ·𐑐𐑲𐑯 ·𐑚𐑨𐑮𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑯 ·𐑕𐑷𐑤𐑟𐑚𐑼𐑦 ·𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑰, 𐑑𐑵 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑝𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑦𐑙 𐑰𐑗 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑻𐑔—𐑪𐑓 𐑤𐑴𐑯 ·𐑓𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑙'𐑟 ·𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛, 𐑹 𐑞 𐑓𐑸 𐑩𐑢𐑱 ·𐑒𐑦𐑙'𐑟 ·𐑥𐑦𐑤𐑟; 𐑣𐑬 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑥𐑹 𐑯𐑨𐑗𐑼𐑩𐑤, 𐑲 𐑕𐑱, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑕𐑻𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑕 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑗𐑱𐑯𐑡 𐑣𐑱𐑤𐑟, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑒𐑤𐑴𐑕𐑼, 𐑥𐑹 𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑯 𐑕𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑨𐑒𐑑. 𐑯 𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑕𐑰𐑥 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑩 𐑥𐑨𐑑𐑼 𐑝 𐑒𐑹𐑕, 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑒𐑱𐑕 𐑝 𐑝𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑴𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑕𐑰𐑐𐑹𐑑, 𐑯 𐑣𐑵𐑟 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑟, 𐑪𐑓𐑦𐑕𐑼𐑟, 𐑯 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑩 𐑓𐑿 𐑝 𐑞 𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑸 𐑐𐑻𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑯𐑴𐑯 𐑑 𐑰𐑗 𐑳𐑞𐑼; 𐑯 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑢𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦, 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑷𐑤 𐑕𐑹𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑛𐑽 𐑛𐑩𐑥𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑑 𐑑𐑷𐑒 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑.

𐑓 𐑞 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑨𐑚𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑖𐑦𐑐, 𐑞 𐑬𐑑𐑢𐑼𐑛-𐑚𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑼, 𐑐𐑼𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑕, 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑤𐑧𐑑𐑼𐑟 𐑪𐑯 𐑚𐑹𐑛; 𐑨𐑑 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑮𐑱𐑑, 𐑖𐑰 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑚𐑰 𐑖𐑫𐑼 𐑑 𐑤𐑧𐑑 𐑣𐑻 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑐𐑱𐑐𐑼𐑟 𐑝 𐑩 𐑛𐑱𐑑 𐑩 𐑘𐑽 𐑹 𐑑𐑵 𐑤𐑱𐑑𐑼 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑞 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑻 𐑚𐑤𐑻𐑛 𐑯 𐑔𐑳𐑥-𐑢𐑹𐑯 𐑓𐑲𐑤𐑟. 𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑻𐑯 𐑓 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑒𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑕𐑦, 𐑞 𐑬𐑑𐑢𐑼𐑛-𐑚𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑰𐑝 𐑞 𐑤𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑡𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑵𐑟𐑦𐑙-𐑜𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑖𐑰 𐑥𐑱 𐑚𐑰 𐑛𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑛, 𐑩 𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑞 𐑳𐑑𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑹𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑑 𐑣𐑻. 𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑛𐑦𐑜𐑮𐑰, 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑑𐑮𐑵 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑝𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑒𐑮𐑪𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑰𐑗 𐑳𐑞𐑼'𐑟 𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑒 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑵𐑟𐑦𐑙-𐑜𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑑𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓, 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑞𐑴 𐑞𐑱 𐑸 𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑨𐑚𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑣𐑴𐑥. 𐑓 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑥𐑱 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑰𐑝𐑛 𐑩 𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑕𐑓𐑻 𐑝 𐑤𐑧𐑑𐑼𐑟 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑔𐑻𐑛, 𐑯 𐑯𐑬 𐑓𐑸 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑴𐑑 𐑝𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑤; 𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑝 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑤𐑧𐑑𐑼𐑟 𐑥𐑱 𐑚𐑰 𐑓 𐑞 𐑐𐑰𐑐𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑖𐑰 𐑯𐑬 𐑥𐑰𐑑𐑕. 𐑚𐑦𐑕𐑲𐑛𐑟, 𐑞𐑱 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑗𐑱𐑯𐑡 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑯𐑿𐑟, 𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑩𐑯 𐑩𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑗𐑨𐑑. 𐑓 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑞𐑱 𐑥𐑰𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑕𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑔𐑦𐑟 𐑝 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑼𐑟, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑤𐑲𐑒𐑢𐑲𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑽 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑡𐑰𐑯𐑦𐑨𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑟 𐑼𐑲𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑩 𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑐𐑼𐑕𐑿𐑑 𐑯 𐑥𐑿𐑗𐑵𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑖𐑺𐑛 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑝𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑯 𐑐𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑤𐑟.

𐑯𐑹 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑛𐑦𐑓𐑼𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑝 𐑒𐑳𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑦 𐑥𐑱𐑒 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑦𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑤 𐑛𐑦𐑓𐑼𐑩𐑯𐑕; 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑟, 𐑕𐑴 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑨𐑟 𐑚𐑴𐑔 𐑐𐑸𐑑𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑒 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑤𐑨𐑙𐑜𐑢𐑦𐑡, 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑟 𐑞 𐑒𐑱𐑕 𐑢𐑦𐑞 ·𐑩𐑥𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑯 ·𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑤𐑦𐑖. 𐑞𐑴, 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑖𐑫𐑼, 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑕𐑥𐑷𐑤 𐑯𐑳𐑥𐑚𐑼 𐑝 ·𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑤𐑦𐑖 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑼𐑟, 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑥𐑰𐑑𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑛𐑵 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑪𐑓𐑩𐑯 𐑩𐑒𐑻, 𐑯 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑞𐑱 𐑛𐑵 𐑩𐑒𐑻 𐑞𐑺 𐑦𐑟 𐑑𐑵 𐑨𐑐𐑑 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑩 𐑕𐑹𐑑 𐑝 𐑖𐑲𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑢𐑰𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑥; 𐑓 𐑘𐑹 ·𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑤𐑦𐑖𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑟 𐑮𐑭𐑞𐑼 𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑻𐑝𐑛, 𐑯 𐑘𐑹 ·𐑘𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑦, 𐑣𐑰 𐑛𐑳𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑓𐑨𐑯𐑕𐑦 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑹𐑑 𐑝 𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑧𐑯𐑦𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓. 𐑚𐑦𐑕𐑲𐑛𐑟, 𐑞 ·𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑤𐑦𐑖 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑼𐑟 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑩𐑓𐑧𐑒𐑑 𐑩 𐑒𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑝 𐑥𐑧𐑑𐑮𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑕𐑵𐑐𐑽𐑦𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑞 ·𐑩𐑥𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑼𐑟; 𐑮𐑦𐑜𐑸𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑤𐑪𐑙, 𐑤𐑰𐑯 ·𐑯𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑑𐑼, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑝𐑦𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑟𐑩𐑥𐑟, 𐑨𐑟 𐑩 𐑕𐑹𐑑 𐑝 𐑕𐑰-𐑐𐑧𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑑. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑺 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑕𐑵𐑐𐑽𐑦𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑤𐑦𐑖 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑛𐑳𐑟 𐑮𐑾𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑕𐑑, 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑚𐑰 𐑣𐑸𐑛 𐑑 𐑕𐑱, 𐑕𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑘𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑛𐑱, 𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑝𐑤𐑦, 𐑒𐑦𐑤 𐑥𐑹 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 ·𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑤𐑦𐑖, 𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑝𐑤𐑦, 𐑦𐑯 𐑑𐑧𐑯 𐑘𐑽𐑟. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑦𐑟 𐑩 𐑣𐑸𐑥𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑓𐑶𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑤𐑦𐑖 𐑢𐑱𐑤-𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑟, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑞 ·𐑯𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑑𐑼 𐑛𐑳𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑑 𐑣𐑸𐑑; 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑚𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑦, 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑪𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑯𐑴𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑩 𐑓𐑿 𐑓𐑶𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓.

𐑕𐑴, 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑢𐑰 𐑕𐑰 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑝 𐑷𐑤 𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑕 𐑕𐑧𐑐𐑼𐑩𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑕𐑰, 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑼𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑮𐑰𐑟𐑩𐑯 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑕𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤—𐑯 𐑞𐑱 𐑸 𐑕𐑴. 𐑢𐑺𐑨𐑟, 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑥𐑻𐑗𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑕 𐑒𐑮𐑪𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑰𐑗 𐑳𐑞𐑼'𐑟 𐑢𐑱𐑒 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑥𐑦𐑛-·𐑩𐑑𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑒, 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑪𐑓𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑐𐑭𐑕 𐑪𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑 𐑕𐑴 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑨𐑟 𐑩 𐑕𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑻𐑛 𐑝 𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑩𐑜𐑯𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯, 𐑥𐑿𐑗𐑵𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑳𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑰𐑗 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑣𐑲 𐑕𐑰𐑟, 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑕 𐑝 𐑛𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑯 ·𐑚𐑮𐑷𐑛𐑢𐑱; 𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑳𐑤𐑡𐑦𐑙, 𐑐𐑼𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑕, 𐑦𐑯 𐑓𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑕𐑦𐑟𐑩𐑥 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑰𐑗 𐑳𐑞𐑼'𐑟 𐑮𐑦𐑜. 𐑨𐑟 𐑓 ·𐑥𐑧𐑯-𐑝-·𐑢𐑹, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑞𐑱 𐑗𐑭𐑯𐑕 𐑑 𐑥𐑰𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑰, 𐑞𐑱 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑜𐑴 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑕𐑦𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑬𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑯 𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑱𐑐𐑦𐑙𐑟, 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩 𐑛𐑳𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑧𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑟, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑛𐑳𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑥 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑮𐑲𐑑-𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑣𐑸𐑑𐑦 𐑜𐑫𐑛-𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑯 𐑚𐑮𐑳𐑞𐑼𐑤𐑦 𐑤𐑳𐑝 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑷𐑤. 𐑨𐑟 𐑑𐑳𐑗𐑦𐑙 ·𐑕𐑤𐑱𐑝-𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑕 𐑥𐑰𐑑𐑦𐑙, 𐑢𐑲, 𐑞𐑱 𐑸 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑛𐑦𐑡𐑩𐑕 𐑣𐑳𐑮𐑦, 𐑞𐑱 𐑮𐑳𐑯 𐑩𐑢𐑱 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑰𐑗 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑨𐑟 𐑕𐑵𐑯 𐑨𐑟 𐑐𐑪𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤. 𐑯 𐑨𐑟 𐑓 ·𐑐𐑲𐑮𐑩𐑑𐑕, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑞𐑱 𐑗𐑭𐑯𐑕 𐑑 𐑒𐑮𐑪𐑕 𐑰𐑗 𐑳𐑞𐑼'𐑟 𐑒𐑮𐑪𐑕-𐑚𐑴𐑯𐑟, 𐑞 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑱𐑤 𐑦𐑟—“𐑣𐑬 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑕𐑒𐑳𐑤𐑟?”—𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑢𐑱 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑼𐑟 𐑣𐑱𐑤—“𐑣𐑬 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑚𐑨𐑮𐑩𐑤𐑟?” 𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑕𐑗𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑕 𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑼𐑛, 𐑐𐑲𐑮𐑩𐑑𐑕 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑑𐑢𐑱 𐑕𐑑𐑽 𐑩𐑐𐑸𐑑, 𐑓 𐑞𐑱 𐑸 𐑦𐑯𐑓𐑻𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑝𐑦𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑪𐑯 𐑚𐑴𐑔 𐑕𐑲𐑛𐑟, 𐑯 𐑛𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑑 𐑕𐑰 𐑴𐑝𐑼𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑝 𐑰𐑗 𐑳𐑞𐑼'𐑟 𐑝𐑦𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑤𐑲𐑒𐑯𐑩𐑕𐑩𐑟.

𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑤𐑫𐑒 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑜𐑪𐑛𐑤𐑦, 𐑪𐑯𐑩𐑕𐑑, 𐑳𐑯𐑪𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑕, 𐑣𐑪𐑕𐑐𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤, 𐑕𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤, 𐑓𐑮𐑰-𐑯-𐑰𐑟𐑦 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑼! 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑛𐑳𐑟 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑼 𐑛𐑵 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑖𐑰 𐑥𐑰𐑑𐑕 𐑩𐑯𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑼 𐑦𐑯 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑕𐑹𐑑 𐑝 𐑛𐑰𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑢𐑧𐑞𐑼? 𐑖𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑩 “𐑜𐑨𐑥,” 𐑩 𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑴 𐑳𐑑𐑼𐑤𐑦 𐑳𐑯𐑯𐑴𐑯 𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑕 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑱 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑣𐑻𐑛 𐑝 𐑞 𐑯𐑱𐑥 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯; 𐑯 𐑦𐑓 𐑚𐑲 𐑗𐑭𐑯𐑕 𐑞𐑱 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑣𐑽 𐑝 𐑦𐑑, 𐑞𐑱 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑜𐑮𐑦𐑯 𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑑, 𐑯 𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑰𐑑 𐑜𐑱𐑥𐑕𐑩𐑥 𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑓 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 “𐑕𐑐𐑬𐑑𐑼𐑟” 𐑯 “𐑚𐑤𐑳𐑚𐑼-𐑚𐑶𐑤𐑼𐑟,” 𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑒𐑤𐑩𐑥𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟. 𐑢𐑲 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑷𐑤 ·𐑥𐑻𐑗𐑩𐑯𐑑-𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑧𐑯, 𐑯 𐑷𐑤𐑕𐑴 𐑷𐑤 ·𐑐𐑲𐑮𐑩𐑑𐑕 𐑯 ·𐑥𐑨𐑯-𐑝-·𐑢𐑹'𐑟 𐑥𐑧𐑯, 𐑯 ·𐑕𐑤𐑱𐑝-𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑼𐑟, 𐑗𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑖 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩 𐑕𐑒𐑹𐑯𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑓𐑰𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑑𐑩𐑢𐑹𐑛𐑟 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤-𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑕; 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑦𐑟 𐑩 𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑕𐑗𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑚𐑰 𐑣𐑸𐑛 𐑑 𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑼. 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑪𐑟, 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑒𐑱𐑕 𐑝 𐑐𐑲𐑮𐑩𐑑𐑕, 𐑕𐑱, 𐑲 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑑 𐑯𐑴 𐑢𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑓𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑞𐑺𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑽 𐑜𐑤𐑹𐑦 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑦𐑑. 𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑳𐑯𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑝𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯, 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑰𐑛; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑜𐑨𐑤𐑴𐑟. 𐑯 𐑚𐑦𐑕𐑲𐑛𐑟, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑩 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑦𐑟 𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑝𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑪𐑛 𐑓𐑨𐑖𐑩𐑯, 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑯𐑴 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑐𐑼 𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑓 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑵𐑐𐑽𐑽 𐑨𐑤𐑑𐑦𐑑𐑿𐑛. 𐑣𐑧𐑯𐑕, 𐑲 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑒𐑤𐑵𐑛, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑚𐑴𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑣𐑲 𐑤𐑦𐑓𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑩𐑚𐑳𐑝 𐑩 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑥𐑩𐑯, 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑩𐑕𐑻𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑞 𐑐𐑲𐑮𐑩𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑯𐑴 𐑕𐑪𐑤𐑦𐑛 𐑚𐑱𐑕𐑦𐑕 𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑪𐑯.

𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑩 ·𐑜𐑨𐑥? 𐑿 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑢𐑺 𐑬𐑑 𐑘𐑹 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑧𐑒𐑕-𐑓𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑼 𐑮𐑳𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑳𐑐 𐑯 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑞 𐑒𐑪𐑤𐑩𐑥𐑟 𐑝 𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑼𐑦𐑟, 𐑯 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑓𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑞 𐑢𐑻𐑛. ·𐑛𐑼 ·𐑡𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑯 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑩𐑑𐑱𐑯𐑛 𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑧𐑮𐑩𐑛𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯; ·𐑯𐑴𐑩 ·𐑢𐑧𐑚𐑕𐑑𐑼'𐑟 𐑸𐑒 𐑛𐑳𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑦𐑑. 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼𐑞𐑩𐑤𐑧𐑕, 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑦𐑝 𐑢𐑻𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑯𐑬 𐑓 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑘𐑽𐑟 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑿𐑕 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑓𐑦𐑓𐑑𐑰𐑯 𐑔𐑬𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑑𐑮𐑵 𐑚𐑹𐑯 ·𐑘𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑦𐑟. 𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑦, 𐑦𐑑 𐑯𐑰𐑛𐑟 𐑩 𐑛𐑧𐑓𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯, 𐑯 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑚𐑰 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑹𐑐𐑼𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 ·𐑤𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑪𐑯. 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑝𐑿, 𐑤𐑧𐑑 𐑥𐑰 𐑤𐑻𐑯𐑩𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑦𐑓𐑲𐑯 𐑦𐑑.

·𐑜𐑨𐑥. ·𐑯𐑬𐑯—𐑩 𐑕𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑤 𐑥𐑰𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑑𐑵 (𐑹 𐑥𐑹) ·𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑕, 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑪𐑯 𐑩 𐑒𐑮𐑵𐑟𐑦𐑙-𐑜𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛; 𐑢𐑧𐑯, 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑗𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑱𐑤𐑟, 𐑞𐑱 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑗𐑱𐑯𐑡 𐑝𐑦𐑟𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑚𐑲 𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕' 𐑒𐑮𐑵𐑟: 𐑞 𐑑𐑵 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑟 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑱𐑯𐑦𐑙, 𐑓 𐑞 𐑑𐑲𐑥, 𐑪𐑯 𐑚𐑹𐑛 𐑝 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑖𐑦𐑐, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑑𐑵 𐑗𐑰𐑓 𐑥𐑱𐑑𐑕 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑳𐑞𐑼.

𐑞𐑺 𐑦𐑟 𐑩𐑯𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑥 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 ·𐑜𐑨𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑓𐑼𐑜𐑪𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑣𐑽. 𐑷𐑤 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑓𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑞𐑺 𐑴𐑯 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑦𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑟 𐑝 𐑛𐑰𐑑𐑱𐑤; 𐑕𐑴 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑼𐑦. 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑐𐑲𐑮𐑩𐑑, 𐑥𐑨𐑯-𐑝-𐑢𐑹, 𐑹 𐑕𐑤𐑱𐑝 𐑖𐑦𐑐, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑞 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 𐑦𐑟 𐑮𐑴𐑛 𐑧𐑯𐑦𐑢𐑺 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑴𐑑, 𐑣𐑰 𐑷𐑤𐑢𐑱𐑟 𐑕𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑻𐑯 𐑖𐑰𐑑𐑕 𐑪𐑯 𐑩 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑓𐑼𐑑𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤, 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑒𐑫𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑕𐑰𐑑 𐑞𐑺, 𐑯 𐑪𐑓𐑩𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑽𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑥𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑯𐑼'𐑟 𐑑𐑦𐑤𐑼 𐑛𐑧𐑒𐑼𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑜𐑱 𐑒𐑹𐑛𐑟 𐑯 𐑮𐑦𐑚𐑩𐑯𐑟. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤-𐑚𐑴𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑯𐑴 𐑕𐑰𐑑 𐑩𐑕𐑑𐑻𐑯, 𐑯𐑴 𐑕𐑴𐑓𐑩 𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑹𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑑𐑧𐑝𐑼, 𐑯 𐑯𐑴 𐑑𐑦𐑤𐑼 𐑨𐑑 𐑷𐑤. 𐑣𐑲 𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑰𐑛, 𐑦𐑓 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑢𐑰𐑤𐑛 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑞 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼 𐑪𐑯 𐑒𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑟 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑜𐑬𐑑𐑦 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑷𐑤𐑛𐑼𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑐𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑗𐑺𐑟. 𐑯 𐑨𐑟 𐑓 𐑩 𐑑𐑦𐑤𐑼, 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤-𐑚𐑴𐑑 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑩𐑛𐑥𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑦𐑓𐑧𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑕𐑦; 𐑯 𐑞𐑺𐑓𐑹 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑜𐑨𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑰𐑑 𐑚𐑴𐑑'𐑕 𐑒𐑮𐑵 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑤𐑰𐑝 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐, 𐑯 𐑣𐑧𐑯𐑕 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑽𐑼 𐑹 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑽 𐑦𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑯𐑳𐑥𐑚𐑼, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑹𐑛𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑽𐑟𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑩𐑒𐑱𐑠𐑩𐑯, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯, 𐑣𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑯𐑴 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕 𐑑 𐑕𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑯, 𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑫𐑤𐑛 𐑪𐑓 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑝𐑦𐑟𐑦𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑐𐑲𐑯 𐑑𐑮𐑰. 𐑯 𐑪𐑓𐑩𐑯 𐑿 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑯𐑴𐑑𐑦𐑕 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑲𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑣𐑴𐑤 𐑝𐑦𐑟𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛 𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑕𐑲𐑛𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑑𐑵 𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑕, 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 𐑦𐑟 𐑷𐑤 𐑩𐑤𐑲𐑝 𐑑 𐑞 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑹𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑝 𐑕𐑩𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑛𐑦𐑜𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑚𐑲 𐑥𐑱𐑯𐑑𐑱𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑤𐑧𐑜𐑟. 𐑯𐑹 𐑦𐑟 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑰𐑟𐑦 𐑥𐑨𐑑𐑼; 𐑓 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑮𐑽 𐑦𐑟 𐑞 𐑦𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑕 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑡𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑑𐑽𐑦𐑙 𐑹 𐑣𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑯𐑬 𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑥𐑷𐑤 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑨𐑒, 𐑞 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼-𐑹 𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑦𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑒𐑱𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑲 𐑮𐑨𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑰𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑳𐑯𐑑. 𐑣𐑰 𐑦𐑟 𐑞𐑳𐑕 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑰𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑢𐑧𐑡𐑛 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑯 𐑚𐑦𐑣𐑲𐑯𐑛, 𐑯 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑕𐑲𐑛𐑢𐑱𐑟 𐑚𐑲 𐑕𐑧𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑧𐑗𐑑 𐑤𐑧𐑜𐑟; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑩 𐑕𐑳𐑛𐑩𐑯, 𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑐𐑦𐑗 𐑝 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑪𐑓𐑩𐑯 𐑜𐑴 𐑓𐑸 𐑑 𐑑𐑪𐑐𐑩𐑤 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑪𐑟 𐑤𐑧𐑙𐑔 𐑝 𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑳𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑 𐑒𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑪𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑔. 𐑥𐑽𐑤𐑦 𐑥𐑱𐑒 𐑩 𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑛 𐑨𐑙𐑜𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑑𐑵 𐑐𐑴𐑤𐑟, 𐑯 𐑿 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑳𐑐. 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯, 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑛𐑵 𐑦𐑯 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑯 𐑕𐑲𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛'𐑟 𐑮𐑦𐑝𐑩𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑲𐑟, 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑛𐑵, 𐑲 𐑕𐑱, 𐑓 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑛𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑕𐑰𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑛𐑦𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑞 𐑕𐑤𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑐𐑸𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑚𐑲 𐑒𐑨𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑝 𐑧𐑯𐑦𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟; 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑰𐑛, 𐑨𐑟 𐑑𐑴𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑲𐑼, 𐑚𐑶𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓-𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑭𐑯𐑛, 𐑣𐑰 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑑𐑮𐑴𐑟𐑼𐑟' 𐑐𐑪𐑒𐑩𐑑𐑕; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑐𐑼𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑕 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑤𐑸𐑡, 𐑣𐑧𐑝𐑦 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟, 𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑟 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑞𐑺 𐑓 𐑚𐑨𐑤𐑩𐑕𐑑. 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼𐑞𐑩𐑤𐑧𐑕 𐑞𐑺 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑩𐑒𐑻𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟, 𐑢𐑧𐑤 𐑷𐑔𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑟 𐑑𐑵, 𐑢𐑺 𐑞 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑯𐑴𐑯 𐑓 𐑩𐑯 𐑳𐑯𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑥𐑴𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑹 𐑑𐑵, 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑕𐑳𐑛𐑩𐑯 𐑕𐑒𐑢𐑷𐑤 𐑕𐑱—𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑟 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑝 𐑞 𐑯𐑽𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑹𐑟𐑥𐑩𐑯'𐑟 𐑣𐑺, 𐑯 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑪𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑜𐑮𐑦𐑥 𐑛𐑧𐑔.

·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 54. 𐑞 ·𐑑𐑬𐑯-·𐑣𐑴'𐑟 ·𐑕𐑑𐑹𐑦.

(𐑨𐑟 𐑑𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑜𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑩𐑯 ·𐑦𐑯.)

𐑞 ·𐑒𐑱𐑐 𐑝 𐑜𐑫𐑛 ·𐑣𐑴𐑐, 𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼𐑦 𐑮𐑰𐑡𐑩𐑯 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑞𐑺, 𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑯𐑴𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑓𐑹 𐑒𐑹𐑯𐑼𐑟 𐑝 𐑩 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑣𐑲𐑢𐑱, 𐑢𐑺 𐑿 𐑥𐑰𐑑 𐑥𐑹 𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑼𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑐𐑸𐑑.

𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑞 ·𐑜𐑪𐑯𐑦 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑩𐑯𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑣𐑴𐑥𐑢𐑼𐑛-𐑚𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑥𐑩𐑯, 𐑞 ·𐑑𐑬𐑯-·𐑣𐑴,* 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑛. 𐑖𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑥𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑲 ·𐑐𐑪𐑤𐑦𐑯𐑰𐑟𐑾𐑯𐑟. 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑖𐑹𐑑 𐑜𐑨𐑥 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑿𐑛 𐑖𐑰 𐑜𐑱𐑝 𐑳𐑕 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑪𐑙 𐑯𐑿𐑟 𐑝 ·𐑥𐑪𐑚𐑦 ·𐑛𐑦𐑒. 𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑞 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑢𐑲𐑑 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑬 𐑢𐑲𐑤𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑣𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑩 𐑕𐑻𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑑𐑬𐑯-·𐑣𐑴'𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑹𐑦, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑩𐑚𐑕𐑒𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑤𐑦 𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑪𐑤𐑝 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑩 𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑕, 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑝𐑦𐑟𐑦𐑑𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑕𐑴 𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑛 𐑡𐑳𐑡𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑝 ·𐑜𐑪𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑨𐑑 𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑸 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑑 𐑴𐑝𐑼𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑥𐑧𐑯. 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑤𐑨𐑑𐑼 𐑕𐑻𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑕, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑴𐑯 𐑐𐑼𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑼 𐑩𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕, 𐑓𐑹𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑥𐑱 𐑚𐑰 𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑛 𐑞 𐑕𐑰𐑒𐑮𐑩𐑑 𐑐𐑸𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑡𐑩𐑛𐑦 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑯𐑼𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛, 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑮𐑰𐑗𐑑 𐑞 𐑽𐑟 𐑝 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑹 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑱𐑑𐑕. 𐑓 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑒𐑮𐑩𐑑 𐑐𐑸𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑹𐑦 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑳𐑯𐑯𐑴𐑯 𐑑 𐑞 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑑𐑬𐑯-·𐑣𐑴 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓. 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑲𐑝𐑩𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑐𐑼𐑑𐑦 𐑝 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑓𐑧𐑛𐑼𐑩𐑑 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑖𐑦𐑐, 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑣𐑵𐑥, 𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑟, 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑿𐑯𐑦𐑒𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑑 𐑑 ·𐑑𐑨𐑖𐑑𐑱𐑜𐑴 𐑢𐑦𐑞 ·𐑮𐑴𐑥𐑦𐑖 𐑦𐑯𐑡𐑳𐑙𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑕𐑰𐑒𐑮𐑩𐑕𐑦, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞 𐑓𐑪𐑤𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑯𐑲𐑑 ·𐑑𐑨𐑖𐑑𐑱𐑜𐑴 𐑮𐑨𐑥𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑤𐑰𐑐, 𐑯 𐑮𐑦𐑝𐑰𐑤𐑛 𐑕𐑴 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑝 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑱, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑢𐑱𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑢𐑧𐑤 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑞 𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑑. 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼𐑞𐑩𐑤𐑧𐑕, 𐑕𐑴 𐑐𐑴𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑓𐑤𐑵𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑪𐑯 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛 𐑣𐑵 𐑒𐑱𐑥 𐑑 𐑞 𐑓𐑫𐑤 𐑯𐑪𐑤𐑦𐑡 𐑝 𐑦𐑑, 𐑯 𐑚𐑲 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡 𐑛𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑕𐑦, 𐑑 𐑒𐑷𐑤 𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑴, 𐑢𐑻 𐑞𐑱 𐑜𐑳𐑝𐑼𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑥𐑨𐑑𐑼, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑱 𐑒𐑧𐑐𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑰𐑒𐑮𐑩𐑑 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑞𐑧𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑝𐑟 𐑕𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑕𐑐𐑲𐑼𐑛 𐑩𐑚𐑭𐑓𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛'𐑟 𐑥𐑱𐑯-𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑. 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑢𐑰𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑐𐑼 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑛𐑸𐑒𐑼 𐑔𐑮𐑧𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑹𐑦 𐑨𐑟 𐑐𐑳𐑚𐑤𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑦 𐑯𐑼𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐, 𐑞 𐑣𐑴𐑤 𐑝 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡 𐑩𐑓𐑺 𐑲 𐑯𐑬 𐑐𐑮𐑴𐑕𐑰𐑛 𐑑 𐑐𐑫𐑑 𐑪𐑯 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑹𐑛.

*𐑞 𐑱𐑯𐑗𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑤-𐑒𐑮𐑲 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑲𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑-𐑣𐑧𐑛, 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑿𐑟𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑓𐑱𐑥𐑩𐑕 ·𐑜𐑨𐑤𐑲𐑐𐑩𐑜𐑴𐑟 𐑑𐑧𐑮𐑩𐑐𐑦𐑯.

𐑓 𐑥𐑲 𐑣𐑿𐑥𐑼'𐑟 𐑕𐑱𐑒, 𐑲 𐑖𐑨𐑤 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑻𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑲𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑲 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑕 𐑯𐑼𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑑 𐑨𐑑 ·𐑤𐑰𐑥𐑩, 𐑑 𐑩 𐑤𐑬𐑯𐑡𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑻𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑥𐑲 ·𐑕𐑐𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑖 𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑟, 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑕𐑱𐑯𐑑'𐑕 𐑰𐑝, 𐑕𐑥𐑴𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑔𐑦𐑒-𐑜𐑦𐑤𐑑 𐑑𐑲𐑤𐑛 𐑐𐑦𐑨𐑑𐑕𐑩 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑜𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑩𐑯 ·𐑦𐑯. 𐑝 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑓𐑲𐑯 𐑒𐑨𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑽𐑟, 𐑞 𐑘𐑳𐑙 ·𐑛𐑪𐑯𐑟, ·𐑐𐑧𐑛𐑮𐑴 𐑯 ·𐑕𐑦𐑚𐑨𐑕𐑗𐑩𐑯, 𐑢𐑻 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑒𐑤𐑴𐑟𐑼 𐑑𐑻𐑥𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑥𐑰; 𐑯 𐑣𐑧𐑯𐑕 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑤𐑵𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑕𐑗𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑞𐑱 𐑩𐑒𐑱𐑠𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑫𐑑, 𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑸 𐑛𐑵𐑤𐑦 𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑼𐑛 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑑𐑲𐑥.

“𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑑𐑵 𐑘𐑽𐑟 𐑐𐑮𐑲𐑼 𐑑 𐑥𐑲 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑤𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑦𐑝𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑲 𐑨𐑥 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑣𐑻𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑿, 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑥𐑧𐑯, 𐑞 ·𐑑𐑬𐑯-·𐑣𐑴, ·𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑼 𐑝 ·𐑯𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑑, 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑒𐑮𐑵𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑘𐑹 ·𐑐𐑩𐑕𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑒 𐑣𐑽, 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑛𐑱𐑟' 𐑕𐑱𐑤 𐑰𐑕𐑑𐑢𐑼𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑰𐑝𐑟 𐑝 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑜𐑫𐑛 ·𐑜𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑩𐑯 ·𐑦𐑯. 𐑖𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑢𐑺 𐑑 𐑞 𐑯𐑹𐑔𐑢𐑼𐑛 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑤𐑲𐑯. 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑥𐑹𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑐𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑕, 𐑩𐑒𐑹𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑛𐑱𐑤𐑦 𐑿𐑕𐑦𐑡, 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩𐑚𐑟𐑻𐑝𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑖𐑰 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑥𐑹 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑻 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑯. 𐑞𐑱 𐑕𐑩𐑐𐑴𐑟𐑛 𐑩 𐑕𐑹𐑛-𐑓𐑦𐑖 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑚𐑛 𐑣𐑻, 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑥𐑧𐑯. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯, 𐑣𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑳𐑯𐑿𐑠𐑵𐑩𐑤 𐑮𐑰𐑟𐑩𐑯 𐑓 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑰𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑮𐑺 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑤𐑳𐑒 𐑩𐑢𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑤𐑨𐑑𐑦𐑑𐑿𐑛𐑟; 𐑯 𐑞𐑺𐑓𐑹 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑩𐑝𐑻𐑕 𐑑 𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑑 𐑞𐑧𐑥, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑤𐑰𐑒 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑼𐑛 𐑨𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑛𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑼𐑩𐑕, 𐑞𐑴, 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑰𐑛, 𐑞𐑱 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑓𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑑 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑕𐑻𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑨𐑟 𐑤𐑴 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑨𐑟 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑐𐑪𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑮𐑭𐑞𐑼 𐑣𐑧𐑝𐑦 𐑢𐑧𐑞𐑼, 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑿𐑛 𐑣𐑻 𐑒𐑮𐑵𐑟𐑦𐑙𐑟, 𐑞 𐑥𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑯𐑼𐑟 𐑢𐑻𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑐𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑕 𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑲𐑛 𐑯 𐑰𐑟𐑦 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑟; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑯𐑴 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑤𐑳𐑒 𐑒𐑱𐑥; 𐑥𐑹 𐑛𐑱𐑟 𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑚𐑲, 𐑯 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞 𐑤𐑰𐑒 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑳𐑝𐑼𐑛, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑮𐑰𐑕𐑑. 𐑕𐑴 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑕𐑴, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑯𐑬 𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑩𐑤𐑸𐑥, 𐑞 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯, 𐑥𐑱𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑷𐑤 𐑕𐑱𐑤, 𐑕𐑑𐑫𐑛 𐑩𐑢𐑱 𐑓 𐑞 𐑯𐑽𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑸𐑚𐑼 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑞 𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛𐑟, 𐑞𐑺 𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑳𐑤 𐑣𐑴𐑝 𐑬𐑑 𐑯 𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑺𐑛.

“𐑞𐑴 𐑯𐑴 𐑕𐑥𐑷𐑤 𐑐𐑨𐑕𐑦𐑡 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑣𐑻, 𐑘𐑧𐑑, 𐑦𐑓 𐑞 𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑗𐑭𐑯𐑕 𐑓𐑱𐑝𐑼𐑛, 𐑣𐑰 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑓𐑽 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑢𐑱, 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑪𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑕 𐑢𐑻 𐑝 𐑞 𐑚𐑧𐑕𐑑, 𐑯 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑐𐑽𐑦𐑪𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑦𐑤𐑰𐑝𐑛 𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑧𐑥, 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑕-𐑯-𐑔𐑻𐑑𐑦 𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑰𐑟𐑦𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑰𐑐 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑓𐑮𐑰; 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑥𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑓 𐑞 𐑤𐑰𐑒 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑛𐑳𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑻. 𐑦𐑯 𐑑𐑮𐑵𐑔, 𐑢𐑧𐑤 𐑯𐑲 𐑞 𐑣𐑴𐑤 𐑝 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑐𐑨𐑕𐑦𐑡 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑕𐑐𐑼𐑩𐑕 𐑚𐑮𐑰𐑟𐑩𐑟, 𐑞 ·𐑑𐑬𐑯-·𐑣𐑴 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑷𐑤 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑼𐑲𐑝𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑐𐑻𐑓𐑦𐑒𐑑 𐑕𐑱𐑓𐑑𐑦 𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑻 𐑐𐑹𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑 𐑞 𐑩𐑒𐑳𐑮𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑤𐑰𐑕𐑑 𐑓𐑩𐑑𐑨𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑦, 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑦𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑓 𐑞 𐑚𐑮𐑵𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑴𐑝𐑼𐑚𐑺𐑦𐑙 𐑝 ·𐑮𐑨𐑛𐑯𐑦, 𐑞 𐑥𐑱𐑑, 𐑩 ·𐑝𐑦𐑯𐑘𐑼𐑛𐑼, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑼𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑝𐑴𐑒𐑑 𐑝𐑧𐑯𐑡𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑝 ·𐑕𐑑𐑰𐑤𐑒𐑦𐑤𐑑, 𐑩 ·𐑤𐑱𐑒𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑯 𐑛𐑧𐑕𐑐𐑼𐑭𐑛𐑴 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 ·𐑚𐑳𐑓𐑩𐑤𐑴.

“'𐑤𐑱𐑒𐑥𐑩𐑯!—𐑚𐑳𐑓𐑩𐑤𐑴! 𐑐𐑮𐑱, 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑩 ·𐑤𐑱𐑒𐑥𐑩𐑯, 𐑯 𐑢𐑺 𐑦𐑟 ·𐑚𐑳𐑓𐑩𐑤𐑴?' 𐑕𐑧𐑛 ·𐑛𐑪𐑯 ·𐑕𐑦𐑚𐑨𐑕𐑗𐑩𐑯, 𐑮𐑲𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑢𐑦𐑙𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑨𐑑 𐑝 𐑜𐑮𐑭𐑕.

“𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑰𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑯 𐑖𐑹 𐑝 𐑬𐑼 ·𐑤𐑱𐑒 ·𐑽𐑦, ·𐑛𐑪𐑯; 𐑚𐑳𐑑—𐑲 𐑒𐑮𐑱𐑝 𐑘𐑹 𐑒𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑕𐑦—𐑥𐑱 𐑚𐑰, 𐑿 𐑖𐑨𐑤 𐑕𐑵𐑯 𐑣𐑽 𐑓𐑻𐑞𐑼 𐑝 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑨𐑑. 𐑯𐑬, 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑥𐑧𐑯, 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑒𐑢𐑺-𐑕𐑱𐑤 𐑚𐑮𐑦𐑜𐑟 𐑯 𐑔𐑮𐑰-𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑕, 𐑢𐑧𐑤-𐑯𐑲 𐑨𐑟 𐑤𐑸𐑡 𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑬𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑛 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑘𐑹 𐑴𐑤𐑛 ·𐑒𐑲𐑬 𐑑 𐑓𐑸 ·𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑤𐑩; 𐑞𐑦𐑕 ·𐑤𐑱𐑒𐑥𐑩𐑯, 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛-𐑤𐑪𐑒𐑑 𐑣𐑸𐑑 𐑝 𐑬𐑼 ·𐑩𐑥𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑩, 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑯𐑻𐑗𐑼𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑩𐑜𐑮𐑼𐑾𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑰𐑚𐑵𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑐𐑪𐑐𐑿𐑤𐑼𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑴𐑐𐑩𐑯 𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯. 𐑓 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑓𐑤𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑨𐑜𐑮𐑦𐑜𐑩𐑑, 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑜𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑖-𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼 𐑕𐑰𐑟 𐑝 𐑬𐑼𐑟,—·𐑽𐑦, 𐑯 ·𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑺𐑦𐑴, 𐑯 ·𐑣𐑿𐑮𐑪𐑯, 𐑯 ·𐑕𐑵𐑐𐑽𐑽, 𐑯 ·𐑥𐑦𐑖𐑦𐑜𐑩𐑯,—𐑐𐑩𐑟𐑧𐑕 𐑩𐑯 𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯-𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑨𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑝𐑯𐑩𐑕, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑝 𐑞 𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯'𐑟 𐑯𐑴𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑑𐑕; 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑝 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑛 𐑝𐑼𐑲𐑩𐑑𐑦𐑟 𐑝 𐑮𐑱𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑯 𐑝 𐑒𐑤𐑲𐑥𐑟. 𐑞𐑱 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑱𐑯 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑸𐑒𐑦𐑐𐑧𐑤𐑩𐑜𐑴𐑟 𐑝 𐑮𐑴𐑥𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑲𐑤𐑟, 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑪𐑤𐑦𐑯𐑰𐑟𐑾𐑯 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼𐑟 𐑛𐑵; 𐑦𐑯 𐑤𐑸𐑡 𐑐𐑸𐑑, 𐑸 𐑖𐑹𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑑𐑵 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑯𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟, 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 ·𐑩𐑑𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑦𐑟; 𐑞𐑱 𐑓𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑖 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑥𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑩𐑐𐑮𐑴𐑗𐑩𐑟 𐑑 𐑬𐑼 𐑯𐑿𐑥𐑼𐑩𐑕 𐑑𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑹𐑾𐑤 𐑒𐑪𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 ·𐑰𐑕𐑑, 𐑛𐑪𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑷𐑤 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑞𐑺 𐑚𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑕; 𐑣𐑽 𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑸 𐑓𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑚𐑲 𐑚𐑨𐑑𐑼𐑦𐑟, 𐑯 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑜𐑴𐑑-𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑒𐑮𐑨𐑜𐑦 𐑜𐑳𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑤𐑪𐑓𐑑𐑦 ·𐑥𐑨𐑒𐑦𐑯𐑷; 𐑞𐑱 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑣𐑻𐑛 𐑞 𐑓𐑤𐑰𐑑 𐑔𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑝 𐑯𐑱𐑝𐑩𐑤 𐑝𐑦𐑒𐑑𐑼𐑦𐑟; 𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑟, 𐑞𐑱 𐑘𐑰𐑤𐑛 𐑞𐑺 𐑚𐑰𐑗𐑩𐑟 𐑑 𐑢𐑲𐑤𐑛 𐑚𐑸𐑚𐑼𐑾𐑯𐑟, 𐑣𐑵𐑟 𐑮𐑧𐑛 𐑐𐑱𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑓𐑱𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑓𐑤𐑨𐑖 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑬𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑐𐑧𐑤𐑑𐑮𐑦 𐑢𐑦𐑜𐑢𐑭𐑥𐑟; 𐑓 𐑤𐑰𐑜𐑟 𐑯 𐑤𐑰𐑜𐑟 𐑸 𐑓𐑤𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑱𐑯𐑗𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑯 𐑳𐑯𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑛 𐑓𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑕, 𐑢𐑺 𐑞 𐑜𐑷𐑯𐑑 𐑐𐑲𐑯𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑕𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑛 𐑤𐑲𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑒𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑦𐑯 ·𐑜𐑪𐑔𐑦𐑒 𐑡𐑰𐑯𐑦𐑨𐑤𐑩𐑡𐑦𐑟; 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑢𐑫𐑛𐑟 𐑣𐑸𐑚𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑲𐑤𐑛 ·𐑨𐑓𐑮𐑦𐑒 𐑚𐑰𐑕𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑐𐑮𐑱, 𐑯 𐑕𐑦𐑤𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑒𐑮𐑰𐑗𐑼𐑟 𐑣𐑵𐑟 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑹𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑓𐑻𐑟 𐑜𐑦𐑝 𐑮𐑴𐑚𐑟 𐑑 ·𐑑𐑸𐑑𐑼 ·𐑧𐑥𐑐𐑼𐑼𐑟; 𐑞𐑱 𐑥𐑦𐑮𐑼 𐑞 𐑐𐑱𐑝𐑛 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑝 ·𐑚𐑳𐑓𐑩𐑤𐑴 𐑯 ·𐑒𐑤𐑰𐑝𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛, 𐑨𐑟 𐑢𐑧𐑤 𐑨𐑟 ·𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑚𐑱𐑜𐑴 𐑝𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑡𐑩𐑟; 𐑞𐑱 𐑓𐑤𐑴𐑑 𐑩𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑞 𐑓𐑫𐑤-𐑮𐑦𐑜𐑛 𐑥𐑻𐑗𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑖𐑦𐑐, 𐑞 𐑸𐑥𐑛 𐑒𐑮𐑵𐑟𐑼 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑑, 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑰𐑥𐑼, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑰𐑗 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑵; 𐑞𐑱 𐑸 𐑕𐑢𐑧𐑐𐑑 𐑚𐑲 ·𐑚𐑹𐑾𐑯 𐑯 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑕 𐑨𐑟 𐑛𐑲𐑼𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑨𐑟 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑨𐑖 𐑞 𐑕𐑷𐑤𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑱𐑝; 𐑞𐑱 𐑯𐑴 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑕 𐑸, 𐑓 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑕𐑲𐑑 𐑝 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛, 𐑣𐑬𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑦𐑯𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛, 𐑞𐑱 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑛𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑓𐑫𐑤 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑩 𐑥𐑦𐑛𐑯𐑲𐑑 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑷𐑤 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑖𐑮𐑰𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑒𐑮𐑵. 𐑞𐑳𐑕, 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑥𐑧𐑯, 𐑞𐑴 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛𐑼, ·𐑕𐑑𐑰𐑤𐑒𐑦𐑤𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑢𐑲𐑤𐑛-𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑚𐑹𐑯, 𐑯 𐑢𐑲𐑤𐑛-𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑯𐑻𐑗𐑼𐑛; 𐑨𐑟 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑝 𐑩𐑯 𐑷𐑛𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑕 𐑥𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑯𐑼 𐑨𐑟 𐑧𐑯𐑦. 𐑯 𐑓 ·𐑮𐑨𐑛𐑯𐑦, 𐑞𐑴 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑓𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦 𐑣𐑰 𐑥𐑱 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑤𐑱𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑤𐑴𐑯 ·𐑯𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑑 𐑚𐑰𐑗, 𐑑 𐑯𐑻𐑕 𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑩𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑰; 𐑞𐑴 𐑦𐑯 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑤𐑲𐑓 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑓𐑪𐑤𐑴𐑛 𐑬𐑼 𐑷𐑕𐑑𐑽 ·𐑩𐑑𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑯 𐑘𐑹 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑩𐑑𐑦𐑝 ·𐑐𐑩𐑕𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑒; 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑝𐑧𐑯𐑡𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑯 𐑓𐑫𐑤 𐑝 𐑕𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑤 𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑮𐑩𐑤 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑚𐑨𐑒𐑢𐑫𐑛𐑟 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑩𐑯, 𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑖 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑤𐑨𐑑𐑦𐑑𐑿𐑛𐑟 𐑝 𐑚𐑳𐑒-𐑣𐑹𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑤𐑛 ·𐑚𐑴𐑦-𐑯𐑲𐑝𐑟. 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞𐑦𐑕 ·𐑯𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑑𐑼 𐑩 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑜𐑫𐑛-𐑣𐑸𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑑𐑕; 𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 ·𐑤𐑱𐑒𐑥𐑩𐑯, 𐑩 𐑥𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑯𐑼, 𐑣𐑵 𐑞𐑴 𐑩 𐑕𐑹𐑑 𐑝 𐑛𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑰𐑛, 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑦𐑯𐑓𐑤𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑓𐑻𐑥𐑯𐑩𐑕, 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑑𐑧𐑥𐑐𐑼𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑛𐑰𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦 𐑝 𐑣𐑿𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑩𐑜𐑯𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑦𐑟 𐑞 𐑥𐑰𐑯𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑤𐑱𐑝'𐑟 𐑮𐑲𐑑; 𐑞𐑳𐑕 𐑑𐑮𐑰𐑑𐑩𐑛, 𐑞𐑦𐑕 ·𐑕𐑑𐑰𐑤𐑒𐑦𐑤𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑱𐑯𐑛 𐑣𐑸𐑥𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑯 𐑛𐑴𐑕𐑲𐑤. 𐑨𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑦𐑝𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑕, 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑐𐑮𐑵𐑝𐑛 𐑕𐑴 𐑞𐑳𐑕 𐑓𐑸; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 ·𐑮𐑨𐑛𐑯𐑦 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑛𐑵𐑥𐑛 𐑯 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑥𐑨𐑛, 𐑯 ·𐑕𐑑𐑰𐑤𐑒𐑦𐑤𐑑—𐑚𐑳𐑑, 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑥𐑧𐑯, 𐑿 𐑖𐑨𐑤 𐑣𐑽.

“𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑥𐑹 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑩 𐑛𐑱 𐑹 𐑑𐑵 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑓𐑻𐑞𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑐𐑶𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑻 𐑐𐑮𐑬 𐑓 𐑣𐑻 𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑣𐑱𐑝𐑩𐑯, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑑𐑬𐑯-·𐑣𐑴'𐑟 𐑤𐑰𐑒 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑮𐑰𐑕𐑦𐑙, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑴 𐑨𐑟 𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑢𐑲𐑼 𐑩𐑯 𐑬𐑼 𐑹 𐑥𐑹 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑐𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑕 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑛𐑱. 𐑿 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑯𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑕𐑧𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑯 𐑕𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑤𐑲𐑟𐑛 𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑬𐑼 ·𐑩𐑑𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑒, 𐑓 𐑦𐑜𐑟𐑭𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑤, 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑕𐑒𐑦𐑐𐑼𐑟 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑐𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑺 𐑣𐑴𐑤 𐑢𐑱 𐑩𐑒𐑮𐑪𐑕 𐑦𐑑; 𐑞𐑴 𐑝 𐑩 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤, 𐑕𐑤𐑰𐑐𐑦 𐑯𐑲𐑑, 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑞 𐑪𐑓𐑦𐑕𐑼 𐑝 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑒 𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑩𐑯 𐑑 𐑓𐑼𐑜𐑧𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑛𐑿𐑑𐑦 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑, 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑚𐑩𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑚𐑰 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑥𐑱𐑑𐑕 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑧𐑥𐑚𐑼 𐑦𐑑, 𐑪𐑯 𐑩𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑷𐑤 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑕𐑲𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑞 𐑚𐑪𐑑𐑩𐑥. 𐑯𐑹 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑪𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑼𐑦 𐑯 𐑕𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑡 𐑕𐑰𐑟 𐑓𐑸 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑿 𐑑 𐑞 𐑢𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑢𐑼𐑛, 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑥𐑧𐑯, 𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑷𐑤𐑑𐑩𐑜𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑳𐑯𐑿𐑠𐑵𐑩𐑤 𐑓 𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑕 𐑑 𐑒𐑰𐑐 𐑒𐑤𐑨𐑙𐑦𐑙 𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑐𐑳𐑥𐑐-𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑓𐑫𐑤 𐑒𐑹𐑩𐑕 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑓 𐑩 𐑝𐑶𐑦𐑡 𐑝 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑼𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑤𐑧𐑙𐑔; 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑟, 𐑦𐑓 𐑦𐑑 𐑤𐑲 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑩 𐑑𐑪𐑤𐑼𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑩𐑒𐑕𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑒𐑴𐑕𐑑, 𐑹 𐑦𐑓 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑮𐑰𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑮𐑰𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑩𐑓𐑹𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑞𐑧𐑥. 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑩 𐑤𐑰𐑒𐑦 𐑝𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑱 𐑐𐑸𐑑 𐑝 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼𐑟, 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑮𐑾𐑤𐑦 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑤𐑨𐑑𐑦𐑑𐑿𐑛, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑻 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 𐑚𐑦𐑜𐑦𐑯𐑟 𐑑 𐑓𐑰𐑤 𐑩 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑕.

“𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑱 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑦𐑑 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 ·𐑑𐑬𐑯-·𐑣𐑴; 𐑕𐑴 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑣𐑻 𐑤𐑰𐑒 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑕 𐑥𐑹, 𐑞𐑺 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑑𐑮𐑵𐑔 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑕𐑥𐑷𐑤 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑻𐑯 𐑥𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑓𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑕𐑧𐑝𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑣𐑻 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑦; 𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑲 ·𐑮𐑨𐑛𐑯𐑦 𐑞 𐑥𐑱𐑑. 𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑭𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑞 𐑳𐑐𐑼 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑢𐑧𐑤 𐑣𐑶𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛, 𐑖𐑰𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑣𐑴𐑥 𐑩𐑯𐑿, 𐑯 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑢𐑱 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑑 𐑞 𐑚𐑮𐑰𐑟. 𐑯𐑬 𐑞𐑦𐑕 ·𐑮𐑨𐑛𐑯𐑦, 𐑲 𐑕𐑩𐑐𐑴𐑟, 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑨𐑟 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑩 𐑒𐑬𐑼𐑛, 𐑯 𐑨𐑟 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑤𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑑 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑕𐑹𐑑 𐑝 𐑯𐑻𐑝𐑩𐑕 𐑨𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑣𐑧𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑝𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑑𐑳𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑴𐑯 𐑐𐑻𐑕𐑩𐑯 𐑨𐑟 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑓𐑽𐑤𐑩𐑕, 𐑳𐑯𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑒𐑮𐑰𐑗𐑼 𐑪𐑯 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑹 𐑪𐑯 𐑕𐑰 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑿 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑝𐑰𐑯𐑾𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑥𐑨𐑡𐑦𐑯, 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑥𐑧𐑯. 𐑞𐑺𐑓𐑹 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑣𐑰 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑛 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑕𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑕𐑦𐑑𐑿𐑛 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑓𐑑𐑦 𐑝 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐, 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑺𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑪𐑯 𐑩𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑐𐑸𐑑 𐑴𐑯𐑼 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑻. 𐑕𐑴 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑞𐑱 𐑢𐑻 𐑢𐑻𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑰𐑝𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑐𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑕, 𐑞𐑺 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑪𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑯𐑴 𐑕𐑥𐑷𐑤 𐑜𐑱𐑥𐑕𐑩𐑥𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑕𐑤𐑲𐑤𐑦 𐑜𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑪𐑯 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑞𐑧𐑥, 𐑨𐑟 𐑞𐑱 𐑕𐑑𐑫𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞𐑺 𐑓𐑰𐑑 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑿𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑴𐑝𐑼𐑓𐑤𐑴𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑒𐑤𐑽 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼; 𐑒𐑤𐑽 𐑨𐑟 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑥𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑙, 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑥𐑧𐑯—𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑚𐑳𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑐𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑕 𐑮𐑨𐑯 𐑩𐑒𐑮𐑪𐑕 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑒, 𐑯 𐑐𐑹𐑛 𐑦𐑑𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑬𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑛𐑦 𐑕𐑐𐑬𐑑𐑕 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑤𐑰 𐑕𐑒𐑳𐑐𐑼-𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑟.

“𐑯𐑬, 𐑨𐑟 𐑿 𐑢𐑧𐑤 𐑯𐑴, 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑛𐑩𐑥 𐑞 𐑒𐑱𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑝𐑧𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛 𐑝 𐑬𐑼𐑟—𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼𐑦 𐑹 𐑳𐑞𐑼𐑢𐑲𐑟; 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑩 𐑐𐑻𐑕𐑩𐑯 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑭𐑯𐑛 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑧𐑤𐑴-𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑓𐑲𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑕𐑦𐑜𐑯𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑵𐑐𐑽𐑽 𐑦𐑯 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑐𐑮𐑲𐑛 𐑝 𐑥𐑨𐑯𐑣𐑫𐑛, 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑑𐑢𐑱 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑰𐑝𐑟 𐑩𐑯 𐑳𐑯𐑒𐑪𐑙𐑒𐑼𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑯 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑼𐑯𐑧𐑕; 𐑯 𐑦𐑓 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑩 𐑗𐑭𐑯𐑕 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑐𐑫𐑤 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑯 𐑐𐑳𐑤𐑝𐑼𐑲𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑑𐑼𐑯'𐑟 𐑑𐑬𐑼, 𐑯 𐑥𐑱𐑒 𐑩 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑣𐑰𐑐 𐑝 𐑛𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑝 𐑦𐑑. 𐑚𐑰 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑰𐑑 𐑝 𐑥𐑲𐑯 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑥𐑱, 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑥𐑧𐑯, 𐑨𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑦𐑝𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑕 ·𐑕𐑑𐑰𐑤𐑒𐑦𐑤𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩 𐑑𐑷𐑤 𐑯 𐑯𐑴𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑥𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 ·𐑮𐑴𐑥𐑩𐑯, 𐑯 𐑩 𐑓𐑤𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑜𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑩𐑯 𐑚𐑽𐑛 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑞 𐑑𐑨𐑕𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑣𐑬𐑟𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑝 𐑘𐑹 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑝𐑲𐑕𐑮𐑶'𐑟 𐑕𐑯𐑹𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑗𐑸𐑡𐑼; 𐑯 𐑩 𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑯, 𐑯 𐑩 𐑣𐑸𐑑, 𐑯 𐑩 𐑕𐑴𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑥𐑧𐑯, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑥𐑱𐑛 ·𐑕𐑑𐑰𐑤𐑒𐑦𐑤𐑑 ·𐑖𐑸𐑤𐑩𐑥𐑭𐑯𐑘𐑩, 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑣𐑰 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑚𐑹𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑯 𐑑 ·𐑖𐑸𐑤𐑩𐑥𐑭𐑯𐑘𐑩'𐑟 𐑓𐑭𐑞𐑼. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 ·𐑮𐑨𐑛𐑯𐑦, 𐑞 𐑥𐑱𐑑, 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑳𐑜𐑤𐑦 𐑨𐑟 𐑩 𐑥𐑿𐑤; 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑣𐑸𐑛𐑦, 𐑨𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚𐑼𐑯, 𐑨𐑟 𐑥𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑕. 𐑣𐑰 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑤𐑳𐑝 ·𐑕𐑑𐑰𐑤𐑒𐑦𐑤𐑑, 𐑯 ·𐑕𐑑𐑰𐑤𐑒𐑦𐑤𐑑 𐑯𐑿 𐑦𐑑.

“𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑲𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑥𐑱𐑑 𐑛𐑮𐑷𐑦𐑙 𐑯𐑽 𐑨𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑑𐑶𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑐𐑳𐑥𐑐 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑑, 𐑞 ·𐑤𐑱𐑒𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑩𐑓𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑑 𐑯𐑴𐑑𐑦𐑕 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑿𐑯𐑷𐑛, 𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑪𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑜𐑱 𐑚𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑦𐑙𐑟.

“'𐑲, 𐑲, 𐑥𐑲 𐑥𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑤𐑨𐑛𐑟, 𐑦𐑑'𐑕 𐑩 𐑤𐑲𐑝𐑤𐑦 𐑤𐑰𐑒 𐑞𐑦𐑕; 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑩 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑒𐑦𐑯, 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑘𐑰, 𐑯 𐑤𐑧𐑑'𐑕 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑩 𐑑𐑱𐑕𐑑. 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 ·𐑤𐑹𐑛, 𐑦𐑑'𐑕 𐑢𐑻𐑔 𐑚𐑪𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙! 𐑲 𐑑𐑧𐑤 𐑘𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑑, 𐑥𐑧𐑯, 𐑴𐑤𐑛 ·𐑮𐑨𐑛'𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑜𐑴 𐑓 𐑦𐑑! 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑒𐑳𐑑 𐑩𐑢𐑱 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑸𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑣𐑳𐑤 𐑯 𐑑𐑴 𐑦𐑑 𐑣𐑴𐑥. 𐑞 𐑓𐑨𐑒𐑑 𐑦𐑟, 𐑚𐑶𐑟, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑹𐑛-𐑓𐑦𐑖 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑦𐑜𐑨𐑯 𐑞 𐑡𐑪𐑚; 𐑣𐑰'𐑟 𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑚𐑨𐑒 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑜𐑨𐑙 𐑝 𐑖𐑦𐑐-𐑒𐑸𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑟, 𐑕𐑷-𐑓𐑦𐑖, 𐑯 𐑓𐑲𐑤-𐑓𐑦𐑖, 𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑑; 𐑯 𐑞 𐑣𐑴𐑤 𐑐𐑪𐑕𐑦 𐑝 '𐑩𐑥 𐑸 𐑯𐑬 𐑣𐑸𐑛 𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑻𐑒 𐑒𐑳𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑯 𐑕𐑤𐑨𐑖𐑦𐑙 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑚𐑪𐑑𐑩𐑥; 𐑥𐑱𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑮𐑵𐑝𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕, 𐑲 𐑕𐑩𐑐𐑴𐑟. 𐑦𐑓 𐑴𐑤𐑛 ·𐑮𐑨𐑛 𐑢𐑻 𐑣𐑽 𐑯𐑬, 𐑲'𐑛 𐑑𐑧𐑤 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑑 𐑡𐑳𐑥𐑐 𐑴𐑝𐑼𐑚𐑹𐑛 𐑯 𐑕𐑒𐑨𐑑𐑼 '𐑩𐑥. 𐑞𐑱'𐑼 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑑, 𐑲 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑑𐑧𐑤 𐑣𐑦𐑥. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑣𐑰'𐑟 𐑩 𐑕𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑤 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑕𐑴𐑤,—·𐑮𐑨𐑛, 𐑯 𐑩 𐑚𐑿𐑑𐑦 𐑑𐑵. 𐑚𐑶𐑟, 𐑞𐑱 𐑕𐑱 𐑞 𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑐𐑼𐑑𐑦 𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑦𐑙-𐑜𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑩𐑟. 𐑲 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑦𐑓 𐑣𐑰'𐑛 𐑜𐑦𐑝 𐑩 𐑐𐑫𐑼 𐑛𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑤 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑥𐑰 𐑞 𐑥𐑪𐑛𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑴𐑟.'

“'𐑛𐑨𐑥 𐑘𐑹 𐑲𐑟! 𐑢𐑪𐑑'𐑕 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑐𐑳𐑥𐑐 𐑕𐑑𐑪𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑓?' 𐑮𐑹𐑛 ·𐑮𐑨𐑛𐑯𐑦, 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑣𐑻𐑛 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑼𐑟' 𐑑𐑷𐑒. '𐑔𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑩𐑢𐑱 𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑑!'

“'𐑲, 𐑲, 𐑕𐑻,' 𐑕𐑧𐑛 ·𐑕𐑑𐑰𐑤𐑒𐑦𐑤𐑑, 𐑥𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑨𐑟 𐑩 𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑑. '𐑤𐑲𐑝𐑤𐑦, 𐑚𐑶𐑟, 𐑤𐑲𐑝𐑤𐑦, 𐑯𐑬!' 𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑐𐑳𐑥𐑐 𐑒𐑤𐑨𐑙𐑛 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑓𐑦𐑓𐑑𐑦 𐑓𐑲𐑼-𐑧𐑯𐑡𐑦𐑯𐑟; 𐑞 𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑑𐑪𐑕𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑣𐑨𐑑𐑕 𐑪𐑓 𐑑 𐑦𐑑, 𐑯 𐑺 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑽 𐑜𐑭𐑕𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑞 𐑤𐑳𐑙𐑟 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑣𐑻𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑛𐑦𐑯𐑴𐑑𐑕 𐑞 𐑓𐑫𐑤𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑤𐑲𐑓'𐑕 𐑳𐑑𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑧𐑯𐑼𐑡𐑦𐑟.

“𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑐𐑳𐑥𐑐 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑨𐑯𐑛, 𐑞 ·𐑤𐑱𐑒𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑓𐑹𐑢𐑼𐑛 𐑷𐑤 𐑐𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑙, 𐑯 𐑕𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑤𐑩𐑕; 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑱𐑕 𐑓𐑲𐑼𐑦 𐑮𐑧𐑛, 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑲𐑟 𐑚𐑤𐑳𐑛𐑖𐑪𐑑, 𐑯 𐑢𐑲𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑓𐑿𐑕 𐑕𐑢𐑧𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑮𐑬. 𐑯𐑬 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑒𐑳𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑰𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟, 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑥𐑧𐑯, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑐𐑩𐑟𐑧𐑕𐑑 ·𐑮𐑨𐑛𐑯𐑦 𐑑 𐑥𐑧𐑛𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑒𐑹𐑐𐑹𐑾𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑜𐑟𐑨𐑕𐑐𐑼𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑑, 𐑲 𐑯𐑴 𐑯𐑪𐑑; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑕𐑴 𐑦𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑛. 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑪𐑤𐑼𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑒, 𐑞 𐑥𐑱𐑑 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑭𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑑 𐑜𐑧𐑑 𐑩 𐑚𐑮𐑵𐑥 𐑯 𐑕𐑢𐑰𐑐 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑞 𐑐𐑤𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑕, 𐑯 𐑷𐑤𐑕𐑴 𐑩 𐑖𐑳𐑝𐑩𐑤, 𐑯 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑵𐑝 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑩𐑓𐑧𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑝 𐑥𐑨𐑑𐑼𐑟 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑢𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑩𐑤𐑬𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑐𐑦𐑜 𐑑 𐑮𐑳𐑯 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑸𐑡.

“𐑯𐑬, 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑥𐑧𐑯, 𐑕𐑢𐑰𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑖𐑦𐑐'𐑕 𐑛𐑧𐑒 𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑰 𐑦𐑟 𐑩 𐑐𐑰𐑕 𐑝 𐑣𐑬𐑕𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑢𐑻𐑒 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑦𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑮𐑱𐑡𐑦𐑙 𐑜𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑦𐑟 𐑮𐑧𐑜𐑿𐑤𐑼𐑤𐑦 𐑩𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑑 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑰𐑝𐑯𐑦𐑙; 𐑦𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑯𐑴𐑯 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑛𐑳𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑒𐑱𐑕 𐑝 𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑕 𐑨𐑒𐑗𐑵𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑑𐑲𐑥. 𐑕𐑳𐑗, 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑥𐑧𐑯, 𐑦𐑟 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑓𐑤𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑝 𐑕𐑰-𐑿𐑕𐑦𐑡𐑩𐑟 𐑯 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑝 𐑤𐑳𐑝 𐑝 𐑯𐑰𐑑𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑧𐑯; 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑝 𐑣𐑵𐑥 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑮𐑬𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑖𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑺 𐑓𐑱𐑕𐑩𐑟. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑝𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑚𐑮𐑵𐑥 𐑚𐑦𐑟𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑦𐑟 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑝 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑝𐑦𐑯𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑚𐑶𐑟, 𐑦𐑓 𐑚𐑶𐑟 𐑞𐑺 𐑚𐑰 𐑩𐑚𐑹𐑛. 𐑚𐑦𐑕𐑲𐑛𐑟, 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑪𐑙𐑜𐑼 𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑑𐑬𐑯-·𐑣𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑛𐑦𐑝𐑲𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑜𐑨𐑙𐑟, 𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑟 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑐𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑕; 𐑯 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑨𐑔𐑤𐑧𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑷𐑤, ·𐑕𐑑𐑰𐑤𐑒𐑦𐑤𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑮𐑧𐑜𐑿𐑤𐑼𐑤𐑦 𐑩𐑕𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 𐑝 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑜𐑨𐑙𐑟; 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑢𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑣𐑰 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑰𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑝𐑾𐑤 𐑚𐑦𐑟𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑑𐑮𐑵𐑤𐑦 𐑯𐑷𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑛𐑿𐑑𐑦𐑟, 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑒𐑱𐑕 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑮𐑱𐑛𐑟. 𐑲 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑐𐑼𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑼𐑟 𐑕𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑿 𐑥𐑱 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑜𐑟𐑨𐑒𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑣𐑬 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑩𐑓𐑺 𐑕𐑑𐑫𐑛 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑢𐑰𐑯 𐑞 𐑑𐑵 𐑥𐑧𐑯.

“𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑥𐑹 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕: 𐑞 𐑹𐑛𐑼 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑞 𐑖𐑳𐑝𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑳𐑤𐑑 ·𐑕𐑑𐑰𐑤𐑒𐑦𐑤𐑑, 𐑨𐑟 𐑞𐑴 ·𐑮𐑨𐑛𐑯𐑦 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑕𐑐𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑱𐑕. 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑣𐑵 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑜𐑪𐑯 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑼 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑢𐑱𐑤-𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑞𐑦𐑕; 𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑯 𐑛𐑬𐑑𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑥𐑹, 𐑞 ·𐑤𐑱𐑒𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑓𐑫𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑣𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑞 𐑥𐑱𐑑 𐑳𐑑𐑼𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑭𐑯𐑛. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑓 𐑩 𐑥𐑴𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑, 𐑯 𐑨𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑛𐑓𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑥𐑱𐑑'𐑕 𐑥𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑜𐑯𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑲 𐑯 𐑐𐑼𐑕𐑰𐑝𐑛 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑒𐑕 𐑝 𐑐𐑬𐑛𐑼-𐑒𐑭𐑕𐑒𐑕 𐑣𐑰𐑐𐑑 𐑳𐑐 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑤𐑴-𐑥𐑨𐑗 𐑕𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑑𐑩𐑢𐑹𐑛𐑟 𐑞𐑧𐑥; 𐑨𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑝𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑷 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑦𐑕, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡 𐑓𐑹𐑚𐑺𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑯 𐑳𐑯𐑢𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑙𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑻 𐑳𐑐 𐑞 𐑛𐑰𐑐𐑼 𐑐𐑨𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑑𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑷𐑤𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑦 𐑲𐑼𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙—𐑩 𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑳𐑜𐑯𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑓𐑧𐑤𐑑, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑓𐑧𐑤𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑷𐑤, 𐑚𐑲 𐑮𐑾𐑤𐑦 𐑝𐑨𐑤𐑾𐑯𐑑 𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑩𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑝𐑛—𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑯𐑱𐑥𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑓𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑥 𐑓𐑰𐑤𐑦𐑙, 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑥𐑧𐑯, 𐑕𐑑𐑴𐑤 𐑴𐑝𐑼 ·𐑕𐑑𐑰𐑤𐑒𐑦𐑤𐑑.

“𐑞𐑺𐑓𐑹, 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑹𐑛𐑦𐑯𐑼𐑦 𐑑𐑴𐑯, 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑩 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑚𐑮𐑴𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑜𐑟𐑷𐑕𐑗𐑩𐑯 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑑𐑧𐑥𐑐𐑼𐑺𐑦𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑯, 𐑣𐑰 𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑼𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑕𐑱𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑢𐑰𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑒 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑦𐑟𐑯𐑩𐑕, 𐑯 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑛𐑵 𐑦𐑑. 𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑩𐑤𐑵𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑞 𐑖𐑳𐑝𐑩𐑤, 𐑣𐑰 𐑐𐑶𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑑 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑤𐑨𐑛𐑟 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑒𐑳𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑥𐑼𐑦 𐑕𐑢𐑰𐑐𐑼𐑟; 𐑣𐑵, 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑩𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑐𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑕, 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑛𐑳𐑯 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑹 𐑯𐑳𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑷𐑤 𐑛𐑱. 𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕, ·𐑮𐑨𐑛𐑯𐑦 𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑤𐑲𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩𐑯 𐑴𐑔, 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑛𐑪𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑽𐑦𐑙 𐑯 𐑬𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑡𐑩𐑕 𐑥𐑨𐑯𐑼 𐑳𐑯𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑰𐑦𐑑𐑼𐑱𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑭𐑯𐑛; 𐑥𐑰𐑯𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑩𐑛𐑝𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑕𐑰𐑑𐑩𐑛 ·𐑤𐑱𐑒𐑥𐑩𐑯, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩𐑯 𐑳𐑐𐑤𐑦𐑓𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑒𐑵𐑐𐑼'𐑟 𐑒𐑤𐑳𐑚 𐑣𐑨𐑥𐑼 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑕𐑯𐑨𐑗𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑩 𐑒𐑭𐑕𐑒 𐑯𐑽 𐑚𐑲.

“𐑣𐑰𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑯 𐑦𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑨𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑚𐑲 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑐𐑨𐑟𐑥𐑪𐑛𐑦𐑒 𐑑𐑶𐑤 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑐𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑕, 𐑓 𐑷𐑤 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑯𐑱𐑥𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑓𐑰𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑓𐑹𐑚𐑺𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑞 𐑕𐑢𐑧𐑑𐑦𐑙 ·𐑕𐑑𐑰𐑤𐑒𐑦𐑤𐑑 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑤 𐑚𐑮𐑫𐑒 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑚𐑺𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑥𐑱𐑑; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑣𐑬 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑕𐑥𐑳𐑞𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑓𐑤𐑩𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑 𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑰 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑱𐑯𐑛 𐑛𐑪𐑜𐑩𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑵𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑰𐑑, 𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑕𐑑 ·𐑮𐑨𐑛𐑯𐑦 𐑖𐑫𐑒 𐑞 𐑣𐑨𐑥𐑼 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑓𐑿 𐑦𐑯𐑗𐑩𐑟 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑱𐑕, 𐑓𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑾𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑭𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑑 𐑛𐑵 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑦𐑛𐑦𐑙.

“𐑕𐑑𐑰𐑤𐑒𐑦𐑤𐑑 𐑮𐑴𐑟, 𐑯 𐑕𐑤𐑴𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑮𐑰𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑞 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑤𐑩𐑕, 𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑦 𐑓𐑪𐑤𐑴𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑥𐑱𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑩𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑨𐑥𐑼, 𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑚𐑼𐑩𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑰𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑑 𐑴𐑚𐑱. 𐑕𐑰𐑦𐑙, 𐑣𐑬𐑧𐑝𐑼, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑹𐑚𐑺𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑤𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑓𐑧𐑒𐑑, 𐑚𐑲 𐑩𐑯 𐑷𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑯 𐑳𐑯𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑥𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑑𐑢𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑹𐑯𐑛 𐑪𐑓 𐑞 𐑓𐑵𐑤𐑦𐑖 𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑓𐑨𐑗𐑵𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑥𐑨𐑯; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑑 𐑯𐑴 𐑐𐑻𐑐𐑩𐑕. 𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑱 𐑞 𐑑𐑵 𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑕 𐑕𐑤𐑴𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑞 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑤𐑩𐑕; 𐑢𐑧𐑯, 𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑪𐑤𐑝𐑛 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑯𐑴 𐑤𐑪𐑙𐑜𐑼 𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑮𐑰𐑑, 𐑚𐑦𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑯𐑬 𐑓𐑹𐑚𐑹𐑯 𐑨𐑟 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑨𐑟 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑹𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑿𐑥𐑼, 𐑞 ·𐑤𐑱𐑒𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑐𐑷𐑟𐑛 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑣𐑨𐑗𐑩𐑟 𐑯 𐑞𐑳𐑕 𐑕𐑐𐑴𐑒 𐑑 𐑞 𐑪𐑓𐑦𐑕𐑼:

“'·𐑥𐑼 ·𐑮𐑨𐑛𐑯𐑦, 𐑲 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑴𐑚𐑱 𐑿. 𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑥𐑼 𐑩𐑢𐑱, 𐑹 𐑤𐑫𐑒 𐑑 𐑘𐑹𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓.' 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑰𐑛𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑥𐑱𐑑 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑒𐑤𐑴𐑕𐑼 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑢𐑺 𐑞 ·𐑤𐑱𐑒𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑫𐑛 𐑓𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑑, 𐑯𐑬 𐑖𐑫𐑒 𐑞 𐑣𐑧𐑝𐑦 𐑣𐑨𐑥𐑼 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑦𐑯 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑗 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑑𐑰𐑔; 𐑥𐑰𐑯𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑰𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑳𐑓𐑼𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑥𐑨𐑤𐑩𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟. 𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑮𐑰𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑞 𐑔𐑬𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑛𐑔 𐑐𐑸𐑑 𐑝 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑗; 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑚𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑲 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑳𐑯𐑓𐑤𐑦𐑯𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑐𐑪𐑯𐑘𐑼𐑛 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑜𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑕, ·𐑕𐑑𐑰𐑤𐑒𐑦𐑤𐑑, 𐑒𐑤𐑧𐑯𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑮𐑲𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑚𐑦𐑣𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑯 𐑒𐑮𐑰𐑐𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑮𐑷𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑑 𐑚𐑨𐑒, 𐑑𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑻𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑑𐑼 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑓 𐑞 𐑣𐑨𐑥𐑼 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑟𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑗𐑰𐑒 𐑣𐑰 (·𐑕𐑑𐑰𐑤𐑒𐑦𐑤𐑑) 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑥𐑻𐑛𐑼 𐑣𐑦𐑥. 𐑚𐑳𐑑, 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑥𐑧𐑯, 𐑞 𐑓𐑵𐑤 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑚𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑓 𐑞 𐑕𐑤𐑷𐑑𐑼 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑜𐑪𐑛𐑟. 𐑦𐑥𐑰𐑛𐑾𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑞 𐑣𐑨𐑥𐑼 𐑑𐑳𐑗𐑑 𐑞 𐑗𐑰𐑒; 𐑞 𐑯𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑞 𐑤𐑴𐑼 𐑡𐑷 𐑝 𐑞 𐑥𐑱𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑴𐑝 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑧𐑛; 𐑣𐑰 𐑓𐑧𐑤 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑣𐑨𐑗 𐑕𐑐𐑬𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑤𐑳𐑛 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑢𐑱𐑤.

“𐑺 𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑲 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑜𐑴 𐑭𐑓𐑑 ·𐑕𐑑𐑰𐑤𐑒𐑦𐑤𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑖𐑱𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑚𐑨𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑟 𐑤𐑰𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑸 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑓𐑑 𐑑 𐑢𐑺 𐑑𐑵 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑮𐑱𐑛𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑺 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑟. 𐑞𐑱 𐑢𐑻 𐑚𐑴𐑔 ·𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑨𐑤𐑼𐑟.

“'𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑨𐑤𐑼𐑟!' 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 ·𐑛𐑪𐑯 ·𐑐𐑧𐑛𐑮𐑴. '𐑢𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑕𐑰𐑯 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑢𐑱𐑤-𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑬𐑼 𐑣𐑸𐑚𐑼𐑟, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑣𐑻𐑛 𐑝 𐑘𐑹 ·𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑨𐑤𐑼𐑟. 𐑐𐑸𐑛𐑩𐑯: 𐑣𐑵 𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑸 𐑞𐑱?'

“'𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑨𐑤𐑼𐑟, ·𐑛𐑪𐑯, 𐑸 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑪𐑙𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑬𐑼 𐑜𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑛 ·𐑽𐑦 ·𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑨𐑤. 𐑿 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑣𐑻𐑛 𐑝 𐑦𐑑.'

“'𐑯𐑱, ·𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑘𐑹; 𐑣𐑽𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑛𐑳𐑤, 𐑢𐑹𐑥, 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑤𐑱𐑟𐑦, 𐑯 𐑣𐑼𐑧𐑛𐑦𐑑𐑼𐑦 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛, 𐑢𐑰 𐑯𐑴 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑘𐑹 𐑝𐑦𐑜𐑼𐑩𐑕 ·𐑯𐑹𐑔.'

“'𐑲? 𐑢𐑧𐑤 𐑞𐑧𐑯, ·𐑛𐑪𐑯, 𐑮𐑰𐑓𐑦𐑤 𐑥𐑲 𐑒𐑳𐑐. 𐑘𐑹 𐑗𐑦𐑗𐑩'𐑟 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑓𐑲𐑯; 𐑯 𐑺 𐑐𐑮𐑴𐑕𐑰𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑻𐑞𐑼 𐑲 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑑𐑧𐑤 𐑘𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑬𐑼 ·𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑨𐑤𐑼𐑟 𐑸; 𐑓 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑦𐑯𐑓𐑼𐑥𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑥𐑱 𐑔𐑮𐑴 𐑕𐑲𐑛-𐑤𐑲𐑑 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑥𐑲 𐑕𐑑𐑹𐑦.'

“𐑓 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑛 𐑯 𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑦 𐑥𐑲𐑤𐑟, 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑥𐑧𐑯, 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑲𐑼 𐑚𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑔 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑑 𐑝 ·𐑯𐑿 ·𐑘𐑹𐑒; 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑯𐑿𐑥𐑼𐑩𐑕 𐑐𐑪𐑐𐑿𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑕𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑟 𐑯 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑔𐑮𐑲𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑝𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑡𐑩𐑟; 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑤𐑪𐑙, 𐑛𐑦𐑟𐑥𐑩𐑤, 𐑳𐑯𐑦𐑯𐑣𐑨𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑕𐑢𐑪𐑥𐑐𐑕, 𐑯 𐑨𐑓𐑤𐑵𐑩𐑯𐑑, 𐑒𐑳𐑤𐑑𐑦𐑝𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑓𐑰𐑤𐑛𐑟, 𐑳𐑯𐑮𐑲𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑓 𐑓𐑼𐑑𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑦; 𐑚𐑲 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑘𐑼𐑛-𐑮𐑵𐑥 𐑯 𐑚𐑸-𐑮𐑵𐑥; 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑞 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑦-𐑝-𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑦𐑟 𐑝 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑓𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑕; 𐑪𐑯 ·𐑮𐑴𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑸𐑗𐑩𐑟 𐑴𐑝𐑼 ·𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑾𐑯 𐑮𐑦𐑝𐑼𐑟; 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑕𐑳𐑯 𐑯 𐑖𐑱𐑛; 𐑚𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑦 𐑣𐑸𐑑𐑕 𐑹 𐑚𐑮𐑴𐑒𐑩𐑯; 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑢𐑲𐑛 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑰𐑯𐑼𐑦 𐑝 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑯𐑴𐑚𐑩𐑤 ·𐑥𐑴𐑣𐑷𐑒 𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑟; 𐑯 𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑤𐑦, 𐑚𐑲 𐑮𐑴𐑟 𐑝 𐑕𐑯𐑴-𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑩𐑤𐑟, 𐑣𐑵𐑟 𐑕𐑐𐑲𐑼𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑥𐑲𐑤𐑕𐑑𐑴𐑯𐑟, 𐑓𐑤𐑴𐑟 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑿𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑰𐑥 𐑝 ·𐑝𐑩𐑯𐑰𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑼𐑳𐑐𐑑 𐑯 𐑪𐑓𐑩𐑯 𐑤𐑷𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑤𐑲𐑓. 𐑞𐑺'𐑟 𐑘𐑹 𐑑𐑮𐑵 ·𐑨𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑰, 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑥𐑧𐑯; 𐑞𐑺 𐑣𐑬𐑤 𐑘𐑹 𐑐𐑱𐑜𐑩𐑯𐑟; 𐑢𐑺 𐑿 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑓𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑞𐑧𐑥, 𐑯𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑 𐑛𐑹 𐑑 𐑿; 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑞 𐑤𐑪𐑙-𐑓𐑤𐑳𐑙 𐑖𐑨𐑛𐑴, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑯𐑳𐑜 𐑐𐑨𐑑𐑮𐑩𐑯𐑲𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑤𐑰 𐑝 𐑗𐑻𐑗𐑩𐑟. 𐑓 𐑚𐑲 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑒𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑾𐑕 𐑓𐑩𐑑𐑨𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑦, 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑪𐑓𐑩𐑯 𐑯𐑴𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑝 𐑘𐑹 𐑥𐑧𐑑𐑮𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑰𐑚𐑵𐑑𐑼𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑱 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑨𐑥𐑐 𐑼𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑞 𐑣𐑷𐑤𐑟 𐑝 𐑡𐑳𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑕, 𐑕𐑴 𐑕𐑦𐑯𐑼𐑟, 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑥𐑧𐑯, 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑾𐑕𐑑 𐑝𐑦𐑕𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑟.

“'𐑦𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑩 𐑓𐑮𐑲𐑼 𐑐𐑭𐑕𐑦𐑙?' 𐑕𐑧𐑛 ·𐑛𐑪𐑯 ·𐑐𐑧𐑛𐑮𐑴, 𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑛𐑬𐑯𐑢𐑼𐑛𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑬𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑐𐑤𐑩𐑟𐑩, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑿𐑥𐑼𐑩𐑕 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑻𐑯.

“'𐑢𐑧𐑤 𐑓 𐑬𐑼 𐑯𐑹𐑞𐑼𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑯𐑛, ·𐑛𐑱𐑥 ·𐑦𐑟𐑩𐑚𐑧𐑤𐑩'𐑟 ·𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑟𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑱𐑯𐑟 𐑦𐑯 ·𐑤𐑰𐑥𐑩,' 𐑤𐑭𐑓𐑑 ·𐑛𐑪𐑯 ·𐑕𐑦𐑚𐑨𐑕𐑗𐑩𐑯. '𐑐𐑮𐑴𐑕𐑰𐑛, ·𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑘𐑹.'

“'𐑩 𐑥𐑴𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑! 𐑐𐑸𐑛𐑩𐑯!' 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 𐑩𐑯𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑝 𐑞 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑦. '𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑯𐑱𐑥 𐑝 𐑷𐑤 𐑳𐑕 ·𐑤𐑲𐑥𐑰𐑟, 𐑲 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑟𐑲𐑼 𐑑 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑕 𐑑 𐑿, 𐑕𐑻 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑼, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑚𐑲 𐑯𐑴 𐑥𐑰𐑯𐑟 𐑴𐑝𐑼𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑑 𐑘𐑹 𐑛𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑕𐑦 𐑦𐑯 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑚𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑑𐑿𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑑 ·𐑤𐑰𐑥𐑩 𐑓 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑 ·𐑝𐑧𐑯𐑦𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑘𐑹 𐑒𐑼𐑳𐑐𐑑 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑩𐑯. 𐑴! 𐑛𐑵 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑚𐑬 𐑯 𐑤𐑫𐑒 𐑕𐑼𐑐𐑮𐑲𐑟𐑛; 𐑿 𐑯𐑴 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑝𐑻𐑚 𐑷𐑤 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑒𐑴𐑕𐑑—“𐑒𐑼𐑳𐑐𐑑 𐑨𐑟 ·𐑤𐑰𐑥𐑩.” 𐑦𐑑 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑚𐑺𐑟 𐑬𐑑 𐑘𐑹 𐑕𐑱𐑦𐑙, 𐑑𐑵; 𐑗𐑻𐑗𐑩𐑟 𐑥𐑹 𐑐𐑤𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑘𐑼𐑛-𐑑𐑱𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑟, 𐑯 𐑓 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑴𐑐𐑩𐑯—𐑯 “𐑒𐑼𐑳𐑐𐑑 𐑨𐑟 ·𐑤𐑰𐑥𐑩.” 𐑕𐑴, 𐑑𐑵, ·𐑝𐑧𐑯𐑦𐑕; 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑞𐑺; 𐑞 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑝 𐑞 𐑚𐑤𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑝𐑨𐑯𐑡𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑕𐑑, ·𐑕𐑑 ·𐑥𐑸𐑒!—𐑕𐑑 ·𐑛𐑪𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑒, 𐑐𐑻𐑡 𐑦𐑑! 𐑘𐑹 𐑒𐑳𐑐! 𐑔𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑕: 𐑣𐑽 𐑲 𐑮𐑰𐑓𐑦𐑤; 𐑯𐑬, 𐑿 𐑐𐑹 𐑬𐑑 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯.'

“𐑓𐑮𐑰𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑦𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑴𐑯 𐑝𐑴𐑒𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯, 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑥𐑧𐑯, 𐑞 ·𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑨𐑤𐑼 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑥𐑱𐑒 𐑩 𐑓𐑲𐑯 𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑥𐑨𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑣𐑽𐑴, 𐑕𐑴 𐑩𐑚𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑯 𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑗𐑼𐑧𐑕𐑒𐑤𐑦 𐑢𐑦𐑒𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑰. 𐑤𐑲𐑒 ·𐑥𐑸𐑒 ·𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑦, 𐑓 𐑛𐑱𐑟 𐑯 𐑛𐑱𐑟 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑯-𐑑𐑻𐑓𐑑, 𐑓𐑤𐑬𐑼𐑦 ·𐑯𐑲𐑤, 𐑣𐑰 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑓𐑤𐑴𐑑𐑕, 𐑴𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑑𐑶𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑮𐑧𐑛-𐑗𐑰𐑒𐑑 ·𐑒𐑤𐑦𐑴𐑐𐑨𐑑𐑮𐑩, 𐑮𐑲𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑱𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑪𐑑 𐑔𐑲 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑯𐑦 𐑛𐑧𐑒. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑩𐑖𐑹, 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑦𐑓𐑧𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑕𐑦 𐑦𐑟 𐑛𐑨𐑖𐑑. 𐑞 𐑚𐑮𐑦𐑜𐑩𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑖 𐑜𐑲𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑞 ·𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑨𐑤𐑼 𐑕𐑴 𐑐𐑮𐑬𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑐𐑹𐑑𐑕; 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑤𐑬𐑗𐑑 𐑯 𐑜𐑱𐑤𐑦-𐑮𐑦𐑚𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑴𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑜𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑓𐑰𐑗𐑼𐑟. 𐑩 𐑑𐑧𐑮𐑼 𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑥𐑲𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑝𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑡𐑩𐑟 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑣𐑰 𐑓𐑤𐑴𐑑𐑕; 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑢𐑸𐑑 𐑝𐑦𐑟𐑦𐑡 𐑯 𐑚𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑕𐑢𐑨𐑜𐑼 𐑸 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑳𐑯𐑖𐑳𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑟. 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑕 𐑩 𐑝𐑨𐑜𐑩𐑚𐑪𐑯𐑛 𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑴𐑯 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑨𐑤, 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑰𐑝𐑛 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑟 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑞𐑰𐑟 ·𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑨𐑤𐑼𐑟; 𐑲 𐑔𐑨𐑙𐑒 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑣𐑸𐑑𐑦𐑤𐑦; 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑓𐑱𐑯 𐑚𐑰 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑳𐑯𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑𐑓𐑩𐑤; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑪𐑓𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑲𐑥 𐑮𐑦𐑛𐑰𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑟 𐑝 𐑘𐑹 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑝 𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑕, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑨𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑓 𐑩𐑯 𐑸𐑥 𐑑 𐑚𐑨𐑒 𐑩 𐑐𐑫𐑼 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑼 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑑, 𐑨𐑟 𐑑 𐑐𐑤𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑩 𐑢𐑧𐑤𐑔𐑦 𐑢𐑳𐑯. 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥, 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑥𐑧𐑯, 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑞 𐑢𐑲𐑤𐑛𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑨𐑤 𐑤𐑲𐑓 𐑦𐑟, 𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑥𐑓𐑨𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑞𐑦𐑕; 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑬𐑼 𐑢𐑲𐑤𐑛 𐑢𐑱𐑤-𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑼𐑦 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑱𐑯𐑟 𐑕𐑴 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑝 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑓𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑖𐑑 𐑜𐑮𐑨𐑡𐑵𐑩𐑑𐑕, 𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑒𐑺𐑕 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑮𐑱𐑕 𐑝 𐑥𐑨𐑯𐑒𐑲𐑯𐑛, 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑧𐑐𐑑 ·𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑯𐑦 𐑥𐑧𐑯, 𐑸 𐑕𐑴 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑬𐑼 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑟. 𐑯𐑹 𐑛𐑳𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑛𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑖 𐑞 𐑒𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑾𐑕𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑥𐑨𐑑𐑼, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑑 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑔𐑬𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑝 𐑬𐑼 𐑮𐑫𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑚𐑶𐑟 𐑯 𐑘𐑳𐑙 𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑚𐑹𐑯 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑤𐑲𐑯, 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑴𐑚𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑼𐑦 𐑤𐑲𐑓 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑜𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑛 ·𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑨𐑤 𐑓𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑟 𐑞 𐑕𐑴𐑤 𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑟𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑢𐑰𐑯 𐑒𐑢𐑲𐑩𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑰𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 ·𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑗𐑩𐑯 𐑒𐑹𐑯-𐑓𐑰𐑤𐑛, 𐑯 𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑤𐑩𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑤𐑬𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑸𐑚𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑒 𐑕𐑰𐑟.

“'𐑲 𐑕𐑰! 𐑲 𐑕𐑰!' 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑧𐑗𐑵𐑩𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑒𐑤𐑱𐑥𐑛 ·𐑛𐑪𐑯 ·𐑐𐑧𐑛𐑮𐑴, 𐑕𐑐𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑗𐑦𐑗𐑩 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑦𐑤𐑝𐑼𐑦 𐑮𐑳𐑓𐑩𐑤𐑟. '𐑯𐑴 𐑯𐑰𐑛 𐑑 𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑝𐑩𐑤! 𐑞 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛'𐑟 𐑢𐑳𐑯 ·𐑤𐑰𐑥𐑩. 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑔𐑷𐑑, 𐑯𐑬, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑘𐑹 𐑑𐑧𐑥𐑐𐑼𐑩𐑑 ·𐑯𐑹𐑔 𐑞 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑼𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑒𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑯 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑦 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑤𐑟.—𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑹𐑦.'

“𐑲 𐑤𐑧𐑓𐑑 𐑪𐑓, 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑥𐑧𐑯, 𐑢𐑺 𐑞 ·𐑤𐑱𐑒𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑖𐑫𐑒 𐑞 𐑚𐑨𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑱. 𐑣𐑸𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑣𐑰 𐑛𐑳𐑯 𐑕𐑴, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑼𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑡𐑵𐑯𐑽 𐑥𐑱𐑑𐑕 𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑹 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑽𐑟, 𐑣𐑵 𐑷𐑤 𐑒𐑮𐑬𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑑 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑒. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑕𐑤𐑲𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑞 𐑮𐑴𐑐𐑕 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑚𐑱𐑤𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑑𐑕, 𐑞 𐑑𐑵 ·𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑨𐑤𐑼𐑟 𐑮𐑳𐑖𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑳𐑐𐑮𐑹, 𐑯 𐑕𐑷𐑑 𐑑 𐑛𐑮𐑨𐑜 𐑞𐑺 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑦𐑑 𐑑𐑩𐑢𐑹𐑛𐑟 𐑞 𐑓𐑴𐑒𐑕𐑩𐑤. 𐑳𐑞𐑼𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑼𐑟 𐑡𐑶𐑯𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑩𐑑𐑧𐑥𐑐𐑑, 𐑯 𐑩 𐑑𐑢𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑑𐑻𐑥𐑶𐑤 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑿𐑛; 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑣𐑸𐑥'𐑟 𐑢𐑱, 𐑞 𐑝𐑨𐑤𐑾𐑯𐑑 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 𐑛𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑳𐑐 𐑯 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑢𐑱𐑤-𐑐𐑲𐑒, 𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑪𐑓𐑦𐑕𐑼𐑟 𐑑 𐑥𐑨𐑯𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑤 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑩𐑑𐑮𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑕 𐑕𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑤, 𐑯 𐑕𐑥𐑴𐑒 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑑 𐑞 𐑒𐑢𐑹𐑑𐑼-𐑛𐑧𐑒. 𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑟, 𐑣𐑰 𐑮𐑨𐑯 𐑒𐑤𐑴𐑕 𐑳𐑐 𐑑 𐑞 𐑮𐑦𐑝𐑪𐑤𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑹𐑛𐑼 𐑝 𐑞 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑓𐑿𐑠𐑩𐑯, 𐑯 𐑐𐑮𐑲𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑣𐑸𐑑 𐑝 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑲𐑒, 𐑕𐑷𐑑 𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑒 𐑬𐑑 𐑞 𐑪𐑚𐑡𐑧𐑒𐑑 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 ·𐑕𐑑𐑰𐑤𐑒𐑦𐑤𐑑 𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑛𐑧𐑕𐑐𐑼𐑭𐑛𐑴𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑑𐑵 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑓 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑷𐑤; 𐑞𐑱 𐑕𐑩𐑒𐑕𐑰𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑓𐑴𐑒𐑕𐑩𐑤 𐑛𐑧𐑒, 𐑢𐑺, 𐑣𐑱𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑤𐑵𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑹 𐑓𐑹 𐑤𐑸𐑡 𐑒𐑭𐑕𐑒𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑤𐑲𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑤𐑩𐑕, 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑕𐑰-·𐑐𐑼𐑦𐑟𐑾𐑯𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑧𐑯𐑗𐑑 𐑞𐑧𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑝𐑟 𐑚𐑦𐑣𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑞 𐑚𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑱𐑛.

“'𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑, 𐑘𐑰 𐑐𐑲𐑮𐑩𐑑𐑕!' 𐑮𐑹𐑛 𐑞 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯, 𐑯𐑬 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑩𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑐𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑰𐑗 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛, 𐑡𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑮𐑷𐑑 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑿𐑼𐑛. '𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑, 𐑘𐑰 𐑒𐑳𐑑-𐑔𐑮𐑴𐑑𐑕!'

“𐑕𐑑𐑰𐑤𐑒𐑦𐑤𐑑 𐑤𐑰𐑐𐑑 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑱𐑛, 𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑳𐑐 𐑯 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑞𐑺, 𐑛𐑦𐑓𐑲𐑛 𐑞 𐑢𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑞 𐑐𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑛𐑵; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑜𐑱𐑝 𐑞 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 𐑑 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑑𐑤𐑦, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 (·𐑕𐑑𐑰𐑤𐑒𐑦𐑤𐑑'𐑕) 𐑛𐑧𐑔 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑚𐑰 𐑞 𐑕𐑦𐑜𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑓 𐑩 𐑥𐑻𐑛𐑼𐑩𐑕 𐑥𐑿𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑦 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑐𐑸𐑑 𐑝 𐑷𐑤 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟. 𐑓𐑽𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑸𐑑 𐑤𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑵𐑝 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑑𐑵 𐑑𐑮𐑵, 𐑞 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑛𐑦𐑟𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑭𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑻𐑡𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑻𐑯 𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑛𐑿𐑑𐑦.

“'𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑿 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑥𐑦𐑕 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑑 𐑑𐑳𐑗 𐑳𐑕, 𐑦𐑓 𐑢𐑰 𐑛𐑵?' 𐑛𐑦𐑥𐑭𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑞𐑺 𐑮𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑰𐑛𐑼.

“'𐑑𐑻𐑯 𐑑! 𐑑𐑻𐑯 𐑑!—𐑲 𐑥𐑱𐑒 𐑯𐑴 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑥𐑦𐑕;—𐑑 𐑘𐑹 𐑛𐑿𐑑𐑦! 𐑛𐑵 𐑿 𐑢𐑪𐑯𐑑 𐑑 𐑕𐑦𐑙𐑒 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐, 𐑚𐑲 𐑯𐑪𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑪𐑓 𐑨𐑑 𐑩 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑞𐑦𐑕? 𐑑𐑻𐑯 𐑑!' 𐑯 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑕 𐑥𐑹 𐑮𐑱𐑟𐑛 𐑩 𐑐𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑤.

“'𐑕𐑦𐑙𐑒 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐?' 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 ·𐑕𐑑𐑰𐑤𐑒𐑦𐑤𐑑. '𐑲, 𐑤𐑧𐑑 𐑣𐑻 𐑕𐑦𐑙𐑒. 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑩 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑝 𐑳𐑕 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑟 𐑑, 𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑧𐑕 𐑿 𐑕𐑢𐑺 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑑 𐑮𐑱𐑟 𐑩 𐑮𐑴𐑐-𐑘𐑸𐑯 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑳𐑕. 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑱 𐑘𐑰, 𐑥𐑧𐑯?' 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑮𐑱𐑛𐑟. 𐑩 𐑓𐑽𐑕 𐑗𐑽 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞𐑺 𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑪𐑯𐑕.

“𐑞 ·𐑤𐑱𐑒𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑯𐑬 𐑐𐑩𐑑𐑮𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑞 𐑚𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑱𐑛, 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑒𐑰𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑲 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯, 𐑯 𐑡𐑻𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑬𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑨𐑟 𐑞𐑰𐑟:—'𐑦𐑑'𐑕 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑬𐑼 𐑓𐑷𐑤𐑑; 𐑢𐑰 𐑛𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑯𐑑 𐑦𐑑; 𐑲 𐑑𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑑 𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑥𐑼 𐑩𐑢𐑱; 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑚𐑶'𐑟 𐑚𐑦𐑟𐑯𐑩𐑕; 𐑣𐑰 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑯𐑴𐑯 𐑥𐑰 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑞𐑦𐑕; 𐑲 𐑑𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑒 𐑞 𐑚𐑳𐑓𐑩𐑤𐑴; 𐑲 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑰𐑝 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑚𐑮𐑴𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑩 𐑓𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑼 𐑣𐑽 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑡𐑷; 𐑱𐑯𐑑 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑯𐑲𐑝𐑟 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑴𐑒𐑕𐑩𐑤 𐑞𐑺, 𐑥𐑧𐑯? 𐑤𐑫𐑒 𐑑 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑕𐑐𐑲𐑒𐑕, 𐑥𐑲 𐑣𐑸𐑑𐑦𐑟. 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯, 𐑚𐑲 ·𐑜𐑪𐑛, 𐑤𐑫𐑒 𐑑 𐑘𐑹𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓; 𐑕𐑱 𐑞 𐑢𐑻𐑛; 𐑛𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑩 𐑓𐑵𐑤; 𐑓𐑼𐑜𐑧𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑷𐑤; 𐑢𐑰 𐑸 𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑦 𐑑 𐑑𐑻𐑯 𐑑; 𐑑𐑮𐑰𐑑 𐑳𐑕 𐑛𐑰𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦, 𐑯 𐑢𐑰'𐑼 𐑘𐑹 𐑥𐑧𐑯; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑰 𐑢𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑓𐑤𐑪𐑜𐑛.'

“'𐑑𐑻𐑯 𐑑! 𐑲 𐑥𐑱𐑒 𐑯𐑴 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑩𐑟, 𐑑𐑻𐑯 𐑑, 𐑲 𐑕𐑱!'

“'𐑤𐑫𐑒 𐑘𐑰, 𐑯𐑬,' 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 𐑞 ·𐑤𐑱𐑒𐑥𐑩𐑯, 𐑓𐑤𐑦𐑙𐑦𐑙 𐑬𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑸𐑥 𐑑𐑩𐑢𐑹𐑛𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑥, '𐑞𐑺 𐑸 𐑩 𐑓𐑿 𐑝 𐑳𐑕 𐑣𐑽 (𐑯 𐑲 𐑨𐑥 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑞𐑧𐑥) 𐑣𐑵 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑑 𐑓 𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑵𐑟, 𐑛'𐑘𐑰 𐑕𐑰; 𐑯𐑬 𐑨𐑟 𐑿 𐑢𐑧𐑤 𐑯𐑴, 𐑕𐑻, 𐑢𐑰 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑒𐑤𐑱𐑥 𐑬𐑼 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑗𐑸𐑡 𐑨𐑟 𐑕𐑵𐑯 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑼 𐑦𐑟 𐑛𐑬𐑯; 𐑕𐑴 𐑢𐑰 𐑛𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑯𐑑 𐑩 𐑮𐑴; 𐑦𐑑'𐑕 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑬𐑼 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑩𐑕𐑑; 𐑢𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑯𐑑 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑐𐑰𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤; 𐑢𐑰 𐑸 𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑦 𐑑 𐑢𐑻𐑒, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑰 𐑢𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑓𐑤𐑪𐑜𐑛.'

“'𐑑𐑻𐑯 𐑑!' 𐑮𐑹𐑛 𐑞 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯.

“𐑕𐑑𐑰𐑤𐑒𐑦𐑤𐑑 𐑜𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑩 𐑥𐑴𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑, 𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑕𐑧𐑛:—'𐑲 𐑑𐑧𐑤 𐑿 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑬, ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯, 𐑮𐑭𐑞𐑼 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑒𐑦𐑤 𐑘𐑰, 𐑯 𐑚𐑰 𐑣𐑳𐑙 𐑓 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩 𐑖𐑨𐑚𐑦 𐑮𐑭𐑕𐑒𐑩𐑤, 𐑢𐑰 𐑢𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑤𐑦𐑓𐑑 𐑩 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑘𐑰 𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑧𐑕 𐑘𐑰 𐑩𐑑𐑨𐑒 𐑳𐑕; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑿 𐑕𐑱 𐑞 𐑢𐑻𐑛 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑓𐑤𐑪𐑜𐑦𐑙 𐑳𐑕, 𐑢𐑰 𐑛𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑛𐑵 𐑩 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛'𐑟 𐑑𐑻𐑯.'

“'𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑓𐑴𐑒𐑕𐑩𐑤 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑘𐑰, 𐑲'𐑤 𐑒𐑰𐑐 𐑘𐑰 𐑞𐑺 𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑘𐑰'𐑼 𐑕𐑦𐑒 𐑝 𐑦𐑑. 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑘𐑰 𐑜𐑴.'

“'𐑖𐑨𐑤 𐑢𐑰?' 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 𐑞 𐑮𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑰𐑛𐑼 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑧𐑯. 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑝 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑢𐑻 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑑; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑧𐑙𐑔, 𐑦𐑯 𐑴𐑚𐑰𐑛𐑾𐑯𐑕 𐑑 ·𐑕𐑑𐑰𐑤𐑒𐑦𐑤𐑑, 𐑞𐑱 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑰𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞𐑺 𐑛𐑸𐑒 𐑛𐑧𐑯, 𐑜𐑮𐑬𐑤𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑩𐑐𐑽𐑦𐑙, 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑚𐑺𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑩 𐑒𐑱𐑝.

“𐑨𐑟 𐑞 ·𐑤𐑱𐑒𐑥𐑩𐑯'𐑟 𐑚𐑺 𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑡𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑤𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑐𐑤𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑕, 𐑞 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑪𐑕𐑦 𐑤𐑰𐑐𐑑 𐑞 𐑚𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑱𐑛, 𐑯 𐑮𐑨𐑐𐑦𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑮𐑷𐑦𐑙 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑞 𐑕𐑤𐑲𐑛 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑒𐑳𐑑𐑩𐑤, 𐑐𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑞𐑺 𐑜𐑮𐑵𐑐 𐑝 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑦𐑑, 𐑯 𐑤𐑬𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑛 𐑓 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑿𐑼𐑛 𐑑 𐑚𐑮𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑣𐑧𐑝𐑦 𐑚𐑮𐑭𐑕 𐑐𐑨𐑛𐑤𐑪𐑒 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑪𐑙𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑞 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑨𐑯𐑘𐑩𐑯𐑢𐑱. 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑴𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑕𐑤𐑲𐑛 𐑩 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤, 𐑞 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑼𐑛 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑨𐑒, 𐑒𐑤𐑴𐑟𐑛 𐑦𐑑, 𐑯 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑛 𐑞 𐑒𐑰 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑥—𐑑𐑧𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑯𐑳𐑥𐑚𐑼—𐑤𐑰𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑪𐑯 𐑛𐑧𐑒 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑑𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑦 𐑹 𐑥𐑹, 𐑣𐑵 𐑞𐑳𐑕 𐑓𐑸 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑱𐑯𐑛 𐑯𐑿𐑑𐑮𐑩𐑤.

“𐑷𐑤 𐑯𐑲𐑑 𐑩 𐑢𐑲𐑛-𐑩𐑢𐑱𐑒 𐑢𐑪𐑗 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑒𐑧𐑐𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑪𐑓𐑦𐑕𐑼𐑟, 𐑓𐑹𐑢𐑼𐑛 𐑯 𐑭𐑓𐑑, 𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑞 𐑓𐑴𐑒𐑕𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑒𐑳𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑯 𐑓𐑹 𐑣𐑨𐑗𐑢𐑱; 𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑓𐑽𐑛 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑻𐑡𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑦𐑥𐑻𐑡, 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑞 𐑚𐑳𐑤𐑒𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑴. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞 𐑬𐑼𐑟 𐑝 𐑛𐑸𐑒𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑐𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑐𐑰𐑕; 𐑞 𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑣𐑵 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑱𐑯𐑛 𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑛𐑿𐑑𐑦 𐑑𐑶𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑸𐑛 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑐𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑕, 𐑣𐑵𐑟 𐑒𐑤𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑯 𐑒𐑤𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑞 𐑛𐑮𐑽𐑦 𐑯𐑲𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑟𐑥𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐.

“𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑯𐑮𐑲𐑟 𐑞 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑓𐑹𐑢𐑼𐑛, 𐑯 𐑯𐑪𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑒, 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑼𐑟 𐑑 𐑢𐑻𐑒; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑘𐑧𐑤 𐑞𐑱 𐑮𐑦𐑓𐑿𐑟𐑛. 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑤𐑴𐑼𐑛 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑑 𐑞𐑧𐑥, 𐑯 𐑩 𐑒𐑳𐑐𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑓𐑫𐑤𐑟 𐑝 𐑚𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑻 𐑑𐑪𐑕𐑑 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑦𐑑; 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑒𐑰 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑯 𐑐𐑪𐑒𐑩𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑑, 𐑞 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 𐑮𐑩𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑛 𐑑 𐑞 𐑒𐑢𐑹𐑑𐑼-𐑛𐑧𐑒. 𐑑𐑢𐑲𐑕 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑛𐑱 𐑓 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑛𐑱𐑟 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑰𐑑𐑩𐑛; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑹𐑔 𐑥𐑹𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑓𐑿𐑟𐑛 𐑮𐑨𐑙𐑜𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙, 𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑩 𐑕𐑒𐑳𐑓𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑣𐑻𐑛, 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑒𐑳𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑥𐑼𐑦 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑝𐑼𐑛; 𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑓𐑹 𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑚𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑳𐑐 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑓𐑴𐑒𐑕𐑩𐑤, 𐑕𐑱𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑱 𐑢𐑻 𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑦 𐑑 𐑑𐑻𐑯 𐑑. 𐑞 𐑓𐑧𐑑𐑦𐑛 𐑒𐑤𐑴𐑕𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑺, 𐑯 𐑩 𐑓𐑨𐑥𐑦𐑖𐑦𐑙 𐑛𐑲𐑩𐑑, 𐑿𐑯𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑐𐑼𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑕 𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑓𐑽𐑟 𐑝 𐑳𐑤𐑑𐑦𐑥𐑩𐑑 𐑮𐑧𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑚𐑿𐑖𐑩𐑯, 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑛 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑑 𐑕𐑼𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑨𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑯. 𐑦𐑥𐑚𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑞𐑦𐑕, 𐑞 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 𐑮𐑰𐑦𐑑𐑼𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑛𐑦𐑥𐑭𐑯𐑛 𐑑 𐑞 𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑑, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 ·𐑕𐑑𐑰𐑤𐑒𐑦𐑤𐑑 𐑖𐑬𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑳𐑐 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑩 𐑑𐑼𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑒 𐑣𐑦𐑯𐑑 𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑪𐑐 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑨𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑯 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑢𐑺 𐑣𐑰 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑪𐑙𐑛. 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑦𐑓𐑔 𐑥𐑹𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑳𐑞𐑼𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑥𐑿𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑽𐑟 𐑚𐑴𐑤𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑳𐑐 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑺 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑕𐑐𐑼𐑩𐑑 𐑸𐑥𐑟 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑷𐑑 𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑥. 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑢𐑻 𐑤𐑧𐑓𐑑.

“'𐑚𐑧𐑑𐑼 𐑑𐑻𐑯 𐑑, 𐑯𐑬?' 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑞 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑣𐑸𐑑𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑡𐑽.

“'𐑖𐑳𐑑 𐑳𐑕 𐑳𐑐 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯, 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑘𐑰!' 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 ·𐑕𐑑𐑰𐑤𐑒𐑦𐑤𐑑.

“'𐑴 𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑦,' 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑞 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑒𐑰 𐑒𐑤𐑦𐑒𐑑.

“𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑐𐑶𐑯𐑑, 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑥𐑧𐑯, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑮𐑱𐑡𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑛𐑦𐑓𐑧𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑕𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑹𐑥𐑼 𐑩𐑕𐑴𐑖𐑾𐑑𐑕, 𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑙 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑥𐑪𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑝𐑶𐑕 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑱𐑤𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑯 𐑥𐑨𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵𐑥𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕 𐑨𐑟 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑒 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑚𐑬𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑝 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑺; 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 ·𐑕𐑑𐑰𐑤𐑒𐑦𐑤𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑐𐑴𐑟𐑛 𐑑 𐑞 𐑑𐑵 ·𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑨𐑤𐑼𐑟, 𐑞𐑳𐑕 𐑓𐑸 𐑩𐑐𐑨𐑮𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑝 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑥𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑑 𐑚𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑞𐑺 𐑣𐑴𐑤 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑯𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑞 𐑜𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑩𐑯; 𐑯 𐑸𐑥𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞𐑺 𐑒𐑰𐑯 𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑯𐑲𐑝𐑟 (𐑤𐑪𐑙, 𐑒𐑮𐑧𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑒, 𐑣𐑧𐑝𐑦 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑦𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑤 𐑨𐑑 𐑰𐑗 𐑧𐑯𐑛) 𐑮𐑳𐑯 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑒 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑑 𐑑 𐑞 𐑑𐑨𐑓𐑮𐑱𐑤; 𐑯 𐑦𐑓 𐑚𐑲 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑛𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑖𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑛𐑧𐑕𐑐𐑼𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑐𐑪𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤, 𐑕𐑰𐑟 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐. 𐑓 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓, 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑛𐑵 𐑞𐑦𐑕, 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑧𐑛, 𐑢𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑞𐑱 𐑡𐑶𐑯𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑹 𐑯𐑪𐑑. 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑯𐑲𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑛𐑧𐑯. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑒𐑰𐑥 𐑥𐑧𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑯𐑴 𐑪𐑐𐑩𐑟𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑐𐑸𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑑𐑵; 𐑞𐑱 𐑕𐑢𐑹 𐑞𐑱 𐑢𐑻 𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑦 𐑓 𐑞𐑨𐑑, 𐑹 𐑓 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑥𐑨𐑛 𐑔𐑦𐑙, 𐑓 𐑧𐑯𐑦𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑖𐑹𐑑 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑩 𐑕𐑼𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑼. 𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑥𐑹, 𐑞𐑱 𐑰𐑗 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑪𐑯 𐑛𐑧𐑒, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑞 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑑 𐑥𐑱𐑒 𐑞 𐑮𐑳𐑖 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑒𐑳𐑥. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑞𐑺 𐑤𐑰𐑛𐑼 𐑨𐑟 𐑓𐑽𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑩𐑚𐑡𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑛, 𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑻𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑲𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑓 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓; 𐑐𐑼𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑼𐑤𐑦 𐑨𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑑𐑵 𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑮𐑱𐑛𐑟 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑘𐑰𐑤𐑛, 𐑞 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑑 𐑞 𐑳𐑞𐑼, 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑥𐑨𐑑𐑼; 𐑯 𐑚𐑴𐑔 𐑝 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑, 𐑓 𐑞 𐑤𐑨𐑛𐑼 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑩𐑛𐑥𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑨𐑑 𐑩 𐑑𐑲𐑥. 𐑯 𐑣𐑽, 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑥𐑧𐑯, 𐑞 𐑓𐑬𐑤 𐑐𐑤𐑱 𐑝 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑾𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑬𐑑.

“𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑽𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑓𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑐𐑮𐑴𐑡𐑧𐑒𐑑 𐑝 𐑞𐑺 𐑤𐑰𐑛𐑼, 𐑰𐑗 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑴𐑯 𐑕𐑧𐑐𐑼𐑩𐑑 𐑕𐑴𐑤 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑕𐑳𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑤𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑛, 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑕𐑰𐑥, 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑐𐑰𐑕 𐑝 𐑑𐑮𐑧𐑗𐑼𐑦, 𐑯𐑱𐑥𐑤𐑦: 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑓𐑹𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑬𐑑, 𐑦𐑯 𐑹𐑛𐑼 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑞 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑔𐑮𐑰, 𐑞𐑴 𐑞 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑑𐑧𐑯, 𐑑 𐑕𐑼𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑼; 𐑯 𐑞𐑺𐑚𐑲 𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑘𐑫𐑼 𐑢𐑪𐑑𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑕𐑥𐑷𐑤 𐑗𐑭𐑯𐑕 𐑝 𐑐𐑸𐑛𐑩𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑛𐑳𐑒𐑑 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑥𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑑. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑧𐑯 ·𐑕𐑑𐑰𐑤𐑒𐑦𐑤𐑑 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑯𐑴𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑛𐑦𐑑𐑻𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑑 𐑤𐑰𐑛 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑑 𐑞 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑, 𐑞𐑱 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑢𐑱, 𐑚𐑲 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑕𐑳𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑒𐑧𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑦 𐑝 𐑝𐑦𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑦, 𐑥𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑕𐑰𐑒𐑮𐑩𐑑 𐑑𐑮𐑧𐑗𐑼𐑦𐑟 𐑑𐑩𐑜𐑧𐑞𐑼; 𐑯 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑤𐑰𐑛𐑼 𐑓𐑧𐑤 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑩 𐑛𐑴𐑟, 𐑝𐑻𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑴𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑞𐑺 𐑕𐑴𐑤𐑟 𐑑 𐑰𐑗 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑦𐑯 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟; 𐑯 𐑚𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑞 𐑕𐑤𐑰𐑐𐑼 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑒𐑹𐑛𐑟, 𐑯 𐑜𐑨𐑜𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑒𐑹𐑛𐑟; 𐑯 𐑖𐑮𐑰𐑒𐑑 𐑬𐑑 𐑓 𐑞 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑦𐑛𐑯𐑲𐑑.

“𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑻𐑛𐑼 𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛, 𐑯 𐑕𐑥𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑛𐑸𐑒 𐑓 𐑞 𐑚𐑤𐑳𐑛, 𐑣𐑰 𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑸𐑥𐑛 𐑥𐑱𐑑𐑕 𐑯 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑽𐑟 𐑮𐑳𐑖𐑑 𐑓 𐑞 𐑓𐑴𐑒𐑕𐑩𐑤. 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑓𐑿 𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑞 𐑕𐑒𐑳𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑴𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑛, 𐑯, 𐑚𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑯 𐑓𐑫𐑑, 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑜𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑮𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑰𐑛𐑼 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑖𐑳𐑝𐑛 𐑳𐑐 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑺 𐑚𐑲 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑼𐑓𐑦𐑛𐑾𐑕 𐑨𐑤𐑲𐑟, 𐑣𐑵 𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑕 𐑒𐑤𐑱𐑥𐑛 𐑞 𐑪𐑯𐑼 𐑝 𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑣𐑵 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑓𐑫𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑲𐑐 𐑓 𐑥𐑻𐑛𐑼. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑒𐑪𐑤𐑼𐑛, 𐑯 𐑛𐑮𐑨𐑜𐑛 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑒 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑛𐑧𐑛 𐑒𐑨𐑑𐑩𐑤; 𐑯, 𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑕𐑲𐑛, 𐑢𐑻 𐑕𐑰𐑟𐑛 𐑳𐑐 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑥𐑦𐑟𐑩𐑯 𐑮𐑦𐑜𐑦𐑙, 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑒𐑢𐑹𐑑𐑼𐑟 𐑝 𐑥𐑰𐑑, 𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑞𐑱 𐑣𐑳𐑙 𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑥𐑹𐑯𐑦𐑙. '𐑛𐑨𐑥 𐑘𐑰,' 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 𐑞 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯, 𐑐𐑱𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑴 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑞𐑧𐑥, '𐑞 𐑝𐑳𐑤𐑗𐑼𐑟 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑑𐑳𐑗 𐑘𐑰, 𐑘𐑰 𐑝𐑦𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑟!'

“𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑯𐑮𐑲𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑷𐑤 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟; 𐑯 𐑕𐑧𐑐𐑼𐑱𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑣𐑵 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑮𐑦𐑚𐑧𐑤𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑣𐑵 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑯𐑴 𐑐𐑸𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑥𐑿𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑦, 𐑣𐑰 𐑑𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑞 𐑓𐑹𐑥𐑼 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑩 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑥𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑑 𐑓𐑤𐑪𐑜 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑷𐑤 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛—𐑔𐑷𐑑, 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑣𐑴𐑤, 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑛𐑵 𐑕𐑴—𐑣𐑰 𐑷𐑑 𐑑—𐑡𐑳𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑕 𐑛𐑦𐑥𐑭𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑑; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑓 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑑, 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑺 𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑼𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑼, 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑤𐑧𐑑 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑜𐑴 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑮𐑧𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑭𐑯𐑛, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑣𐑰 𐑩𐑒𐑹𐑛𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑩𐑛𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑝𐑼𐑯𐑨𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑼.

“'𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑓 𐑿, 𐑘𐑰 𐑒𐑨𐑮𐑾𐑯 𐑮𐑴𐑜𐑟,' 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑞 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑮𐑦𐑜𐑦𐑙—'𐑓 𐑿, 𐑲 𐑥𐑰𐑯 𐑑 𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑕 𐑘𐑰 𐑳𐑐 𐑓 𐑞 𐑑𐑮𐑲-𐑐𐑪𐑑𐑕;' 𐑯, 𐑕𐑰𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑮𐑴𐑐, 𐑣𐑰 𐑩𐑐𐑤𐑲𐑛 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑷𐑤 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑑 𐑞 𐑚𐑨𐑒𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑑𐑵 𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑑𐑼𐑟, 𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑞𐑱 𐑘𐑧𐑤𐑛 𐑯𐑴 𐑥𐑹, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑤𐑲𐑓𐑤𐑩𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑣𐑳𐑙 𐑞𐑺 𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑟 𐑕𐑲𐑛𐑢𐑱𐑟, 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑑𐑵 𐑒𐑮𐑵𐑕𐑦𐑓𐑲𐑛 𐑔𐑰𐑝𐑟 𐑸 𐑛𐑮𐑷𐑯.

“'𐑥𐑲 𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑘𐑰!' 𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛, 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑; '𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑮𐑴𐑐 𐑦𐑯𐑳𐑓 𐑤𐑧𐑓𐑑 𐑓 𐑿, 𐑥𐑲 𐑓𐑲𐑯 𐑚𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑥, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑫𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑜𐑦𐑝 𐑳𐑐. 𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑜𐑨𐑜 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑬𐑔, 𐑯 𐑤𐑧𐑑 𐑳𐑕 𐑣𐑽 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑕𐑱 𐑓 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓.'

“𐑓 𐑩 𐑥𐑴𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑞 𐑦𐑜𐑟𐑷𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑥𐑿𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑽 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑩 𐑑𐑮𐑧𐑥𐑿𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑥𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑮𐑨𐑥𐑐𐑑 𐑡𐑷𐑟, 𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑐𐑱𐑯𐑓𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑑𐑢𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑧𐑛, 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑕𐑹𐑑 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑕, '𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑲 𐑕𐑱 𐑦𐑟 𐑞𐑦𐑕—𐑯 𐑥𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑧𐑤—𐑦𐑓 𐑿 𐑓𐑤𐑪𐑜 𐑥𐑰, 𐑲 𐑥𐑻𐑛𐑼 𐑿!'

“'𐑕𐑱 𐑘𐑰 𐑕𐑴? 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑕𐑰 𐑣𐑬 𐑘𐑰 𐑓𐑮𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑥𐑰'—𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 𐑛𐑮𐑵 𐑪𐑓 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑮𐑴𐑐 𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑒.

“'𐑚𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑑,' 𐑣𐑦𐑕𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑤𐑱𐑒𐑥𐑩𐑯.

“'𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑲 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑,'—𐑯 𐑞 𐑮𐑴𐑐 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑕 𐑥𐑹 𐑛𐑮𐑷𐑯 𐑚𐑨𐑒 𐑓 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑴𐑒.

“𐑕𐑑𐑰𐑤𐑒𐑦𐑤𐑑 𐑣𐑽 𐑣𐑦𐑕𐑑 𐑬𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑔𐑦𐑙, 𐑦𐑯𐑷𐑛𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯; 𐑣𐑵, 𐑑 𐑞 𐑩𐑥𐑱𐑟𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑷𐑤 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟, 𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑨𐑒, 𐑐𐑱𐑕𐑑 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑒 𐑮𐑨𐑐𐑦𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑑𐑵 𐑹 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟, 𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑔𐑮𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑮𐑴𐑐, 𐑕𐑧𐑛, '𐑲 𐑢𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑛𐑵 𐑦𐑑—𐑤𐑧𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑜𐑴—𐑒𐑳𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑛𐑬𐑯: 𐑛'𐑘𐑰 𐑣𐑽?'

“𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑡𐑵𐑯𐑽 𐑥𐑱𐑑𐑕 𐑢𐑻 𐑣𐑳𐑮𐑦𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑑 𐑞 𐑹𐑛𐑼, 𐑩 𐑐𐑱𐑤 𐑥𐑨𐑯, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑚𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑡𐑛 𐑣𐑧𐑛, 𐑼𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑞𐑧𐑥—·𐑮𐑨𐑛𐑯𐑦 𐑞 𐑗𐑰𐑓 𐑥𐑱𐑑. 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑕𐑦𐑯𐑕 𐑞 𐑚𐑤𐑴, 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑤𐑱𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑻𐑔; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑹𐑯𐑦𐑙, 𐑣𐑽𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑑𐑿𐑥𐑳𐑤𐑑 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑒, 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑒𐑮𐑧𐑐𐑑 𐑬𐑑, 𐑯 𐑞𐑳𐑕 𐑓𐑸 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑢𐑪𐑗𐑑 𐑞 𐑣𐑴𐑤 𐑕𐑰𐑯. 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑑 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑬𐑔, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑣𐑸𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑒; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑥𐑳𐑥𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑯 𐑱𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑑 𐑛𐑵 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑞 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 𐑛𐑺𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑩𐑑𐑧𐑥𐑐𐑑, 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑯𐑨𐑗𐑑 𐑞 𐑮𐑴𐑐 𐑯 𐑩𐑛𐑝𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑦𐑯𐑘𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑓𐑴.

“'𐑿 𐑸 𐑩 𐑒𐑬𐑼𐑛!' 𐑣𐑦𐑕𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑤𐑱𐑒𐑥𐑩𐑯.

“'𐑕𐑴 𐑲 𐑨𐑥, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑞𐑨𐑑.' 𐑞 𐑥𐑱𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑨𐑒𐑑 𐑝 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑒𐑦𐑙, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑩𐑯𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑣𐑦𐑕 𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑳𐑐𐑤𐑦𐑓𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑸𐑥. 𐑣𐑰 𐑐𐑷𐑟𐑛: 𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑐𐑷𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑯𐑴 𐑥𐑹, 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑻𐑛, 𐑕𐑐𐑲𐑑 𐑝 ·𐑕𐑑𐑰𐑤𐑒𐑦𐑤𐑑'𐑕 𐑔𐑮𐑧𐑑, 𐑢𐑪𐑑𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑯. 𐑞 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑢𐑻 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑒𐑳𐑑 𐑛𐑬𐑯, 𐑷𐑤 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑛 𐑑, 𐑯, 𐑕𐑳𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑢𐑻𐑒𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑥𐑵𐑛𐑦 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑧𐑯, 𐑞 𐑲𐑼𐑯 𐑐𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑕 𐑒𐑤𐑨𐑙𐑛 𐑨𐑟 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹.

“𐑡𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑛𐑸𐑒 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑛𐑱, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑗 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑲𐑼𐑛 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑴, 𐑩 𐑒𐑤𐑨𐑥𐑼 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑣𐑻𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑴𐑒𐑕𐑩𐑤; 𐑯 𐑞 𐑑𐑵 𐑑𐑮𐑧𐑥𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑑𐑼𐑟 𐑮𐑳𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑳𐑐, 𐑚𐑦𐑕𐑰𐑡𐑛 𐑞 𐑒𐑨𐑚𐑦𐑯 𐑛𐑹, 𐑕𐑱𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑱 ·𐑛𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑹𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑵. 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑰𐑑𐑦𐑟, 𐑒𐑳𐑓𐑕, 𐑯 𐑒𐑦𐑒𐑕 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑛𐑮𐑲𐑝 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑚𐑨𐑒, 𐑕𐑴 𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑴𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑞𐑱 𐑢𐑻 𐑐𐑫𐑑 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐'𐑕 𐑮𐑳𐑯 𐑓 𐑕𐑨𐑤𐑝𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯. 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤, 𐑯𐑴 𐑕𐑲𐑯 𐑝 𐑥𐑿𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑦 𐑮𐑰𐑩𐑐𐑽𐑛 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑞 𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑑. 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑺𐑦, 𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑱𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑨𐑑 ·𐑕𐑑𐑰𐑤𐑒𐑦𐑤𐑑'𐑕 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑜𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯, 𐑞𐑱 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑪𐑤𐑝𐑛 𐑑 𐑥𐑱𐑯𐑑𐑱𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑐𐑰𐑕𐑓𐑩𐑤𐑯𐑩𐑕, 𐑴𐑚𐑱 𐑷𐑤 𐑹𐑛𐑼𐑟 𐑑 𐑞 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑, 𐑯, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑮𐑰𐑗𐑑 𐑐𐑹𐑑, 𐑛𐑦𐑟𐑻𐑑 𐑣𐑻 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑹𐑛𐑼 𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑖𐑫𐑼 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑛𐑾𐑕𐑑 𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑑 𐑞 𐑝𐑶𐑦𐑡, 𐑞𐑱 𐑷𐑤 𐑩𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑛 𐑑 𐑩𐑯𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑔𐑦𐑙—𐑯𐑱𐑥𐑤𐑦, 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑑 𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑬𐑑 𐑓 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟, 𐑦𐑯 𐑒𐑱𐑕 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑚𐑰 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑳𐑝𐑼𐑛. 𐑓, 𐑕𐑐𐑲𐑑 𐑝 𐑣𐑻 𐑤𐑰𐑒, 𐑯 𐑕𐑐𐑲𐑑 𐑝 𐑷𐑤 𐑣𐑻 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑐𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑤𐑟, 𐑞 ·𐑑𐑬𐑯-·𐑣𐑴 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑥𐑱𐑯𐑑𐑱𐑯𐑛 𐑣𐑻 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑-𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑟, 𐑯 𐑣𐑻 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑡𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑤𐑴𐑼 𐑓 𐑩 𐑓𐑦𐑖 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑴𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑, 𐑨𐑟 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑛𐑱 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑮𐑭𐑓𐑑 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑒 𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑵𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑜𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛; 𐑯 ·𐑮𐑨𐑛𐑯𐑦 𐑞 𐑥𐑱𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑒𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑦 𐑑 𐑗𐑱𐑯𐑡 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑻𐑔 𐑓 𐑩 𐑚𐑴𐑑, 𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑡𐑛 𐑥𐑬𐑔 𐑕𐑰𐑒 𐑑 𐑜𐑨𐑜 𐑦𐑯 𐑛𐑧𐑔 𐑞 𐑝𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑡𐑷 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤.

“𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞𐑴 𐑞 ·𐑤𐑱𐑒𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑿𐑕𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑑 𐑩𐑛𐑪𐑐𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑕𐑹𐑑 𐑝 𐑐𐑨𐑕𐑦𐑝𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑛𐑳𐑒𐑑, 𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑧𐑐𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑴𐑯 𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑤 (𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑰𐑕𐑑 𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑷𐑤 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑴𐑝𐑼) 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑴𐑯 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑐𐑼 𐑯 𐑐𐑮𐑲𐑝𐑩𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑝𐑧𐑯𐑡 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑣𐑵 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑝𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑸𐑑. 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑦𐑯 ·𐑮𐑨𐑛𐑯𐑦 𐑞 𐑗𐑰𐑓 𐑥𐑱𐑑'𐑕 𐑢𐑪𐑗; 𐑯 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑓 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑓𐑨𐑗𐑵𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑕𐑷𐑑 𐑑 𐑮𐑳𐑯 𐑥𐑹 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑣𐑭𐑓 𐑢𐑱 𐑑 𐑥𐑰𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑛𐑵𐑥, 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑞 𐑕𐑰𐑯 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑮𐑦𐑜𐑦𐑙, 𐑣𐑰 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛, 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑞 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑕 𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑞 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯, 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑿𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑪𐑗 𐑨𐑑 𐑯𐑲𐑑. 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕, 𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑹 𐑑𐑵 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑕𐑻𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟, ·𐑕𐑑𐑰𐑤𐑒𐑦𐑤𐑑 𐑕𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑥𐑨𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑑 𐑞 𐑐𐑤𐑨𐑯 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑮𐑦𐑝𐑧𐑯𐑡.

“𐑛𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑯𐑲𐑑, ·𐑮𐑨𐑛𐑯𐑦 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑩𐑯 𐑳𐑯𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑢𐑱 𐑝 𐑕𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑫𐑤𐑢𐑼𐑒𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑒𐑢𐑹𐑑𐑼-𐑛𐑧𐑒, 𐑯 𐑤𐑰𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑸𐑥 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑜𐑳𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑣𐑶𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑳𐑐 𐑞𐑺, 𐑩 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑩𐑚𐑳𐑝 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐'𐑕 𐑕𐑲𐑛. 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑨𐑑𐑦𐑑𐑿𐑛, 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑢𐑧𐑤 𐑯𐑴𐑯, 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑛𐑴𐑟𐑛. 𐑞𐑺 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑼𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑝𐑱𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑢𐑰𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑 𐑯 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐, 𐑯 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑢𐑰𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞 𐑕𐑰. 𐑕𐑑𐑰𐑤𐑒𐑦𐑤𐑑 𐑒𐑨𐑤𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑑𐑲𐑥, 𐑯 𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑 𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑒 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑥 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑨𐑑 𐑑𐑵 𐑴'𐑒𐑤𐑪𐑒, 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑥𐑹𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑞 𐑔𐑻𐑛 𐑛𐑱 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑛. 𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑤𐑧𐑠𐑼, 𐑣𐑰 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑶𐑛 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑝𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑒𐑺𐑓𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑪𐑗𐑩𐑟 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑴.

“'𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑸 𐑿 𐑥𐑱𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑺?' 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑩 𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑥𐑱𐑑.

“'𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑛𐑵 𐑿 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒? 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑛𐑳𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑤𐑫𐑒 𐑤𐑲𐑒?'

“'𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑘𐑼𐑛 𐑓 𐑘𐑹 𐑚𐑨𐑜; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑑'𐑕 𐑩𐑯 𐑪𐑛 𐑢𐑳𐑯, 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑟 𐑑 𐑥𐑰.'

“'𐑘𐑧𐑕, 𐑮𐑭𐑞𐑼 𐑪𐑛𐑦𐑖,' 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑞 ·𐑤𐑱𐑒𐑥𐑩𐑯, 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑸𐑥'𐑟 𐑤𐑧𐑙𐑔 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑣𐑦𐑥; '𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑲 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑼. 𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑥𐑱𐑑, 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑝𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑳𐑓 𐑑𐑢𐑲𐑯,—𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑿 𐑧𐑯𐑦?'

“𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑳𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑴𐑒𐑕𐑩𐑤.

“'𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑲 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑜𐑧𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑴𐑤𐑛 ·𐑮𐑨𐑛;' 𐑯 𐑣𐑰 𐑮𐑴𐑟 𐑑 𐑜𐑴 𐑭𐑓𐑑.

“'𐑿 𐑛𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑥𐑰𐑯 𐑑 𐑜𐑴 𐑩 𐑚𐑧𐑜𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥!' 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑩 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑼.

“'𐑢𐑲 𐑯𐑪𐑑? 𐑛𐑵 𐑿 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑛𐑵 𐑥𐑰 𐑩 𐑑𐑻𐑯, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑦𐑑'𐑕 𐑑 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑐 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑧𐑯𐑛, 𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑥𐑱𐑑?' 𐑯 𐑜𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑞 𐑥𐑱𐑑, 𐑣𐑰 𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑒𐑢𐑲𐑩𐑑𐑤𐑦, 𐑯 𐑭𐑕𐑒𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑓 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑑𐑢𐑲𐑯 𐑑 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑥𐑩𐑒. 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑜𐑦𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥—𐑯𐑲𐑞𐑼 𐑑𐑢𐑲𐑯 𐑯𐑹 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑘𐑼𐑛 𐑢𐑻 𐑕𐑰𐑯 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞 𐑯𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑 𐑯𐑲𐑑 𐑩𐑯 𐑲𐑼𐑯 𐑚𐑷𐑤, 𐑒𐑤𐑴𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑯𐑧𐑑𐑩𐑛, 𐑐𐑸𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑐𐑪𐑒𐑩𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑤𐑱𐑒𐑥𐑩𐑯'𐑟 𐑥𐑳𐑙𐑒𐑦 𐑡𐑨𐑒𐑩𐑑, 𐑨𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑑𐑳𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑒𐑴𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑥𐑩𐑒 𐑓 𐑩 𐑐𐑦𐑤𐑴. 𐑑𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑦-𐑓𐑹 𐑬𐑼𐑟 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼, 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑒 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑥—𐑯𐑲 𐑑 𐑞 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑣𐑵 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑨𐑐𐑑 𐑑 𐑛𐑴𐑟 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑝 𐑷𐑤𐑢𐑱𐑟 𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑦 𐑛𐑳𐑜 𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑩𐑯'𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛—𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑓𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑬𐑼 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑑 𐑒𐑳𐑥; 𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑹-𐑹𐑛𐑱𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑴𐑤 𐑝 ·𐑕𐑑𐑰𐑤𐑒𐑦𐑤𐑑, 𐑞 𐑥𐑱𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑷𐑤𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑦 𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑒 𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑧𐑗𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑩 𐑒𐑹𐑐𐑕, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑛 𐑒𐑮𐑳𐑖𐑑 𐑦𐑯.

“𐑚𐑳𐑑, 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑥𐑧𐑯, 𐑩 𐑓𐑵𐑤 𐑕𐑱𐑝𐑛 𐑞 𐑢𐑫𐑛-𐑚𐑰 𐑥𐑻𐑛𐑼𐑼 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑚𐑤𐑳𐑛𐑦 𐑛𐑰𐑛 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑐𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛. 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑰𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑝𐑧𐑯𐑡 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛, 𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑩𐑝𐑧𐑯𐑡𐑼. 𐑓 𐑚𐑲 𐑩 𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑽𐑾𐑕 𐑓𐑩𐑑𐑨𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑦, ·𐑣𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑑𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑐 𐑦𐑯 𐑑 𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑴𐑯 𐑞 𐑛𐑨𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑛𐑳𐑯.

“𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑡𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑢𐑰𐑯 𐑛𐑱𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑒 𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑯𐑮𐑲𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑥𐑹𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑧𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑛𐑱, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑞𐑱 𐑢𐑻 𐑢𐑪𐑖𐑦𐑙 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑒𐑕, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑩 𐑕𐑑𐑵𐑐𐑦𐑛 ·𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑻𐑤𐑰𐑓 𐑥𐑨𐑯, 𐑛𐑮𐑷𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑥𐑱𐑯-𐑗𐑱𐑯𐑟, 𐑷𐑤 𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑕 𐑖𐑬𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑬𐑑, '𐑞𐑺 𐑖𐑰 𐑮𐑴𐑤𐑟! 𐑞𐑺 𐑖𐑰 𐑮𐑴𐑤𐑟!' ·𐑠𐑧𐑟𐑵, 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑩 𐑢𐑱𐑤! 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 ·𐑥𐑪𐑚𐑦 ·𐑛𐑦𐑒.

“'𐑥𐑪𐑚𐑦 ·𐑛𐑦𐑒!' 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 ·𐑛𐑪𐑯 ·𐑕𐑦𐑚𐑨𐑕𐑗𐑩𐑯; '·𐑕𐑑 ·𐑛𐑪𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑒! 𐑕𐑻 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑼, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑛𐑵 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑙𐑟? 𐑣𐑵𐑥 𐑒𐑷𐑤 𐑿 ·𐑥𐑪𐑚𐑦 ·𐑛𐑦𐑒?'

“'𐑩 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑢𐑲𐑑, 𐑯 𐑓𐑱𐑥𐑩𐑕, 𐑯 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑛𐑧𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑥𐑹𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑥𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑼, ·𐑛𐑪𐑯;—𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑚𐑰 𐑑𐑵 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑩 𐑕𐑑𐑹𐑦.'

“'𐑣𐑬? 𐑣𐑬?' 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑘𐑳𐑙 ·𐑕𐑐𐑨𐑯𐑘𐑼𐑛𐑟, 𐑒𐑮𐑬𐑛𐑦𐑙.

“'𐑯𐑱, ·𐑛𐑪𐑯𐑟, ·𐑛𐑪𐑯𐑟—𐑯𐑱, 𐑯𐑱! 𐑲 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑣𐑻𐑕 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑯𐑬. 𐑤𐑧𐑑 𐑥𐑰 𐑜𐑧𐑑 𐑥𐑹 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑺, ·𐑕𐑻𐑟.'

“'𐑞 𐑗𐑦𐑗𐑩! 𐑞 𐑗𐑦𐑗𐑩!' 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 ·𐑛𐑪𐑯 ·𐑐𐑧𐑛𐑮𐑴; '𐑬𐑼 𐑝𐑦𐑜𐑼𐑩𐑕 𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑕 𐑓𐑱𐑯𐑑;—𐑓𐑦𐑤 𐑳𐑐 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑧𐑥𐑐𐑑𐑦 𐑜𐑤𐑭𐑕!'

“𐑯𐑴 𐑯𐑰𐑛, 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑥𐑧𐑯; 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑥𐑴𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑, 𐑯 𐑲 𐑐𐑮𐑴𐑕𐑰𐑛.—𐑯𐑬, 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑥𐑧𐑯, 𐑕𐑴 𐑕𐑳𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑼𐑕𐑰𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑕𐑯𐑴𐑦 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑦𐑯 𐑓𐑦𐑓𐑑𐑦 𐑘𐑸𐑛𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐—𐑓𐑼𐑜𐑧𐑑𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑞 𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑐𐑨𐑒𐑑 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑵—𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑲𐑑𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑥𐑴𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑, 𐑞 ·𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑻𐑤𐑰𐑓 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑝𐑤𐑦 𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑪𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑺𐑦𐑤𐑦 𐑤𐑦𐑓𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑝𐑶𐑕 𐑓 𐑞 𐑥𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑼, 𐑞𐑴 𐑓 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑐𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑦𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑕𐑳𐑤𐑩𐑯 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑-𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑟. 𐑷𐑤 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑬 𐑩 𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑯𐑟𐑦. '𐑞 ·𐑢𐑲𐑑 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤—𐑞 ·𐑢𐑲𐑑 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤!' 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑲 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯, 𐑥𐑱𐑑𐑕, 𐑯 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑽𐑟, 𐑣𐑵, 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑑𐑻𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑓𐑽𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑮𐑵𐑥𐑼𐑟, 𐑢𐑻 𐑷𐑤 𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑕 𐑑 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑗𐑼 𐑕𐑴 𐑓𐑱𐑥𐑩𐑕 𐑯 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑕 𐑩 𐑓𐑦𐑖; 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑞 𐑛𐑪𐑜𐑩𐑛 𐑒𐑮𐑵 𐑲𐑛 𐑩𐑕𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑕, 𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑒𐑻𐑕𐑩𐑟, 𐑞 𐑩𐑐𐑷𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑿𐑑𐑦 𐑝 𐑞 𐑝𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑥𐑦𐑤𐑒𐑦 𐑥𐑨𐑕, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑦𐑑 𐑳𐑐 𐑚𐑲 𐑩 𐑣𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑐𐑨𐑙𐑜𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑳𐑯, 𐑖𐑦𐑓𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑯 𐑜𐑤𐑦𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑤𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑴𐑐𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑤𐑵 𐑥𐑹𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑰. 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑥𐑧𐑯, 𐑩 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡 𐑓𐑩𐑑𐑨𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑐𐑼𐑝𐑱𐑛𐑟 𐑞 𐑣𐑴𐑤 𐑒𐑼𐑽 𐑝 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑦𐑝𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑕, 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑓 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑤𐑦 𐑥𐑨𐑐𐑑 𐑬𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑞 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛 𐑦𐑑𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑗𐑸𐑑𐑩𐑛. 𐑞 𐑥𐑿𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑽 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞 𐑚𐑬𐑟𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑥𐑱𐑑, 𐑯 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑓𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑑 𐑩 𐑓𐑦𐑖, 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑛𐑿𐑑𐑦 𐑑 𐑕𐑦𐑑 𐑯𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑢𐑲𐑤 ·𐑮𐑨𐑛𐑯𐑦 𐑕𐑑𐑫𐑛 𐑳𐑐 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑬, 𐑯 𐑣𐑷𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑹 𐑕𐑤𐑨𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑞 𐑤𐑲𐑯, 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑢𐑻𐑛 𐑝 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑭𐑯𐑛. 𐑥𐑹𐑴𐑝𐑼, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑹 𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕 𐑢𐑻 𐑤𐑴𐑼𐑛, 𐑞 𐑥𐑱𐑑'𐑕 𐑜𐑪𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑑; 𐑯 𐑯𐑳𐑯 𐑣𐑬𐑤𐑛 𐑥𐑹 𐑓𐑽𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑲𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑛𐑦𐑛 ·𐑕𐑑𐑰𐑤𐑒𐑦𐑤𐑑, 𐑨𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑛 𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑹. 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑩 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑓 𐑐𐑫𐑤, 𐑞𐑺 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑽 𐑜𐑪𐑑 𐑓𐑭𐑕𐑑, 𐑯, 𐑕𐑐𐑽 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛, ·𐑮𐑨𐑛𐑯𐑦 𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑨𐑙 𐑑 𐑞 𐑚𐑬. 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑷𐑤𐑢𐑱𐑟 𐑩 𐑓𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑾𐑕 𐑥𐑨𐑯, 𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑟, 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑚𐑴𐑑. 𐑯 𐑯𐑬 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑡𐑛 𐑒𐑮𐑲 𐑢𐑪𐑟, 𐑑 𐑚𐑰𐑗 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤'𐑟 𐑑𐑪𐑐𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑨𐑒. 𐑯𐑳𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑤𐑴𐑞, 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑬𐑟𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑣𐑷𐑤𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑳𐑐 𐑯 𐑳𐑐, 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑩 𐑚𐑤𐑲𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑴𐑥 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑚𐑤𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑑𐑵 𐑢𐑲𐑑𐑯𐑩𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑑𐑩𐑜𐑧𐑞𐑼; 𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑝 𐑩 𐑕𐑳𐑛𐑩𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑒 𐑨𐑟 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑩 𐑕𐑳𐑙𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑤𐑧𐑡, 𐑯 𐑒𐑰𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑴𐑝𐑼, 𐑕𐑐𐑦𐑤𐑛 𐑬𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑱𐑑. 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑, 𐑨𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑓𐑧𐑤 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤'𐑟 𐑕𐑤𐑦𐑐𐑼𐑦 𐑚𐑨𐑒, 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑 𐑮𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑛, 𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑛𐑨𐑖𐑑 𐑩𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑕𐑢𐑧𐑤, 𐑢𐑲𐑤 ·𐑮𐑨𐑛𐑯𐑦 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑑𐑪𐑕𐑑 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑕𐑰, 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑓𐑤𐑨𐑙𐑒 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤. 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑒 𐑬𐑑 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑱, 𐑯, 𐑓 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑, 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑛𐑦𐑥𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑰𐑯 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑝𐑱𐑤, 𐑢𐑲𐑤𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑰𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑵𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑲 𐑝 ·𐑥𐑪𐑚𐑦 ·𐑛𐑦𐑒. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑮𐑳𐑖𐑑 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑕𐑳𐑛𐑩𐑯 𐑥𐑱𐑤𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑩𐑥; 𐑕𐑰𐑟𐑛 𐑞 𐑕𐑢𐑦𐑥𐑼 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑢𐑰𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑡𐑷𐑟; 𐑯 𐑮𐑽𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑲 𐑳𐑐 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑐𐑤𐑳𐑯𐑡𐑛 𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯, 𐑯 𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑛𐑬𐑯.

“𐑥𐑰𐑯𐑑𐑲𐑥, 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑑𐑨𐑐 𐑝 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑'𐑕 𐑚𐑪𐑑𐑩𐑥, 𐑞 ·𐑤𐑱𐑒𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑕𐑤𐑨𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑞 𐑤𐑲𐑯, 𐑕𐑴 𐑨𐑟 𐑑 𐑛𐑮𐑪𐑐 𐑩𐑕𐑑𐑻𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑐𐑵𐑤; 𐑒𐑭𐑥𐑤𐑦 𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑪𐑯, 𐑣𐑰 𐑔𐑷𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑴𐑯 𐑔𐑷𐑑𐑕. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑩 𐑕𐑳𐑛𐑩𐑯, 𐑑𐑼𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑒, 𐑛𐑬𐑯𐑢𐑼𐑛 𐑡𐑻𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑, 𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑮𐑷𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑲𐑓 𐑑 𐑞 𐑤𐑲𐑯. 𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑑; 𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑓𐑮𐑰. 𐑚𐑳𐑑, 𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕, ·𐑥𐑪𐑚𐑦 ·𐑛𐑦𐑒 𐑮𐑴𐑟 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑑𐑨𐑑𐑼𐑟 𐑝 ·𐑮𐑨𐑛𐑯𐑦'𐑟 𐑮𐑧𐑛 𐑢𐑫𐑤𐑩𐑯 𐑖𐑻𐑑, 𐑒𐑷𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑑𐑰𐑔 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑶𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥. 𐑷𐑤 𐑓𐑹 𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕 𐑜𐑱𐑝 𐑗𐑱𐑕 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑦𐑤𐑵𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑞𐑧𐑥, 𐑯 𐑓𐑲𐑯𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑩𐑐𐑽𐑛.

“𐑦𐑯 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑑𐑲𐑥, 𐑞 ·𐑑𐑬𐑯-·𐑣𐑴 𐑮𐑰𐑗𐑑 𐑣𐑻 𐑐𐑹𐑑—𐑩 𐑕𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑡, 𐑕𐑪𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑼𐑦 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕—𐑢𐑺 𐑯𐑴 𐑕𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑤𐑲𐑟𐑛 𐑒𐑮𐑰𐑗𐑼 𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑲𐑛𐑩𐑛. 𐑞𐑺, 𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 ·𐑤𐑱𐑒𐑥𐑩𐑯, 𐑷𐑤 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑓𐑲𐑝 𐑹 𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑓𐑹𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑚𐑼𐑩𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑦𐑟𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑞 𐑐𐑭𐑥𐑟; 𐑦𐑝𐑧𐑯𐑗𐑵𐑩𐑤𐑦, 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑛 𐑬𐑑, 𐑕𐑰𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑤𐑸𐑡 𐑛𐑳𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑹-𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑵 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑡𐑩𐑟, 𐑯 𐑕𐑧𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑱𐑤 𐑓 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑣𐑸𐑚𐑼.

“𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐'𐑕 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑦 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑮𐑦𐑛𐑿𐑕𐑑 𐑑 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑩 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑓𐑫𐑤, 𐑞 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑛 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑲𐑕𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑟 𐑑 𐑩𐑕𐑦𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑤𐑩𐑚𐑹𐑾𐑕 𐑚𐑦𐑟𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑣𐑰𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑪𐑐 𐑞 𐑤𐑰𐑒. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑳𐑯𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑝𐑦𐑡𐑦𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑞𐑺 𐑛𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑼𐑩𐑕 𐑨𐑤𐑲𐑟 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑕𐑥𐑷𐑤 𐑚𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑝 𐑢𐑲𐑑𐑕 𐑯𐑦𐑕𐑧𐑕𐑦𐑑𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛, 𐑚𐑴𐑔 𐑚𐑲 𐑯𐑲𐑑 𐑯 𐑚𐑲 𐑛𐑱, 𐑯 𐑕𐑴 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑰𐑥 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞 𐑣𐑸𐑛 𐑢𐑻𐑒 𐑞𐑱 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑑, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑝𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑤 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑦 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯 𐑓 𐑕𐑰, 𐑞𐑱 𐑢𐑻 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩 𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 ·𐑛𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑐𐑫𐑑 𐑪𐑓 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑴 𐑣𐑧𐑝𐑦 𐑩 𐑝𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑤. 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑪𐑓𐑦𐑕𐑼𐑟, 𐑣𐑰 𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑼𐑛 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑨𐑟 𐑓𐑸 𐑪𐑓 𐑖𐑹 𐑨𐑟 𐑐𐑪𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤; 𐑤𐑴𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑯 𐑮𐑨𐑯 𐑬𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑑𐑵 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑩𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑚𐑬𐑟; 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑒𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑒𐑩𐑑𐑕 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑐𐑵𐑐; 𐑯 𐑢𐑹𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑞 ·𐑲𐑕𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑑 𐑩𐑐𐑮𐑴𐑗 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑐𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑤, 𐑑𐑫𐑒 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑯 𐑕𐑧𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑤 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑤-𐑚𐑴𐑑, 𐑕𐑑𐑽𐑛 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑞 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛 𐑓 ·𐑑𐑭𐑣𐑰𐑑𐑦, 𐑓𐑲𐑝 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑛 𐑥𐑲𐑤𐑟 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑, 𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑒𐑘𐑫𐑼 𐑩 𐑮𐑰𐑦𐑯𐑓𐑹𐑕𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑮𐑵.

“𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑹𐑔 𐑛𐑱 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑤, 𐑩 𐑤𐑸𐑡 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑵 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑑𐑳𐑗𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑩 𐑤𐑴 𐑲𐑤 𐑝 𐑒𐑪𐑮𐑩𐑤𐑟. 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑑𐑽𐑛 𐑩𐑢𐑱 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑦𐑑; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑡 𐑒𐑮𐑭𐑓𐑑 𐑚𐑹 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥; 𐑯 𐑕𐑵𐑯 𐑞 𐑝𐑶𐑕 𐑝 ·𐑕𐑑𐑰𐑤𐑒𐑦𐑤𐑑 𐑣𐑱𐑤𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑑 𐑣𐑰𐑝 𐑑, 𐑹 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑮𐑳𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼. 𐑞 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑩 𐑐𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑤. 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑓𐑫𐑑 𐑪𐑯 𐑰𐑗 𐑐𐑮𐑬 𐑝 𐑞 𐑘𐑴𐑒𐑑 𐑢𐑹-𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑵𐑟, 𐑞 ·𐑤𐑱𐑒𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑤𐑭𐑓𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑑 𐑕𐑒𐑹𐑯; 𐑩𐑖𐑫𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑓 𐑞 𐑐𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑴 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑨𐑟 𐑒𐑤𐑦𐑒𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑤𐑪𐑒, 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑚𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑦𐑯 𐑚𐑳𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑯 𐑓𐑴𐑥.

“'𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑛𐑵 𐑿 𐑢𐑪𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑥𐑰?' 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 𐑞 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯.

“'𐑢𐑺 𐑸 𐑿 𐑚𐑬𐑯𐑛? 𐑯 𐑓 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑸 𐑿 𐑚𐑬𐑯𐑛?' 𐑛𐑦𐑥𐑭𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 ·𐑕𐑑𐑰𐑤𐑒𐑦𐑤𐑑; '𐑯𐑴 𐑤𐑲𐑟.'

“'𐑲 𐑨𐑥 𐑚𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑑 ·𐑑𐑭𐑣𐑰𐑑𐑦 𐑓 𐑥𐑹 𐑥𐑧𐑯.'

“'𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑜𐑫𐑛. 𐑤𐑧𐑑 𐑥𐑰 𐑚𐑹𐑛 𐑿 𐑩 𐑥𐑴𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑—𐑲 𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑦𐑯 𐑐𐑰𐑕.' 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑤𐑰𐑐𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑵, 𐑕𐑢𐑨𐑥 𐑑 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑; 𐑯 𐑒𐑤𐑲𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑜𐑳𐑯𐑩𐑤, 𐑕𐑑𐑫𐑛 𐑓𐑱𐑕 𐑑 𐑓𐑱𐑕 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯.

“'𐑒𐑮𐑪𐑕 𐑘𐑹 𐑸𐑥𐑟, 𐑕𐑻; 𐑔𐑮𐑴 𐑚𐑨𐑒 𐑘𐑹 𐑣𐑧𐑛. 𐑯𐑬, 𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑰𐑑 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑥𐑰. 𐑨𐑟 𐑕𐑵𐑯 𐑨𐑟 ·𐑕𐑑𐑰𐑤𐑒𐑦𐑤𐑑 𐑤𐑰𐑝𐑟 𐑥𐑰, 𐑲 𐑕𐑢𐑺 𐑑 𐑚𐑰𐑗 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑚𐑴𐑑 𐑪𐑯 𐑘𐑪𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛, 𐑯 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑱𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑕 𐑛𐑱𐑟. 𐑦𐑓 𐑲 𐑛𐑵 𐑯𐑪𐑑, 𐑥𐑱 𐑤𐑲𐑑𐑯𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑒 𐑥𐑰!'

“'𐑩 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑕𐑒𐑪𐑤𐑼,' 𐑤𐑭𐑓𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑤𐑱𐑒𐑥𐑩𐑯. '𐑭𐑛𐑦𐑪𐑕, ·𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑘𐑹!' 𐑯 𐑤𐑰𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑕𐑰, 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑢𐑨𐑥 𐑚𐑨𐑒 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑮𐑱𐑛𐑟.

“𐑢𐑪𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑 𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑓𐑺𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑰𐑗𐑑, 𐑯 𐑛𐑮𐑷𐑯 𐑳𐑐 𐑑 𐑞 𐑮𐑵𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑒𐑴𐑒𐑴-𐑯𐑳𐑑 𐑑𐑮𐑰𐑟, ·𐑕𐑑𐑰𐑤𐑒𐑦𐑤𐑑 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑕𐑱𐑤 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯, 𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑛𐑿 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑼𐑲𐑝𐑛 𐑨𐑑 ·𐑑𐑭𐑣𐑰𐑑𐑦, 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑴𐑯 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕 𐑝 𐑛𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯. 𐑞𐑺, 𐑤𐑳𐑒 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥; 𐑑𐑵 𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑕 𐑢𐑻 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑑 𐑕𐑱𐑤 𐑓 ·𐑓𐑮𐑭𐑯𐑕, 𐑯 𐑢𐑻 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑝𐑦𐑛𐑧𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑲𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑯𐑳𐑥𐑚𐑼 𐑝 𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑼 𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑩𐑛. 𐑞𐑱 𐑦𐑥𐑚𐑸𐑒𐑑; 𐑯 𐑕𐑴 𐑓 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑜𐑪𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑑 𐑝 𐑞𐑺 𐑓𐑹𐑥𐑼 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯, 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑣𐑰 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑨𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑥𐑲𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑑 𐑢𐑻𐑒 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑤𐑰𐑜𐑩𐑤 𐑮𐑧𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑚𐑿𐑖𐑩𐑯.

“𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑑𐑧𐑯 𐑛𐑱𐑟 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑞 ·𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑯𐑗 𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑕 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑛, 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤-𐑚𐑴𐑑 𐑼𐑲𐑝𐑛, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑓𐑹𐑕𐑑 𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑤𐑦𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑝 𐑞 𐑥𐑹 𐑕𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑤𐑲𐑟𐑛 ·𐑑𐑭𐑣𐑰𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟, 𐑣𐑵 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑿𐑟𐑛 𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑰. 𐑗𐑸𐑑𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑕𐑥𐑷𐑤 𐑯𐑱𐑑𐑦𐑝 𐑕𐑒𐑵𐑯𐑼, 𐑣𐑰 𐑮𐑩𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑝𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑤; 𐑯 𐑓𐑲𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑷𐑤 𐑮𐑲𐑑 𐑞𐑺, 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯 𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑿𐑥𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑮𐑵𐑟𐑦𐑙𐑟.

“𐑢𐑺 ·𐑕𐑑𐑰𐑤𐑒𐑦𐑤𐑑 𐑯𐑬 𐑦𐑟, 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑥𐑧𐑯, 𐑯𐑳𐑯 𐑯𐑴; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑝 ·𐑯𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑑, 𐑞 𐑢𐑦𐑛𐑴 𐑝 ·𐑮𐑨𐑛𐑯𐑦 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑟 𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑰 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑮𐑦𐑓𐑿𐑟𐑩𐑟 𐑑 𐑜𐑦𐑝 𐑳𐑐 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑛𐑧𐑛; 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑛𐑮𐑰𐑥𐑟 𐑕𐑰𐑟 𐑞 𐑷𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑶𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥. * * * *

“'𐑸 𐑿 𐑔𐑮𐑵?' 𐑕𐑧𐑛 ·𐑛𐑪𐑯 ·𐑕𐑦𐑚𐑨𐑕𐑗𐑩𐑯, 𐑒𐑢𐑲𐑩𐑑𐑤𐑦.

“'𐑲 𐑨𐑥, ·𐑛𐑪𐑯.'

“'𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑲 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑰𐑑 𐑿, 𐑑𐑧𐑤 𐑥𐑰 𐑦𐑓 𐑑 𐑞 𐑚𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑝 𐑘𐑹 𐑴𐑯 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑝𐑦𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟, 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑘𐑹 𐑕𐑑𐑹𐑦 𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑚𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑮𐑾𐑤𐑦 𐑑𐑮𐑵? 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑴 𐑐𐑭𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑓𐑩𐑤! 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑿 𐑜𐑧𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑩𐑯 𐑳𐑯𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑕𐑗𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑹𐑕? 𐑚𐑺 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑥𐑰 𐑦𐑓 𐑲 𐑕𐑰𐑥 𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑕.'

“'𐑷𐑤𐑕𐑴 𐑚𐑺 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑷𐑤 𐑝 𐑳𐑕, 𐑕𐑻 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑼; 𐑓 𐑢𐑰 𐑷𐑤 𐑡𐑶𐑯 𐑦𐑯 ·𐑛𐑪𐑯 ·𐑕𐑦𐑚𐑨𐑕𐑗𐑩𐑯'𐑟 𐑕𐑵𐑑,' 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 𐑞 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑦, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑰𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑩𐑕𐑑.

“'𐑦𐑟 𐑞𐑺 𐑩 𐑒𐑪𐑐𐑦 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑦 ·𐑦𐑝𐑨𐑯𐑡𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑜𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑩𐑯 ·𐑦𐑯, 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑥𐑧𐑯?'

“'𐑯𐑱,' 𐑕𐑧𐑛 ·𐑛𐑪𐑯 ·𐑕𐑦𐑚𐑨𐑕𐑗𐑩𐑯; '𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑲 𐑯𐑴 𐑩 𐑢𐑻𐑞𐑦 𐑐𐑮𐑰𐑕𐑑 𐑯𐑽 𐑚𐑲, 𐑣𐑵 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑒𐑘𐑫𐑼 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑓 𐑥𐑰. 𐑲 𐑜𐑴 𐑓 𐑦𐑑; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑸 𐑿 𐑢𐑧𐑤 𐑩𐑛𐑝𐑲𐑟𐑛? 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑥𐑱 𐑜𐑮𐑴 𐑑𐑵 𐑕𐑽𐑾𐑕.'

“'𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑿 𐑚𐑰 𐑕𐑴 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑨𐑟 𐑑 𐑚𐑮𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑰𐑕𐑑 𐑷𐑤𐑕𐑴, ·𐑛𐑪𐑯?'

“'𐑞𐑴 𐑞𐑺 𐑸 𐑯𐑴 ·𐑷𐑑𐑴-𐑛𐑭-·𐑓𐑧𐑕 𐑦𐑯 ·𐑤𐑰𐑥𐑩 𐑯𐑬,' 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑦 𐑑 𐑩𐑯𐑳𐑞𐑼; '𐑲 𐑓𐑽 𐑬𐑼 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑼 𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑮𐑳𐑯𐑟 𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑒 𐑝 𐑞 archiepiscopacy. 𐑤𐑧𐑑 𐑳𐑕 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑛𐑮𐑷 𐑥𐑹 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑥𐑵𐑯𐑤𐑲𐑑. 𐑲 𐑕𐑰 𐑯𐑴 𐑯𐑰𐑛 𐑝 𐑞𐑦𐑕.'

“'𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑒𐑿𐑕 𐑥𐑰 𐑓 𐑮𐑳𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑿, ·𐑛𐑪𐑯 ·𐑕𐑦𐑚𐑨𐑕𐑗𐑩𐑯; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑥𐑱 𐑲 𐑷𐑤𐑕𐑴 𐑚𐑧𐑜 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑿 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑚𐑰 𐑐𐑼𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑼 𐑦𐑯 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑒𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑤𐑸𐑡𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑲𐑟𐑛 ·𐑦𐑝𐑨𐑯𐑡𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑕 𐑿 𐑒𐑨𐑯.'

* * * * * *

“'𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑦𐑟 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑰𐑕𐑑, 𐑣𐑰 𐑚𐑮𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑿 𐑞 ·𐑦𐑝𐑨𐑯𐑡𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑕,' 𐑕𐑧𐑛 ·𐑛𐑪𐑯 ·𐑕𐑦𐑚𐑨𐑕𐑗𐑩𐑯, 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑝𐑤𐑦, 𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑑𐑷𐑤 𐑯 𐑕𐑪𐑤𐑩𐑥 𐑓𐑦𐑜𐑼.

“'𐑤𐑧𐑑 𐑥𐑰 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑵𐑝 𐑥𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑑. 𐑯𐑬, 𐑝𐑧𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑐𐑮𐑰𐑕𐑑, 𐑓𐑻𐑞𐑼 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑤𐑲𐑑, 𐑯 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑞 ·𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑦 ·𐑚𐑫𐑒 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑥𐑰 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑲 𐑥𐑱 𐑑𐑳𐑗 𐑦𐑑.

“'𐑕𐑴 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑐 𐑥𐑰 ·𐑣𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑯, 𐑯 𐑪𐑯 𐑥𐑲 𐑪𐑯𐑼 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑹𐑦 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑑𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑘𐑰, 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑥𐑧𐑯, 𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑚𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑯 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑥𐑟, 𐑑𐑮𐑵. 𐑲 𐑯𐑴 𐑦𐑑 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑑𐑮𐑵; 𐑦𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑪𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑚𐑷𐑤; 𐑲 𐑑𐑮𐑪𐑛 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐; 𐑲 𐑯𐑿 𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑵; 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑕𐑰𐑯 𐑯 𐑑𐑷𐑒𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 ·𐑕𐑑𐑰𐑤𐑒𐑦𐑤𐑑 𐑕𐑦𐑯𐑕 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑔 𐑝 ·𐑮𐑨𐑛𐑯𐑦.'”

·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 55. 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑥𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑩𐑕 ·𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑗𐑼𐑟 𐑝 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟.

𐑲 𐑖𐑨𐑤 𐑺 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑐𐑱𐑯𐑑 𐑑 𐑿 𐑨𐑟 𐑢𐑧𐑤 𐑨𐑟 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑝𐑩𐑕, 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑞 𐑑𐑮𐑵 𐑓𐑹𐑥 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑨𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑨𐑒𐑗𐑵𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑩𐑐𐑽𐑟 𐑑 𐑞 𐑲 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑴𐑯 𐑨𐑚𐑕𐑩𐑤𐑵𐑑 𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑫𐑼𐑛 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑙𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤-𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑕𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑚𐑰 𐑓𐑺𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑐𐑑 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞𐑺. 𐑦𐑑 𐑥𐑱 𐑚𐑰 𐑢𐑻𐑔 𐑢𐑲𐑤, 𐑞𐑺𐑓𐑹, 𐑐𐑮𐑰𐑝𐑾𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑑 𐑨𐑛𐑝𐑻𐑑 𐑑 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑒𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑾𐑕 𐑦𐑥𐑨𐑡𐑦𐑯𐑼𐑦 𐑐𐑹𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑑 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑛𐑱 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑓𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑗𐑨𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑡 𐑞 𐑓𐑱𐑔 𐑝 𐑞 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟𐑥𐑩𐑯. 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑑 𐑕𐑧𐑑 𐑞 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛 𐑮𐑲𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑥𐑨𐑑𐑼, 𐑚𐑲 𐑐𐑮𐑵𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑗𐑼𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑷𐑤 𐑮𐑪𐑙.

𐑦𐑑 𐑥𐑱 𐑚𐑰 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑲𐑥𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑹𐑕 𐑝 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑑𐑹𐑾𐑤 𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑵𐑠𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑚𐑰 𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑞 𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑩𐑕𐑑 ·𐑣𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑵, ·𐑦𐑡𐑦𐑐𐑖𐑩𐑯, 𐑯 ·𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑕𐑒𐑳𐑤𐑐𐑗𐑼𐑟. 𐑓 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑕𐑦𐑯𐑕 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑝 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑳𐑯𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑵𐑐𐑿𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑥𐑸𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑐𐑨𐑯𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑝 𐑑𐑧𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑤𐑟, 𐑞 𐑐𐑧𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑝 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑗𐑿𐑟, 𐑯 𐑪𐑯 𐑖𐑰𐑤𐑛𐑟, 𐑥𐑦𐑛𐑨𐑤𐑾𐑯𐑟, 𐑒𐑳𐑐𐑕, 𐑯 𐑒𐑶𐑯𐑟, 𐑞 𐑛𐑪𐑤𐑓𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑛𐑮𐑷𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑒𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑝 𐑗𐑱𐑯-𐑸𐑥𐑼 𐑤𐑲𐑒 ·𐑕𐑭𐑤𐑩𐑛𐑰𐑯'𐑟, 𐑯 𐑩 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑥𐑩𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑤𐑲𐑒 ·𐑕𐑑 ·𐑡𐑹𐑡'𐑩𐑟; 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑕𐑦𐑯𐑕 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑕𐑹𐑑 𐑝 𐑤𐑲𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑝𐑱𐑤𐑛, 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑐𐑪𐑐𐑿𐑤𐑼 𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑗𐑼𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑕𐑲𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑒 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑥.

𐑯𐑬, 𐑚𐑲 𐑷𐑤 𐑪𐑛𐑟, 𐑞 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑱𐑯𐑗𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑑 𐑐𐑹𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑧𐑯𐑦𐑢𐑱𐑟 𐑐𐑼𐑐𐑹𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤'𐑟, 𐑦𐑟 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑱𐑥𐑩𐑕 𐑒𐑨𐑝𐑼𐑯-𐑐𐑩𐑜𐑴𐑛𐑩 𐑝 ·𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑓𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑩, 𐑦𐑯 ·𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑾. 𐑞 ·𐑚𐑮𐑭𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑟 𐑥𐑱𐑯𐑑𐑱𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑕𐑒𐑳𐑤𐑐𐑗𐑼𐑟 𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑥𐑩𐑥𐑹𐑾𐑤 𐑐𐑩𐑜𐑴𐑛𐑩, 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑛𐑟 𐑯 𐑐𐑼𐑕𐑿𐑑𐑕, 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑨𐑝𐑩𐑒𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑥𐑨𐑯, 𐑢𐑻 𐑐𐑮𐑰𐑓𐑦𐑜𐑼𐑛 𐑱𐑡𐑩𐑟 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑝 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑨𐑒𐑗𐑵𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑱𐑥 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙. 𐑯𐑴 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑕𐑹𐑑 𐑬𐑼 𐑯𐑴𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑓𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑖𐑨𐑛𐑴𐑛 𐑓𐑹𐑔. 𐑞 ·𐑣𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑵 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑮𐑦𐑓𐑻𐑛 𐑑, 𐑩𐑒𐑻𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑕𐑧𐑐𐑼𐑩𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑐𐑸𐑑𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑷𐑤, 𐑛𐑦𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑸𐑯𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 ·𐑝𐑰𐑖𐑯𐑵 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑹𐑥 𐑝 𐑤𐑩𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑔𐑩𐑯, 𐑤𐑻𐑯𐑩𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑯𐑴𐑯 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 ·𐑥𐑨𐑑𐑕𐑩 ·𐑨𐑝𐑩𐑑𐑸. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞𐑴 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑕𐑒𐑳𐑤𐑐𐑗𐑼 𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑭𐑓 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑯 𐑣𐑭𐑓 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑕𐑴 𐑨𐑟 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑑 𐑜𐑦𐑝 𐑞 𐑑𐑱𐑤 𐑝 𐑞 𐑤𐑨𐑑𐑼, 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑥𐑷𐑤 𐑕𐑧𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑦𐑟 𐑷𐑤 𐑮𐑪𐑙. 𐑦𐑑 𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑕 𐑥𐑹 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑞 𐑑𐑱𐑐𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑑𐑱𐑤 𐑝 𐑩𐑯 𐑨𐑯𐑩𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑛𐑩, 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑮𐑷𐑛 𐑐𐑭𐑥𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑑𐑮𐑵 𐑢𐑱𐑤'𐑟 𐑥𐑩𐑡𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑓𐑤𐑵𐑒𐑕.

𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑜𐑴 𐑑 𐑞 𐑴𐑤𐑛 ·𐑜𐑨𐑤𐑼𐑦𐑟, 𐑯 𐑤𐑫𐑒 𐑯𐑬 𐑨𐑑 𐑩 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 ·𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑗𐑩𐑯 𐑐𐑱𐑯𐑑𐑼'𐑟 𐑐𐑹𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑝 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑓𐑦𐑖; 𐑓 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑩𐑒𐑕𐑰𐑛𐑟 𐑯𐑴 𐑚𐑧𐑑𐑼 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑞 𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑵𐑝𐑾𐑯 ·𐑣𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑵. 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 ·𐑜𐑲𐑛𐑴'𐑟 𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑗𐑼 𐑝 ·𐑐𐑻𐑕𐑾𐑕 𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑒𐑿𐑦𐑙 ·𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑮𐑪𐑥𐑦𐑛𐑩 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑕𐑰-𐑥𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑼 𐑹 𐑢𐑱𐑤. 𐑢𐑺 𐑛𐑦𐑛 ·𐑜𐑲𐑛𐑴 𐑜𐑧𐑑 𐑞 𐑥𐑪𐑛𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡 𐑒𐑮𐑰𐑗𐑼 𐑨𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑? 𐑯𐑹 𐑛𐑳𐑟 ·𐑣𐑴𐑜𐑸𐑔, 𐑦𐑯 𐑐𐑱𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑕𐑰𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑴𐑯 “𐑐𐑻𐑕𐑾𐑕 ·𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙,” 𐑥𐑱𐑒 𐑬𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑑 𐑚𐑧𐑑𐑼. 𐑞 𐑣𐑿𐑡 𐑒𐑹𐑐𐑿𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑 ·𐑣𐑴𐑜𐑸𐑔𐑾𐑯 𐑥𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑼 𐑳𐑯𐑡𐑩𐑤𐑱𐑑𐑕 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑻𐑓𐑦𐑕, 𐑕𐑒𐑺𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑮𐑷𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑗 𐑝 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼. 𐑦𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑩 𐑕𐑹𐑑 𐑝 𐑣𐑬𐑛𐑩 𐑪𐑯 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑚𐑨𐑒, 𐑯 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑑𐑳𐑕𐑒𐑑 𐑥𐑬𐑔 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑞 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑴𐑟 𐑸 𐑮𐑴𐑤𐑦𐑙, 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑓 𐑞 ·𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑑𐑼𐑟' ·𐑜𐑱𐑑 𐑤𐑰𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 ·𐑑𐑧𐑥𐑟 𐑚𐑲 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 ·𐑑𐑬𐑼. 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑞𐑺 𐑸 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑮𐑴𐑛𐑮𐑴𐑥𐑩𐑕 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑝 𐑴𐑤𐑛 ·𐑕𐑒𐑪𐑗 ·𐑕𐑦𐑚𐑨𐑤𐑑, 𐑯 ·𐑡𐑴𐑯𐑩'𐑟 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑨𐑟 𐑛𐑦𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑴𐑤𐑛 ·𐑚𐑲𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑯 𐑞 𐑒𐑳𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑐𐑮𐑲𐑥𐑼𐑟. 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑖𐑨𐑤 𐑚𐑰 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑝 𐑞𐑰𐑟? 𐑨𐑟 𐑓 𐑞 𐑚𐑫𐑒-𐑚𐑲𐑯𐑛𐑼'𐑟 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑢𐑲𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑝𐑲𐑯-𐑕𐑑𐑷𐑒 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑪𐑒 𐑝 𐑩 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑼—𐑨𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑥𐑐𐑑 𐑯 𐑜𐑦𐑤𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑨𐑒𐑕 𐑯 𐑑𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑤-𐑐𐑱𐑡𐑩𐑟 𐑝 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑚𐑫𐑒𐑕 𐑚𐑴𐑔 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑯 𐑯𐑿—𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑩 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑗𐑼𐑧𐑕𐑒 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑐𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑤𐑦 𐑓𐑨𐑚𐑿𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑒𐑮𐑰𐑗𐑼, 𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑑𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛, 𐑲 𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑦𐑑, 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑓𐑦𐑜𐑼𐑟 𐑪𐑯 𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑰𐑒 𐑝𐑭𐑟𐑩𐑟. 𐑞𐑴 𐑿𐑯𐑦𐑝𐑻𐑕𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑦𐑯𐑪𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑩 𐑛𐑪𐑤𐑓𐑦𐑯, 𐑲 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼𐑞𐑩𐑤𐑧𐑕 𐑒𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑚𐑫𐑒-𐑚𐑲𐑯𐑛𐑼'𐑟 𐑓𐑦𐑖 𐑩𐑯 𐑩𐑑𐑧𐑥𐑐𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑩 𐑢𐑱𐑤; 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑪𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑴 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑞 𐑛𐑦𐑝𐑲𐑕 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑩𐑛𐑿𐑕𐑑. 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑩𐑛𐑿𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑩𐑯 𐑴𐑤𐑛 ·𐑦𐑑𐑨𐑤𐑾𐑯 𐑐𐑳𐑚𐑤𐑦𐑖𐑼 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑢𐑺 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑞 15𐑔 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑗𐑼𐑦, 𐑛𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑞 ·𐑮𐑦𐑝𐑲𐑝𐑩𐑤 𐑝 ·𐑤𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑙; 𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑛𐑱𐑟, 𐑯 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑑 𐑩 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑨𐑮𐑩𐑑𐑦𐑝𐑤𐑦 𐑤𐑱𐑑 𐑐𐑽𐑾𐑛, 𐑛𐑪𐑤𐑓𐑦𐑯𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑐𐑪𐑐𐑿𐑤𐑼𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑩𐑐𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑩 𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑖𐑰𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑤𐑩𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑔𐑩𐑯.

𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑝𐑦𐑯𐑘𐑧𐑑𐑕 𐑯 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑦𐑥𐑚𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑖𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑱𐑯𐑗𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑚𐑫𐑒𐑕 𐑿 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑨𐑑 𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑥𐑰𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑒𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑾𐑕 𐑑𐑳𐑗𐑩𐑟 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑢𐑺 𐑷𐑤 𐑥𐑨𐑯𐑼 𐑝 𐑕𐑐𐑬𐑑𐑕, 𐑡𐑧𐑑𐑕 𐑛'𐑴, 𐑣𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑯 𐑒𐑴𐑤𐑛, ·𐑕𐑨𐑮𐑩𐑑𐑴𐑜𐑩 𐑯 ·𐑚𐑭𐑛𐑧𐑯-·𐑚𐑭𐑛𐑧𐑯, 𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑚𐑳𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑳𐑐 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑳𐑯𐑦𐑜𐑟𐑷𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑯. 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑑𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑤-𐑐𐑱𐑡 𐑝 𐑞 𐑼𐑦𐑡𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑧𐑛𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 “𐑩𐑛𐑝𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑝 ·𐑤𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑙” 𐑿 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑓𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑒𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑾𐑕 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟.

𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑳𐑯𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑓𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑩𐑑𐑧𐑥𐑐𐑑𐑕, 𐑤𐑧𐑑 𐑳𐑕 𐑜𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑕 𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑗𐑼𐑟 𐑝 𐑤𐑩𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑔𐑩𐑯 𐑐𐑼𐑐𐑹𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑕𐑴𐑚𐑼, 𐑕𐑲𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑒 𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟, 𐑚𐑲 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑣𐑵 𐑯𐑴. 𐑦𐑯 𐑴𐑤𐑛 ·𐑣𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑕'𐑩𐑟 𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑧𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑝𐑶𐑦𐑡𐑩𐑟 𐑞𐑺 𐑸 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑩 ·𐑛𐑳𐑗 𐑚𐑫𐑒 𐑝 𐑝𐑶𐑦𐑡𐑩𐑟, ⸰𐑱𐑛 1671, 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑛 “𐑩 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙 ·𐑝𐑶𐑦𐑡 𐑑 ·𐑕𐑐𐑦𐑑𐑕𐑚𐑼𐑜𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐 ·𐑡𐑴𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤, ·𐑐𐑰𐑑𐑼 ·𐑐𐑰𐑑𐑼𐑕𐑩𐑯 𐑝 ·𐑓𐑮𐑲𐑟𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛, 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑼.” 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑑𐑕 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟, 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑮𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑤𐑪𐑜𐑟, 𐑸 𐑮𐑧𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑤𐑲𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑲𐑕-𐑲𐑤𐑟, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑚𐑺𐑟 𐑮𐑳𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑞𐑺 𐑤𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑨𐑒𐑕. 𐑦𐑯 𐑩𐑯𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑑, 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑛𐑦𐑡𐑩𐑕 𐑚𐑤𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑝 𐑮𐑧𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑐𐑻𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑼 𐑓𐑤𐑵𐑒𐑕.

𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯, 𐑞𐑺 𐑦𐑟 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑴𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑒𐑢𐑹𐑑𐑴, 𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑚𐑲 𐑢𐑳𐑯 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 ·𐑒𐑴𐑯𐑧𐑑, 𐑩 ·𐑐𐑴𐑕𐑑 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑤𐑦𐑖 𐑯𐑱𐑝𐑦, 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑛 “𐑩 ·𐑝𐑶𐑦𐑡 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 ·𐑒𐑱𐑐 ·𐑣𐑹𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑬𐑔 ·𐑕𐑰𐑟, 𐑓 𐑞 𐑐𐑻𐑐𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥𐑩𐑕𐑧𐑑𐑦 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤 ·𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑼𐑦𐑟.” 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑚𐑫𐑒 𐑦𐑟 𐑩𐑯 𐑬𐑑𐑤𐑲𐑯 𐑐𐑼𐑐𐑹𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑩 “𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑗𐑼 𐑝 𐑩 ·𐑓𐑦𐑟𐑩𐑑𐑼 𐑹 ·𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥𐑩𐑕𐑧𐑑𐑦 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑛𐑮𐑷𐑯 𐑚𐑲 𐑕𐑒𐑱𐑤 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑒𐑦𐑤𐑛 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑒𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑝 ·𐑥𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑴, 𐑷𐑜𐑩𐑕𐑑, 1793, 𐑯 𐑣𐑶𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑪𐑯 𐑛𐑧𐑒.” 𐑲 𐑛𐑬𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑞 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑝𐑼𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑕 𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑗𐑼 𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑓 𐑞 𐑚𐑧𐑯𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑑 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑼𐑰𐑯𐑟. 𐑑 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑦𐑑, 𐑤𐑧𐑑 𐑥𐑰 𐑕𐑱 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑩𐑯 𐑲 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑩𐑐𐑤𐑲𐑛, 𐑩𐑒𐑹𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑞 𐑩𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑒𐑱𐑤, 𐑑 𐑩 𐑓𐑫𐑤 𐑜𐑮𐑴𐑯 𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑥𐑱𐑒 𐑞 𐑲 𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑩 𐑚𐑴-𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑴 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑓𐑲𐑝 𐑓𐑰𐑑 𐑤𐑪𐑙. 𐑭, 𐑥𐑲 𐑜𐑨𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯, 𐑢𐑲 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑘𐑰 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑜𐑦𐑝 𐑳𐑕 ·𐑡𐑴𐑯𐑩 𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑲!

𐑯𐑹 𐑸 𐑞 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑖𐑦𐑧𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑕 𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑐𐑦𐑤𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑝 ·𐑯𐑨𐑗𐑼𐑩𐑤 ·𐑣𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑦 𐑓 𐑞 𐑚𐑧𐑯𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑘𐑳𐑙 𐑯 𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑼, 𐑓𐑮𐑰 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑣𐑰𐑯𐑩𐑕𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑒. 𐑤𐑫𐑒 𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑐𐑪𐑐𐑿𐑤𐑼 𐑢𐑻𐑒 “𐑜𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑕𐑥𐑦𐑔'𐑕 ·𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑥𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 ·𐑯𐑱𐑗𐑼.” 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑩𐑚𐑮𐑦𐑡𐑛 ·𐑤𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑯 𐑧𐑛𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 1807, 𐑞𐑺 𐑸 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑩𐑯 𐑩𐑤𐑧𐑡𐑛 “𐑢𐑱𐑤” 𐑯 𐑩 “𐑯𐑸𐑢𐑪𐑤.” 𐑲 𐑛𐑵 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑖 𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑥 𐑦𐑯𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑜𐑩𐑯𐑑, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑳𐑯𐑕𐑲𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑕 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩𐑯 𐑨𐑥𐑐𐑿𐑑𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑕𐑬; 𐑯, 𐑨𐑟 𐑓 𐑞 𐑯𐑸𐑢𐑪𐑤, 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑜𐑤𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑕 𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑳𐑓 𐑑 𐑩𐑥𐑱𐑟 𐑢𐑳𐑯, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑯𐑲𐑯𐑑𐑰𐑯𐑔 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑗𐑼𐑦 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩 𐑙𐑦𐑐𐑴𐑜𐑮𐑦𐑓 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑚𐑰 𐑐𐑭𐑥𐑛 𐑓 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑿𐑦𐑯 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑡𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑐𐑳𐑚𐑤𐑦𐑒 𐑝 𐑕𐑒𐑵𐑤𐑚𐑶𐑟.

𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯, 𐑦𐑯 1825, ·𐑚𐑻𐑯𐑸𐑛 ·𐑡𐑻𐑥𐑱𐑯, ·𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑 𐑛𐑦 ·𐑤𐑱𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑛, 𐑩 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑯𐑨𐑗𐑼𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑕𐑑, 𐑐𐑳𐑚𐑤𐑦𐑖𐑑 𐑩 𐑕𐑲𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑒 𐑕𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑥𐑲𐑟𐑛 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑚𐑫𐑒, 𐑢𐑺𐑦𐑯 𐑸 𐑕𐑧𐑝𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑗𐑼𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑛𐑦𐑓𐑼𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑖𐑰𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑤𐑩𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑔𐑩𐑯. 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑸 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑼𐑧𐑒𐑑, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞 𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑗𐑼 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑕𐑰𐑑𐑩𐑕 𐑹 ·𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑯𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑢𐑱𐑤 (𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑑 𐑕𐑱, 𐑞 ·𐑮𐑲𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑤), 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 ·𐑕𐑒𐑹𐑟𐑚𐑦, 𐑩 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑽𐑾𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑨𐑟 𐑑𐑳𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑖𐑰𐑟, 𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑺𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑐𐑸𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑯𐑱𐑗𐑼.

𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑞 𐑒𐑨𐑐-𐑖𐑰𐑓 𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑚𐑤𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑦𐑟𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑻𐑝𐑛 𐑓 𐑞 𐑕𐑲𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑒 ·𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑼𐑦𐑒 ·𐑒𐑿𐑝𐑽, 𐑚𐑮𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑑 𐑞 𐑓𐑱𐑥𐑩𐑕 ·𐑚𐑨𐑮𐑩𐑯. 𐑦𐑯 1836, 𐑣𐑰 𐑐𐑳𐑚𐑤𐑦𐑖𐑑 𐑩 ·𐑯𐑨𐑗𐑼𐑩𐑤 ·𐑣𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑦 𐑝 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟, 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑣𐑰 𐑜𐑦𐑝𐑟 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑟 𐑩 𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑗𐑼 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤. 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑖𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑗𐑼 𐑑 𐑧𐑯𐑦 ·𐑯𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑑𐑼, 𐑿 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑝𐑲𐑛 𐑓 𐑘𐑹 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑼𐑦 𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑮𐑰𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 ·𐑯𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑑. 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑢𐑻𐑛, ·𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑼𐑦𐑒 ·𐑒𐑿𐑝𐑽'𐑟 ·𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑩 ·𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑩 𐑕𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑖. 𐑝 𐑒𐑹𐑕, 𐑣𐑰 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑞 𐑚𐑧𐑯𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑑 𐑝 𐑩 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑝𐑶𐑦𐑡 (𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑛𐑩𐑥 𐑣𐑨𐑝), 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑕 𐑣𐑰 𐑛𐑦𐑮𐑲𐑝𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑗𐑼, 𐑣𐑵 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑑𐑧𐑤? 𐑐𐑼𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑕 𐑣𐑰 𐑜𐑪𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑲𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑒 𐑐𐑮𐑰𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑧𐑕𐑼 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑓𐑰𐑤𐑛, ·𐑛𐑧𐑥𐑸𐑱, 𐑜𐑪𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑷𐑔𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑩𐑚𐑹𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟; 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑟, 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑩 ·𐑗𐑲𐑯𐑰𐑟 𐑛𐑮𐑷𐑦𐑙. 𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑹𐑑 𐑝 𐑤𐑲𐑝𐑤𐑦 𐑤𐑨𐑛𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑤 𐑞𐑴𐑟 ·𐑗𐑲𐑯𐑰𐑟 𐑸, 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑒𐑢𐑽 𐑒𐑳𐑐𐑕 𐑯 𐑕𐑷𐑕𐑼𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑓𐑹𐑥 𐑳𐑕.

𐑨𐑟 𐑓 𐑞 𐑕𐑲𐑯-𐑐𐑱𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑟' 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑕𐑰𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑰𐑑𐑕 𐑣𐑨𐑙𐑦𐑙 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑞 𐑖𐑪𐑐𐑕 𐑝 𐑶𐑤-𐑛𐑰𐑤𐑼𐑟, 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑖𐑨𐑤 𐑚𐑰 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑝 𐑞𐑧𐑥? 𐑞𐑱 𐑸 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑤𐑦 ·𐑮𐑦𐑗𐑼𐑛 III. 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑛𐑮𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑛𐑼𐑦 𐑣𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑕, 𐑯 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑕𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑡; 𐑚𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑓𐑩𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑪𐑯 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑹 𐑓𐑹 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑼 𐑑𐑸𐑑𐑕, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕 𐑓𐑫𐑤 𐑝 𐑥𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑯𐑼𐑟: 𐑞𐑺 𐑛𐑦𐑓𐑹𐑥𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑤𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑰𐑟 𐑝 𐑚𐑤𐑳𐑛 𐑯 𐑚𐑤𐑵 𐑐𐑱𐑯𐑑.

𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑥𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑓𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑛𐑦𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑸 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑴 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑕𐑼𐑐𐑮𐑲𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑷𐑤. 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑼! 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑲𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑒 𐑛𐑮𐑷𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑓𐑦𐑖; 𐑯 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑸 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑒𐑼𐑧𐑒𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑩 𐑛𐑮𐑷𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑩 𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑑 𐑖𐑦𐑐, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑚𐑮𐑴𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑚𐑨𐑒, 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑒𐑼𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑧𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑞 𐑯𐑴𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑥𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑑𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑦𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑨𐑖𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑲𐑛 𐑝 𐑣𐑳𐑤 𐑯 𐑕𐑐𐑸𐑟. 𐑞𐑴 𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑓𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑕𐑑𐑫𐑛 𐑓 𐑞𐑺 𐑓𐑫𐑤-𐑤𐑧𐑙𐑔𐑕, 𐑞 𐑤𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑙 ·𐑤𐑩𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑔𐑩𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑓𐑺𐑤𐑦 𐑓𐑤𐑴𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑓 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑹𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑑. 𐑞 𐑤𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑫𐑤 𐑥𐑨𐑡𐑩𐑕𐑑𐑦 𐑯 𐑕𐑦𐑜𐑯𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕, 𐑦𐑟 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑕𐑰𐑯 𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑰 𐑦𐑯 𐑳𐑯𐑓𐑨𐑞𐑩𐑥𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼𐑟; 𐑯 𐑩𐑓𐑤𐑴𐑑 𐑞 𐑝𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑳𐑤𐑒 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑦𐑟 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑕𐑲𐑑, 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑤𐑷𐑯𐑗𐑑 𐑤𐑲𐑯-𐑝-𐑚𐑨𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑖𐑦𐑐; 𐑯 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑩 𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑪𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑓 𐑥𐑹𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑑 𐑣𐑶𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑺, 𐑕𐑴 𐑨𐑟 𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑻𐑝 𐑷𐑤 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑲𐑑𐑦 𐑕𐑢𐑧𐑤𐑟 𐑯 𐑳𐑯𐑡𐑩𐑤𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟. 𐑯, 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑑 𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑒 𐑝 𐑞 𐑣𐑲𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑿𐑥𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑛𐑦𐑓𐑼𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑝 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑫𐑼 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑢𐑰𐑯 𐑩 𐑘𐑳𐑙 𐑕𐑳𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑯 𐑩 𐑓𐑫𐑤-𐑜𐑮𐑴𐑯 ·𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑑𐑴𐑯𐑾𐑯 ·𐑤𐑩𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑔𐑩𐑯; 𐑘𐑧𐑑, 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑒𐑱𐑕 𐑝 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑘𐑳𐑙 𐑕𐑳𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑣𐑶𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑑 𐑩 𐑖𐑦𐑐'𐑕 𐑛𐑧𐑒, 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑦𐑟 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑞 𐑬𐑑𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑖, 𐑰𐑤-𐑤𐑲𐑒, 𐑤𐑦𐑥𐑚𐑼𐑛, 𐑝𐑺𐑦𐑦𐑙 𐑖𐑱𐑐 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑲𐑕 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑤 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑒𐑨𐑗.

𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑥𐑱 𐑚𐑰 𐑓𐑨𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑛, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑯𐑱𐑒𐑩𐑛 𐑕𐑒𐑧𐑤𐑩𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑨𐑒𐑘𐑼𐑩𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑥𐑱 𐑚𐑰 𐑛𐑦𐑮𐑲𐑝𐑛 𐑑𐑳𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑑𐑮𐑵 𐑓𐑹𐑥. 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑷𐑤. 𐑓 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑥𐑹 𐑒𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑾𐑕 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 ·𐑤𐑩𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑔𐑩𐑯, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑒𐑧𐑤𐑩𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑜𐑦𐑝𐑟 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑲𐑛𐑾 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑖𐑱𐑐. 𐑞𐑴 ·𐑡𐑧𐑮𐑩𐑥𐑦 ·𐑚𐑧𐑯𐑔𐑩𐑥'𐑟 𐑕𐑒𐑧𐑤𐑩𐑑𐑩𐑯, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑣𐑨𐑙𐑟 𐑓 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑤𐑭𐑚𐑮𐑩 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑤𐑲𐑚𐑮𐑺𐑦 𐑝 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑜𐑟𐑧𐑒𐑿𐑑𐑼𐑟, 𐑒𐑼𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑝𐑱𐑟 𐑞 𐑲𐑛𐑾 𐑝 𐑩 𐑚𐑻𐑤𐑦-𐑚𐑮𐑬𐑛 𐑿𐑑𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑼𐑾𐑯 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑥𐑩𐑯, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑷𐑤 ·𐑡𐑧𐑮𐑩𐑥𐑦'𐑟 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑤𐑰𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑐𐑻𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑒𐑨𐑮𐑩𐑒𐑑𐑼𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑕; 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑯𐑳𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑒𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑚𐑰 𐑦𐑯𐑓𐑻𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑤𐑩𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑔𐑩𐑯'𐑟 𐑸𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑴𐑯𐑟. 𐑦𐑯 𐑓𐑨𐑒𐑑, 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 ·𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑑𐑼 𐑕𐑧𐑟, 𐑞 𐑥𐑽 𐑕𐑒𐑧𐑤𐑩𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑚𐑺𐑟 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑮𐑦𐑤𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑑 𐑞 𐑓𐑫𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑯 𐑐𐑨𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑥𐑩𐑤 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑧𐑒𐑑 𐑛𐑳𐑟 𐑑 𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑕 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑴 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑧𐑤𐑩𐑐𐑕 𐑦𐑑. 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑦𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑒𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑣𐑧𐑛, 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑐𐑸𐑑 𐑝 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑚𐑫𐑒 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑚𐑰 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑖𐑴𐑯. 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑷𐑤𐑕𐑴 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑒𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑾𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑓𐑦𐑯, 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑜𐑟𐑨𐑒𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑼 𐑑 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑣𐑿𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛, 𐑥𐑲𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑞 𐑔𐑳𐑥. 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑓𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑓𐑹 𐑮𐑧𐑜𐑿𐑤𐑼 𐑚𐑴𐑯-𐑓𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑼𐑟, 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑧𐑒𐑕, 𐑥𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑤, 𐑮𐑦𐑙, 𐑯 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑓𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑼. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑸 𐑐𐑻𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑤𐑪𐑡𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑓𐑤𐑧𐑖𐑦 𐑒𐑳𐑝𐑼𐑦𐑙, 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑣𐑿𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑓𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑼𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑩𐑯 𐑸𐑑𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑤 𐑒𐑳𐑝𐑼𐑦𐑙. “𐑣𐑬𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑤𐑩𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑥𐑱 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑕𐑻𐑝 𐑳𐑕,” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑣𐑿𐑥𐑼𐑩𐑕 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑛𐑱, “𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑚𐑰 𐑑𐑮𐑵𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑤 𐑳𐑕 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑 𐑥𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑟.”

𐑓 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑮𐑰𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑟, 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑢𐑱 𐑿 𐑥𐑱 𐑤𐑫𐑒 𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑑, 𐑿 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑯𐑰𐑛𐑟 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑒𐑤𐑵𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 ·𐑤𐑩𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑔𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑒𐑮𐑰𐑗𐑼 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑱𐑯 𐑳𐑯𐑐𐑱𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑑 𐑞 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑. 𐑑𐑮𐑵, 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑐𐑹𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑥𐑱 𐑣𐑦𐑑 𐑞 𐑥𐑸𐑒 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑯𐑽𐑼 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑩𐑯𐑳𐑞𐑼, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑯𐑳𐑯 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑼𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑛𐑦𐑜𐑮𐑰 𐑝 𐑦𐑜𐑟𐑨𐑒𐑑𐑯𐑩𐑕. 𐑕𐑴 𐑞𐑺 𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑴 𐑻𐑔𐑤𐑦 𐑢𐑱 𐑝 𐑓𐑲𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑬𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑲𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑮𐑾𐑤𐑦 𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑕 𐑤𐑲𐑒. 𐑯 𐑞 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑥𐑴𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑿 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑛𐑦𐑮𐑲𐑝 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑩 𐑑𐑪𐑤𐑼𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑲𐑛𐑾 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑤𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑫𐑼, 𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑲 𐑜𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑘𐑹𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑕𐑴 𐑛𐑵𐑦𐑙, 𐑿 𐑮𐑳𐑯 𐑯𐑴 𐑕𐑥𐑷𐑤 𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑒 𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑑𐑴𐑝 𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑙𐑒 𐑚𐑲 𐑣𐑦𐑥. 𐑢𐑺𐑓𐑹, 𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑟 𐑑 𐑥𐑰 𐑿 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑑𐑵 𐑓𐑩𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑛𐑾𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑘𐑹 𐑒𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑦𐑪𐑕𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑑𐑳𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑦𐑕 ·𐑤𐑩𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑔𐑩𐑯.

·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 56. 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑤𐑧𐑕 ·𐑦𐑮𐑴𐑯𐑾𐑕 ·𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑗𐑼𐑟 𐑝 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟, 𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑑𐑮𐑵 ·𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑗𐑼𐑟 𐑝 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙 ·𐑕𐑰𐑯𐑟.

𐑦𐑯 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑧𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑥𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑩𐑕 𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑗𐑼𐑟 𐑝 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟, 𐑲 𐑨𐑥 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑪𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑑𐑧𐑥𐑐𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑣𐑽 𐑑 𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑼 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑥𐑹 𐑥𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑩𐑕 𐑕𐑑𐑹𐑦𐑟 𐑝 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑸 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑚𐑫𐑒𐑕, 𐑚𐑴𐑔 𐑱𐑯𐑗𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑯 𐑥𐑪𐑛𐑼𐑯, 𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑯 ·𐑐𐑤𐑲𐑯𐑦, ·𐑐𐑻𐑗𐑩𐑟, ·𐑙𐑨𐑒𐑤𐑶𐑑, ·𐑣𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑕, ·𐑒𐑿𐑝𐑽, 𐑧𐑑𐑕 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑲 𐑐𐑭𐑕 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑨𐑑𐑼 𐑚𐑲.

𐑲 𐑯𐑴 𐑝 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑓𐑹 𐑐𐑳𐑚𐑤𐑦𐑖𐑑 𐑬𐑑𐑤𐑲𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 ·𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤; ·𐑒𐑴𐑯𐑧𐑑'𐑕, ·𐑣𐑳𐑜𐑦𐑯𐑟'𐑩𐑟, ·𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑼𐑦𐑒 ·𐑒𐑿𐑝𐑽'𐑟, 𐑯 ·𐑚𐑦𐑱𐑤'𐑟. 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑰𐑝𐑾𐑕 𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 ·𐑒𐑴𐑯𐑧𐑑 𐑯 ·𐑒𐑿𐑝𐑽 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑮𐑦𐑓𐑻𐑛 𐑑. 𐑣𐑳𐑜𐑦𐑯𐑟'𐑩𐑟 𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑸 𐑚𐑧𐑑𐑼 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑞𐑺𐑟; 𐑚𐑳𐑑, 𐑚𐑲 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑪𐑛𐑟, ·𐑚𐑦𐑱𐑤'𐑟 𐑦𐑟 𐑞 𐑚𐑧𐑕𐑑. 𐑷𐑤 ·𐑚𐑦𐑱𐑤'𐑟 𐑛𐑮𐑷𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑝 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑸 𐑜𐑫𐑛, 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑧𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑥𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑤 𐑓𐑦𐑜𐑼 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑗𐑼 𐑝 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑝𐑺𐑾𐑕 𐑨𐑑𐑦𐑑𐑿𐑛𐑟, 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑧𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼. 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑮𐑳𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑕, 𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕 𐑩𐑑𐑨𐑒𐑦𐑙 ·𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟, 𐑞𐑴 𐑯𐑴 𐑛𐑬𐑑 𐑒𐑨𐑤𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑑 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑲𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑤 𐑕𐑒𐑧𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑕𐑦𐑟𐑩𐑥 𐑝 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑐𐑸𐑤𐑼 𐑥𐑧𐑯, 𐑦𐑟 𐑨𐑛𐑥𐑼𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑼𐑧𐑒𐑑 𐑯 𐑤𐑲𐑓-𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑦𐑯 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑓𐑧𐑒𐑑. 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑛𐑮𐑷𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑦𐑯 J. ·𐑮𐑪𐑕 ·𐑚𐑮𐑬𐑯 𐑸 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑒𐑼𐑧𐑒𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑫𐑼; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞𐑱 𐑸 𐑮𐑧𐑗𐑩𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑯𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑝𐑛. 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑷𐑤𐑑 𐑞𐑴.

𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑮𐑲𐑑 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑞 𐑚𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑬𐑑𐑤𐑲𐑯 𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑗𐑼𐑟 𐑸 𐑦𐑯 ·𐑕𐑒𐑹𐑟𐑚𐑦; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞𐑱 𐑸 𐑛𐑮𐑷𐑯 𐑪𐑯 𐑑𐑵 𐑕𐑥𐑷𐑤 𐑩 𐑕𐑒𐑱𐑤 𐑑 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑝𐑱 𐑩 𐑛𐑦𐑟𐑲𐑼𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑯. 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑗𐑼 𐑝 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑰𐑯𐑟, 𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑦𐑟 𐑩 𐑕𐑨𐑛 𐑛𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦, 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑪𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑲 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑗𐑼𐑟 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑨𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑢𐑧𐑤 𐑛𐑳𐑯, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑿 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑛𐑦𐑮𐑲𐑝 𐑧𐑯𐑦𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑑𐑮𐑵𐑔𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑲𐑛𐑾 𐑝 𐑞 𐑤𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑨𐑟 𐑕𐑰𐑯 𐑚𐑲 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑤𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑟.

𐑚𐑳𐑑, 𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑓 𐑷𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑷𐑤, 𐑚𐑲 𐑓𐑸 𐑞 𐑓𐑲𐑯𐑩𐑕𐑑, 𐑞𐑴 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑛𐑰𐑑𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑞 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑒𐑼𐑧𐑒𐑑, 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑯 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑰𐑯𐑟 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑧𐑯𐑦𐑢𐑺 𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛, 𐑸 𐑑𐑵 𐑤𐑸𐑡 ·𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑯𐑗 𐑦𐑯𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑝𐑦𐑙𐑟, 𐑢𐑧𐑤 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑑𐑩𐑛, 𐑯 𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑐𐑱𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑚𐑲 𐑢𐑳𐑯 ·𐑜𐑸𐑯𐑼𐑦. 𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑝𐑤𐑦, 𐑞𐑱 𐑮𐑧𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑩𐑑𐑨𐑒𐑕 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 𐑯 ·𐑮𐑲𐑑 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤. 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑯𐑴𐑚𐑩𐑤 ·𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑦𐑟 𐑛𐑦𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑓𐑫𐑤 𐑥𐑨𐑡𐑩𐑕𐑑𐑦 𐑝 𐑥𐑲𐑑, 𐑡𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑩𐑯 𐑚𐑦𐑯𐑰𐑔 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑓𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯, 𐑯 𐑚𐑺𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑲 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑺 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑨𐑒 𐑞 𐑑𐑼𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑒 𐑮𐑧𐑒 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑴𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑐𐑤𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑕. 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑬 𐑝 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑸𐑖𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑳𐑯𐑚𐑮𐑴𐑒𐑩𐑯, 𐑯 𐑦𐑟 𐑛𐑮𐑷𐑯 𐑡𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑨𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑥𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑼'𐑟 𐑕𐑐𐑲𐑯; 𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑬, 𐑓 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑕𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑿𐑑𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑓𐑤𐑨𐑖 𐑝 𐑑𐑲𐑥, 𐑿 𐑚𐑦𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑩𐑯 𐑹𐑟𐑥𐑩𐑯, 𐑣𐑭𐑓 𐑖𐑮𐑬𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑶𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑐𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑨𐑒𐑑 𐑝 𐑤𐑰𐑐𐑦𐑙, 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑓 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑩 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑦𐑐𐑦𐑕. 𐑞 𐑨𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑣𐑴𐑤 𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑓𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑯 𐑑𐑮𐑵. 𐑞 𐑣𐑭𐑓-𐑧𐑥𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑛 𐑤𐑲𐑯-𐑑𐑳𐑚 𐑓𐑤𐑴𐑑𐑕 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑕𐑰; 𐑞 𐑢𐑫𐑛𐑩𐑯 𐑐𐑴𐑤𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑦𐑤𐑛 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑟 𐑴𐑚𐑤𐑰𐑒𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑪𐑚 𐑦𐑯 𐑦𐑑; 𐑞 𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑢𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑒𐑮𐑵 𐑸 𐑕𐑒𐑨𐑑𐑼𐑛 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑩𐑓𐑮𐑲𐑑; 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑒 𐑕𐑑𐑹𐑥𐑦 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑺𐑦𐑙 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑰𐑯. 𐑕𐑽𐑾𐑕 𐑓𐑷𐑤𐑑 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑨𐑯𐑩𐑑𐑪𐑥𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑛𐑰𐑑𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑝 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑤𐑧𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑐𐑭𐑕; 𐑕𐑦𐑯𐑕, 𐑓 𐑞 𐑤𐑲𐑓 𐑝 𐑥𐑰, 𐑲 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑛𐑮𐑷 𐑕𐑴 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑩 𐑢𐑳𐑯.

𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑧𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑝𐑦𐑙, 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑨𐑒𐑑 𐑝 𐑛𐑮𐑷𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑙𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑞 𐑚𐑸𐑯𐑩𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑓𐑤𐑨𐑙𐑒 𐑝 𐑩 𐑤𐑸𐑡 𐑮𐑳𐑯𐑦𐑙 ·𐑮𐑲𐑑 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑮𐑴𐑤𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑒 𐑢𐑰𐑛𐑦 𐑚𐑳𐑤𐑒 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑰 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑥𐑪𐑕𐑦 𐑮𐑪𐑒-𐑕𐑤𐑲𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑨𐑑𐑩𐑜𐑴𐑯𐑾𐑯 𐑒𐑤𐑦𐑓𐑕. 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑡𐑧𐑑𐑕 𐑸 𐑦𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑑, 𐑓𐑫𐑤, 𐑯 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑒 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑕𐑫𐑑; 𐑕𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑕𐑴 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑕𐑥𐑴𐑒 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑗𐑦𐑥𐑯𐑦, 𐑿 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒 𐑞𐑺 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑩 𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑝 𐑕𐑳𐑐𐑼 𐑒𐑫𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑚𐑬𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑴. 𐑕𐑰 𐑓𐑬𐑤𐑟 𐑸 𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑥𐑷𐑤 𐑒𐑮𐑨𐑚𐑟, 𐑖𐑧𐑤-𐑓𐑦𐑖, 𐑯 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑕𐑰 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑟 𐑯 𐑥𐑩𐑒𐑺𐑩𐑯𐑦, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑞 ·𐑮𐑲𐑑 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑒𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑟 𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑚𐑨𐑒. 𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑞 𐑔𐑦𐑒-𐑤𐑦𐑐𐑑 𐑤𐑩𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑔𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑟 𐑮𐑳𐑖𐑦𐑙 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑞 𐑛𐑰𐑐, 𐑤𐑰𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑑𐑳𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑑𐑿𐑥𐑳𐑤𐑗𐑵𐑩𐑕 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑒𐑻𐑛𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑱𐑒, 𐑯 𐑒𐑷𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑕𐑤𐑲𐑑 𐑚𐑴𐑑 𐑑 𐑮𐑪𐑒 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑢𐑧𐑤𐑟 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑕𐑒𐑦𐑓 𐑒𐑷𐑑 𐑯𐑲 𐑞 𐑐𐑨𐑛𐑩𐑤-𐑢𐑰𐑤𐑟 𐑝 𐑩𐑯 𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑰𐑥𐑼. 𐑞𐑳𐑕, 𐑞 𐑓𐑹𐑜𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑟 𐑷𐑤 𐑮𐑱𐑡𐑦𐑙 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑣𐑲𐑯𐑛, 𐑦𐑯 𐑨𐑛𐑥𐑼𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑸𐑑𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑭𐑕𐑑, 𐑦𐑟 𐑞 𐑜𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑦 𐑤𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑩 𐑕𐑰 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑭𐑥𐑛, 𐑞 𐑛𐑮𐑵𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑳𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑗𐑑 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑐𐑬𐑼𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑖𐑦𐑐, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑻𐑑 𐑥𐑨𐑕 𐑝 𐑩 𐑛𐑧𐑛 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑩 𐑒𐑪𐑙𐑒𐑼𐑛 𐑓𐑹𐑑𐑮𐑩𐑕, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑓𐑤𐑨𐑜 𐑝 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑗𐑼 𐑤𐑱𐑟𐑦𐑤𐑦 𐑣𐑨𐑙𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤-𐑐𐑴𐑤 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑐𐑬𐑑-𐑣𐑴𐑤.

𐑣𐑵 ·𐑜𐑸𐑯𐑼𐑦 𐑞 𐑐𐑱𐑯𐑑𐑼 𐑦𐑟, 𐑹 𐑢𐑪𐑟, 𐑲 𐑯𐑴 𐑯𐑪𐑑. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑥𐑲 𐑤𐑲𐑓 𐑓 𐑦𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑲𐑞𐑼 𐑐𐑮𐑨𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑝𐑻𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑳𐑚𐑡𐑧𐑒𐑑, 𐑹 𐑧𐑤𐑕 𐑥𐑸𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑩𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑑𐑿𐑑𐑼𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑽𐑾𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑥𐑩𐑯. 𐑞 ·𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑯𐑗 𐑸 𐑞 𐑤𐑨𐑛𐑟 𐑓 𐑐𐑱𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑨𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯. 𐑜𐑴 𐑯 𐑜𐑱𐑟 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑐𐑱𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑝 ·𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑩𐑐, 𐑯 𐑢𐑺 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑿 𐑓𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩 𐑜𐑨𐑤𐑼𐑦 𐑝 𐑤𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑯 𐑚𐑮𐑰𐑞𐑦𐑙 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑪𐑯 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑝𐑩𐑕, 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑳𐑥𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑣𐑷𐑤 𐑨𐑑 ·𐑝𐑼𐑕𐑲; 𐑢𐑺 𐑞 𐑚𐑦𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑼 𐑓𐑲𐑑𐑕 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑱, 𐑐𐑧𐑤-𐑥𐑧𐑤, 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑞 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑧𐑒𐑿𐑑𐑦𐑝 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑚𐑨𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑝 ·𐑓𐑮𐑭𐑯𐑕; 𐑢𐑺 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑕𐑹𐑛 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑟 𐑩 𐑓𐑤𐑨𐑖 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑯𐑹𐑞𐑼𐑯 ·𐑤𐑲𐑑𐑕, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑩𐑒𐑕𐑧𐑕𐑦𐑝 𐑸𐑥𐑛 𐑒𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑯 ·𐑧𐑥𐑐𐑼𐑼𐑟 𐑛𐑨𐑖 𐑚𐑲, 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑗𐑸𐑡 𐑝 𐑒𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑹𐑟? 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑦 𐑳𐑯𐑢𐑻𐑞𐑦 𐑝 𐑩 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑜𐑨𐑤𐑼𐑦, 𐑸 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑕𐑰 𐑚𐑨𐑑𐑩𐑤-𐑐𐑰𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑝 ·𐑜𐑸𐑯𐑼𐑦.

𐑞 𐑯𐑨𐑗𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑑𐑿𐑛 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑯𐑗 𐑓 𐑕𐑰𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑗𐑼𐑧𐑕𐑒𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑟 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑽𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑐𐑱𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑝𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑞𐑱 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑝 𐑞𐑺 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑰𐑯𐑟. 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑔 𐑝 ·𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛'𐑟 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑽𐑾𐑯𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑼𐑦, 𐑯 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑞 𐑔𐑬𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑛𐑔 𐑐𐑸𐑑 𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑩𐑥𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑟, 𐑞𐑱 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼𐑞𐑩𐑤𐑧𐑕 𐑓𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑖𐑑 𐑚𐑴𐑔 𐑯𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑓𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑖𐑑 𐑕𐑒𐑧𐑗𐑩𐑟 𐑨𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑒𐑱𐑐𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑝𐑱𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑮𐑾𐑤 𐑕𐑐𐑦𐑮𐑦𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑑. 𐑓 𐑞 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑐𐑸𐑑, 𐑞 ·𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑤𐑦𐑖 𐑯 ·𐑩𐑥𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑛𐑮𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑕𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑕𐑰𐑥 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑲𐑼𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑥𐑦𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑬𐑑𐑤𐑲𐑯 𐑝 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑟, 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑝𐑱𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑴𐑓𐑲𐑤 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤; 𐑢𐑦𐑗, 𐑕𐑴 𐑓𐑸 𐑨𐑟 𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑗𐑼𐑧𐑕𐑒𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑦𐑓𐑧𐑒𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑻𐑯𐑛, 𐑦𐑟 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑥𐑬𐑯𐑑 𐑑 𐑕𐑒𐑧𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑴𐑓𐑲𐑤 𐑝 𐑩 𐑐𐑦𐑮𐑩𐑥𐑦𐑛. 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 ·𐑕𐑒𐑹𐑟𐑚𐑦, 𐑞 𐑡𐑳𐑕𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑦𐑯𐑬𐑯𐑛 ·𐑮𐑲𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑥𐑩𐑯, 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑜𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑳𐑕 𐑩 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑓 𐑓𐑫𐑤 𐑤𐑧𐑙𐑔 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑯𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑯 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑹 𐑓𐑹 𐑛𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑑 𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑗𐑼𐑟 𐑝 𐑯𐑸𐑢𐑪𐑤𐑕 𐑯 𐑐𐑹𐑐𐑩𐑕𐑩𐑟, 𐑑𐑮𐑰𐑑𐑕 𐑳𐑕 𐑑 𐑩 𐑕𐑽𐑰𐑟 𐑝 𐑒𐑤𐑨𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑯𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑝𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑝 𐑚𐑴𐑑 𐑣𐑫𐑒𐑕, 𐑗𐑪𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑯𐑲𐑝𐑟, 𐑯 𐑜𐑮𐑨𐑐𐑯𐑩𐑤𐑟; 𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑥𐑲𐑒𐑮𐑩𐑕𐑒𐑪𐑐𐑦𐑒 𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑡𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑝 𐑩 ·𐑤𐑵𐑢𐑩𐑯𐑙𐑴𐑒 𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑥𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑑 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑩 𐑖𐑦𐑝𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛 𐑯𐑲𐑯𐑑𐑦-𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑕 𐑓𐑭𐑒-𐑕𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑟 𐑝 𐑥𐑨𐑜𐑯𐑦𐑓𐑲𐑛 ·𐑸𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑕𐑯𐑴 𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑟. 𐑲 𐑥𐑰𐑯 𐑯𐑴 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑡𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑑 𐑞 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑩𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑝𐑶𐑦𐑡𐑼 (𐑲 𐑪𐑯𐑼 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑓 𐑩 𐑝𐑧𐑑𐑼𐑩𐑯), 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑴 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑹𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑩 𐑥𐑨𐑑𐑼 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑩𐑯 𐑴𐑝𐑼𐑕𐑲𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑒𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑛 𐑓 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑩 𐑕𐑢𐑹𐑯 𐑨𐑓𐑦𐑛𐑱𐑝𐑦𐑑 𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑩 ·𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑯𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛 ·𐑡𐑳𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑕.

𐑦𐑯 𐑩𐑛𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑑 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑓𐑲𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑝𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 ·𐑜𐑸𐑯𐑼𐑦, 𐑞𐑺 𐑸 𐑑𐑵 𐑳𐑞𐑼 ·𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑯𐑗 𐑦𐑯𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑝𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑢𐑻𐑞𐑦 𐑝 𐑯𐑴𐑑, 𐑚𐑲 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑣𐑵 𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑚𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 “H. ·𐑛𐑼𐑨𐑯𐑛.” 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑞𐑧𐑥, 𐑞𐑴 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑲𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑩𐑛𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑑 𐑬𐑼 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑐𐑻𐑐𐑩𐑕, 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼𐑞𐑩𐑤𐑧𐑕 𐑛𐑦𐑟𐑻𐑝𐑟 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑪𐑯 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑩𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑕. 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑩 𐑒𐑢𐑲𐑩𐑑 𐑯𐑵𐑯-𐑕𐑰𐑯 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑞 𐑲𐑤𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑩𐑕𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑒; 𐑩 ·𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑯𐑗 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑼 𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑼𐑛, 𐑦𐑯𐑖𐑹, 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑒𐑭𐑥, 𐑯 𐑤𐑱𐑟𐑦𐑤𐑦 𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼 𐑪𐑯 𐑚𐑹𐑛; 𐑞 𐑤𐑵𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑤𐑰𐑝𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑐𐑭𐑥𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑨𐑒𐑜𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛, 𐑚𐑴𐑔 𐑛𐑮𐑵𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑑𐑩𐑜𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑮𐑰𐑟𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑺. 𐑞 𐑦𐑓𐑧𐑒𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑓𐑲𐑯, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑼𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑮𐑧𐑓𐑼𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑑 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑣𐑸𐑛𐑦 𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑼𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑞𐑺 𐑓𐑿 𐑨𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑕 𐑝 ·𐑹𐑦𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑴𐑟. 𐑞 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑦𐑯𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑩 𐑛𐑦𐑓𐑼𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑩𐑓𐑺: 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑣𐑴𐑝-𐑑 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑴𐑐𐑩𐑯 𐑕𐑰, 𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑣𐑸𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑤𐑩𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑔𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑒 𐑤𐑲𐑓, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 ·𐑮𐑲𐑑 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑙𐑕𐑲𐑛; 𐑞 𐑝𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑤 (𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑨𐑒𐑑 𐑝 𐑒𐑳𐑑𐑦𐑙-𐑦𐑯) 𐑣𐑴𐑝 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑑 𐑞 𐑥𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑼 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑓 𐑑 𐑩 𐑒𐑰; 𐑯 𐑩 𐑚𐑴𐑑, 𐑣𐑳𐑮𐑦𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑫𐑖𐑦𐑙 𐑪𐑓 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑕𐑰𐑯 𐑝 𐑨𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑑𐑦, 𐑦𐑟 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑜𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑗𐑱𐑕 𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕. 𐑞 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑟 𐑯 𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑤𐑲 𐑤𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑓 𐑿𐑕; 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑹𐑟𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑸 𐑡𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑧𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑣𐑴𐑤; 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑩 𐑕𐑳𐑛𐑩𐑯 𐑮𐑴𐑤 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑰, 𐑞 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑒𐑮𐑭𐑓𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑣𐑭𐑓-𐑦𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑑 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼, 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑮𐑽𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑹𐑕. 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐, 𐑞 𐑕𐑥𐑴𐑒 𐑝 𐑞 𐑑𐑹𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑚𐑶𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑦𐑟 𐑜𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑳𐑐 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑞 𐑕𐑥𐑴𐑒 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑩 𐑝𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑡 𐑝 𐑕𐑥𐑦𐑞𐑦𐑟; 𐑯 𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑢𐑼𐑛, 𐑩 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑒 𐑒𐑤𐑬𐑛, 𐑮𐑲𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑳𐑐 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑻𐑯𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑝 𐑕𐑒𐑢𐑷𐑤𐑟 𐑯 𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑟, 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑟 𐑑 𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑞 𐑨𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑝 𐑞 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑧𐑯.

·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 57. 𐑝 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑦𐑯 ·𐑐𐑱𐑯𐑑; 𐑦𐑯 ·𐑑𐑰𐑔; 𐑦𐑯 ·𐑢𐑫𐑛; 𐑦𐑯 ·𐑖𐑰𐑑-·𐑲𐑼𐑯; 𐑦𐑯 ·𐑕𐑑𐑴𐑯; 𐑦𐑯 ·𐑥𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑟; 𐑦𐑯 ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑟.

𐑪𐑯 ·𐑑𐑬𐑼-𐑣𐑦𐑤, 𐑨𐑟 𐑿 𐑜𐑴 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑤𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑯 𐑛𐑪𐑒𐑕, 𐑿 𐑥𐑱 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑕𐑰𐑯 𐑩 𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑚𐑧𐑜𐑼 (𐑹 𐑒𐑧𐑡𐑩, 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑼𐑟 𐑕𐑱) 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑐𐑱𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑹𐑛 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑮𐑧𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑡𐑦𐑒 𐑕𐑰𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑣𐑰 𐑤𐑪𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑤𐑧𐑜. 𐑞𐑺 𐑸 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑯 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕; 𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕 (𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑿𐑥𐑛 𐑑 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑱𐑯 𐑞 𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑤𐑧𐑜 𐑦𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑼𐑦𐑡𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑜𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑦) 𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑒𐑮𐑳𐑯𐑗𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑡𐑷𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑓𐑹𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑤. 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑑𐑧𐑯 𐑘𐑽𐑟, 𐑞𐑱 𐑑𐑧𐑤 𐑥𐑰, 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑛 𐑳𐑐 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑗𐑼, 𐑯 𐑦𐑜𐑟𐑦𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑥𐑐 𐑑 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑮𐑧𐑡𐑵𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑡𐑳𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑒𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑯𐑬 𐑒𐑳𐑥. 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑸 𐑨𐑟 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑨𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑐𐑳𐑚𐑤𐑦𐑖𐑑 𐑦𐑯 ·𐑢𐑪𐑐𐑦𐑙, 𐑨𐑑 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑮𐑱𐑑; 𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑥𐑐 𐑨𐑟 𐑳𐑯𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑕𐑗𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑩 𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑥𐑐 𐑨𐑟 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑿 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑓𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑯 𐑒𐑤𐑽𐑦𐑙𐑟. 𐑚𐑳𐑑, 𐑞𐑴 𐑓 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑥𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑪𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑥𐑐, 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑩 𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑥𐑐-𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑗 𐑛𐑳𐑟 𐑞 𐑐𐑫𐑼 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑥𐑱𐑒; 𐑚𐑳𐑑, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑛𐑬𐑯𐑒𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑲𐑟, 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑮𐑵𐑓𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑴𐑯 𐑨𐑥𐑐𐑿𐑑𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯.

𐑔𐑮𐑵𐑬𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑩𐑕𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑒, 𐑯 𐑷𐑤𐑕𐑴 𐑦𐑯 ·𐑯𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑑, 𐑯 ·𐑯𐑿 ·𐑚𐑧𐑛𐑓𐑼𐑛, 𐑯 ·𐑕𐑨𐑜 ·𐑣𐑸𐑚𐑼, 𐑿 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑩𐑒𐑮𐑪𐑕 𐑤𐑲𐑝𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑒𐑧𐑗𐑩𐑟 𐑝 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑯 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙-𐑕𐑰𐑯𐑟, 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑼𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑝𐑟 𐑪𐑯 ·𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤-𐑑𐑰𐑔, 𐑹 𐑤𐑱𐑛𐑦𐑟' 𐑚𐑳𐑕𐑒𐑕 𐑮𐑷𐑑 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑮𐑲𐑑 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤-𐑚𐑴𐑯, 𐑯 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑟𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑸𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑟, 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑒𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑯𐑿𐑥𐑼𐑩𐑕 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑯𐑡𐑰𐑯𐑾𐑕 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑝𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑞𐑱 𐑦𐑤𐑨𐑚𐑼𐑩𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑸𐑝 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑮𐑳𐑓 𐑥𐑩𐑑𐑽𐑾𐑤, 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑬𐑼𐑟 𐑝 𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑤𐑧𐑠𐑼. 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑝 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑚𐑪𐑒𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑝 𐑛𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤-𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑦𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑕, 𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑓 𐑞 𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑟𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑦𐑟𐑯𐑩𐑕. 𐑚𐑳𐑑, 𐑦𐑯 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑤, 𐑞𐑱 𐑑𐑶𐑤 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞𐑺 𐑡𐑨𐑒-𐑯𐑲𐑝𐑟 𐑩𐑤𐑴𐑯; 𐑯, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑪𐑥𐑯𐑦𐑐𐑩𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑑𐑵𐑤 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑼, 𐑞𐑱 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑑𐑻𐑯 𐑿 𐑬𐑑 𐑧𐑯𐑦𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑿 𐑐𐑤𐑰𐑟, 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑱 𐑝 𐑩 𐑥𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑯𐑼'𐑟 𐑓𐑨𐑯𐑕𐑦.

𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑲𐑤 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 ·𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑥 𐑯 𐑕𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑤𐑲𐑟𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑹𐑟 𐑩 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑗 ·𐑜𐑪𐑛 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑲𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑛 𐑕𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑡𐑮𐑦. 𐑘𐑹 𐑑𐑮𐑵 𐑢𐑱𐑤-𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑑𐑼 𐑦𐑟 𐑨𐑟 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑩 𐑕𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑡 𐑨𐑟 𐑩𐑯 ·𐑽𐑩𐑒𐑢𐑭. 𐑲 𐑥𐑲𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑨𐑥 𐑩 𐑕𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑡, 𐑴𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑯𐑴 𐑩𐑤𐑰𐑡𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑟; 𐑯 𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑦 𐑨𐑑 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑥𐑴𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑚𐑧𐑤 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥.

𐑯𐑬, 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑽 𐑒𐑨𐑮𐑩𐑒𐑑𐑼𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑡 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑛𐑩𐑥𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑬𐑼𐑟, 𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑐𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑝 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑳𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑦. 𐑩𐑯 𐑱𐑯𐑗𐑩𐑯𐑑 ·𐑣𐑩𐑢𐑲𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑹-𐑒𐑤𐑳𐑚 𐑹 𐑕𐑐𐑽-𐑐𐑨𐑛𐑩𐑤, 𐑦𐑯 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑓𐑫𐑤 𐑥𐑳𐑤𐑑𐑦𐑐𐑤𐑦𐑕𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑯 𐑦𐑤𐑨𐑚𐑼𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑒𐑸𐑝𐑦𐑙, 𐑦𐑟 𐑨𐑟 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑩 𐑑𐑮𐑴𐑓𐑦 𐑝 𐑣𐑿𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑐𐑻𐑕𐑩𐑝𐑽𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑨𐑟 𐑩 ·𐑤𐑨𐑑𐑦𐑯 𐑤𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑪𐑯. 𐑓, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑩 𐑚𐑦𐑑 𐑝 𐑚𐑮𐑴𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑕𐑰-𐑖𐑧𐑤 𐑹 𐑩 𐑖𐑸𐑒'𐑕 𐑑𐑵𐑔, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑦𐑮𐑨𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑕𐑦 𐑝 𐑢𐑫𐑛𐑩𐑯 𐑯𐑧𐑑-𐑢𐑻𐑒 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑩𐑗𐑰𐑝𐑛; 𐑯 𐑦𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑒𐑪𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑛𐑦 𐑘𐑽𐑟 𐑝 𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑛𐑦 𐑨𐑐𐑤𐑦𐑒𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯.

𐑨𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 ·𐑣𐑩𐑢𐑲𐑩𐑯 𐑕𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑡, 𐑕𐑴 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑼-𐑕𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑡. 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑥𐑸𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑐𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑕, 𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑕𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑩𐑤 𐑖𐑸𐑒'𐑕 𐑑𐑵𐑔, 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑐𐑫𐑼 𐑡𐑨𐑒-𐑯𐑲𐑓, 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑒𐑸𐑝 𐑿 𐑩 𐑚𐑦𐑑 𐑝 𐑚𐑴𐑯 𐑕𐑒𐑳𐑤𐑐𐑗𐑼, 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑒𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑢𐑻𐑒𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑲𐑒, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑒𐑤𐑴𐑕 𐑐𐑨𐑒𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑥𐑱𐑟𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑛𐑦𐑟𐑲𐑯, 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 ·𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑒 𐑕𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑡, ·𐑩𐑒𐑦𐑤𐑰𐑟'𐑩𐑟 𐑖𐑰𐑤𐑛; 𐑯 𐑓𐑫𐑤 𐑝 𐑚𐑸𐑚𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑒 𐑕𐑐𐑦𐑮𐑦𐑑 𐑯 𐑕𐑩𐑡𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑝𐑯𐑩𐑕, 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑓𐑲𐑯 𐑴𐑤𐑛 ·𐑛𐑳𐑗 𐑕𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑡, ·𐑨𐑤𐑚𐑼𐑑 ·𐑛𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑼.

𐑢𐑫𐑛𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟, 𐑹 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑒𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑐𐑮𐑴𐑓𐑲𐑤 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑥𐑷𐑤 𐑛𐑸𐑒 𐑕𐑤𐑨𐑚𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑯𐑴𐑚𐑩𐑤 ·𐑕𐑬𐑔 ·𐑕𐑰 𐑢𐑹-𐑢𐑫𐑛, 𐑸 𐑓𐑮𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑥𐑧𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑴𐑒𐑕𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑝 ·𐑩𐑥𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑼𐑟. 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑝 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑸 𐑛𐑳𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑨𐑒𐑘𐑼𐑩𐑕𐑦.

𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑜𐑱𐑚𐑩𐑤-𐑮𐑵𐑓𐑑 𐑒𐑳𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑦 𐑣𐑬𐑟𐑩𐑟 𐑿 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑕𐑰 𐑚𐑮𐑭𐑕 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑣𐑳𐑙 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑑𐑱𐑤 𐑓 𐑯𐑪𐑒𐑼𐑟 𐑑 𐑞 𐑮𐑴𐑛-𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑛𐑹. 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑞 𐑐𐑹𐑑𐑼 𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑤𐑰𐑐𐑦, 𐑞 𐑨𐑯𐑝𐑦𐑤-𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑚𐑰 𐑚𐑧𐑕𐑑. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑸 𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑛𐑩𐑥 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑸𐑒𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑨𐑟 𐑓𐑱𐑔𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑧𐑕𐑱𐑟. 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑲𐑼𐑟 𐑝 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑴𐑤𐑛-𐑓𐑨𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑗𐑻𐑗𐑩𐑟 𐑿 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑕𐑰 𐑖𐑰𐑑-𐑲𐑼𐑯 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑓 𐑢𐑧𐑞𐑼-𐑒𐑪𐑒𐑕; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞𐑱 𐑸 𐑕𐑴 𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑝𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛, 𐑯 𐑚𐑦𐑕𐑲𐑛𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑸 𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑯 𐑐𐑻𐑐𐑩𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑕𐑴 𐑤𐑱𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 “𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑪𐑓!” 𐑿 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑦𐑜𐑟𐑨𐑥𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑒𐑤𐑴𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑯𐑳𐑓 𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑥𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑑.

𐑦𐑯 𐑚𐑴𐑯𐑦, 𐑮𐑦𐑚𐑦 𐑮𐑰𐑡𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑻𐑔, 𐑢𐑺 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑚𐑱𐑕 𐑝 𐑣𐑲 𐑚𐑮𐑴𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑒𐑤𐑦𐑓𐑕 𐑥𐑨𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑝 𐑮𐑪𐑒 𐑤𐑲 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑵𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑓𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑨𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑜𐑮𐑵𐑐𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑯, 𐑿 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑪𐑓𐑩𐑯 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑳𐑝𐑼 𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑡𐑩𐑟 𐑨𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑐𐑧𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑓𐑲𐑛 𐑓𐑹𐑥𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑤𐑩𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑔𐑩𐑯 𐑐𐑸𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑥𐑻𐑡𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑜𐑮𐑭𐑕, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑝 𐑩 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑦 𐑛𐑱 𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑒𐑕 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑕𐑻𐑓 𐑝 𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑯 𐑕𐑻𐑡𐑩𐑟.

𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯, 𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑒𐑳𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑺 𐑞 𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑼 𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑿𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑜𐑻𐑛𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑨𐑥𐑓𐑦𐑔𐑦𐑨𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑣𐑲𐑑𐑕; 𐑣𐑽 𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑤𐑳𐑒𐑦 𐑐𐑶𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑝𐑿 𐑿 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑒𐑨𐑗 𐑐𐑭𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑜𐑤𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑴𐑓𐑲𐑤𐑟 𐑝 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑛𐑦𐑓𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑞 𐑳𐑯𐑡𐑩𐑤𐑱𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑮𐑦𐑡𐑩𐑟. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑿 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑩 𐑔𐑳𐑮𐑴 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑥𐑩𐑯, 𐑑 𐑕𐑰 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑕𐑲𐑑𐑕; 𐑯 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑞𐑨𐑑, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑓 𐑿 𐑢𐑦𐑖 𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑻𐑯 𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩 𐑕𐑲𐑑 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯, 𐑿 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑖𐑫𐑼 𐑯 𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑞 𐑦𐑜𐑟𐑨𐑒𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑕𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑤𐑨𐑑𐑦𐑑𐑿𐑛 𐑯 𐑤𐑪𐑯𐑜𐑦𐑑𐑿𐑛 𐑝 𐑘𐑹 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛-𐑐𐑶𐑯𐑑, 𐑧𐑤𐑕 𐑕𐑴 𐑗𐑭𐑯𐑕-𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑸 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑪𐑚𐑟𐑼𐑝𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑤𐑟, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑘𐑹 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑲𐑕, 𐑐𐑮𐑰𐑝𐑾𐑕 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛-𐑐𐑶𐑯𐑑 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑢𐑲𐑼 𐑩 𐑤𐑩𐑚𐑹𐑾𐑕 𐑮𐑰-𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑳𐑝𐑼𐑦; 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑴𐑤𐑴𐑥𐑩 ·𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛𐑟, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑱𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑪𐑜𐑯𐑰𐑑𐑩, 𐑞𐑴 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑕 𐑣𐑲-𐑮𐑳𐑓𐑑 ·𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑩 𐑑𐑮𐑪𐑛 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑯 𐑴𐑤𐑛 ·𐑝𐑦𐑜𐑻𐑮𐑩 𐑒𐑮𐑪𐑯𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑞𐑧𐑥.

𐑯𐑹 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑤𐑦𐑓𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑘𐑹 𐑕𐑳𐑚𐑡𐑧𐑒𐑑, 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑿 𐑓𐑱𐑤 𐑑 𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑕 𐑬𐑑 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑦 𐑣𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑯𐑟, 𐑯 𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑐𐑼𐑕𐑿𐑑 𐑝 𐑞𐑧𐑥; 𐑨𐑟 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑓𐑦𐑤𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑔𐑷𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑢𐑹 𐑞 ·𐑰𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑯 𐑯𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑕𐑷 𐑸𐑥𐑦𐑟 𐑤𐑪𐑒𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑚𐑨𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑞 𐑒𐑤𐑬𐑛𐑟. 𐑞𐑳𐑕 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑯𐑹𐑔 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑲 𐑗𐑱𐑕𐑑 ·𐑤𐑩𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑔𐑩𐑯 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑯 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑴𐑤 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑮𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑵𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑚𐑮𐑲𐑑 𐑐𐑶𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑓𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑑 𐑥𐑰. 𐑯 𐑚𐑦𐑯𐑰𐑔 𐑞 𐑦𐑓𐑳𐑤𐑡𐑩𐑯𐑑 ·𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑸𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑕𐑒𐑲𐑟 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑚𐑹𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑞 ·𐑸𐑜𐑴-·𐑯𐑱𐑝𐑦𐑕, 𐑯 𐑡𐑶𐑯𐑛 𐑞 𐑗𐑱𐑕 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑦 ·𐑕𐑰𐑑𐑩𐑕 𐑓𐑸 𐑚𐑦𐑘𐑪𐑯𐑛 𐑞 𐑳𐑑𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑧𐑗 𐑝 ·𐑣𐑲𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑕 𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑓𐑤𐑲𐑦𐑙 ·𐑓𐑦𐑖.

𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑓𐑮𐑦𐑜𐑩𐑑'𐑕 𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑼𐑟 𐑓 𐑥𐑲 𐑚𐑮𐑲𐑛𐑩𐑤-𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑯 𐑓𐑨𐑖𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑟 𐑓 𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑟, 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑲 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑥𐑬𐑯𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑯 𐑤𐑰𐑐 𐑞 𐑑𐑪𐑐𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑒𐑲𐑟, 𐑑 𐑕𐑰 𐑢𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑞 𐑓𐑱𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑣𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑺 𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑮𐑾𐑤𐑦 𐑤𐑲 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑨𐑥𐑐𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑘𐑪𐑯𐑛 𐑥𐑲 𐑥𐑹𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑲𐑑!

·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 58. ·𐑚𐑮𐑦𐑑.

𐑕𐑑𐑽𐑦𐑙 𐑯𐑹𐑔-𐑰𐑕𐑑𐑢𐑼𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 ·𐑒𐑮𐑴𐑟𐑧𐑑𐑕, 𐑢𐑰 𐑓𐑧𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑝𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑥𐑧𐑛𐑴𐑟 𐑝 ·𐑚𐑮𐑦𐑑, 𐑞 𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑑, 𐑘𐑧𐑤𐑴 𐑕𐑳𐑚𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕, 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑞 ·𐑮𐑲𐑑 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑤𐑸𐑡𐑤𐑦 𐑓𐑰𐑛𐑟. 𐑓 𐑤𐑰𐑜𐑟 𐑯 𐑤𐑰𐑜𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑳𐑯𐑡𐑩𐑤𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑳𐑕, 𐑕𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑰 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑚𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑓𐑰𐑤𐑛𐑟 𐑝 𐑮𐑲𐑐 𐑯 𐑜𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑰𐑑.

𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑧𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑛𐑱, 𐑯𐑳𐑥𐑚𐑼𐑟 𐑝 ·𐑮𐑲𐑑 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑕𐑰𐑯, 𐑣𐑵, 𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑘𐑫𐑼 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑩𐑑𐑨𐑒 𐑝 𐑩 ·𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑼 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑴𐑐𐑩𐑯 𐑡𐑷𐑟 𐑕𐑤𐑳𐑜𐑦𐑖𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑢𐑨𐑥 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑞 ·𐑚𐑮𐑦𐑑, 𐑢𐑦𐑗, 𐑨𐑛𐑣𐑽𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑞 𐑓𐑮𐑦𐑯𐑡𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑲𐑚𐑼𐑟 𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑕 ·𐑝𐑩𐑯𐑰𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑚𐑤𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑥𐑬𐑞𐑟, 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑨𐑯𐑼 𐑕𐑧𐑐𐑼𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑱𐑐𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑤𐑦𐑐.

𐑨𐑟 𐑥𐑹𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑴𐑼𐑟, 𐑣𐑵 𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑕𐑤𐑴𐑤𐑦 𐑯 𐑕𐑰𐑞𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑩𐑛𐑝𐑭𐑯𐑕 𐑞𐑺 𐑕𐑲𐑞𐑟 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑞 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑢𐑧𐑑 𐑜𐑮𐑭𐑕 𐑝 𐑥𐑸𐑖𐑦 𐑥𐑰𐑛𐑟; 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑕𐑴 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑥𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑟 𐑕𐑢𐑨𐑥, 𐑥𐑱𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡, 𐑜𐑮𐑭𐑕𐑦, 𐑒𐑳𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑬𐑯𐑛; 𐑯 𐑤𐑰𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑦𐑣𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑕𐑢𐑭𐑔𐑕 𐑝 𐑚𐑤𐑵 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑘𐑧𐑤𐑴 𐑕𐑰.*

*𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑐𐑸𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑰 𐑯𐑴𐑯 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 “·𐑚𐑮𐑩𐑟𐑦𐑤 ·𐑚𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑕” 𐑛𐑳𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑚𐑺 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑯𐑱𐑥 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 ·𐑚𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑕 𐑝 ·𐑯𐑿𐑓𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑛𐑵, 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑪𐑟 𐑝 𐑞𐑺 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑖𐑨𐑤𐑴𐑟 𐑯 𐑕𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑞𐑺, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑪𐑟 𐑝 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑸𐑒𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑥𐑧𐑛𐑴-𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩𐑐𐑽𐑩𐑯𐑕, 𐑒𐑷𐑟𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑝𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑛𐑮𐑦𐑓𐑑𐑕 𐑝 ·𐑚𐑮𐑦𐑑 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑿𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑓𐑤𐑴𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑤𐑨𐑑𐑦𐑑𐑿𐑛𐑟, 𐑢𐑺 𐑞 ·𐑮𐑲𐑑 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑦𐑟 𐑪𐑓𐑩𐑯 𐑗𐑱𐑕𐑑.

𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑞 𐑕𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑞𐑱 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑨𐑟 𐑞𐑱 𐑐𐑸𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑞 ·𐑚𐑮𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑨𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑲𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑥𐑴𐑼𐑟. 𐑕𐑰𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑-𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑟, 𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑞𐑱 𐑐𐑷𐑟𐑛 𐑯 𐑢𐑻 𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑼𐑦 𐑓 𐑩 𐑢𐑲𐑤, 𐑞𐑺 𐑝𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑒 𐑓𐑹𐑥𐑟 𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑑 𐑥𐑹 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑤𐑲𐑓𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑥𐑨𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑝 𐑮𐑪𐑒 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑧𐑯𐑦𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑧𐑤𐑕. 𐑯 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑒𐑳𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑟 𐑝 ·𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑾, 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑼 𐑨𐑑 𐑩 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑐𐑭𐑕 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑯𐑟 𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑚𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑓𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑 𐑯𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑕𐑳𐑗, 𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑓 𐑚𐑺, 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑝𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑶𐑤; 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑕𐑴, 𐑪𐑓𐑩𐑯, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑣𐑵 𐑓 𐑞 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑚𐑦𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑟 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑖𐑰𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑤𐑩𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑔𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑰. 𐑯 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑩𐑜𐑯𐑲𐑟𐑛 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑, 𐑞𐑺 𐑦𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑕 𐑥𐑨𐑜𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑿𐑛 𐑮𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑣𐑸𐑛 𐑮𐑾𐑤𐑦 𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑰𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑚𐑳𐑤𐑒𐑦 𐑥𐑨𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑝 𐑴𐑝𐑼𐑜𐑮𐑴𐑔 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑐𐑪𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑰 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑑, 𐑦𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑐𐑸𐑑𐑕, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑕𐑹𐑑 𐑝 𐑤𐑲𐑓 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑦𐑝𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑛𐑪𐑜 𐑹 𐑩 𐑣𐑹𐑕.

𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑰𐑛, 𐑦𐑯 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑕, 𐑿 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑣𐑸𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑦𐑜𐑸𐑛 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑒𐑮𐑰𐑗𐑼𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑛𐑰𐑐 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑓𐑰𐑤𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑿 𐑛𐑵 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑖𐑹. 𐑓 𐑞𐑴 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑯𐑨𐑗𐑼𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑕 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑥𐑱𐑯𐑑𐑱𐑯𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑒𐑮𐑰𐑗𐑼𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑸 𐑝 𐑞𐑺 𐑒𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑰; 𐑯 𐑞𐑴 𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑚𐑮𐑷𐑛 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑝𐑿 𐑝 𐑞 𐑔𐑦𐑙, 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑥𐑱 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑢𐑧𐑤 𐑚𐑰; 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑤𐑑𐑦𐑟, 𐑢𐑺, 𐑓 𐑦𐑜𐑟𐑭𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑤, 𐑛𐑳𐑟 𐑞 𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑓𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑖 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑓𐑦𐑖 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑩𐑟𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑼𐑟 𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑕 𐑒𐑲𐑯𐑛𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑛𐑪𐑜? 𐑞 𐑩𐑒𐑻𐑕𐑩𐑛 𐑖𐑸𐑒 𐑩𐑤𐑴𐑯 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑡𐑦𐑯𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑒 𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑑 𐑚𐑺 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑨𐑮𐑩𐑑𐑦𐑝 𐑩𐑯𐑨𐑤𐑩𐑡𐑦 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥.

𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞𐑴, 𐑑 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑤, 𐑞 𐑯𐑱𐑑𐑦𐑝 𐑦𐑯𐑣𐑨𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑰𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑮𐑦𐑜𐑸𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑦𐑥𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑳𐑯𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑳𐑯𐑕𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑤 𐑯 𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑙; 𐑞𐑴 𐑢𐑰 𐑯𐑴 𐑞 𐑕𐑰 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑩𐑯 𐑧𐑝𐑼𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑑𐑧𐑮𐑩 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑪𐑜𐑯𐑰𐑑𐑩, 𐑕𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑 ·𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑳𐑥𐑚𐑩𐑕 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑛 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑯𐑳𐑥𐑚𐑼𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑳𐑯𐑯𐑴𐑯 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛𐑟 𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑳𐑝𐑼 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑕𐑵𐑐𐑼𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯; 𐑞𐑴, 𐑚𐑲 𐑝𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑪𐑛𐑟, 𐑞 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑑𐑼𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑒 𐑝 𐑷𐑤 𐑥𐑹𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑛𐑦𐑟𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑦𐑥𐑩𐑥𐑹𐑾𐑤𐑦 𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑷𐑤𐑩𐑯 𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑟 𐑯 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑛𐑟 𐑝 𐑔𐑬𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑝 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑣𐑵 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑜𐑪𐑯 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼𐑟; 𐑞𐑴 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑩 𐑥𐑴𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑'𐑕 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑼𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑑𐑰𐑗, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑬𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑚𐑱𐑚𐑦 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑥𐑱 𐑚𐑮𐑨𐑜 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑲𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑯 𐑕𐑒𐑦𐑤, 𐑯 𐑣𐑬𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑥𐑳𐑗, 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑓𐑤𐑨𐑑𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑿𐑗𐑼, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑲𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑯 𐑕𐑒𐑦𐑤 𐑥𐑱 𐑷𐑜𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑; 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑓 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑯 𐑓 𐑧𐑝𐑼, 𐑑 𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑨𐑒 𐑝 𐑛𐑵𐑥, 𐑞 𐑕𐑰 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑳𐑤𐑑 𐑯 𐑥𐑻𐑛𐑼 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑯 𐑐𐑳𐑤𐑝𐑼𐑲𐑟 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑑𐑤𐑾𐑕𐑑, 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑓𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑦𐑜𐑩𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑥𐑱𐑒; 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼𐑞𐑩𐑤𐑧𐑕, 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑿𐑩𐑤 𐑮𐑧𐑐𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟, 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑤𐑪𐑕𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑓𐑫𐑤 𐑷𐑓𐑩𐑤𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑰 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑨𐑚𐑼𐑦𐑡𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑪𐑙𐑟 𐑑 𐑦𐑑.

𐑞 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑴𐑑 𐑢𐑰 𐑮𐑰𐑛 𐑝, 𐑓𐑤𐑴𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑪𐑯 𐑩𐑯 𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 ·𐑐𐑹𐑗𐑩𐑜𐑰𐑟 𐑝𐑧𐑯𐑡𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑢𐑧𐑤𐑥𐑛 𐑩 𐑣𐑴𐑤 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑 𐑤𐑰𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑴 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑨𐑟 𐑩 𐑢𐑦𐑛𐑴. 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑮𐑴𐑤𐑟 𐑯𐑬; 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑶𐑛 𐑞 𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑑 𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑕 𐑝 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑘𐑽. 𐑘𐑱, 𐑓𐑵𐑤𐑦𐑖 𐑥𐑹𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑟, ·𐑯𐑴𐑩'𐑟 𐑓𐑤𐑳𐑛 𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑕𐑲𐑛𐑩𐑛; 𐑑𐑵 𐑔𐑻𐑛𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑓𐑺 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛 𐑦𐑑 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑒𐑳𐑝𐑼𐑟.

𐑢𐑺𐑦𐑯 𐑛𐑦𐑓𐑼 𐑞 𐑕𐑰 𐑯 𐑞 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑩 𐑥𐑦𐑮𐑩𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑩 𐑥𐑦𐑮𐑩𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑳𐑞𐑼? 𐑐𐑮𐑰𐑑𐑼𐑯𐑨𐑗𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑑𐑧𐑮𐑼𐑟 𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑣𐑰𐑚𐑮𐑵𐑟, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑞 𐑓𐑰𐑑 𐑝 ·𐑒𐑹𐑩 𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑦 𐑞 𐑤𐑲𐑝 𐑜𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑴𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑯 𐑕𐑢𐑪𐑤𐑴𐑛 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑳𐑐 𐑓 𐑧𐑝𐑼; 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑩 𐑥𐑪𐑛𐑼𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑯 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑕𐑧𐑑𐑕, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑲𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑥𐑨𐑯𐑼 𐑞 𐑤𐑲𐑝 𐑕𐑰 𐑕𐑢𐑪𐑤𐑴𐑟 𐑳𐑐 𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑕 𐑯 𐑒𐑮𐑵𐑟.

𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑟 𐑞 𐑕𐑰 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩 𐑓𐑴 𐑑 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑣𐑵 𐑦𐑟 𐑩𐑯 𐑱𐑤𐑾𐑯 𐑑 𐑦𐑑, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑷𐑤𐑕𐑴 𐑩 𐑓𐑰𐑯𐑛 𐑑 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑴𐑯 𐑪𐑓-𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑙; 𐑢𐑻𐑕 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑻𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑣𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑵 𐑥𐑻𐑛𐑼𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑴𐑯 𐑜𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑕; 𐑕𐑐𐑺𐑦𐑙 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑰𐑗𐑼𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑦𐑑𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑣𐑨𐑔 𐑕𐑐𐑷𐑯𐑛. 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑕𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑡 𐑑𐑲𐑜𐑮𐑩𐑕 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑑𐑪𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑡𐑳𐑙𐑜𐑩𐑤 𐑴𐑝𐑼𐑤𐑱𐑟 𐑣𐑻 𐑴𐑯 𐑒𐑳𐑚𐑟, 𐑕𐑴 𐑞 𐑕𐑰 𐑛𐑨𐑖𐑩𐑟 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑞 𐑥𐑲𐑑𐑾𐑕𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑞 𐑮𐑪𐑒𐑕, 𐑯 𐑤𐑰𐑝𐑟 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑞𐑺 𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑤𐑦𐑑 𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑕 𐑝 𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑕. 𐑯𐑴 𐑥𐑻𐑕𐑦, 𐑯𐑴 𐑐𐑬𐑼 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑴𐑯 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑴𐑤𐑟 𐑦𐑑. 𐑐𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑯 𐑕𐑯𐑹𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑥𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑨𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑑𐑰𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑤𐑪𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑮𐑲𐑛𐑼, 𐑞 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑴𐑝𐑼𐑮𐑳𐑯𐑟 𐑞 𐑜𐑤𐑴𐑚.

𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑼 𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑰; 𐑣𐑬 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑛𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑒𐑮𐑰𐑗𐑼𐑟 𐑜𐑤𐑲𐑛 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼, 𐑳𐑯𐑩𐑐𐑨𐑮𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑓 𐑞 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑐𐑸𐑑, 𐑯 𐑑𐑮𐑧𐑗𐑼𐑩𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑣𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑯 𐑚𐑦𐑯𐑰𐑔 𐑞 𐑤𐑳𐑝𐑤𐑾𐑕𐑑 𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑨𐑠𐑼. 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑼 𐑷𐑤𐑕𐑴 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑖 𐑚𐑮𐑦𐑤𐑾𐑯𐑕 𐑯 𐑚𐑿𐑑𐑦 𐑝 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑝 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑹𐑕𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑚𐑟, 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑛𐑱𐑯𐑑𐑦 𐑦𐑥𐑚𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑖𐑑 𐑖𐑱𐑐 𐑝 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑖𐑰𐑟 𐑝 𐑖𐑸𐑒𐑕. 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑼, 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑕 𐑥𐑹, 𐑞 𐑿𐑯𐑦𐑝𐑻𐑕𐑩𐑤 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑟𐑩𐑥 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑰; 𐑷𐑤 𐑣𐑵𐑟 𐑒𐑮𐑰𐑗𐑼𐑟 𐑐𐑮𐑱 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑰𐑗 𐑳𐑞𐑼, 𐑒𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑦𐑙 𐑪𐑯 𐑦𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑹 𐑕𐑦𐑯𐑕 𐑞 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛 𐑚𐑦𐑜𐑨𐑯.

𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑼 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑦𐑕; 𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑑𐑻𐑯 𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑯, 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤, 𐑯 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑛𐑴𐑕𐑲𐑤 𐑻𐑔; 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑼 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑚𐑴𐑔, 𐑞 𐑕𐑰 𐑯 𐑞 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛; 𐑯 𐑛𐑵 𐑿 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑓𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑩 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡 𐑩𐑯𐑨𐑤𐑩𐑡𐑦 𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑘𐑹𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓? 𐑓 𐑨𐑟 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑩𐑐𐑷𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑕𐑼𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑞 𐑝𐑻𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛, 𐑕𐑴 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑴𐑤 𐑝 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑤𐑲𐑟 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑤𐑼 ·𐑑𐑭𐑣𐑰𐑑𐑦, 𐑓𐑫𐑤 𐑝 𐑐𐑰𐑕 𐑯 𐑡𐑶, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑣𐑪𐑮𐑼𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑣𐑭𐑓 𐑯𐑴𐑯 𐑤𐑲𐑓. 𐑜𐑪𐑛 𐑒𐑰𐑐 𐑞𐑰! 𐑐𐑫𐑖 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑪𐑓 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑲𐑤, 𐑞𐑬 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑻𐑯!

·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 59. 𐑕𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑛.

𐑕𐑤𐑴𐑤𐑦 𐑢𐑱𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑞 𐑥𐑧𐑛𐑴𐑟 𐑝 ·𐑚𐑮𐑦𐑑, 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑛 𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑻 𐑢𐑱 𐑯𐑹𐑔-𐑰𐑕𐑑𐑢𐑼𐑛 𐑑𐑩𐑢𐑹𐑛𐑟 𐑞 𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑝 ·𐑡𐑭𐑝𐑩; 𐑩 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑺 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑻 𐑒𐑰𐑤, 𐑕𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑼𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑼𐑧𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑣𐑻 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑑𐑷𐑤 𐑑𐑱𐑐𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑕 𐑥𐑲𐑤𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑢𐑱𐑝𐑛 𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑨𐑙𐑜𐑢𐑦𐑛 𐑚𐑮𐑰𐑟, 𐑨𐑟 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑥𐑲𐑤𐑛 𐑐𐑭𐑥𐑟 𐑪𐑯 𐑩 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑯. 𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤, 𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑲𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑦𐑤𐑝𐑼𐑦 𐑯𐑲𐑑, 𐑞 𐑤𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦, 𐑩𐑤𐑫𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑡𐑧𐑑 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑚𐑰 𐑕𐑰𐑯.

𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑕𐑐𐑨𐑮𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑚𐑤𐑵 𐑥𐑹𐑯𐑦𐑙, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑩 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑰𐑑𐑼𐑯𐑨𐑗𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑛 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑞 𐑕𐑰, 𐑣𐑬𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑳𐑯𐑩𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑜𐑯𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑒𐑭𐑥; 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑞 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑚𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑖𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑯-𐑜𐑤𐑱𐑛 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼𐑟 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑩 𐑜𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑩𐑯 𐑓𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑼 𐑤𐑱𐑛 𐑩𐑒𐑮𐑪𐑕 𐑞𐑧𐑥, 𐑦𐑯𐑡𐑶𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑕𐑰𐑒𐑮𐑩𐑕𐑦; 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑤𐑦𐑐𐑼𐑛 𐑢𐑱𐑝𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑼𐑛 𐑑𐑩𐑜𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑨𐑟 𐑞𐑱 𐑕𐑪𐑓𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑨𐑯 𐑪𐑯; 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑣𐑳𐑖 𐑝 𐑞 𐑝𐑦𐑟𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑓𐑽 𐑩 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡 𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑼 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑰𐑯 𐑚𐑲 ·𐑛𐑨𐑜𐑵 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑥𐑱𐑯-𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑-𐑣𐑧𐑛.

𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕, 𐑩 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑥𐑨𐑕 𐑤𐑱𐑟𐑦𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑴𐑟, 𐑯 𐑮𐑲𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑲𐑼 𐑯 𐑣𐑲𐑼, 𐑯 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑨𐑙𐑜𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑑𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑨𐑠𐑼, 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑜𐑤𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑬𐑼 𐑐𐑮𐑬 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑕𐑯𐑴-𐑕𐑤𐑲𐑛, 𐑯𐑿 𐑕𐑤𐑦𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑤𐑟. 𐑞𐑳𐑕 𐑜𐑤𐑦𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑓 𐑩 𐑥𐑴𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑, 𐑨𐑟 𐑕𐑤𐑴𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑕𐑲𐑛𐑩𐑛, 𐑯 𐑕𐑨𐑙𐑒. 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑕 𐑥𐑹 𐑼𐑴𐑟, 𐑯 𐑕𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑜𐑤𐑰𐑥𐑛. 𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑩 𐑢𐑱𐑤; 𐑯 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑞𐑦𐑕 ·𐑥𐑪𐑚𐑦 ·𐑛𐑦𐑒? 𐑔𐑷𐑑 ·𐑛𐑨𐑜𐑵. 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑥 𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑛𐑬𐑯, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑪𐑯 𐑮𐑰-𐑩𐑐𐑽𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑕 𐑥𐑹, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤𐑧𐑑𐑴-𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑒𐑮𐑲 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑛, 𐑞 𐑯𐑰𐑜𐑮𐑴 𐑘𐑧𐑤𐑛 𐑬𐑑—“𐑞𐑺! 𐑞𐑺 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯! 𐑞𐑺 𐑖𐑰 𐑚𐑮𐑰𐑗𐑩𐑟! 𐑮𐑲𐑑 𐑩𐑣𐑧𐑛! 𐑞 ·𐑢𐑲𐑑 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑞 ·𐑢𐑲𐑑 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤!”

𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕, 𐑞 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑮𐑳𐑖𐑑 𐑑 𐑞 𐑘𐑸𐑛-𐑸𐑥𐑟, 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑢𐑹𐑥𐑦𐑙-𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑞 𐑚𐑰𐑟 𐑮𐑳𐑖 𐑑 𐑞 𐑚𐑬𐑟. 𐑚𐑺-𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑤𐑑𐑮𐑦 𐑕𐑳𐑯, ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑕𐑑𐑫𐑛 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑑, 𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑐𐑫𐑖𐑑 𐑓𐑸 𐑚𐑦𐑣𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑹𐑛𐑼𐑟 𐑑 𐑞 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑥𐑟𐑥𐑩𐑯, 𐑒𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑰𐑜𐑼 𐑜𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑛𐑦𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑓𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑬𐑑𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑧𐑗𐑑 𐑥𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑸𐑥 𐑝 ·𐑛𐑨𐑜𐑵.

𐑢𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑞 𐑓𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑯 𐑕𐑪𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑼𐑦 𐑡𐑧𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑜𐑮𐑨𐑡𐑵𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑢𐑻𐑒𐑑 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚, 𐑕𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑬 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑺𐑛 𐑑 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑧𐑒𐑑 𐑞 𐑲𐑛𐑾𐑟 𐑝 𐑥𐑲𐑤𐑛𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑯 𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑴𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑲𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑐𐑼𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑼 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑣𐑰 𐑐𐑼𐑕𐑿𐑛; 𐑣𐑬𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑪𐑟, 𐑹 𐑢𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑰𐑜𐑼𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥; 𐑢𐑦𐑗𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑢𐑱 𐑦𐑑 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑯, 𐑯𐑴 𐑕𐑵𐑯𐑼 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑣𐑰 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑼𐑕𐑰𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑥𐑨𐑕, 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑒 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑣𐑰 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑜𐑱𐑝 𐑹𐑛𐑼𐑟 𐑓 𐑤𐑴𐑼𐑦𐑙.

𐑞 𐑓𐑹 𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕 𐑢𐑻 𐑕𐑵𐑯 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼; ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚'𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑩𐑛𐑝𐑭𐑯𐑕, 𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑕𐑢𐑦𐑓𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑫𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑑𐑩𐑢𐑹𐑛𐑟 𐑞𐑺 𐑐𐑮𐑱. 𐑕𐑵𐑯 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑛𐑬𐑯, 𐑯 𐑢𐑲𐑤, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑹𐑟 𐑕𐑩𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛, 𐑢𐑰 𐑢𐑻 𐑩𐑢𐑱𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑮𐑰𐑩𐑐𐑽𐑩𐑯𐑕, 𐑤𐑴! 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑕𐑐𐑪𐑑 𐑢𐑺 𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑨𐑙𐑒, 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑕 𐑥𐑹 𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑤𐑴𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑴𐑟. 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑓𐑼𐑜𐑧𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑓 𐑞 𐑥𐑴𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑔𐑷𐑑𐑕 𐑝 ·𐑥𐑪𐑚𐑦 ·𐑛𐑦𐑒, 𐑢𐑰 𐑯𐑬 𐑜𐑱𐑟𐑛 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑕 𐑓𐑦𐑯𐑪𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑪𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑞 𐑕𐑰𐑒𐑮𐑩𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑞𐑼𐑑𐑵 𐑮𐑦𐑝𐑰𐑤𐑛 𐑑 𐑥𐑨𐑯𐑒𐑲𐑯𐑛. 𐑩 𐑝𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑐𐑳𐑤𐑐𐑦 𐑥𐑨𐑕, 𐑓𐑻𐑤𐑪𐑙𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑤𐑧𐑙𐑔 𐑯 𐑚𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑔, 𐑝 𐑩 𐑜𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑒𐑮𐑰𐑥-𐑒𐑳𐑤𐑼, 𐑤𐑱 𐑓𐑤𐑴𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼, 𐑦𐑯𐑿𐑥𐑼𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑸𐑥𐑟 𐑮𐑱𐑛𐑦𐑱𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑼, 𐑯 𐑒𐑻𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑯 𐑑𐑢𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑯𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑝 𐑨𐑯𐑩𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑟, 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑓 𐑚𐑤𐑲𐑯𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑑 𐑒𐑤𐑳𐑗 𐑨𐑑 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑪𐑚𐑡𐑧𐑒𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑦𐑯 𐑮𐑰𐑗. 𐑯𐑴 𐑐𐑼𐑕𐑧𐑐𐑑𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑓𐑱𐑕 𐑹 𐑓𐑮𐑳𐑯𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑦𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝; 𐑯𐑴 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑑𐑴𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑲𐑞𐑼 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑕𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑹 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑑; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑳𐑯𐑡𐑩𐑤𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑞𐑺 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑴𐑟, 𐑩𐑯 𐑳𐑯𐑻𐑔𐑤𐑦, 𐑓𐑹𐑥𐑤𐑩𐑕, 𐑗𐑭𐑯𐑕-𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑨𐑐𐑼𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑤𐑲𐑓.

𐑨𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑤𐑴 𐑕𐑳𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑤𐑴𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑩𐑐𐑽𐑛 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯, ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑜𐑱𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑨𐑡𐑦𐑑𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼𐑟 𐑢𐑺 𐑦𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑕𐑳𐑙𐑒, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑢𐑲𐑤𐑛 𐑝𐑶𐑕 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑒𐑤𐑱𐑥𐑛—“𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑮𐑭𐑞𐑼 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑲 𐑕𐑰𐑯 ·𐑥𐑪𐑚𐑦 ·𐑛𐑦𐑒 𐑯 𐑓𐑷𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑕𐑰𐑯 𐑞𐑰, 𐑞𐑬 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑜𐑴𐑕𐑑!”

“𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑦𐑑, ·𐑕𐑻?” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 ·𐑓𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑒.

“𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑤𐑲𐑝 𐑕𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑛, 𐑢𐑦𐑗, 𐑞𐑱 𐑕𐑱, 𐑓𐑿 𐑢𐑱𐑤-𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑕 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑚𐑦𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑛, 𐑯 𐑮𐑩𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑛 𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑐𐑹𐑑𐑕 𐑑 𐑑𐑧𐑤 𐑝 𐑦𐑑.”

𐑚𐑳𐑑 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑯𐑳𐑔𐑦𐑙; 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑴𐑑, 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑛 𐑚𐑨𐑒 𐑑 𐑞 𐑝𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑤; 𐑞 𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑕𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑓𐑪𐑤𐑴𐑦𐑙.

𐑢𐑪𐑑𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑕𐑵𐑐𐑼𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑕𐑲𐑑 𐑝 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑪𐑚𐑡𐑧𐑒𐑑, 𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑩 𐑜𐑤𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑕 𐑝 𐑦𐑑 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑴 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑳𐑯𐑿𐑠𐑵𐑩𐑤, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑻𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑕 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑜𐑪𐑯 𐑓𐑸 𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑐𐑹𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑕𐑯𐑩𐑕. 𐑕𐑴 𐑮𐑺𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑛, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑴 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑝 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑺 𐑦𐑑 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑞 𐑤𐑸𐑡𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑥𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯, 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑓𐑿 𐑝 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑝𐑱𐑜 𐑲𐑛𐑾𐑟 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑑𐑮𐑵 𐑯𐑱𐑗𐑼 𐑯 𐑓𐑹𐑥; 𐑯𐑪𐑑𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙, 𐑞𐑱 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑰𐑝 𐑦𐑑 𐑑 𐑓𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑖 𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑓𐑵𐑛. 𐑓 𐑞𐑴 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑖𐑰𐑟 𐑝 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑓𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑞𐑺 𐑓𐑵𐑛 𐑩𐑚𐑳𐑝 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼, 𐑯 𐑥𐑱 𐑚𐑰 𐑕𐑰𐑯 𐑚𐑲 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑨𐑒𐑑 𐑝 𐑓𐑰𐑛𐑦𐑙, 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥𐑩𐑕𐑧𐑑𐑦 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑩𐑚𐑑𐑱𐑯𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑴𐑤 𐑓𐑵𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑳𐑯𐑯𐑴𐑯 𐑟𐑴𐑯𐑟 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑴 𐑞 𐑕𐑻𐑓𐑦𐑕; 𐑯 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑲 𐑦𐑯𐑓𐑼𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑑𐑧𐑤 𐑝 𐑢𐑪𐑑, 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑲𐑕𐑤𐑦, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑓𐑵𐑛 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑕. 𐑨𐑑 𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑒𐑤𐑴𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑼𐑕𐑿𐑛, 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑜𐑹𐑡 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑸 𐑕𐑩𐑐𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑞 𐑛𐑦𐑑𐑨𐑗𐑑 𐑸𐑥𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑛; 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑝 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑞𐑳𐑕 𐑦𐑜𐑟𐑦𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑰𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑑𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑦 𐑯 𐑔𐑻𐑑𐑦 𐑓𐑰𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑤𐑧𐑙𐑔. 𐑞𐑱 𐑓𐑨𐑯𐑕𐑦 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑥𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑼 𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑸𐑥𐑟 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑪𐑙𐑛 𐑹𐑛𐑦𐑯𐑺𐑦𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑤𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑚𐑲 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑑 𐑞 𐑚𐑧𐑛 𐑝 𐑞 𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯; 𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑳𐑯𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑖𐑰𐑟, 𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑩𐑐𐑤𐑲𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑑𐑰𐑔 𐑦𐑯 𐑹𐑛𐑼 𐑑 𐑩𐑑𐑨𐑒 𐑯 𐑑𐑺 𐑦𐑑.

𐑞𐑺 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑟 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑜𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑑 𐑦𐑥𐑨𐑡𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 ·𐑒𐑮𐑭𐑒𐑧𐑯 𐑝 ·𐑚𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑐 ·𐑐𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑪𐑐𐑐𐑪𐑛𐑩𐑯 𐑥𐑱 𐑳𐑤𐑑𐑦𐑥𐑩𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑪𐑤𐑝 𐑦𐑑𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 ·𐑕𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑛. 𐑞 𐑥𐑨𐑯𐑼 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑞 ·𐑚𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑐 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑚𐑟 𐑦𐑑, 𐑨𐑟 𐑷𐑤𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑩𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑲𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑯 𐑕𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑦𐑙, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑐𐑼𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑼𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑯𐑼𐑱𐑑𐑕, 𐑦𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑞 𐑑𐑵 𐑒𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑪𐑯𐑛. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑩𐑚𐑱𐑑𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑧𐑕𐑦𐑕𐑺𐑦 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑 𐑑 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑚𐑳𐑤𐑒 𐑣𐑰 𐑩𐑕𐑲𐑯𐑟 𐑦𐑑.

𐑚𐑲 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑯𐑨𐑗𐑼𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑕 𐑣𐑵 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑝𐑱𐑜𐑤𐑦 𐑣𐑻𐑛 𐑮𐑵𐑥𐑼𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑽𐑾𐑕 𐑒𐑮𐑰𐑗𐑼, 𐑣𐑽 𐑕𐑐𐑴𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑝, 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑤𐑵𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑞 𐑒𐑤𐑭𐑕 𐑝 𐑒𐑳𐑑𐑩𐑤-𐑓𐑦𐑖, 𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑗, 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑰𐑛, 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑕 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑕𐑰𐑥 𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑪𐑙, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 ·𐑱𐑯𐑨𐑒 𐑝 𐑞 𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑚.

·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 60. 𐑞 ·𐑤𐑲𐑯.

𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑮𐑧𐑓𐑼𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑑 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑰𐑯 𐑖𐑹𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑚𐑛, 𐑨𐑟 𐑢𐑧𐑤 𐑨𐑟 𐑓 𐑞 𐑚𐑧𐑑𐑼 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑷𐑤 𐑕𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑤𐑼 𐑕𐑰𐑯𐑟 𐑧𐑤𐑕𐑢𐑺 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛, 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑣𐑽 𐑑 𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑒 𐑝 𐑞 𐑥𐑨𐑡𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤, 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑣𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑱𐑤-𐑤𐑲𐑯.

𐑞 𐑤𐑲𐑯 𐑼𐑦𐑡𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑿𐑟𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑼𐑦 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑚𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑧𐑥𐑐, 𐑕𐑤𐑲𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑝𐑱𐑐𐑼𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑑𐑸, 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑜𐑯𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑦𐑑, 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑒𐑱𐑕 𐑝 𐑹𐑛𐑦𐑯𐑼𐑦 𐑮𐑴𐑐𐑕; 𐑓 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑑𐑸, 𐑨𐑟 𐑹𐑛𐑦𐑯𐑺𐑦𐑤𐑦 𐑿𐑟𐑛, 𐑥𐑱𐑒𐑕 𐑞 𐑣𐑧𐑥𐑐 𐑥𐑹 𐑐𐑤𐑲𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑑 𐑞 𐑮𐑴𐑐-𐑥𐑱𐑒𐑼, 𐑯 𐑷𐑤𐑕𐑴 𐑮𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑟 𐑞 𐑮𐑴𐑐 𐑦𐑑𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑥𐑹 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑝𐑰𐑯𐑾𐑯𐑑 𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑼 𐑓 𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑿𐑕; 𐑘𐑧𐑑, 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑞 𐑹𐑛𐑦𐑯𐑼𐑦 𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑑𐑵 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑓𐑩𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤-𐑤𐑲𐑯 𐑓 𐑞 𐑒𐑤𐑴𐑕 𐑒𐑶𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑦𐑑 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑡𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑛; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑸 𐑚𐑦𐑜𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑤𐑻𐑯, 𐑑𐑸 𐑦𐑯 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑚𐑲 𐑯𐑴 𐑥𐑰𐑯𐑟 𐑨𐑛𐑟 𐑑 𐑞 𐑮𐑴𐑐'𐑕 𐑛𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑩𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑹 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑧𐑙𐑔, 𐑣𐑬𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑦𐑑 𐑥𐑱 𐑜𐑦𐑝 𐑦𐑑 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑨𐑒𐑑𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑯 𐑜𐑤𐑪𐑕.

𐑝 𐑤𐑱𐑑 𐑘𐑽𐑟 𐑞 ·𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑤𐑩 𐑮𐑴𐑐 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑩𐑥𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑼𐑦 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑲𐑼𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑵𐑐𐑼𐑕𐑰𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑣𐑧𐑥𐑐 𐑨𐑟 𐑩 𐑥𐑩𐑑𐑽𐑾𐑤 𐑓 𐑢𐑱𐑤-𐑤𐑲𐑯𐑟; 𐑓, 𐑞𐑴 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑴 𐑛𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑨𐑟 𐑣𐑧𐑥𐑐, 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑪𐑙𐑜𐑼, 𐑯 𐑓𐑸 𐑥𐑹 𐑕𐑪𐑓𐑑 𐑯 𐑦𐑤𐑨𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑒; 𐑯 𐑲 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑨𐑛 (𐑕𐑦𐑯𐑕 𐑞𐑺 𐑦𐑟 𐑩𐑯 𐑧𐑕𐑔𐑧𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑟), 𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑥𐑹 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑕𐑩𐑥 𐑯 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑, 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑣𐑧𐑥𐑐. 𐑣𐑧𐑥𐑐 𐑦𐑟 𐑩 𐑛𐑳𐑕𐑒𐑦, 𐑛𐑸𐑒 𐑓𐑧𐑤𐑴, 𐑩 𐑕𐑹𐑑 𐑝 ·𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑾𐑯; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 ·𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑤𐑩 𐑦𐑟 𐑨𐑟 𐑩 𐑜𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑩𐑯-𐑣𐑺𐑛 ·𐑕𐑻𐑒𐑨𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛.

𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤-𐑤𐑲𐑯 𐑦𐑟 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑑𐑵-𐑔𐑻𐑛𐑟 𐑝 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑗 𐑦𐑯 𐑔𐑦𐑒𐑯𐑩𐑕. 𐑨𐑑 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑲𐑑, 𐑿 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒 𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑴 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑪𐑙 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑮𐑾𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑟. 𐑚𐑲 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑯 𐑓𐑦𐑓𐑑𐑦 𐑘𐑸𐑯𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑰𐑗 𐑕𐑩𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑩 𐑢𐑱𐑑 𐑝 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑛 𐑯 𐑑𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑦 𐑐𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑟; 𐑕𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑣𐑴𐑤 𐑮𐑴𐑐 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑚𐑺 𐑩 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯 𐑯𐑽𐑤𐑦 𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑩𐑤 𐑑 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑑𐑳𐑯𐑟. 𐑦𐑯 𐑤𐑧𐑙𐑔, 𐑞 𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 𐑢𐑱𐑤-𐑤𐑲𐑯 𐑥𐑧𐑠𐑼𐑟 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑑𐑵 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑛 𐑓𐑨𐑞𐑩𐑥𐑟. 𐑑𐑩𐑢𐑹𐑛𐑟 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑻𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑐𐑲𐑮𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑶𐑤𐑛 𐑩𐑢𐑱 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑑𐑳𐑚, 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑞 𐑢𐑻𐑥-𐑐𐑲𐑐 𐑝 𐑩 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑞𐑴, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑕𐑴 𐑨𐑟 𐑑 𐑓𐑹𐑥 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛, 𐑗𐑰𐑟-𐑖𐑱𐑐𐑑 𐑥𐑨𐑕 𐑝 𐑛𐑧𐑯𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑧𐑛𐑩𐑛 “𐑖𐑰𐑝𐑟,” 𐑹 𐑤𐑱𐑼𐑟 𐑝 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑒 𐑕𐑐𐑲𐑮𐑩𐑤𐑲𐑟𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟, 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑣𐑪𐑤𐑴 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞 “𐑣𐑸𐑑,” 𐑹 𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑑 𐑝𐑻𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑑𐑿𐑚 𐑓𐑹𐑥𐑛 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑨𐑒𐑕𐑦𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑗𐑰𐑟. 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑤𐑰𐑕𐑑 𐑑𐑨𐑙𐑜𐑩𐑤 𐑹 𐑒𐑦𐑙𐑒 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑒𐑶𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑫𐑛, 𐑦𐑯 𐑮𐑳𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑬𐑑, 𐑦𐑯𐑓𐑨𐑤𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦'𐑟 𐑸𐑥, 𐑤𐑧𐑜, 𐑹 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑲𐑼 𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦 𐑪𐑓, 𐑞 𐑳𐑑𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑷𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑟 𐑿𐑟𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑤𐑲𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑑𐑳𐑚. 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑽𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑿𐑥 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑲𐑼 𐑥𐑹𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑚𐑦𐑟𐑯𐑩𐑕, 𐑒𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑤𐑲𐑯 𐑣𐑲 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑓𐑑 𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑮𐑰𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑑 𐑛𐑬𐑯𐑢𐑼𐑛𐑟 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑩 𐑚𐑤𐑪𐑒 𐑑𐑩𐑢𐑹𐑛𐑟 𐑞 𐑑𐑳𐑚, 𐑕𐑴 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑨𐑒𐑑 𐑝 𐑒𐑶𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑰 𐑦𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑷𐑤 𐑐𐑪𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑮𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑯 𐑑𐑢𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑕.

𐑦𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑤𐑦𐑖 𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕 𐑑𐑵 𐑑𐑳𐑚𐑟 𐑸 𐑿𐑟𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑛 𐑝 𐑢𐑳𐑯; 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑤𐑲𐑯 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑿𐑩𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑶𐑤𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑚𐑴𐑔 𐑑𐑳𐑚𐑟. 𐑞𐑺 𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑩𐑛𐑝𐑭𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑡 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕; 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑪𐑟 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑑𐑢𐑦𐑯-𐑑𐑳𐑚𐑟 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑴 𐑕𐑥𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑱 𐑓𐑦𐑑 𐑥𐑹 𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑, 𐑯 𐑛𐑵 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯 𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑴 𐑥𐑳𐑗; 𐑢𐑺𐑨𐑟, 𐑞 ·𐑩𐑥𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑑𐑳𐑚, 𐑯𐑽𐑤𐑦 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑓𐑰𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑛𐑲𐑨𐑥𐑦𐑑𐑼 𐑯 𐑝 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑐𐑹𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑑 𐑛𐑧𐑐𐑔, 𐑥𐑱𐑒𐑕 𐑩 𐑮𐑭𐑞𐑼 𐑚𐑳𐑤𐑒𐑦 𐑓𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑓 𐑩 𐑒𐑮𐑭𐑓𐑑 𐑣𐑵𐑟 𐑐𐑤𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑕 𐑸 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑣𐑭𐑓-𐑦𐑯𐑗 𐑦𐑯 𐑔𐑦𐑒𐑯𐑩𐑕; 𐑓 𐑞 𐑚𐑪𐑑𐑩𐑥 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤-𐑚𐑴𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑲𐑕, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑚𐑺 𐑳𐑐 𐑩 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑼𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑚𐑿𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑱𐑑, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑝 𐑩 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑳𐑯. 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑞 𐑐𐑱𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑝𐑩𐑕 𐑒𐑳𐑝𐑼 𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑤𐑨𐑐𐑑 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑩𐑥𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑤𐑲𐑯-𐑑𐑳𐑚, 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑 𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑕 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑓 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑻 𐑐𐑫𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑪𐑓 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑛𐑦𐑡𐑩𐑕 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑢𐑧𐑛𐑦𐑙-𐑒𐑱𐑒 𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑑 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟.

𐑚𐑴𐑔 𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑤𐑲𐑯 𐑸 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑴𐑟𐑛; 𐑞 𐑤𐑴𐑼 𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑑𐑻𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑱𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑩𐑯 𐑲-𐑕𐑐𐑤𐑲𐑕 𐑹 𐑤𐑵𐑐 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑳𐑐 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑚𐑪𐑑𐑩𐑥 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑝 𐑞 𐑑𐑳𐑚, 𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑙𐑦𐑙 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑧𐑡 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑰𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑦𐑯𐑜𐑱𐑡𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦𐑔𐑦𐑙. 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑼𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑤𐑴𐑼 𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑧𐑕𐑦𐑕𐑺𐑦 𐑪𐑯 𐑑𐑵 𐑩𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑕. 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑: 𐑦𐑯 𐑹𐑛𐑼 𐑑 𐑓𐑩𐑕𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑱𐑑 𐑞 𐑓𐑭𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑝 𐑩𐑯 𐑩𐑛𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑤𐑲𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑩 𐑯𐑱𐑚𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑴𐑑, 𐑦𐑯 𐑒𐑱𐑕 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑕𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑕𐑴 𐑛𐑰𐑐 𐑨𐑟 𐑑 𐑔𐑮𐑧𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑑 𐑒𐑨𐑮𐑦 𐑪𐑓 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑲𐑼 𐑤𐑲𐑯 𐑼𐑦𐑡𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑩𐑑𐑨𐑗𐑑 𐑑 𐑞 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯. 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟, 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑝 𐑒𐑹𐑕 𐑦𐑟 𐑖𐑦𐑓𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑥𐑳𐑜 𐑝 𐑱𐑤, 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑻, 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑚𐑴𐑑 𐑑 𐑞 𐑳𐑞𐑼; 𐑞𐑴 𐑞 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑴𐑑 𐑷𐑤𐑢𐑱𐑟 𐑣𐑪𐑝𐑼𐑟 𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑑 𐑩𐑕𐑦𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑹𐑑. 𐑕𐑧𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑛: 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑼𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑓 𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑕𐑱𐑓𐑑𐑦'𐑟 𐑕𐑱𐑒; 𐑓 𐑢𐑻 𐑞 𐑤𐑴𐑼 𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑝 𐑞 𐑤𐑲𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑢𐑱 𐑩𐑑𐑨𐑗𐑑 𐑑 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑, 𐑯 𐑢𐑻 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑑 𐑮𐑳𐑯 𐑞 𐑤𐑲𐑯 𐑬𐑑 𐑑 𐑞 𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑕𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑩𐑤, 𐑕𐑥𐑴𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑛𐑳𐑟, 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑪𐑐 𐑞𐑺, 𐑓 𐑞 𐑛𐑵𐑥𐑛 𐑚𐑴𐑑 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑓𐑨𐑤𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑰 𐑛𐑮𐑨𐑜𐑛 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑓𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑰; 𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑒𐑱𐑕 𐑯𐑴 𐑑𐑬𐑯-𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑼 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑓𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑣𐑻 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯.

𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑤𐑴𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑 𐑓 𐑞 𐑗𐑱𐑕, 𐑞 𐑳𐑐𐑼 𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑝 𐑞 𐑤𐑲𐑯 𐑦𐑟 𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑭𐑓𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑑𐑳𐑚, 𐑯 𐑐𐑭𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑞 𐑤𐑪𐑜𐑼𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑞𐑺, 𐑦𐑟 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯 𐑒𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑛 𐑓𐑹𐑢𐑼𐑛 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑲𐑼 𐑤𐑧𐑙𐑔 𐑝 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑, 𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑒𐑮𐑪𐑕𐑢𐑲𐑟 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑤𐑵𐑥 𐑹 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑥𐑨𐑯'𐑟 𐑹, 𐑕𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑡𐑪𐑜𐑟 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑮𐑴𐑦𐑙; 𐑯 𐑷𐑤𐑕𐑴 𐑐𐑭𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑢𐑰𐑯 𐑞 𐑥𐑧𐑯, 𐑨𐑟 𐑞𐑱 𐑷𐑤𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑩𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑦𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑪𐑐𐑩𐑟𐑦𐑑 𐑜𐑳𐑯𐑩𐑤𐑟, 𐑑 𐑞 𐑤𐑧𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑗𐑪𐑒𐑕 𐑹 𐑜𐑮𐑵𐑝𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑰𐑥 𐑐𐑶𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑐𐑮𐑬 𐑝 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑, 𐑢𐑺 𐑩 𐑢𐑫𐑛𐑩𐑯 𐑐𐑦𐑯 𐑹 𐑕𐑒𐑿𐑼 𐑞 𐑕𐑲𐑟 𐑝 𐑩 𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑤, 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑝𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑦𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑕𐑤𐑦𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑬𐑑. 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑗𐑪𐑒𐑕 𐑦𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑙𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑕𐑤𐑲𐑑 𐑓𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑵𐑯 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑞 𐑚𐑬𐑟, 𐑯 𐑦𐑟 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑐𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯; 𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑑𐑧𐑯 𐑹 𐑑𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑦 𐑓𐑨𐑞𐑩𐑥𐑟 (𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑛 𐑚𐑪𐑒𐑕-𐑤𐑲𐑯) 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑒𐑶𐑤𐑛 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑪𐑒𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑬𐑟, 𐑦𐑑 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑿𐑟 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑢𐑱 𐑑 𐑞 𐑜𐑳𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑩 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑓𐑻𐑞𐑼 𐑭𐑓𐑑, 𐑯 𐑦𐑟 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑩𐑑𐑨𐑗𐑑 𐑑 𐑞 𐑖𐑹𐑑-𐑢𐑹𐑐—𐑞 𐑮𐑴𐑐 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑥𐑰𐑛𐑾𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑰𐑝𐑾𐑕 𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑧𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯, 𐑞 𐑖𐑹𐑑-𐑢𐑹𐑐 𐑜𐑴𐑟 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑕𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑮𐑦 𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑒𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑑𐑵 𐑑𐑰𐑛𐑾𐑕 𐑑 𐑛𐑰𐑑𐑱𐑤.

𐑞𐑳𐑕 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤-𐑤𐑲𐑯 𐑓𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑟 𐑞 𐑣𐑴𐑤 𐑚𐑴𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑦𐑒𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑒𐑶𐑤𐑟, 𐑑𐑢𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑯 𐑮𐑲𐑞𐑦𐑙 𐑼𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑛𐑦𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯. 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑹𐑟𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑸 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑪𐑤𐑝𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑐𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑹𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟; 𐑕𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑑 𐑞 𐑑𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑛 𐑲 𐑝 𐑞 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟𐑥𐑩𐑯, 𐑞𐑱 𐑕𐑰𐑥 𐑨𐑟 ·𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑾𐑯 𐑡𐑳𐑜𐑩𐑤𐑼𐑟, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑛𐑤𐑾𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑯𐑱𐑒𐑕 𐑕𐑐𐑹𐑑𐑦𐑝𐑤𐑦 𐑓𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑵𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑺 𐑤𐑦𐑥𐑟. 𐑯𐑹 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑕𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑥𐑹𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑫𐑥𐑩𐑯, 𐑓 𐑞 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑑𐑲𐑥, 𐑕𐑰𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑩𐑥𐑦𐑛 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑣𐑧𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑕𐑦𐑟, 𐑯 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑳𐑑𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑹, 𐑚𐑦𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑳𐑯𐑯𐑴𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑞 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯 𐑥𐑱 𐑚𐑰 𐑛𐑸𐑑𐑩𐑛, 𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑣𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑹𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑚𐑰 𐑐𐑫𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑐𐑤𐑱 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑮𐑦𐑙𐑛 𐑤𐑲𐑑𐑯𐑦𐑙𐑟; 𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑞𐑳𐑕 𐑕𐑻𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑 𐑩 𐑖𐑳𐑛𐑼 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑱𐑒𐑕 𐑞 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑥𐑨𐑮𐑴 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑴𐑯𐑟 𐑑 𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑝𐑼 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑖𐑱𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑡𐑧𐑤𐑦. 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑚𐑦𐑑—𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡 𐑔𐑦𐑙! 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑚𐑦𐑑 𐑩𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑦𐑖?—𐑜𐑱𐑼 𐑕𐑨𐑤𐑦𐑟, 𐑥𐑹 𐑥𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑥𐑻𐑔, 𐑚𐑧𐑑𐑼 𐑡𐑴𐑒𐑕, 𐑯 𐑚𐑮𐑲𐑑𐑼 𐑮𐑧𐑐𐑸𐑑𐑰𐑟, 𐑿 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑣𐑻𐑛 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑘𐑹 𐑥𐑩𐑣𐑪𐑜𐑩𐑯𐑦, 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑿 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑣𐑽 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑞 𐑣𐑭𐑓-𐑦𐑯𐑗 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑛𐑼 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤-𐑚𐑴𐑑, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑞𐑳𐑕 𐑣𐑳𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑙𐑥𐑩𐑯'𐑟 𐑯𐑵𐑕𐑩𐑟; 𐑯, 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑞 𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑕 𐑚𐑻𐑜𐑼𐑟 𐑝 ·𐑒𐑨𐑤𐑱 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 ·𐑒𐑦𐑙 ·𐑧𐑛𐑢𐑼𐑛, 𐑞 𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑕 𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑴𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑵 𐑐𐑫𐑤 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑡𐑷𐑟 𐑝 𐑛𐑧𐑔, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑣𐑷𐑤𐑑𐑼 𐑼𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑯𐑧𐑒, 𐑨𐑟 𐑿 𐑥𐑱 𐑕𐑱.

𐑐𐑼𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑕 𐑩 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑔𐑷𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑯𐑬 𐑦𐑯𐑱𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑿 𐑑 𐑩𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑 𐑓 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑰𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑛𐑦𐑟𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑟—𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑓𐑿 𐑝 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑸 𐑒𐑨𐑠𐑵𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑮𐑪𐑯𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑛—𐑝 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑹 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑤𐑲𐑯, 𐑯 𐑤𐑪𐑕𐑑. 𐑓, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑞 𐑤𐑲𐑯 𐑦𐑟 𐑛𐑸𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑬𐑑, 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑕𐑰𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑, 𐑦𐑟 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑰𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑥𐑦𐑛𐑕𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑥𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑓𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑟𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑝 𐑩 𐑕𐑑𐑰𐑥-𐑧𐑯𐑡𐑦𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑓𐑫𐑤 𐑐𐑤𐑱, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑓𐑤𐑲𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑰𐑥, 𐑯 𐑖𐑭𐑓𐑑, 𐑯 𐑢𐑰𐑤, 𐑦𐑟 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑿. 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑻𐑕; 𐑓 𐑿 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑦𐑑 𐑥𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑣𐑸𐑑 𐑝 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑐𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑤𐑟, 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑪𐑟 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑮𐑪𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑒𐑮𐑱𐑛𐑩𐑤, 𐑯 𐑿 𐑸 𐑐𐑦𐑗𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑢𐑱 𐑯 𐑞 𐑳𐑞𐑼, 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑤𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑢𐑹𐑯𐑦𐑙; 𐑯 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑲 𐑩 𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓-𐑩𐑡𐑳𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑶𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦 𐑯 𐑕𐑦𐑥𐑩𐑤𐑑𐑱𐑯𐑾𐑕𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑝𐑴𐑤𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑯 𐑨𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯, 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑿 𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑱𐑐 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑩 ·𐑯𐑨𐑟𐑧𐑐𐑩 𐑝, 𐑯 𐑮𐑳𐑯 𐑩𐑢𐑱 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑢𐑺 𐑞 𐑷𐑤-𐑕𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑳𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑐𐑽𐑕 𐑿 𐑬𐑑.

𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯: 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑒𐑭𐑥 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑩𐑐𐑨𐑮𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑰𐑛𐑟 𐑯 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑓𐑩𐑕𐑦𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑹𐑥, 𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑼𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑕 𐑥𐑹 𐑷𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑹𐑥 𐑦𐑑𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓; 𐑓, 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑰𐑛, 𐑞 𐑒𐑭𐑥 𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞 𐑮𐑨𐑐𐑼 𐑯 𐑧𐑯𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑴𐑐 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑹𐑥; 𐑯 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑱𐑯𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑦𐑑𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓, 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑣𐑸𐑥𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑮𐑲𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑟 𐑞 𐑓𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑐𐑬𐑛𐑼, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑷𐑤, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑤𐑴𐑠𐑩𐑯; 𐑕𐑴 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑕𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑴𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑤𐑲𐑯, 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑻𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑲𐑯𐑟 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑞 𐑹𐑟𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑮𐑷𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑨𐑒𐑗𐑵𐑩𐑤 𐑐𐑤𐑱—𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑦𐑟 𐑩 𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑒𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑹 𐑝 𐑑𐑮𐑵 𐑑𐑧𐑮𐑼 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑨𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑 𐑝 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑛𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑼𐑩𐑕 𐑩𐑓𐑺. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑲 𐑕𐑱 𐑥𐑹? 𐑷𐑤 𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑤𐑦𐑝 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑧𐑤𐑩𐑐𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑱𐑤-𐑤𐑲𐑯𐑟. 𐑷𐑤 𐑸 𐑚𐑹𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑷𐑤𐑑𐑼𐑟 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑞𐑺 𐑯𐑧𐑒𐑕; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑒𐑷𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑢𐑦𐑓𐑑, 𐑕𐑳𐑛𐑩𐑯 𐑑𐑻𐑯 𐑝 𐑛𐑧𐑔, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑹𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑮𐑾𐑤𐑲𐑟 𐑞 𐑕𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑑, 𐑕𐑳𐑑𐑩𐑤, 𐑧𐑝𐑼-𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑐𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑤𐑟 𐑝 𐑤𐑲𐑓. 𐑯 𐑦𐑓 𐑿 𐑚𐑰 𐑩 𐑓𐑦𐑤𐑪𐑕𐑩𐑓𐑼, 𐑞𐑴 𐑕𐑰𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤-𐑚𐑴𐑑, 𐑿 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑸𐑑 𐑓𐑰𐑤 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑑 𐑥𐑹 𐑝 𐑑𐑧𐑮𐑼, 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑞𐑴 𐑕𐑰𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑘𐑹 𐑰𐑝𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑲𐑼 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑐𐑴𐑒𐑼, 𐑯 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑩 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯, 𐑚𐑲 𐑘𐑹 𐑕𐑲𐑛.

·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 61. 𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚 ·𐑒𐑦𐑤𐑟 𐑩 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤.

𐑦𐑓 𐑑 ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒 𐑞 𐑨𐑐𐑼𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑛 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩 𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑐𐑹𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑕, 𐑑 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑒𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑩 𐑛𐑦𐑓𐑼𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑪𐑚𐑡𐑧𐑒𐑑.

“𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑿 𐑕𐑰 𐑣𐑦𐑥 '𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑛,” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑞 𐑕𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑡, 𐑣𐑴𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑬 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑶𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑴𐑑, “𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑿 𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑒 𐑕𐑰 𐑣𐑦𐑥 '·𐑐𐑸𐑥 𐑢𐑱𐑤.”

𐑞 𐑯𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑 𐑛𐑱 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑰𐑛𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑤𐑑𐑮𐑦, 𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑯𐑳𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑤 𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑜𐑱𐑡 𐑞𐑧𐑥, 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛'𐑟 𐑒𐑮𐑵 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑣𐑸𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑦𐑕𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑤 𐑝 𐑕𐑤𐑰𐑐 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑿𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩 𐑝𐑱𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑕𐑰. 𐑓 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑐𐑸𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑾𐑯 ·𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑢𐑰 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑢𐑻 𐑝𐑶𐑦𐑡𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑒𐑷𐑤 𐑩 𐑤𐑲𐑝𐑤𐑦 𐑜𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛; 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑟, 𐑦𐑑 𐑩𐑓𐑹𐑛𐑟 𐑓𐑿𐑼 𐑜𐑤𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑝 𐑐𐑹𐑐𐑩𐑕𐑩𐑟, 𐑛𐑪𐑤𐑓𐑦𐑯𐑟, 𐑓𐑤𐑲𐑦𐑙-𐑓𐑦𐑖, 𐑯 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑝𐑦𐑝𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑕 𐑛𐑧𐑯𐑦𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑥𐑹 𐑕𐑑𐑻𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼𐑟, 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑪𐑓 𐑞 ·𐑮𐑰𐑴 𐑛𐑦 𐑤𐑭 ·𐑐𐑤𐑭𐑑𐑩, 𐑹 𐑞 𐑦𐑯-𐑖𐑹 𐑜𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑪𐑓 ·𐑐𐑼𐑵.

𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑥𐑲 𐑑𐑻𐑯 𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑓𐑹𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑-𐑣𐑧𐑛; 𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑥𐑲 𐑖𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑼𐑟 𐑤𐑰𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑤𐑨𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑮𐑶𐑩𐑤 𐑖𐑮𐑬𐑛𐑟, 𐑑 𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑴 𐑲 𐑲𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑢𐑱𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑗𐑭𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑺. 𐑯𐑴 𐑮𐑧𐑟𐑩𐑤𐑵𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑑; 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑛𐑮𐑰𐑥𐑦 𐑥𐑵𐑛 𐑤𐑵𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑷𐑤 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑕𐑯𐑩𐑕, 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑥𐑲 𐑕𐑴𐑤 𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑥𐑲 𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦; 𐑞𐑴 𐑥𐑲 𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑿𐑛 𐑑 𐑕𐑢𐑱 𐑨𐑟 𐑩 𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑡𐑩𐑤𐑩𐑥 𐑢𐑦𐑤, 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑞 𐑐𐑬𐑼 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑥𐑵𐑝𐑛 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑛𐑮𐑷𐑯.

𐑺 𐑓𐑼𐑜𐑧𐑑𐑓𐑩𐑤𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑷𐑤𐑑𐑩𐑜𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑒𐑱𐑥 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑥𐑰, 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑯𐑴𐑑𐑦𐑕𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑥𐑱𐑯 𐑯 𐑥𐑦𐑟𐑩𐑯-𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑-𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑷𐑤𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑦 𐑛𐑮𐑬𐑟𐑦. 𐑕𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑝 𐑳𐑕 𐑤𐑲𐑓𐑤𐑩𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑢𐑳𐑙 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑸𐑟, 𐑯 𐑓 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑕𐑢𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑰 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑞𐑺 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩 𐑯𐑪𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑴 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑕𐑤𐑳𐑥𐑚𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑥𐑟𐑥𐑩𐑯. 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑝𐑟, 𐑑𐑵, 𐑯𐑪𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑞𐑺 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑒𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑕; 𐑯 𐑩𐑒𐑮𐑪𐑕 𐑞 𐑢𐑲𐑛 𐑑𐑮𐑭𐑯𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑰, 𐑰𐑕𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑑 𐑢𐑧𐑕𐑑, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑯 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑷𐑤.

𐑕𐑳𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑳𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑚𐑻𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑦𐑯𐑰𐑔 𐑥𐑲 𐑒𐑤𐑴𐑟𐑛 𐑲𐑟; 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑝𐑲𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑥𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑜𐑮𐑭𐑕𐑐𐑑 𐑞 𐑖𐑮𐑬𐑛𐑟; 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑦𐑟𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤, 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑕 𐑱𐑡𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑻𐑝𐑛 𐑥𐑰; 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑖𐑪𐑒 𐑲 𐑒𐑱𐑥 𐑚𐑨𐑒 𐑑 𐑤𐑲𐑓. 𐑯 𐑤𐑴! 𐑒𐑤𐑴𐑕 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑬𐑼 𐑤𐑰, 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑓𐑹𐑑𐑦 𐑓𐑨𐑞𐑩𐑥𐑟 𐑪𐑓, 𐑩 𐑡𐑲𐑜𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑒 ·𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑤𐑱 𐑮𐑴𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑞 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑕𐑲𐑟𐑛 𐑣𐑳𐑤 𐑝 𐑩 𐑓𐑮𐑦𐑜𐑩𐑑, 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑮𐑷𐑛, 𐑜𐑤𐑪𐑕𐑦 𐑚𐑨𐑒, 𐑝 𐑩𐑯 ·𐑰𐑔𐑦𐑴𐑐𐑾𐑯 𐑣𐑿, 𐑜𐑤𐑦𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑯'𐑟 𐑮𐑱𐑟 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑥𐑦𐑮𐑼. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑤𐑱𐑟𐑦𐑤𐑦 𐑳𐑯𐑡𐑩𐑤𐑱𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑑𐑮𐑪𐑓 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑰, 𐑯 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑯 𐑩𐑯𐑪𐑯 𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑐𐑬𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑝𐑱𐑐𐑼𐑦 𐑡𐑧𐑑, 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑑 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑐𐑹𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑻𐑜𐑼 𐑕𐑥𐑴𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑲𐑐 𐑝 𐑩 𐑢𐑹𐑥 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼𐑯𐑵𐑯. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑐𐑲𐑐, 𐑐𐑫𐑼 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞𐑲 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑. 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑓 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑒 𐑚𐑲 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑦𐑯𐑗𐑭𐑯𐑑𐑼'𐑟 𐑢𐑪𐑯𐑛, 𐑞 𐑕𐑤𐑰𐑐𐑦 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑯 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑕𐑤𐑰𐑐𐑼 𐑦𐑯 𐑦𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑕 𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑢𐑱𐑒𐑓𐑩𐑤𐑯𐑩𐑕; 𐑯 𐑥𐑹 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑩 𐑕𐑒𐑹 𐑝 𐑝𐑶𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑷𐑤 𐑐𐑸𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑝𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑤, 𐑕𐑦𐑥𐑩𐑤𐑑𐑱𐑯𐑾𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑯𐑴𐑑𐑕 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑓𐑑, 𐑖𐑬𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑓𐑹𐑔 𐑞 𐑩𐑒𐑳𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑥𐑛 𐑒𐑮𐑲, 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑓𐑦𐑖 𐑕𐑤𐑴𐑤𐑦 𐑯 𐑮𐑧𐑜𐑿𐑤𐑼𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑐𐑬𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑸𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑮𐑲𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑺.

“𐑒𐑤𐑽 𐑩𐑢𐑱 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕! 𐑤𐑳𐑓!” 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚. 𐑯 𐑴𐑚𐑱𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑴𐑯 𐑹𐑛𐑼, 𐑣𐑰 𐑛𐑨𐑖𐑑 𐑞 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑥 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑞 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑥𐑟𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑤 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑴𐑒𐑕.

𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑛𐑩𐑯 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑒𐑤𐑩𐑥𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑵 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑩𐑤𐑸𐑥𐑛 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤; 𐑯 𐑺 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕 𐑢𐑻 𐑛𐑬𐑯, 𐑥𐑩𐑡𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑦 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑙, 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑢𐑨𐑥 𐑩𐑢𐑱 𐑑 𐑞 𐑤𐑰𐑢𐑼𐑛, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩 𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑛𐑦 𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑦, 𐑯 𐑥𐑱𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑴 𐑓𐑿 𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑨𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑢𐑨𐑥, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑷𐑤 𐑣𐑰 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑩𐑤𐑸𐑥𐑛, ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑜𐑱𐑝 𐑹𐑛𐑼𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑩𐑯 𐑹 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑚𐑰 𐑿𐑟𐑛, 𐑯 𐑯𐑴 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑒 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑼𐑟. 𐑕𐑴 𐑕𐑰𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑤𐑲𐑒 ·𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑺𐑦𐑴 ·𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑾𐑯𐑟 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑜𐑳𐑯𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕, 𐑢𐑰 𐑕𐑢𐑦𐑓𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑕𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑨𐑛𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑙; 𐑞 𐑒𐑭𐑥 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑩𐑛𐑥𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑞 𐑯𐑶𐑟𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑧𐑑. 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦, 𐑨𐑟 𐑢𐑰 𐑞𐑳𐑕 𐑜𐑤𐑲𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑗𐑱𐑕, 𐑞 𐑥𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑼 𐑐𐑻𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑼𐑤𐑦 𐑓𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑑𐑱𐑤 𐑓𐑹𐑑𐑦 𐑓𐑰𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑺, 𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑕𐑨𐑙𐑒 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑕𐑲𐑑 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑑𐑬𐑼 𐑕𐑢𐑪𐑤𐑴𐑛 𐑳𐑐.

“𐑞𐑺 𐑜𐑴 𐑓𐑤𐑵𐑒𐑕!” 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑲, 𐑩𐑯 𐑩𐑯𐑬𐑯𐑕𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑦𐑥𐑰𐑛𐑾𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑓𐑪𐑤𐑴𐑛 𐑚𐑲 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚'𐑟 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑛𐑿𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑨𐑗 𐑯 𐑦𐑜𐑯𐑲𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑲𐑐, 𐑓 𐑯𐑬 𐑩 𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑐𐑲𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑜𐑮𐑭𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛. 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑞 𐑓𐑫𐑤 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑝𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑦𐑤𐑨𐑐𐑕𐑑, 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑮𐑴𐑟 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯, 𐑯 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑯𐑬 𐑦𐑯 𐑩𐑛𐑝𐑭𐑯𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑥𐑴𐑒𐑼'𐑟 𐑚𐑴𐑑, 𐑯 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑯𐑽𐑼 𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑑 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑝 𐑞 𐑳𐑞𐑼𐑟, ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚 𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑪𐑯𐑼 𐑝 𐑞 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑗𐑼. 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑪𐑚𐑝𐑾𐑕, 𐑯𐑬, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑧𐑙𐑔 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑩𐑢𐑺 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑼𐑕𐑿𐑼𐑟. 𐑷𐑤 𐑕𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑝 𐑒𐑷𐑖𐑩𐑕𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞𐑺𐑓𐑹 𐑯𐑴 𐑤𐑪𐑙𐑜𐑼 𐑝 𐑿𐑕. 𐑐𐑨𐑛𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑛𐑮𐑪𐑐𐑑, 𐑯 𐑹𐑟 𐑒𐑱𐑥 𐑤𐑬𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑐𐑤𐑱. 𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑐𐑳𐑓𐑦𐑙 𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑲𐑐, ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚 𐑗𐑽𐑛 𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑮𐑵 𐑑 𐑞 𐑩𐑕𐑷𐑤𐑑.

𐑘𐑧𐑕, 𐑩 𐑥𐑲𐑑𐑦 𐑗𐑱𐑯𐑡 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑞 𐑓𐑦𐑖. 𐑷𐑤 𐑩𐑤𐑲𐑝 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑡𐑧𐑐𐑼𐑛𐑦, 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑜𐑴𐑦𐑙 “𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑬𐑑”; 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑐𐑸𐑑 𐑴𐑚𐑤𐑰𐑒𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑡𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑥𐑨𐑛 𐑘𐑰𐑕𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑣𐑰 𐑚𐑮𐑵𐑛.*

*𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑚𐑰 𐑕𐑰𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕 𐑝 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑩 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑤𐑲𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑚𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑲𐑼 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑽𐑽 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 𐑢𐑱𐑤'𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑹𐑥𐑩𐑕 𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑕. 𐑞𐑴 𐑩𐑐𐑨𐑮𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑞 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑥𐑨𐑕𐑦𐑝, 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑲 𐑓𐑸 𐑞 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑶𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑐𐑸𐑑 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥. 𐑕𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑰𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑝𐑱𐑑𐑕 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑺, 𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑺𐑾𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑳𐑟 𐑕𐑴 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑜𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑳𐑑𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑛. 𐑚𐑦𐑕𐑲𐑛𐑟, 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑦𐑟 𐑞 𐑚𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑔 𐑝 𐑞 𐑳𐑐𐑼 𐑐𐑸𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑓𐑮𐑳𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑧𐑛, 𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑞 𐑑𐑱𐑐𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑒𐑳𐑑-𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼 𐑓𐑹𐑥𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑤𐑴𐑼 𐑐𐑸𐑑, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑴𐑚𐑤𐑰𐑒𐑤𐑦 𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑝𐑱𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑧𐑛, 𐑣𐑰 𐑞𐑺𐑚𐑲 𐑥𐑱 𐑚𐑰 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑑 𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑕𐑓𐑹𐑥 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑩 𐑚𐑤𐑳𐑓-𐑚𐑬𐑛 𐑕𐑤𐑳𐑜𐑦𐑖 𐑜𐑨𐑤𐑦𐑪𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑩 𐑖𐑸𐑐𐑐𐑶𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 ·𐑯𐑿 ·𐑘𐑹𐑒 𐑐𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑑-𐑚𐑴𐑑.

“𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑑 𐑣𐑻, 𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑑 𐑣𐑻, 𐑥𐑲 𐑥𐑧𐑯! 𐑛𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑣𐑳𐑮𐑦 𐑘𐑹𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑝𐑟; 𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑐𐑤𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑦 𐑝 𐑑𐑲𐑥—𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑑 𐑣𐑻; 𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑑 𐑣𐑻 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑔𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼-𐑒𐑤𐑨𐑐𐑕, 𐑞𐑨𐑑'𐑕 𐑷𐑤,” 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚, 𐑕𐑐𐑤𐑳𐑑𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑬𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑥𐑴𐑒 𐑨𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑐𐑴𐑒. “𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑑 𐑣𐑻, 𐑯𐑬; 𐑜𐑦𐑝 '𐑩𐑥 𐑞 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑪𐑙 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑴𐑒, ·𐑑𐑨𐑖𐑑𐑱𐑜𐑴. 𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑑 𐑣𐑻, ·𐑑𐑨𐑖, 𐑥𐑲 𐑚𐑶—𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑑 𐑣𐑻, 𐑷𐑤; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑒𐑰𐑐 𐑒𐑵𐑤, 𐑒𐑰𐑐 𐑒𐑵𐑤—𐑒𐑿𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑚𐑼𐑟 𐑦𐑟 𐑞 𐑢𐑻𐑛—𐑰𐑟𐑦, 𐑰𐑟𐑦—𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑑 𐑣𐑻 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑜𐑮𐑦𐑥 𐑛𐑧𐑔 𐑯 𐑜𐑮𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑛𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑟, 𐑯 𐑮𐑱𐑟 𐑞 𐑚𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑛 𐑛𐑧𐑛 𐑐𐑻𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑼 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑞𐑺 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑝𐑟, 𐑚𐑶𐑟—𐑞𐑨𐑑'𐑕 𐑷𐑤. 𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑑 𐑣𐑻!”

“𐑢𐑵-𐑣𐑵! ·𐑢𐑭-𐑣𐑰!” 𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑞 ·𐑜𐑱-·𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑼 𐑦𐑯 𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑤𐑲, 𐑮𐑱𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑢𐑹-𐑢𐑵𐑐 𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑒𐑲𐑟; 𐑨𐑟 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑹𐑟𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑛 𐑚𐑴𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑪𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑺𐑦𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑬𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑓𐑹𐑢𐑼𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑕 𐑤𐑰𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑴𐑒 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑞 𐑰𐑜𐑼 ·𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑾𐑯 𐑜𐑱𐑝.

𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑲𐑤𐑛 𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑰𐑥𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑼𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑳𐑞𐑼𐑟 𐑒𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑢𐑲𐑤𐑛. “𐑒𐑰-𐑣𐑰! 𐑒𐑰-𐑣𐑰!” 𐑘𐑧𐑤𐑛 ·𐑛𐑨𐑜𐑵, 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑹𐑢𐑼𐑛𐑟 𐑯 𐑚𐑨𐑒𐑢𐑼𐑛𐑟 𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑰𐑑, 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑐𐑱𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑑𐑲𐑜𐑼 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑱𐑡.

“𐑒𐑭-𐑤𐑭! ·𐑜𐑵-𐑤𐑵!” 𐑣𐑬𐑤𐑛 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜, 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑓 𐑕𐑥𐑨𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑤𐑦𐑐𐑕 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑩 𐑥𐑬𐑔𐑓𐑫𐑤 𐑝 ·𐑜𐑮𐑧𐑯𐑩𐑛𐑽'𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑒. 𐑯 𐑞𐑳𐑕 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑹𐑟 𐑯 𐑘𐑧𐑤𐑟 𐑞 𐑒𐑰𐑤𐑟 𐑒𐑳𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑰. 𐑥𐑰𐑯𐑢𐑲𐑤, ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚 𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑱𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑝𐑨𐑯, 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑳𐑮𐑦𐑡𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑑 𐑞 𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑧𐑑, 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑐𐑳𐑓𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑕𐑥𐑴𐑒 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑬𐑔. 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑛𐑧𐑕𐑐𐑼𐑭𐑛𐑴𐑟 𐑞𐑱 𐑑𐑳𐑜𐑛 𐑯 𐑞𐑱 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑛, 𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑞 𐑢𐑧𐑤𐑒𐑩𐑥 𐑒𐑮𐑲 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑣𐑻𐑛—“𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑳𐑐, ·𐑑𐑨𐑖𐑑𐑱𐑜𐑴!—𐑜𐑦𐑝 𐑦𐑑 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥!” 𐑞 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑣𐑻𐑤𐑛. “𐑕𐑑𐑻𐑯 𐑷𐑤!” 𐑞 𐑹𐑟𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑚𐑨𐑒𐑑 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼; 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑥𐑴𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑣𐑪𐑑 𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑞𐑺 𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑕. 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞 𐑥𐑨𐑡𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑤𐑲𐑯. 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹, ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑕𐑢𐑦𐑓𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑷𐑑 𐑑𐑵 𐑩𐑛𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑦𐑑 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑞 𐑤𐑪𐑜𐑼𐑣𐑧𐑛, 𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑕, 𐑚𐑲 𐑮𐑰𐑟𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑮𐑰𐑕𐑑 𐑮𐑨𐑐𐑦𐑛 𐑕𐑻𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙𐑟, 𐑩 𐑣𐑧𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑯 𐑚𐑤𐑵 𐑕𐑥𐑴𐑒 𐑯𐑬 𐑡𐑧𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑳𐑐 𐑯 𐑥𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑛𐑦 𐑓𐑿𐑥𐑟 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑲𐑐. 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑤𐑲𐑯 𐑐𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑯 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑞 𐑤𐑪𐑜𐑼𐑣𐑧𐑛; 𐑕𐑴 𐑷𐑤𐑕𐑴, 𐑡𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑮𐑰𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑐𐑶𐑯𐑑, 𐑦𐑑 𐑚𐑤𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑯 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑚𐑴𐑔 𐑝 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚'𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟, 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑞 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛-𐑒𐑤𐑪𐑔𐑕, 𐑹 𐑕𐑒𐑢𐑺𐑟 𐑝 𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑤𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑝𐑩𐑕 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑢𐑹𐑯 𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟, 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑨𐑒𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑮𐑪𐑐𐑑. 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑯 𐑧𐑯𐑩𐑥𐑦'𐑟 𐑖𐑸𐑐 𐑑𐑵-𐑧𐑡𐑛 𐑕𐑹𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑚𐑤𐑱𐑛, 𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑧𐑯𐑩𐑥𐑦 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑘𐑹 𐑒𐑤𐑳𐑗.

“𐑢𐑧𐑑 𐑞 𐑤𐑲𐑯! 𐑢𐑧𐑑 𐑞 𐑤𐑲𐑯!” 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚 𐑑 𐑞 𐑑𐑳𐑚 𐑹𐑟𐑥𐑩𐑯 (𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑕𐑰𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑑𐑳𐑚) 𐑣𐑵, 𐑕𐑯𐑨𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑪𐑓 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑑, 𐑛𐑨𐑖𐑑 𐑕𐑰-𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑦𐑑.* 𐑥𐑹 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑩𐑯, 𐑕𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑤𐑲𐑯 𐑚𐑦𐑜𐑨𐑯 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕. 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑 𐑯𐑬 𐑓𐑤𐑵 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑞 𐑚𐑶𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑖𐑸𐑒 𐑷𐑤 𐑓𐑦𐑯𐑟. 𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚 𐑯 ·𐑑𐑨𐑖𐑑𐑱𐑜𐑴 𐑣𐑽 𐑗𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑛 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕𐑩𐑟—𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑥 𐑓 𐑕𐑑𐑻𐑯—𐑩 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑜𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑦𐑟𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑑𐑮𐑵𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑮𐑪𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯.

*𐑐𐑸𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑑 𐑖𐑴 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑨𐑒𐑑, 𐑦𐑑 𐑥𐑱 𐑣𐑽 𐑚𐑰 𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛, 𐑞𐑨𐑑, 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑴𐑤𐑛 ·𐑛𐑳𐑗 𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑼𐑦, 𐑩 𐑥𐑪𐑐 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑿𐑟𐑛 𐑑 𐑛𐑨𐑖 𐑞 𐑮𐑳𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑤𐑲𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼; 𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑕, 𐑩 𐑢𐑫𐑛𐑩𐑯 𐑐𐑦𐑜𐑦𐑯, 𐑹 𐑚𐑱𐑤𐑼, 𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑧𐑑 𐑩𐑐𐑸𐑑 𐑓 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑐𐑻𐑐𐑩𐑕. 𐑘𐑹 𐑣𐑨𐑑, 𐑣𐑬𐑧𐑝𐑼, 𐑦𐑟 𐑞 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑝𐑰𐑯𐑾𐑯𐑑.

𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑝𐑲𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑤𐑲𐑯 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑲𐑼 𐑤𐑧𐑙𐑔 𐑝 𐑞 𐑳𐑐𐑼 𐑐𐑸𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑, 𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑯𐑬 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑹 𐑑𐑲𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑩 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑙, 𐑿 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑔𐑷𐑑 𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑭𐑓𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑑𐑵 𐑒𐑰𐑤𐑟—𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑒𐑤𐑰𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼, 𐑞 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑞 𐑺—𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑 𐑗𐑻𐑯𐑛 𐑪𐑯 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑚𐑴𐑔 𐑩𐑐𐑴𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑕. 𐑩 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑿𐑩𐑤 𐑒𐑨𐑕𐑒𐑱𐑛 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑛 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑚𐑬𐑟; 𐑩 𐑕𐑰𐑕𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑧𐑛𐑦 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑻 𐑢𐑱𐑒; 𐑯, 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑤𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑥𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑦𐑯, 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑝 𐑩 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑓𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑼, 𐑞 𐑝𐑲𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑑𐑦𐑙, 𐑒𐑮𐑨𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑒𐑮𐑭𐑓𐑑 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑣𐑻 𐑕𐑐𐑨𐑟𐑥𐑪𐑛𐑦𐑒 𐑜𐑳𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑕𐑰. 𐑞𐑳𐑕 𐑞𐑱 𐑮𐑳𐑖𐑑; 𐑰𐑗 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑯 𐑥𐑱𐑯 𐑒𐑤𐑦𐑙𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑰𐑑, 𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑝𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑑𐑪𐑕𐑑 𐑑 𐑞 𐑓𐑴𐑥; 𐑯 𐑞 𐑑𐑷𐑤 𐑓𐑹𐑥 𐑝 ·𐑑𐑨𐑖𐑑𐑱𐑜𐑴 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑽𐑦𐑙 𐑹 𐑒𐑮𐑬𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑛𐑳𐑚𐑩𐑤, 𐑦𐑯 𐑹𐑛𐑼 𐑑 𐑚𐑮𐑦𐑙 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑼 𐑝 𐑜𐑮𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑑𐑦. 𐑣𐑴𐑤 ·𐑩𐑑𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑕 𐑯 ·𐑐𐑩𐑕𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑒𐑕 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑐𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑞𐑱 𐑖𐑪𐑑 𐑪𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑢𐑱, 𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑧𐑙𐑔 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑤𐑨𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑤𐑲𐑑.

“𐑣𐑷𐑤 𐑦𐑯—𐑣𐑷𐑤 𐑦𐑯!” 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚 𐑑 𐑞 𐑚𐑬𐑟𐑥𐑩𐑯! 𐑯, 𐑓𐑱𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑑𐑩𐑢𐑹𐑛𐑟 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑷𐑤 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑚𐑦𐑜𐑨𐑯 𐑐𐑫𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑 𐑳𐑐 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑑𐑴𐑛 𐑪𐑯. 𐑕𐑵𐑯 𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑦𐑙 𐑳𐑐 𐑚𐑲 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑤𐑨𐑙𐑒, ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚, 𐑓𐑻𐑥𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑰 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑒𐑤𐑳𐑥𐑟𐑦 𐑒𐑤𐑰𐑑, 𐑛𐑸𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑛𐑸𐑑 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑛𐑸𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑓𐑤𐑲𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑦𐑖; 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑢𐑻𐑛 𐑝 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑭𐑯𐑛, 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑 𐑷𐑤𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑩𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑱 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤'𐑟 𐑣𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑪𐑤𐑴, 𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑦𐑙 𐑳𐑐 𐑓 𐑩𐑯𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑓𐑤𐑦𐑙.

𐑞 𐑮𐑧𐑛 𐑑𐑲𐑛 𐑯𐑬 𐑐𐑹𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑷𐑤 𐑕𐑲𐑛𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑥𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑼 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑚𐑮𐑫𐑒𐑕 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑩 𐑣𐑦𐑤. 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑑𐑹𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦 𐑮𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑚𐑮𐑲𐑯 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑚𐑤𐑳𐑛, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑚𐑳𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑯 𐑕𐑰𐑞𐑛 𐑓 𐑓𐑻𐑤𐑪𐑙𐑟 𐑚𐑦𐑣𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑢𐑱𐑒. 𐑞 𐑕𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑳𐑯 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑟𐑩𐑯 𐑐𐑪𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑰, 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑚𐑨𐑒 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑮𐑦𐑓𐑤𐑧𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑓𐑱𐑕, 𐑕𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑱 𐑷𐑤 𐑜𐑤𐑴𐑛 𐑑 𐑰𐑗 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑮𐑧𐑛 𐑥𐑧𐑯. 𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑢𐑲𐑤, 𐑡𐑧𐑑 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑡𐑧𐑑 𐑝 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑕𐑥𐑴𐑒 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑨𐑜𐑩𐑯𐑲𐑟𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑖𐑪𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑦𐑮𐑩𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑯 𐑝𐑾𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑐𐑳𐑓 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑐𐑳𐑓 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑥𐑬𐑔 𐑝 𐑞 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑟𐑥𐑩𐑯; 𐑨𐑟 𐑨𐑑 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑛𐑸𐑑, 𐑣𐑷𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑮𐑫𐑒𐑩𐑛 𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑕 (𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑤𐑲𐑯 𐑩𐑑𐑨𐑗𐑑 𐑑 𐑦𐑑), ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑑 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯 𐑯 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯, 𐑚𐑲 𐑩 𐑓𐑿 𐑮𐑨𐑐𐑦𐑛 𐑚𐑤𐑴𐑟 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑞 𐑜𐑳𐑯𐑩𐑤, 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯 𐑯 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤.

“𐑐𐑫𐑤 𐑳𐑐—𐑐𐑫𐑤 𐑳𐑐!” 𐑣𐑰 𐑯𐑬 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 𐑑 𐑞 𐑚𐑬𐑟𐑥𐑩𐑯, 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑮𐑦𐑤𐑨𐑒𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑮𐑪𐑔. “𐑐𐑫𐑤 𐑳𐑐!—𐑒𐑤𐑴𐑕 𐑑!” 𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑 𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑛 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑞 𐑓𐑦𐑖'𐑩𐑟 𐑓𐑤𐑨𐑙𐑒. 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑮𐑰𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑸 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑞 𐑚𐑬, ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚 𐑕𐑤𐑴𐑤𐑦 𐑗𐑻𐑯𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑖𐑸𐑐 𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑕 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑓𐑦𐑖, 𐑯 𐑒𐑧𐑐𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑞𐑺, 𐑒𐑺𐑓𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑗𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑯 𐑗𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑙, 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑓 𐑒𐑷𐑖𐑩𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑰𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑓𐑰𐑤 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑜𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑢𐑪𐑗 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑕𐑢𐑪𐑤𐑴𐑛, 𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑓𐑽𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑺 𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑣𐑫𐑒 𐑦𐑑 𐑬𐑑. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑜𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑢𐑪𐑗 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑷𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑼𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑤𐑲𐑓 𐑝 𐑞 𐑓𐑦𐑖. 𐑯 𐑯𐑬 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑒; 𐑓, 𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑑𐑮𐑭𐑯𐑕 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑳𐑯𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 “𐑓𐑤𐑳𐑮𐑦,” 𐑞 𐑥𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑼 𐑣𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑢𐑪𐑤𐑴𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑤𐑳𐑛, 𐑴𐑝𐑼𐑮𐑨𐑐𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑦𐑯 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑮𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤, 𐑥𐑨𐑛, 𐑚𐑶𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑱, 𐑕𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑤𐑛 𐑒𐑮𐑭𐑓𐑑, 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑮𐑪𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑕𐑑𐑻𐑯, 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑩𐑛𐑵 𐑚𐑤𐑲𐑯𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑜𐑩𐑤 𐑬𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑯𐑟𐑦𐑛 𐑑𐑢𐑲𐑤𐑲𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑒𐑤𐑽 𐑺 𐑝 𐑞 𐑛𐑱.

𐑯 𐑯𐑬 𐑩𐑚𐑱𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑤𐑳𐑮𐑦, 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑕 𐑥𐑹 𐑮𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑬𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑝𐑿; 𐑕𐑻𐑡𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑑 𐑕𐑲𐑛; 𐑕𐑐𐑨𐑟𐑥𐑪𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑲𐑤𐑱𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑯 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑐𐑬𐑑-𐑣𐑴𐑤, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑖𐑸𐑐, 𐑒𐑮𐑨𐑒𐑦𐑙, 𐑨𐑜𐑩𐑯𐑲𐑟𐑛 𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑐𐑼𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟. 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑, 𐑜𐑳𐑖 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑜𐑳𐑖 𐑝 𐑒𐑤𐑪𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑮𐑧𐑛 𐑜𐑹, 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑓 𐑦𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑞 𐑐𐑻𐑐𐑩𐑤 𐑤𐑰𐑟 𐑝 𐑮𐑧𐑛 𐑢𐑲𐑯, 𐑖𐑪𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑓𐑮𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑺; 𐑯 𐑓𐑷𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑨𐑒 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯, 𐑮𐑨𐑯 𐑛𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑓𐑤𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑕 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑕𐑰. 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑸𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑻𐑕𐑑!

“𐑣𐑰'𐑟 𐑛𐑧𐑛, ·𐑥𐑼 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚,” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 ·𐑛𐑨𐑜𐑵.

“𐑘𐑧𐑕; 𐑚𐑴𐑔 𐑐𐑲𐑐𐑕 𐑕𐑥𐑴𐑒𐑑 𐑬𐑑!” 𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑛𐑮𐑷𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑴𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑬𐑔, ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚 𐑕𐑒𐑨𐑑𐑼𐑛 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑛 𐑨𐑖𐑩𐑟 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑞 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼; 𐑯, 𐑓 𐑩 𐑥𐑴𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑, 𐑕𐑑𐑫𐑛 𐑔𐑷𐑑𐑓𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑲𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑝𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑒𐑹𐑐𐑕 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑥𐑱𐑛.

·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 62. 𐑞 ·𐑛𐑸𐑑.

𐑩 𐑢𐑻𐑛 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼.

𐑩𐑒𐑹𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑺𐑾𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑿𐑕𐑦𐑡 𐑝 𐑞 𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑼𐑦, 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤-𐑚𐑴𐑑 𐑐𐑫𐑖𐑩𐑟 𐑪𐑓 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑟𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑹 𐑢𐑱𐑤-𐑒𐑦𐑤𐑼 𐑨𐑟 𐑑𐑧𐑥𐑐𐑼𐑼𐑦 𐑕𐑑𐑽𐑟𐑥𐑩𐑯, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑽 𐑹 𐑢𐑱𐑤-𐑓𐑭𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑼 𐑐𐑫𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑓𐑹𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑹, 𐑞 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑯𐑴𐑯 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑽-𐑹. 𐑯𐑬 𐑦𐑑 𐑯𐑰𐑛𐑟 𐑩 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑪𐑙, 𐑯𐑻𐑝𐑩𐑕 𐑸𐑥 𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑒 𐑞 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑲𐑼𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑓𐑦𐑖; 𐑓 𐑪𐑓𐑩𐑯, 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑛 𐑩 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑛𐑸𐑑, 𐑞 𐑣𐑧𐑝𐑦 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑦𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑕 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑓𐑤𐑳𐑙 𐑑 𐑞 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑝 𐑑𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑦 𐑹 𐑔𐑻𐑑𐑦 𐑓𐑰𐑑. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑣𐑬𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑐𐑮𐑴𐑤𐑪𐑙𐑛 𐑯 𐑦𐑜𐑟𐑷𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑗𐑱𐑕, 𐑞 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑽 𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑑 𐑐𐑫𐑤 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑹 𐑥𐑰𐑯𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑑 𐑞 𐑳𐑑𐑼𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑; 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑰𐑛, 𐑣𐑰 𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑑 𐑕𐑧𐑑 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑜𐑟𐑭𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑕𐑵𐑐𐑼𐑣𐑿𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑨𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑑 𐑞 𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑑, 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑲 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑮𐑴𐑦𐑙, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑰𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑤𐑬𐑛 𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑧𐑐𐑦𐑛 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑒𐑤𐑩𐑥𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟; 𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑑 𐑒𐑰𐑐 𐑖𐑬𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑑𐑪𐑐 𐑝 𐑢𐑳𐑯'𐑟 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑕, 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑸 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑛 𐑯 𐑣𐑭𐑓 𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑑𐑩𐑛—𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑳𐑯 𐑯𐑴 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑣𐑵 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑛 𐑦𐑑. 𐑓 𐑢𐑳𐑯, 𐑲 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑚𐑷𐑤 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑣𐑸𐑑𐑦𐑤𐑦 𐑯 𐑢𐑻𐑒 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑤𐑩𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑑𐑲𐑥. 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑦𐑙, 𐑚𐑷𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑑, 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑨𐑒 𐑑 𐑞 𐑓𐑦𐑖, 𐑷𐑤 𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑕 𐑞 𐑦𐑜𐑟𐑷𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑽 𐑣𐑽𐑟 𐑞 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑲𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑒𐑮𐑲—“𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑳𐑐, 𐑯 𐑜𐑦𐑝 𐑦𐑑 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥!” 𐑣𐑰 𐑯𐑬 𐑣𐑨𐑕 𐑑 𐑛𐑮𐑪𐑐 𐑯 𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑘𐑫𐑼 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑹, 𐑑𐑻𐑯 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑼 𐑣𐑭𐑓 𐑢𐑱, 𐑕𐑰𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑪𐑗, 𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑧𐑙𐑔 𐑥𐑱 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑱𐑯, 𐑣𐑰 𐑧𐑕𐑱𐑟 𐑑 𐑐𐑦𐑗 𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑣𐑬 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤. 𐑯𐑴 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼, 𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑣𐑴𐑤 𐑓𐑤𐑰𐑑 𐑝 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑓𐑦𐑓𐑑𐑦 𐑓𐑺 𐑗𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑓 𐑩 𐑛𐑸𐑑, 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑓𐑲𐑝 𐑸 𐑕𐑩𐑒𐑕𐑧𐑕𐑓𐑩𐑤; 𐑯𐑴 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑴 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑽𐑟 𐑸 𐑥𐑨𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑯 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑮𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛; 𐑯𐑴 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑝 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑨𐑒𐑗𐑵𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑚𐑤𐑳𐑛-𐑝𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑; 𐑯𐑴 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑸 𐑨𐑚𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑓𐑹 𐑘𐑽𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑓𐑹 𐑚𐑨𐑮𐑩𐑤𐑟; 𐑯𐑴 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑑 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑴𐑯𐑼𐑟, 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑩 𐑤𐑵𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑻𐑯; 𐑓 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑞 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑽 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑱𐑒𐑕 𐑞 𐑝𐑶𐑦𐑡, 𐑯 𐑦𐑓 𐑿 𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑞 𐑚𐑮𐑧𐑔 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦 𐑣𐑬 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑿 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑 𐑑 𐑓𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛!

𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯, 𐑦𐑓 𐑞 𐑛𐑸𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑕𐑩𐑒𐑕𐑧𐑕𐑓𐑩𐑤, 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑧𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑟, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑑𐑕 𐑑 𐑮𐑳𐑯, 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑼 𐑯 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑽 𐑤𐑲𐑒𐑢𐑲𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑑 𐑑 𐑮𐑳𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑹 𐑯 𐑭𐑓𐑑, 𐑑 𐑞 𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑡𐑧𐑐𐑼𐑛𐑦 𐑝 𐑞𐑧𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑝𐑟 𐑯 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑧𐑤𐑕. 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑞𐑱 𐑗𐑱𐑯𐑡 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕𐑩𐑟; 𐑯 𐑞 𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑟𐑥𐑩𐑯, 𐑞 𐑗𐑰𐑓 𐑪𐑓𐑦𐑕𐑼 𐑝 𐑞 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑒𐑮𐑭𐑓𐑑, 𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑕 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑐𐑼 𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑬𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑.

𐑯𐑬, 𐑲 𐑒𐑺 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑣𐑵 𐑥𐑱𐑯𐑑𐑱𐑯𐑟 𐑞 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑺𐑦, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑴𐑔 𐑓𐑵𐑤𐑦𐑖 𐑯 𐑳𐑯𐑯𐑧𐑕𐑦𐑕𐑺𐑦. 𐑞 𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑟𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑕𐑑𐑱 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑬𐑟 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑; 𐑣𐑰 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑚𐑴𐑔 𐑛𐑸𐑑 𐑞 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯 𐑯 𐑞 𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑕, 𐑯 𐑯𐑴 𐑮𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑪𐑑𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑚𐑰 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑧𐑐𐑑 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑕𐑻𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑪𐑚𐑝𐑾𐑕 𐑑 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑼𐑥𐑩𐑯. 𐑲 𐑯𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑪𐑤𐑝 𐑩 𐑕𐑤𐑲𐑑 𐑤𐑪𐑕 𐑝 𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑗𐑱𐑕; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑽𐑾𐑯𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑝𐑺𐑾𐑕 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑝 𐑥𐑹 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑯𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑝𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑥𐑰 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑝𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑥𐑩𐑡𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑝 𐑓𐑱𐑤𐑘𐑼𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑼𐑦, 𐑦𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑥𐑰𐑯𐑟 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑕𐑴 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑛 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑚𐑛 𐑦𐑜𐑟𐑷𐑕𐑗𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑽 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑒𐑷𐑟𐑛 𐑞𐑧𐑥.

𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑖𐑫𐑼 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑛𐑸𐑑, 𐑞 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑽𐑟 𐑝 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑑 𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑓𐑰𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑲𐑛𐑩𐑤𐑯𐑩𐑕, 𐑯 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑑𐑶𐑤.

·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 63. 𐑞 ·𐑒𐑮𐑪𐑗.

𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑙𐑒, 𐑞 𐑚𐑮𐑭𐑯𐑗𐑩𐑟 𐑜𐑮𐑴; 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑞𐑧𐑥, 𐑞 𐑑𐑢𐑦𐑜𐑟. 𐑕𐑴, 𐑦𐑯 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑛𐑳𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑝 𐑕𐑳𐑚𐑡𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑕, 𐑜𐑮𐑴 𐑞 𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼𐑟.

𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑪𐑗 𐑩𐑤𐑵𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑑 𐑪𐑯 𐑩 𐑐𐑮𐑰𐑝𐑾𐑕 𐑐𐑱𐑡 𐑛𐑦𐑟𐑻𐑝𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑯. 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑩 𐑯𐑪𐑗𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑝 𐑩 𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑽 𐑓𐑹𐑥, 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑑𐑵 𐑓𐑰𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑤𐑧𐑙𐑔, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑻𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑼𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑼𐑛 𐑜𐑳𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑯𐑽 𐑞 𐑚𐑬, 𐑓 𐑞 𐑐𐑻𐑐𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑓𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑖𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑓 𐑞 𐑢𐑫𐑛𐑩𐑯 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑧𐑥𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑝 𐑞 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯, 𐑣𐑵𐑟 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑯𐑱𐑒𐑩𐑛, 𐑚𐑸𐑚𐑛 𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑕𐑤𐑴𐑐𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑡𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑕 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑬. 𐑞𐑺𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑢𐑧𐑐𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑑 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑣𐑻𐑤𐑼, 𐑣𐑵 𐑕𐑯𐑨𐑗𐑩𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑳𐑐 𐑨𐑟 𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑦 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑩 𐑚𐑨𐑒𐑢𐑫𐑛𐑟𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑕𐑢𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑮𐑲𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑢𐑷𐑤. 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑳𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑥𐑼𐑦 𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑑𐑵 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑟 𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑴𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑪𐑗, 𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑝𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑛 𐑞 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑯 𐑕𐑧𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑲𐑼𐑯𐑟.

𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑑𐑵 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑟, 𐑰𐑗 𐑚𐑲 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑴𐑯 𐑒𐑹𐑛, 𐑸 𐑚𐑴𐑔 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑤𐑲𐑯; 𐑞 𐑪𐑚𐑡𐑧𐑒𐑑 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑦𐑕: 𐑑 𐑛𐑸𐑑 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑚𐑴𐑔, 𐑦𐑓 𐑐𐑪𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤, 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑞 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑢𐑱𐑤; 𐑕𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑓, 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑛𐑮𐑨𐑜, 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑛𐑮𐑷 𐑬𐑑, 𐑞 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑥𐑱 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑱𐑯 𐑩 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛. 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑩 𐑛𐑳𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑞 𐑗𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑪𐑓𐑩𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑱𐑯𐑾𐑕, 𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑑, 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑝𐑳𐑤𐑕𐑦𐑝 𐑮𐑳𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑰𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑲𐑼𐑯, 𐑦𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑟 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑪𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑓 𐑞 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑽, 𐑣𐑬𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑤𐑲𐑑𐑯𐑦𐑙-𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑵𐑝𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕, 𐑑 𐑐𐑦𐑗 𐑞 𐑕𐑧𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑲𐑼𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑣𐑦𐑥. 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼𐑞𐑩𐑤𐑧𐑕, 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑕𐑧𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑲𐑼𐑯 𐑦𐑟 𐑷𐑤𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑦 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑤𐑲𐑯, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑤𐑲𐑯 𐑦𐑟 𐑮𐑳𐑯𐑦𐑙, 𐑣𐑧𐑯𐑕 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑧𐑐𐑩𐑯 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑, 𐑨𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑦𐑝𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑕, 𐑚𐑰 𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑕𐑦𐑐𐑱𐑑𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑑𐑪𐑕𐑑 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑, 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑣𐑬 𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑢𐑺; 𐑧𐑤𐑕 𐑞 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑑𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑡𐑧𐑐𐑼𐑛𐑦 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑪𐑤𐑝 𐑷𐑤 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟. 𐑑𐑳𐑥𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼, 𐑦𐑑 𐑩𐑒𐑹𐑛𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑒𐑱𐑕𐑩𐑟; 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑺 𐑒𐑶𐑤𐑟 𐑝 𐑚𐑪𐑒𐑕 𐑤𐑲𐑯 (𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑰𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼) 𐑥𐑱𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑓𐑰𐑑, 𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟, 𐑐𐑮𐑵𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑮𐑨𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑨𐑒𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑷𐑤𐑢𐑱𐑟 𐑳𐑯𐑩𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑕𐑨𐑛𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑯 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑓𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑒𐑨𐑠𐑵𐑩𐑤𐑑𐑦𐑟.

𐑓𐑻𐑞𐑼𐑥𐑹: 𐑿 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑯𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑧𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑲𐑼𐑯 𐑦𐑟 𐑔𐑮𐑴𐑯 𐑴𐑝𐑼𐑚𐑹𐑛, 𐑦𐑑 𐑞𐑧𐑯𐑕𐑓𐑹𐑔 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑟 𐑩 𐑛𐑨𐑙𐑜𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙, 𐑖𐑸𐑐-𐑧𐑡𐑛 𐑑𐑧𐑮𐑼, 𐑕𐑒𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑖𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑻𐑝𐑧𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑚𐑴𐑔 𐑚𐑴𐑑 𐑯 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑨𐑙𐑜𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑤𐑲𐑯𐑟, 𐑹 𐑒𐑳𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑧𐑥, 𐑯 𐑥𐑱𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑛𐑦𐑡𐑩𐑕 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑕𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑛𐑦𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟. 𐑯𐑹, 𐑦𐑯 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑤, 𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑐𐑪𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑑 𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑘𐑫𐑼 𐑦𐑑 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯 𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑺𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑗𐑼𐑛 𐑯 𐑩 𐑒𐑹𐑐𐑕.

𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑼, 𐑯𐑬, 𐑣𐑬 𐑦𐑑 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑒𐑱𐑕 𐑝 𐑓𐑹 𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕 𐑷𐑤 𐑦𐑯𐑜𐑱𐑡𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑳𐑯𐑿𐑠𐑵𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑪𐑙, 𐑨𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑝, 𐑯 𐑯𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑱𐑤; 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑨𐑟 𐑢𐑧𐑤 𐑨𐑟 𐑑 𐑞 𐑔𐑬𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑒𐑻𐑦𐑙 𐑨𐑒𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩𐑯 𐑷𐑛𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑕 𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑐𐑮𐑲𐑟, 𐑱𐑑 𐑹 𐑑𐑧𐑯 𐑤𐑵𐑕 𐑕𐑧𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑲𐑼𐑯𐑟 𐑥𐑱 𐑚𐑰 𐑕𐑦𐑥𐑩𐑤𐑑𐑱𐑯𐑾𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑨𐑙𐑜𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥. 𐑓, 𐑝 𐑒𐑹𐑕, 𐑰𐑗 𐑚𐑴𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑩𐑐𐑤𐑲𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑕𐑧𐑝𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑟 𐑑 𐑚𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑪𐑯 𐑑 𐑞 𐑤𐑲𐑯 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑞 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑚𐑰 𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑓𐑧𐑒𐑗𐑵𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑸𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑳𐑝𐑼𐑦. 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑐𐑼𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑼𐑟 𐑸 𐑓𐑱𐑔𐑓𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑯𐑼𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑣𐑽, 𐑨𐑟 𐑞𐑱 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑓𐑱𐑤 𐑑 𐑦𐑤𐑵𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑱𐑑 𐑕𐑧𐑝𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑹𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑, 𐑣𐑬𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑑 𐑐𐑨𐑕𐑦𐑡𐑩𐑟, 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑰𐑯𐑟 𐑣𐑽𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑐𐑱𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛.

·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 64. 𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚'𐑟 ·𐑕𐑳𐑐𐑼.

𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚'𐑟 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑒𐑦𐑤𐑛 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐. 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩 𐑒𐑭𐑥; 𐑕𐑴, 𐑓𐑹𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑥 𐑝 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕, 𐑢𐑰 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑤𐑴 𐑚𐑦𐑟𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑑𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑑𐑮𐑴𐑓𐑦 𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛. 𐑯 𐑯𐑬, 𐑨𐑟 𐑢𐑰 𐑱𐑑𐑰𐑯 𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑬𐑼 𐑔𐑻𐑑𐑦-𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑕 𐑸𐑥𐑟, 𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑛 𐑯 𐑱𐑑𐑦 𐑔𐑳𐑥𐑟 𐑯 𐑓𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑼𐑟, 𐑕𐑤𐑴𐑤𐑦 𐑑𐑶𐑤𐑛 𐑬𐑼 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑬𐑼 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑻𐑑, 𐑕𐑤𐑳𐑜𐑦𐑖 𐑒𐑹𐑐𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑰; 𐑯 𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑣𐑸𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑑 𐑚𐑳𐑡 𐑨𐑑 𐑷𐑤, 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑧𐑐𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑟; 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑧𐑝𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑣𐑽𐑚𐑲 𐑓𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑖𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑹𐑥𐑩𐑕𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑥𐑨𐑕 𐑢𐑰 𐑥𐑵𐑝𐑛. 𐑓, 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑨𐑤 𐑝 ·𐑣𐑨𐑙-·𐑣𐑴, 𐑹 𐑢𐑪𐑑𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑞𐑱 𐑒𐑷𐑤 𐑦𐑑, 𐑦𐑯 ·𐑗𐑲𐑯𐑩, 𐑓𐑹 𐑹 𐑓𐑲𐑝 𐑤𐑱𐑚𐑼𐑼𐑟 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑫𐑑-𐑐𐑭𐑔 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑛𐑮𐑷 𐑩 𐑚𐑳𐑤𐑒𐑦 𐑓𐑮𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑡𐑳𐑙𐑒 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑝 𐑩 𐑥𐑲𐑤 𐑩𐑯 𐑬𐑼; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑜𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑸𐑜𐑩𐑕𐑦 𐑢𐑰 𐑑𐑴𐑛 𐑣𐑧𐑝𐑦𐑤𐑦 𐑓𐑹𐑡𐑛 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑙, 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑓 𐑤𐑱𐑛𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑐𐑦𐑜-𐑤𐑧𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑚𐑳𐑤𐑒.

𐑛𐑸𐑒𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑒𐑱𐑥 𐑪𐑯; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑤𐑲𐑑𐑕 𐑳𐑐 𐑯 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛'𐑟 𐑥𐑱𐑯-𐑮𐑦𐑜𐑦𐑙 𐑛𐑦𐑥𐑤𐑦 𐑜𐑲𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑬𐑼 𐑢𐑱; 𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑛𐑮𐑷𐑦𐑙 𐑯𐑽𐑼 𐑢𐑰 𐑕𐑷 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑛𐑮𐑪𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑕𐑧𐑝𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑥𐑹 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑯𐑟 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑞 𐑚𐑫𐑤𐑢𐑼𐑒𐑕. 𐑝𐑱𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑲𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑣𐑰𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑓 𐑩 𐑥𐑴𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑, 𐑣𐑰 𐑦𐑖𐑿𐑛 𐑞 𐑿𐑠𐑵𐑩𐑤 𐑹𐑛𐑼𐑟 𐑓 𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑑 𐑓 𐑞 𐑯𐑲𐑑, 𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑯 𐑑 𐑩 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑩𐑯, 𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑱 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑒𐑨𐑚𐑦𐑯, 𐑯 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑓𐑹𐑢𐑼𐑛 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯 𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑥𐑹𐑯𐑦𐑙.

𐑞𐑴, 𐑦𐑯 𐑴𐑝𐑼𐑕𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑐𐑼𐑕𐑿𐑑 𐑝 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑱𐑤, ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑳𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑥𐑼𐑦 𐑨𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑑𐑦, 𐑑 𐑒𐑷𐑤 𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑴; 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑯𐑬 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑰𐑗𐑼 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑛𐑧𐑛, 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑝𐑱𐑜 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑕𐑨𐑑𐑦𐑕𐑓𐑨𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯, 𐑹 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑕, 𐑹 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑺, 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑢𐑻𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥; 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑓 𐑞 𐑕𐑲𐑑 𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑛𐑧𐑛 𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑲𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑞𐑨𐑑 ·𐑥𐑪𐑚𐑦 ·𐑛𐑦𐑒 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑕𐑤𐑱𐑯; 𐑯 𐑞𐑴 𐑩 𐑔𐑬𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑚𐑮𐑷𐑑 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑖𐑦𐑐, 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑡𐑪𐑑 𐑩𐑛𐑝𐑭𐑯𐑕 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑜𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑛, 𐑥𐑪𐑯𐑩𐑥𐑱𐑯𐑦𐑨𐑒 𐑪𐑚𐑡𐑧𐑒𐑑. 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑕𐑵𐑯 𐑿 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑔𐑷𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑕𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛'𐑟 𐑛𐑧𐑒𐑕, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑺𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑒𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑼 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑛𐑰𐑐; 𐑓 𐑣𐑧𐑝𐑦 𐑗𐑱𐑯𐑟 𐑸 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑛𐑮𐑨𐑜𐑛 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑒, 𐑯 𐑔𐑮𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑮𐑨𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑐𐑹𐑑-𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑟. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑒𐑤𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑤𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑕, 𐑞 𐑝𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑒𐑹𐑐𐑕 𐑦𐑑𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓, 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐, 𐑦𐑟 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑥𐑫𐑼𐑛. 𐑑𐑲𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑻𐑯, 𐑯 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑑𐑱𐑤 𐑑 𐑞 𐑚𐑬𐑟, 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑯𐑬 𐑤𐑲𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑒 𐑣𐑳𐑤 𐑒𐑤𐑴𐑟 𐑑 𐑞 𐑝𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑤'𐑟 𐑯 𐑕𐑰𐑯 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑞 𐑛𐑸𐑒𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑯𐑲𐑑, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑩𐑚𐑕𐑒𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑛 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑸𐑟 𐑯 𐑮𐑦𐑜𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑓𐑑, 𐑞 𐑑𐑵—𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑯 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑘𐑴𐑒𐑑 𐑑𐑩𐑜𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑕𐑩𐑤 𐑚𐑫𐑤𐑩𐑒𐑕, 𐑢𐑺𐑪𐑝 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑲𐑯𐑟 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑞 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑱𐑯𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙.*

*𐑩 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑥 𐑥𐑱 𐑨𐑟 𐑢𐑧𐑤 𐑚𐑰 𐑮𐑦𐑤𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑣𐑽. 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑪𐑙𐑜𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑯 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑤𐑲𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑥𐑫𐑼𐑛 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑙𐑕𐑲𐑛, 𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑓𐑤𐑵𐑒𐑕 𐑹 𐑑𐑱𐑤; 𐑯 𐑨𐑟 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑𐑼 𐑛𐑧𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑐𐑸𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑮𐑧𐑤𐑩𐑑𐑦𐑝𐑤𐑦 𐑣𐑧𐑝𐑽 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑳𐑞𐑼 (𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑧𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑕𐑲𐑛-𐑓𐑦𐑯𐑟), 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑓𐑤𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑛𐑧𐑔, 𐑒𐑷𐑟𐑩𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑑 𐑕𐑦𐑙𐑒 𐑤𐑴 𐑚𐑦𐑯𐑰𐑔 𐑞 𐑕𐑻𐑓𐑦𐑕; 𐑕𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑿 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑜𐑧𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑, 𐑦𐑯 𐑹𐑛𐑼 𐑑 𐑐𐑫𐑑 𐑞 𐑗𐑱𐑯 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑑. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑛𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑒𐑳𐑤𐑑𐑦 𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑡𐑰𐑯𐑾𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑴𐑝𐑼𐑒𐑳𐑥: 𐑩 𐑕𐑥𐑷𐑤, 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑪𐑙 𐑤𐑲𐑯 𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑺𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑢𐑫𐑛𐑩𐑯 𐑓𐑤𐑴𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑬𐑑𐑼 𐑧𐑯𐑛, 𐑯 𐑩 𐑢𐑱𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑥𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑤, 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑞 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑛 𐑑 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐. 𐑚𐑲 𐑩𐑛𐑮𐑶𐑑 𐑥𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑡𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑞 𐑢𐑫𐑛𐑩𐑯 𐑓𐑤𐑴𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑑 𐑮𐑲𐑟 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑝 𐑞 𐑥𐑨𐑕, 𐑕𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑯𐑬 𐑣𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑜𐑻𐑛𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑞 𐑗𐑱𐑯 𐑦𐑟 𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑦 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑑 𐑓𐑪𐑤𐑴 𐑕𐑵𐑑; 𐑯 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑤𐑦𐑐𐑑 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑞 𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦, 𐑦𐑟 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑤𐑪𐑒𐑑 𐑓𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑞 𐑕𐑥𐑷𐑤𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑐𐑸𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑑𐑱𐑤, 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑐𐑶𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑡𐑳𐑙𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑚𐑮𐑷𐑛 𐑓𐑤𐑵𐑒𐑕 𐑹 𐑤𐑴𐑚𐑟.

𐑦𐑓 𐑥𐑵𐑛𐑦 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑬 𐑷𐑤 𐑒𐑢𐑲𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑕, 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑰𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑴 𐑓𐑸 𐑨𐑟 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑚𐑰 𐑯𐑴𐑯 𐑪𐑯 𐑛𐑧𐑒, ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚, 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑧𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑥𐑱𐑑, 𐑓𐑤𐑳𐑖𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑒𐑪𐑙𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑕𐑑, 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑛 𐑩𐑯 𐑳𐑯𐑿𐑠𐑵𐑩𐑤 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑜𐑫𐑛-𐑯𐑱𐑗𐑼𐑛 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑲𐑑𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑. 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩𐑯 𐑳𐑯𐑢𐑴𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑳𐑕𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑛 ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒, 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑩𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑵𐑐𐑽𐑽, 𐑒𐑢𐑲𐑩𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑓 𐑞 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑞 𐑕𐑴𐑤 𐑥𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑡𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑩𐑓𐑺𐑟. 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑕𐑥𐑷𐑤, 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑒𐑷𐑟 𐑝 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑤𐑲𐑝𐑤𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑦𐑯 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚, 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑵𐑯 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑤𐑦 𐑥𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑓𐑧𐑕𐑑. 𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩 𐑣𐑲 𐑤𐑦𐑝𐑼; 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑥𐑐𐑼𐑩𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑓𐑪𐑯𐑛 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑨𐑟 𐑩 𐑓𐑤𐑱𐑝𐑼𐑦𐑖 𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑨𐑤𐑩𐑑.

“𐑩 𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑒, 𐑩 𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑒, 𐑺 𐑲 𐑕𐑤𐑰𐑐! 𐑿, ·𐑛𐑨𐑜𐑵! 𐑴𐑝𐑼𐑚𐑹𐑛 𐑿 𐑜𐑴, 𐑯 𐑒𐑳𐑑 𐑥𐑰 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑥𐑷𐑤!”

𐑣𐑽 𐑚𐑰 𐑦𐑑 𐑯𐑴𐑯, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑴 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑢𐑲𐑤𐑛 𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑼𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑛𐑵 𐑯𐑪𐑑, 𐑨𐑟 𐑩 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑔𐑦𐑙, 𐑯 𐑩𐑒𐑹𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑥𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑺𐑦 𐑥𐑨𐑒𐑕𐑦𐑥, 𐑥𐑱𐑒 𐑞 𐑧𐑯𐑩𐑥𐑦 𐑛𐑦𐑓𐑮𐑱 𐑞 𐑒𐑳𐑮𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑹 (𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑰𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑮𐑾𐑤𐑲𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑴𐑕𐑰𐑛𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑝𐑶𐑦𐑡), 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑯𐑬 𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑿 𐑓𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑝 𐑞𐑰𐑟 ·𐑯𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑑𐑼𐑟 𐑣𐑵 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑩 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑿𐑦𐑯 𐑮𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑖 𐑓 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑐𐑼𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑼 𐑐𐑸𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑛𐑧𐑟𐑦𐑜𐑯𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑲 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚; 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑮𐑲𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑑𐑱𐑐𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑧𐑥𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑝 𐑞 𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦.

𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑥𐑦𐑛𐑯𐑲𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑒𐑳𐑑 𐑯 𐑒𐑫𐑒𐑑; 𐑯 𐑤𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑑𐑵 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 𐑶𐑤, ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚 𐑕𐑑𐑬𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑑𐑫𐑛 𐑳𐑐 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥𐑩𐑕𐑧𐑑𐑦 𐑕𐑳𐑐𐑼 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯-𐑣𐑧𐑛, 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑓 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑻 𐑩 𐑕𐑲𐑛𐑚𐑹𐑛. 𐑯𐑹 𐑢𐑪𐑟 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚 𐑞 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑢𐑩𐑑𐑼 𐑪𐑯 𐑢𐑱𐑤'𐑟 𐑓𐑤𐑧𐑖 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑯𐑲𐑑. 𐑥𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑺 𐑥𐑳𐑥𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑴𐑯 𐑥𐑨𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟, 𐑔𐑬𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑪𐑯 𐑔𐑬𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑝 𐑖𐑸𐑒𐑕, 𐑕𐑢𐑹𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑛 𐑤𐑩𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑔𐑩𐑯, 𐑕𐑥𐑨𐑒𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑓𐑰𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑪𐑯 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑓𐑨𐑑𐑯𐑩𐑕. 𐑞 𐑓𐑿 𐑕𐑤𐑰𐑐𐑼𐑟 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑴 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑚𐑳𐑙𐑒𐑕 𐑢𐑻 𐑪𐑓𐑩𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑖𐑸𐑐 𐑕𐑤𐑨𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑞𐑺 𐑑𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑞 𐑣𐑳𐑤, 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑓𐑿 𐑦𐑯𐑗𐑩𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑤𐑰𐑐𐑼𐑟' 𐑣𐑸𐑑𐑕. 𐑐𐑽𐑦𐑙 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑞 𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑿 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑡𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑰 𐑞𐑧𐑥 (𐑨𐑟 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑿 𐑣𐑻𐑛 𐑞𐑧𐑥) 𐑢𐑪𐑤𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑤𐑩𐑯, 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑒 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼𐑟, 𐑯 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑪𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑚𐑨𐑒𐑕 𐑨𐑟 𐑞𐑱 𐑕𐑒𐑵𐑐𐑑 𐑬𐑑 𐑣𐑿𐑡 𐑜𐑤𐑪𐑚𐑿𐑤𐑼 𐑐𐑰𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑝 𐑞 𐑚𐑦𐑜𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑩 𐑣𐑿𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑣𐑧𐑛. 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑐𐑼𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑼 𐑓𐑰𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑖𐑸𐑒 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑟 𐑷𐑤 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑥𐑦𐑮𐑨𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑩𐑕. 𐑣𐑬 𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩𐑯 𐑩𐑐𐑨𐑮𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑳𐑯𐑩𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑻𐑓𐑦𐑕, 𐑞𐑱 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑝 𐑑 𐑜𐑬𐑡 𐑬𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑕𐑦𐑥𐑧𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑥𐑬𐑔𐑓𐑫𐑤𐑟, 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑱𐑯𐑟 𐑩 𐑐𐑸𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑿𐑯𐑦𐑝𐑻𐑕𐑩𐑤 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑚𐑤𐑩𐑥 𐑝 𐑷𐑤 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑟. 𐑞 𐑥𐑸𐑒 𐑞𐑱 𐑞𐑳𐑕 𐑤𐑰𐑝 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑥𐑱 𐑚𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑤𐑲𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑑 𐑞 𐑣𐑪𐑤𐑴 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑩 𐑒𐑸𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑼 𐑦𐑯 𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑕𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑓 𐑩 𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑵.

𐑞𐑴 𐑩𐑥𐑦𐑛 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑕𐑥𐑴𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑪𐑮𐑼 𐑯 𐑛𐑲𐑩𐑚𐑪𐑤𐑦𐑟𐑩𐑥 𐑝 𐑩 𐑕𐑰-𐑓𐑲𐑑, 𐑖𐑸𐑒𐑕 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑚𐑰 𐑕𐑰𐑯 𐑤𐑪𐑙𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑜𐑱𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑳𐑐 𐑑 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐'𐑕 𐑛𐑧𐑒𐑕, 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑣𐑳𐑙𐑜𐑮𐑦 𐑛𐑪𐑜𐑟 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑩 𐑑𐑱𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑺 𐑮𐑧𐑛 𐑥𐑰𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑒𐑸𐑝𐑛, 𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑦 𐑑 𐑚𐑴𐑤𐑑 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑒𐑦𐑤𐑛 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑑𐑪𐑕𐑑 𐑑 𐑞𐑧𐑥; 𐑯 𐑞𐑴, 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑞 𐑝𐑨𐑤𐑾𐑯𐑑 𐑚𐑫𐑗𐑼𐑟 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑒-𐑑𐑱𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑸 𐑞𐑳𐑕 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑸𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑰𐑗 𐑳𐑞𐑼'𐑟 𐑤𐑲𐑝 𐑥𐑰𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑒𐑸𐑝𐑦𐑙-𐑯𐑲𐑝𐑟 𐑷𐑤 𐑜𐑦𐑤𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑯 𐑑𐑨𐑕𐑩𐑤𐑛, 𐑞 𐑖𐑸𐑒𐑕, 𐑷𐑤𐑕𐑴, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞𐑺 𐑡𐑵𐑩𐑤-𐑣𐑦𐑤𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑥𐑬𐑞𐑟, 𐑸 𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑮𐑩𐑤𐑕𐑩𐑥𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑸𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑢𐑱 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑞 𐑑𐑱𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑛 𐑥𐑰𐑑; 𐑯 𐑞𐑴, 𐑢𐑻 𐑿 𐑑 𐑑𐑻𐑯 𐑞 𐑣𐑴𐑤 𐑩𐑓𐑺 𐑳𐑐𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑛𐑬𐑯, 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑚𐑰 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑔𐑦𐑙, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑑 𐑕𐑱, 𐑩 𐑖𐑪𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑖𐑸𐑒𐑦𐑖 𐑚𐑦𐑟𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑦𐑯𐑳𐑓 𐑓 𐑷𐑤 𐑐𐑸𐑑𐑦𐑟; 𐑯 𐑞𐑴 𐑖𐑸𐑒𐑕 𐑷𐑤𐑕𐑴 𐑸 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑺𐑾𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑬𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑛𐑼𐑟 𐑝 𐑷𐑤 𐑕𐑤𐑱𐑝 𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑕 𐑒𐑮𐑪𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑞 ·𐑩𐑑𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑒, 𐑕𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑥𐑨𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑦 𐑑𐑮𐑪𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑙𐑕𐑲𐑛, 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑦 𐑦𐑯 𐑒𐑱𐑕 𐑩 𐑐𐑸𐑕𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑟 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑒𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑛 𐑧𐑯𐑦𐑢𐑺, 𐑹 𐑩 𐑛𐑧𐑛 𐑕𐑤𐑱𐑝 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑛𐑰𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑛; 𐑯 𐑞𐑴 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑹 𐑑𐑵 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑕𐑧𐑑 𐑛𐑬𐑯, 𐑑𐑳𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑕𐑧𐑑 𐑑𐑻𐑥𐑟, 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕𐑩𐑟, 𐑯 𐑩𐑒𐑱𐑠𐑩𐑯𐑟, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑖𐑸𐑒𐑕 𐑛𐑵 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑪𐑙𐑜𐑮𐑦𐑜𐑱𐑑, 𐑯 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑤𐑺𐑾𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑓𐑰𐑕𐑑; 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑞𐑺 𐑯𐑴 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑹 𐑩𐑒𐑱𐑠𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑿 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑓𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑯𐑳𐑥𐑚𐑼𐑟, 𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑜𐑱𐑼 𐑹 𐑥𐑹 𐑡𐑴𐑝𐑾𐑤 𐑕𐑐𐑦𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑕, 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑼𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑩 𐑛𐑧𐑛 𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑥𐑫𐑼𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑯𐑲𐑑 𐑑 𐑩 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑰. 𐑦𐑓 𐑿 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑕𐑰𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑲𐑑, 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑕𐑩𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑘𐑹 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑦𐑠𐑩𐑯 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑐𐑮𐑲𐑩𐑑𐑦 𐑝 𐑛𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑤-𐑢𐑻𐑖𐑦𐑐, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑛𐑾𐑯𐑕𐑦 𐑝 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑱𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑤.

𐑚𐑳𐑑, 𐑨𐑟 𐑘𐑧𐑑, ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚 𐑣𐑰𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑞 𐑥𐑳𐑥𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑚𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑢𐑩𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑜𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑪𐑯 𐑕𐑴 𐑯𐑲 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑯𐑴 𐑥𐑹 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑞 𐑖𐑸𐑒𐑕 𐑣𐑰𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑞 𐑕𐑥𐑨𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑴𐑯 𐑧𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑘𐑻𐑾𐑯 𐑤𐑦𐑐𐑕.

“𐑒𐑫𐑒, 𐑒𐑫𐑒!—𐑢𐑺'𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑴𐑤𐑛 ·𐑓𐑤𐑰𐑕?” 𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑧𐑙𐑔, 𐑢𐑲𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑤𐑧𐑜𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑓𐑻𐑞𐑼, 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑓 𐑑 𐑓𐑹𐑥 𐑩 𐑥𐑹 𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑘𐑫𐑼 𐑚𐑱𐑕 𐑓 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑳𐑐𐑼; 𐑯, 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑛𐑸𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑹𐑒 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑛𐑦𐑖, 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑓 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑚𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑕; “𐑒𐑫𐑒, 𐑿 𐑒𐑫𐑒!—𐑕𐑱𐑤 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑱, 𐑒𐑫𐑒!”

𐑞 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑒, 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑣𐑲 𐑜𐑤𐑰 𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑐𐑮𐑰𐑝𐑾𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑬𐑟𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑹𐑥 𐑣𐑨𐑥𐑩𐑒 𐑨𐑑 𐑩 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑳𐑯𐑕𐑰𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑬𐑼, 𐑒𐑱𐑥 𐑖𐑨𐑥𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑜𐑨𐑤𐑦, 𐑓, 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑒𐑕, 𐑞𐑺 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑥𐑨𐑑𐑼 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑰-𐑐𐑨𐑯𐑟, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑣𐑰 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑒𐑰𐑐 𐑢𐑧𐑤 𐑕𐑒𐑬𐑼𐑛 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑐𐑨𐑯𐑟; 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑴𐑤𐑛 ·𐑓𐑤𐑰𐑕, 𐑨𐑟 𐑞𐑱 𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑒𐑱𐑥 𐑖𐑳𐑓𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑯 𐑤𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑙, 𐑩𐑕𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑐 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑑𐑪𐑙𐑟, 𐑢𐑦𐑗, 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑩 𐑒𐑤𐑳𐑥𐑟𐑦 𐑓𐑨𐑖𐑩𐑯, 𐑢𐑻 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑝 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑲𐑼𐑯 𐑣𐑵𐑐𐑕; 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑴𐑤𐑛 ·𐑧𐑚𐑩𐑯𐑦 𐑓𐑤𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑛 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑙, 𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑴𐑚𐑰𐑛𐑾𐑯𐑕 𐑑 𐑞 𐑢𐑻𐑛 𐑝 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑭𐑯𐑛, 𐑒𐑱𐑥 𐑑 𐑩 𐑛𐑧𐑛 𐑕𐑑𐑪𐑐 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑪𐑐𐑩𐑟𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑝 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚'𐑟 𐑕𐑲𐑛𐑚𐑹𐑛; 𐑢𐑧𐑯, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑔 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑓𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑯 𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑑𐑵-𐑤𐑧𐑜𐑩𐑛 𐑒𐑱𐑯, 𐑣𐑰 𐑚𐑴𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑸𐑗𐑑 𐑚𐑨𐑒 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑓𐑻𐑞𐑼 𐑴𐑝𐑼, 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑕𐑲𐑛𐑢𐑱𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑤𐑲𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑧𐑛, 𐑕𐑴 𐑨𐑟 𐑑 𐑚𐑮𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑽 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑐𐑤𐑱.

“𐑒𐑫𐑒,” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚, 𐑮𐑨𐑐𐑦𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑤𐑦𐑓𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑮𐑭𐑞𐑼 𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑦𐑖 𐑥𐑹𐑕𐑩𐑤 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑬𐑔, “𐑛𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑿 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑦𐑟 𐑮𐑭𐑞𐑼 𐑴𐑝𐑼𐑛𐑳𐑯? 𐑿'𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑚𐑰𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑑𐑵 𐑥𐑳𐑗, 𐑒𐑫𐑒; 𐑦𐑑'𐑕 𐑑𐑵 𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑼. 𐑛𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑲 𐑷𐑤𐑢𐑱𐑟 𐑕𐑱 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑜𐑫𐑛, 𐑩 𐑢𐑱𐑤-𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑑𐑳𐑓? 𐑞𐑺 𐑸 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑖𐑸𐑒𐑕 𐑯𐑬 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑞 𐑕𐑲𐑛, 𐑛𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑿 𐑕𐑰 𐑞𐑱 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑓𐑻 𐑦𐑑 𐑑𐑳𐑓 𐑯 𐑮𐑺? 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑩 𐑖𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑦 𐑞𐑱 𐑸 𐑒𐑦𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑳𐑐! 𐑒𐑫𐑒, 𐑜𐑴 𐑯 𐑑𐑷𐑒 𐑑 '𐑩𐑥; 𐑑𐑧𐑤 '𐑩𐑥 𐑞𐑱 𐑸 𐑢𐑧𐑤𐑒𐑩𐑥 𐑑 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑐 𐑞𐑧𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑝𐑟 𐑕𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑤𐑦, 𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑪𐑛𐑼𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞𐑱 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑒𐑰𐑐 𐑒𐑢𐑲𐑩𐑑. 𐑚𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑥𐑰, 𐑦𐑓 𐑲 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑣𐑽 𐑥𐑲 𐑴𐑯 𐑝𐑶𐑕. 𐑩𐑢𐑱, 𐑒𐑫𐑒, 𐑯 𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑝𐑼 𐑥𐑲 𐑥𐑧𐑕𐑦𐑡. 𐑣𐑽, 𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑯,” 𐑕𐑯𐑨𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑲𐑛𐑚𐑹𐑛; “𐑯𐑬 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑜𐑴 𐑯 𐑐𐑮𐑰𐑗 𐑑 '𐑩𐑥!”

𐑕𐑳𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑪𐑓𐑼𐑛 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑯, 𐑴𐑤𐑛 ·𐑓𐑤𐑰𐑕 𐑤𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑑 𐑩𐑒𐑮𐑪𐑕 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑒 𐑑 𐑞 𐑚𐑫𐑤𐑢𐑼𐑒𐑕; 𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑛𐑮𐑪𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑤𐑲𐑑 𐑤𐑴 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑞 𐑕𐑰, 𐑕𐑴 𐑨𐑟 𐑑 𐑜𐑧𐑑 𐑩 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑝𐑿 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑪𐑙𐑜𐑮𐑦𐑜𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑪𐑤𐑩𐑥𐑤𐑦 𐑓𐑤𐑳𐑮𐑦𐑖𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑑𐑪𐑙𐑟, 𐑯 𐑤𐑰𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑸 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑞 𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑥𐑳𐑥𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑝𐑶𐑕 𐑚𐑦𐑜𐑨𐑯 𐑩𐑛𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑖𐑸𐑒𐑕, 𐑢𐑲𐑤 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚, 𐑕𐑪𐑓𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑮𐑷𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑦𐑣𐑲𐑯𐑛, 𐑴𐑝𐑼𐑣𐑻𐑛 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑧𐑛.

“𐑓𐑧𐑤𐑴-𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑼𐑟: ·𐑲'𐑟 𐑹𐑛𐑼𐑛 𐑣𐑽 𐑑 𐑕𐑱 𐑛𐑨𐑑 𐑿 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑪𐑐 𐑛𐑨𐑑 𐑛𐑨𐑥 𐑯𐑶𐑟 𐑛𐑺. 𐑿 𐑣𐑽? 𐑕𐑑𐑪𐑐 𐑛𐑨𐑑 𐑛𐑨𐑥 𐑕𐑥𐑨𐑒𐑦𐑯' 𐑪𐑚 𐑛𐑦 𐑤𐑦𐑐! ·𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑩 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚 𐑕𐑱 𐑛𐑨𐑑 𐑿 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑓𐑦𐑤 𐑘𐑹 𐑛𐑨𐑥 𐑚𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑟 𐑳𐑐 𐑑 𐑛𐑦 𐑣𐑨𐑗𐑦𐑙𐑟, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑚𐑲 ·𐑜𐑹! 𐑿 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑪𐑐 𐑛𐑨𐑑 𐑛𐑨𐑥 𐑮𐑨𐑒𐑩𐑑!”

“𐑒𐑫𐑒,” 𐑣𐑽 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑐𐑴𐑟𐑛 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚, 𐑩𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑢𐑻𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑕𐑳𐑛𐑩𐑯 𐑕𐑤𐑨𐑐 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑖𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑼,—“𐑒𐑫𐑒! 𐑢𐑲, 𐑛𐑨𐑥 𐑘𐑹 𐑲𐑟, 𐑿 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑕𐑢𐑺 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑱 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑿'𐑼 𐑐𐑮𐑰𐑗𐑦𐑙. 𐑞𐑨𐑑'𐑕 𐑯𐑴 𐑢𐑱 𐑑 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑝𐑻𐑑 𐑕𐑦𐑯𐑼𐑟, 𐑒𐑫𐑒!”

“𐑣𐑵 𐑛𐑨𐑑? 𐑛𐑧𐑯 𐑐𐑮𐑰𐑗 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑘𐑹𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓,” 𐑕𐑳𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑜𐑴.

“𐑯𐑴, 𐑒𐑫𐑒; 𐑜𐑴 𐑪𐑯, 𐑜𐑴 𐑪𐑯.”

“𐑢𐑧𐑤, 𐑛𐑧𐑯, ·𐑚𐑧𐑤𐑳𐑚𐑛 𐑓𐑧𐑤𐑴-𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑼𐑟:”—

“𐑮𐑲𐑑!” 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑒𐑤𐑱𐑥𐑛 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚, 𐑩𐑐𐑮𐑵𐑝𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦, “𐑒𐑴𐑒𐑕 '𐑩𐑥 𐑑 𐑦𐑑; 𐑑𐑮𐑲 𐑞𐑨𐑑,” 𐑯 ·𐑓𐑤𐑰𐑕 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑿𐑛.

“𐑛𐑵 𐑿 𐑦𐑟 𐑷𐑤 𐑖𐑸𐑒𐑕, 𐑯 𐑚𐑲 𐑯𐑭𐑑𐑫𐑼 𐑢𐑻𐑦 𐑢𐑹𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑕, 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑲 ·𐑟𐑱 𐑑 𐑿, 𐑓𐑧𐑤𐑴-𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑼𐑟, 𐑛𐑨𐑑 𐑛𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑹𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑕𐑯𐑩𐑕—'𐑑𐑪𐑐 𐑛𐑨𐑑 𐑛𐑨𐑥 𐑕𐑤𐑨𐑐𐑦𐑯' 𐑪𐑚 𐑛𐑦 𐑑𐑱𐑤! 𐑣𐑬 𐑿 𐑑𐑦𐑙𐑒 𐑑 𐑣𐑽, 𐑕𐑐𐑴𐑟 𐑿 𐑒𐑰𐑐 𐑳𐑐 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩 𐑛𐑨𐑥 𐑕𐑤𐑨𐑐𐑦𐑯' 𐑯 𐑚𐑲𐑑𐑦𐑯' 𐑛𐑺?”

“𐑒𐑫𐑒,” 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚, 𐑒𐑪𐑤𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑥, “𐑲 𐑢𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑢𐑺𐑦𐑙. 𐑑𐑷𐑒 𐑑 '𐑩𐑥 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑦.”

𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑕 𐑥𐑹 𐑞 𐑕𐑻𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑐𐑮𐑴𐑕𐑰𐑛𐑩𐑛.

“𐑘𐑹 𐑢𐑹𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑕𐑯𐑩𐑕, 𐑓𐑧𐑤𐑴-𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑼𐑟, 𐑲 𐑛𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑚𐑤𐑱𐑥 𐑘𐑰 𐑕𐑴 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑓; 𐑛𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑭𐑑𐑫𐑼, 𐑯 𐑒𐑭𐑯𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑐𐑑; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑑 𐑜𐑪𐑚𐑼𐑯 𐑛𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑛 𐑯𐑭𐑑𐑫𐑼, 𐑛𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑛𐑦 𐑐𐑲𐑯𐑑. 𐑿 𐑦𐑟 𐑖𐑸𐑒𐑕, 𐑕𐑸𐑑𐑦𐑯; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑓 𐑿 𐑜𐑪𐑚𐑼𐑯 𐑛𐑦 𐑖𐑸𐑒 𐑦𐑯 𐑿, 𐑢𐑲 𐑛𐑧𐑯 𐑿 𐑚𐑰 𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑩𐑤; 𐑓 𐑷𐑤 𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑'𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑹 𐑛𐑨𐑯 𐑛𐑦 𐑖𐑸𐑒 𐑢𐑧𐑤 𐑜𐑪𐑚𐑼𐑯𐑛. 𐑯𐑬, 𐑤𐑫𐑒 𐑣𐑽, 𐑚𐑮𐑧𐑛'𐑼𐑩𐑯, 𐑡𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑑𐑮𐑲 𐑢𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 ·𐑕𐑦𐑚𐑦𐑤, 𐑩 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑘𐑹𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑚𐑕 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑛𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑤. 𐑛𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑑𐑺𐑦𐑯' 𐑛𐑦 𐑚𐑤𐑳𐑚𐑼 𐑬𐑑 𐑘𐑹 𐑯𐑱𐑚𐑼'𐑟 𐑥𐑬𐑑, 𐑲 𐑕𐑱. 𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑖𐑸𐑒 𐑛𐑵𐑛 𐑮𐑲𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑑𐑪𐑛𐑼 𐑑 𐑛𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑤? 𐑯, 𐑚𐑲 ·𐑜𐑹, 𐑯𐑳𐑯 𐑪𐑯 𐑿 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑛𐑦 𐑮𐑲𐑑 𐑑 𐑛𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑤; 𐑛𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑧𐑤𐑕. 𐑲 𐑯𐑴 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑴' 𐑿 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑚𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑚𐑮𐑦𐑜 𐑥𐑬𐑑, 𐑚𐑮𐑦𐑜𐑼 𐑛𐑨𐑯 𐑴𐑛𐑼𐑟; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑛𐑧𐑯 𐑛𐑦 𐑚𐑮𐑦𐑜 𐑥𐑬𐑑𐑕 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑛𐑦 𐑕𐑥𐑷𐑤 𐑚𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑟; 𐑕𐑴 𐑛𐑨𐑑 𐑛𐑦 𐑚𐑮𐑦𐑜𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑛𐑦 𐑥𐑬𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑑 ·𐑕𐑢𐑷𐑤𐑼 ·𐑢𐑦𐑛, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑑 𐑪𐑓 𐑛𐑦 𐑚𐑤𐑳𐑚𐑼 𐑓 𐑛𐑦 𐑕𐑥𐑷𐑤 𐑓𐑮𐑲 𐑪𐑚 𐑖𐑸𐑒𐑕, 𐑛𐑨𐑑 𐑒𐑭𐑯𐑑 𐑜𐑧𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑛𐑦 𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑵𐑡 𐑑 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑐 𐑛𐑧𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑝𐑟.”

“𐑢𐑧𐑤 𐑛𐑳𐑯, 𐑴𐑤𐑛 ·𐑓𐑤𐑰𐑕!” 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚, “𐑞𐑨𐑑'𐑕 ·𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑦; 𐑜𐑴 𐑪𐑯.”

“𐑯𐑴 𐑿𐑕 𐑜𐑴𐑦𐑯' 𐑪𐑯; 𐑛𐑦 𐑛𐑨𐑥 𐑢𐑦𐑤𐑱𐑯𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑒𐑰𐑐 𐑩 𐑕𐑒𐑴𐑳𐑜𐑦𐑯' 𐑯 𐑕𐑤𐑨𐑐𐑦𐑯' 𐑰𐑗 𐑴𐑛𐑼, ·𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑩 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚; 𐑛𐑱 𐑛𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑣𐑽 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑢𐑻𐑛; 𐑯𐑴 𐑿𐑕 𐑩-𐑐𐑮𐑰𐑗𐑦𐑯' 𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑛𐑨𐑥 𐑜'𐑳𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑨𐑟 𐑿 𐑒𐑷𐑤 '𐑩𐑥, 𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑛𐑺 𐑚𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑫𐑤, 𐑯 𐑛𐑺 𐑚𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑪𐑑𐑩𐑥𐑤𐑩𐑕; 𐑯 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑛𐑱 𐑛𐑵 𐑜𐑧𐑑 '𐑩𐑥 𐑓𐑫𐑤, 𐑛𐑱 𐑢𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑣𐑽 𐑿 𐑛𐑧𐑯; 𐑓 𐑛𐑧𐑯 𐑛𐑱 𐑕𐑦𐑙𐑒 𐑦𐑯 𐑛𐑦 𐑕𐑰, 𐑜𐑴 𐑓𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑑 𐑕𐑤𐑰𐑐 𐑪𐑯 𐑛𐑦 𐑒𐑪𐑮𐑩𐑤, 𐑯 𐑒𐑭𐑯𐑑 𐑣𐑽 𐑯𐑪𐑑'𐑦𐑙 𐑨𐑑 𐑷𐑤, 𐑯𐑴 𐑥𐑹, 𐑓 ·𐑧𐑚𐑼 𐑯 ·𐑧𐑚𐑼.”

“𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑥𐑲 𐑕𐑴𐑤, 𐑲 𐑨𐑥 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑩𐑐𐑦𐑯𐑘𐑩𐑯; 𐑕𐑴 𐑜𐑦𐑝 𐑞 𐑚𐑧𐑯𐑦𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯, ·𐑓𐑤𐑰𐑕, 𐑯 𐑲'𐑤 𐑩𐑢𐑱 𐑑 𐑥𐑲 𐑕𐑳𐑐𐑼.”

𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕, ·𐑓𐑤𐑰𐑕, 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑴𐑔 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑞 𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑦 𐑥𐑪𐑚, 𐑮𐑱𐑟𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑖𐑮𐑦𐑤 𐑝𐑶𐑕, 𐑯 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛—

“𐑒𐑳𐑕𐑩𐑛 𐑓𐑧𐑤𐑴-𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑼𐑟! 𐑒𐑦𐑒 𐑳𐑐 𐑛𐑦 𐑛𐑨𐑥𐑛𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑮𐑴 𐑨𐑟 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑿 𐑒𐑨𐑯; 𐑓𐑦𐑤 𐑘𐑹 𐑛𐑨𐑥' 𐑚𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑟 '𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑛𐑱 𐑚𐑳𐑕𐑑—𐑯 𐑛𐑧𐑯 𐑛𐑲.”

“𐑯𐑬, 𐑒𐑫𐑒,” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚, 𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑿𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑳𐑐𐑼 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯; “𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑡𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑢𐑺 𐑿 𐑕𐑑𐑫𐑛 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹, 𐑞𐑺, 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑥𐑰, 𐑯 𐑐𐑱 𐑐𐑼𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑼 𐑩𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑯.”

“𐑷𐑤 𐑛𐑧𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑯,” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 ·𐑓𐑤𐑰𐑕, 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑵𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑑𐑪𐑙𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑛𐑦𐑟𐑲𐑼𐑛 𐑐𐑩𐑟𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯.

“𐑢𐑧𐑤,” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚, 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑓𐑮𐑰𐑤𐑦 𐑥𐑰𐑯𐑢𐑲𐑤; “𐑲 𐑖𐑨𐑤 𐑯𐑬 𐑜𐑴 𐑚𐑨𐑒 𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑚𐑡𐑧𐑒𐑑 𐑝 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑒. 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕, 𐑣𐑬 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑸 𐑿, 𐑒𐑫𐑒?”

“𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑛𐑨𐑑 𐑛𐑵 ·𐑢𐑦𐑛 𐑛𐑦 '𐑑𐑰𐑒,” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑞 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑒, 𐑑𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤𐑦.

“𐑕𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑕! 𐑣𐑬 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑸 𐑿, 𐑒𐑫𐑒?”

“'𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑯𐑲𐑯𐑑𐑦, 𐑛𐑱 𐑕𐑱,” 𐑣𐑰 𐑜𐑤𐑵𐑥𐑦𐑤𐑦 𐑥𐑳𐑑𐑼𐑛.

“𐑯 𐑿 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑤𐑦𐑝𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛 𐑣𐑸𐑛 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑛 𐑘𐑽𐑟, 𐑒𐑫𐑒, 𐑯 𐑛𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑯𐑴 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑣𐑬 𐑑 𐑒𐑫𐑒 𐑩 𐑢𐑱𐑤-𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑒?” 𐑮𐑨𐑐𐑦𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑴𐑤𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑯𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑥𐑬𐑔𐑓𐑫𐑤 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑢𐑻𐑛, 𐑕𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑹𐑕𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑩 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑿𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑕𐑗𐑩𐑯. “𐑢𐑺 𐑢𐑻 𐑿 𐑚𐑹𐑯, 𐑒𐑫𐑒?”

“'𐑣𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑛𐑦 𐑣𐑨𐑗𐑢𐑱, 𐑦𐑯 𐑓𐑧𐑮𐑦-𐑚𐑴𐑑, 𐑜𐑴𐑦𐑯' 𐑴𐑚𐑼 𐑛𐑦 ·𐑮𐑴𐑯𐑴𐑒.”

“𐑚𐑹𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑓𐑧𐑮𐑦-𐑚𐑴𐑑! 𐑞𐑨𐑑'𐑕 𐑒𐑢𐑽, 𐑑𐑵. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑲 𐑢𐑪𐑯𐑑 𐑑 𐑯𐑴 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑒𐑳𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑦 𐑿 𐑢𐑻 𐑚𐑹𐑯 𐑦𐑯, 𐑒𐑫𐑒!”

“𐑛𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑲 𐑕𐑱 𐑛𐑦 ·𐑮𐑴𐑯𐑴𐑒 𐑒𐑳𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑦?” 𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 𐑖𐑸𐑐𐑤𐑦.

“𐑯𐑴, 𐑿 𐑛𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑑, 𐑒𐑫𐑒; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑲'𐑤 𐑑𐑧𐑤 𐑿 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑲'𐑥 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑑, 𐑒𐑫𐑒. 𐑿 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑜𐑴 𐑣𐑴𐑥 𐑯 𐑚𐑰 𐑚𐑹𐑯 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯; 𐑿 𐑛𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑯𐑴 𐑣𐑬 𐑑 𐑒𐑫𐑒 𐑩 𐑢𐑱𐑤-𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑘𐑧𐑑.”

“·𐑚𐑮𐑰𐑧𐑕 𐑥𐑲 𐑕𐑴𐑤, 𐑦𐑓 𐑲 𐑒𐑫𐑒 𐑯𐑴𐑛𐑼 𐑢𐑳𐑯,” 𐑣𐑰 𐑜𐑮𐑬𐑤𐑛, 𐑨𐑙𐑜𐑮𐑦𐑤𐑦, 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑐𐑸𐑑.

“𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑚𐑨𐑒, 𐑒𐑫𐑒;—𐑣𐑽, 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑥𐑰 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑑𐑪𐑙𐑟;—𐑯𐑬 𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑑 𐑝 𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑞𐑺, 𐑯 𐑑𐑧𐑤 𐑥𐑰 𐑦𐑓 𐑿 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑒𐑫𐑒𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑚𐑰? 𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑦𐑑, 𐑲 𐑕𐑱”—𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑑𐑪𐑙𐑟 𐑑𐑩𐑢𐑹𐑛𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑥—“𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑦𐑑, 𐑯 𐑑𐑱𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑑.”

𐑓𐑱𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑥𐑨𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑼𐑛 𐑤𐑦𐑐𐑕 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑦𐑑 𐑓 𐑩 𐑥𐑴𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑, 𐑞 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑯𐑰𐑜𐑮𐑴 𐑥𐑳𐑑𐑼𐑛, “𐑚𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑒𐑫𐑒𐑑 '𐑑𐑰𐑒 𐑲 ·𐑧𐑚𐑼 𐑑𐑱𐑕𐑑; ·𐑡𐑵𐑟𐑦, 𐑚𐑧𐑮𐑦 ·𐑡𐑵𐑟𐑦.”

“𐑒𐑫𐑒,” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚, 𐑕𐑒𐑢𐑺𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑕 𐑥𐑹; “𐑛𐑵 𐑿 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑑 𐑞 𐑗𐑻𐑗?”

“𐑐𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑕 𐑦𐑯 ·𐑒𐑱𐑐-·𐑛𐑬𐑯,” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑞 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑦.

“𐑯 𐑿 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑘𐑹 𐑤𐑲𐑓 𐑐𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑩 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑦 𐑗𐑻𐑗 𐑦𐑯 ·𐑒𐑱𐑐-·𐑑𐑬𐑯, 𐑢𐑺 𐑿 𐑛𐑬𐑑𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑴𐑝𐑼𐑣𐑻𐑛 𐑩 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑸𐑟𐑩𐑯 𐑩𐑛𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑽𐑼𐑟 𐑨𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑳𐑝𐑩𐑛 𐑓𐑧𐑤𐑴-𐑒𐑮𐑰𐑗𐑼𐑟, 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑿, 𐑒𐑫𐑒! 𐑯 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑿 𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑣𐑽, 𐑯 𐑑𐑧𐑤 𐑥𐑰 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩 𐑛𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑤𐑲 𐑨𐑟 𐑿 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑡𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑯𐑬, 𐑱?” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚. “𐑢𐑺 𐑛𐑵 𐑿 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑 𐑑 𐑜𐑴 𐑑, 𐑒𐑫𐑒?”

“𐑜𐑴 𐑑 𐑚𐑧𐑛 𐑚𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑕𐑵𐑯,” 𐑣𐑰 𐑥𐑳𐑥𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑛, 𐑣𐑭𐑓-𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑨𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑐𐑴𐑒.

“𐑩𐑝𐑭𐑕𐑑! 𐑣𐑰𐑝 𐑑! 𐑲 𐑥𐑰𐑯 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑿 𐑛𐑲, 𐑒𐑫𐑒. 𐑦𐑑'𐑕 𐑩𐑯 𐑷𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑕𐑗𐑩𐑯. 𐑯𐑬 𐑢𐑪𐑑'𐑕 𐑘𐑹 𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑼?”

“𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑛𐑦𐑕 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑚𐑮𐑨𐑒 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑛𐑲𐑟,” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑞 𐑯𐑰𐑜𐑮𐑴 𐑕𐑤𐑴𐑤𐑦, 𐑗𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑴𐑤 𐑺 𐑯 𐑛𐑦𐑥𐑰𐑯𐑼, “𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑦𐑟𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑢𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑜𐑴 𐑯𐑴𐑢𐑺; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑥 ·𐑚𐑮𐑰𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑯 𐑓𐑧𐑗 𐑣𐑦𐑥.”

“𐑓𐑧𐑗 𐑣𐑦𐑥? 𐑣𐑬? 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑒𐑴𐑗 𐑯 𐑓𐑹, 𐑨𐑟 𐑞𐑱 𐑓𐑧𐑗𐑑 ·𐑦𐑤𐑲𐑡𐑩? 𐑯 𐑓𐑧𐑗 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑢𐑺?”

“𐑳𐑐 𐑛𐑸,” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 ·𐑓𐑤𐑰𐑕, 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑑𐑪𐑙𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑧𐑛, 𐑯 𐑒𐑰𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑕𐑪𐑤𐑩𐑥𐑤𐑦.

“𐑕𐑴, 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑿 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑 𐑑 𐑜𐑴 𐑳𐑐 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑬𐑼 𐑥𐑱𐑯-𐑑𐑪𐑐, 𐑛𐑵 𐑿, 𐑒𐑫𐑒, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑿 𐑸 𐑛𐑧𐑛? 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑛𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑿 𐑯𐑴 𐑞 𐑣𐑲𐑼 𐑿 𐑒𐑤𐑲𐑥, 𐑞 𐑒𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑼 𐑦𐑑 𐑜𐑧𐑑𐑕? 𐑥𐑱𐑯-𐑑𐑪𐑐, 𐑱?”

“𐑛𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑕𐑱 𐑛𐑨𐑑 𐑑'𐑷𐑤,” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 ·𐑓𐑤𐑰𐑕, 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑤𐑒𐑕.

“𐑿 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑳𐑐 𐑞𐑺, 𐑛𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑿? 𐑯 𐑯𐑬 𐑤𐑫𐑒 𐑘𐑹𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓, 𐑯 𐑕𐑰 𐑢𐑺 𐑘𐑹 𐑑𐑪𐑙𐑟 𐑸 𐑐𐑶𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑙. 𐑚𐑳𐑑, 𐑐𐑼𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑕 𐑿 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑 𐑑 𐑜𐑧𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑣𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑚𐑲 𐑒𐑮𐑷𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑞 𐑤𐑳𐑚𐑼'𐑟 𐑣𐑴𐑤, 𐑒𐑫𐑒; 𐑚𐑳𐑑, 𐑯𐑴, 𐑯𐑴, 𐑒𐑫𐑒, 𐑿 𐑛𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑜𐑧𐑑 𐑞𐑺, 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑧𐑐𐑑 𐑿 𐑜𐑴 𐑞 𐑮𐑧𐑜𐑿𐑤𐑼 𐑢𐑱, 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑮𐑦𐑜𐑦𐑙. 𐑦𐑑'𐑕 𐑩 𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑖 𐑚𐑦𐑟𐑯𐑩𐑕, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑛𐑳𐑯, 𐑹 𐑧𐑤𐑕 𐑦𐑑'𐑕 𐑯𐑴 𐑜𐑴. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑯𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑳𐑕 𐑸 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑘𐑧𐑑. 𐑛𐑮𐑪𐑐 𐑘𐑹 𐑑𐑪𐑙𐑟, 𐑒𐑫𐑒, 𐑯 𐑣𐑽 𐑥𐑲 𐑹𐑛𐑼𐑟. 𐑛𐑵 𐑘𐑰 𐑣𐑽? 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑘𐑹 𐑣𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛, 𐑯 𐑒𐑤𐑨𐑐 𐑑𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑩'𐑑𐑪𐑐 𐑝 𐑘𐑹 𐑣𐑸𐑑, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑲'𐑥 𐑜𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑲 𐑹𐑛𐑼𐑟, 𐑒𐑫𐑒. 𐑢𐑪𐑑! 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑘𐑹 𐑣𐑸𐑑, 𐑞𐑺?—𐑞𐑨𐑑'𐑕 𐑘𐑹 𐑜𐑦𐑟𐑼𐑛! 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑓𐑑! 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑓𐑑!—𐑞𐑨𐑑'𐑕 𐑦𐑑—𐑯𐑬 𐑿 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑦𐑑. 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑦𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑯𐑬, 𐑯 𐑐𐑱 𐑩𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑯.”

“𐑷𐑤 '𐑛𐑧𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑯,” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑞 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑒, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑔 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑛𐑦𐑟𐑲𐑼𐑛, 𐑝𐑱𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑦𐑜𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑜𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑣𐑧𐑛, 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑓 𐑑 𐑜𐑧𐑑 𐑚𐑴𐑔 𐑽𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑳𐑯𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑑𐑲𐑥.

“𐑢𐑧𐑤 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑒𐑫𐑒, 𐑿 𐑕𐑰 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑱𐑤-𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑝 𐑘𐑹𐑟 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑴 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑚𐑨𐑛, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑐𐑫𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑕𐑲𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑕𐑵𐑯 𐑨𐑟 𐑐𐑪𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤; 𐑿 𐑕𐑰 𐑞𐑨𐑑, 𐑛𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑿? 𐑢𐑧𐑤, 𐑓 𐑞 𐑓𐑿𐑗𐑼, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑿 𐑒𐑫𐑒 𐑩𐑯𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑢𐑱𐑤-𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑓 𐑥𐑲 𐑐𐑮𐑲𐑝𐑩𐑑 𐑑𐑱𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑣𐑽, 𐑞 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯, 𐑲'𐑤 𐑑𐑧𐑤 𐑿 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑑 𐑛𐑵 𐑕𐑴 𐑨𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑑 𐑕𐑐𐑶𐑤 𐑦𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑴𐑝𐑼𐑛𐑵𐑦𐑙. 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛, 𐑯 𐑖𐑴 𐑩 𐑤𐑲𐑝 𐑒𐑴𐑤 𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑳𐑞𐑼; 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑛𐑳𐑯, 𐑛𐑦𐑖 𐑦𐑑; 𐑛'𐑘𐑰 𐑣𐑽? 𐑯 𐑯𐑬 𐑑-𐑥𐑪𐑮𐑴, 𐑒𐑫𐑒, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑢𐑰 𐑸 𐑒𐑳𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑦𐑖, 𐑚𐑰 𐑖𐑫𐑼 𐑿 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑑 𐑜𐑧𐑑 𐑞 𐑑𐑦𐑐𐑕 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑦𐑯𐑟; 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑐𐑫𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤. 𐑨𐑟 𐑓 𐑞 𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑓𐑤𐑵𐑒𐑕, 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑕𐑬𐑕𐑑, 𐑒𐑫𐑒. 𐑞𐑺, 𐑯𐑬 𐑘𐑰 𐑥𐑱 𐑜𐑴.”

𐑚𐑳𐑑 ·𐑓𐑤𐑰𐑕 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑣𐑸𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑜𐑪𐑑 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑐𐑱𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑪𐑓, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑛.

“𐑒𐑫𐑒, 𐑜𐑦𐑝 𐑥𐑰 𐑒𐑳𐑑𐑤𐑩𐑑𐑕 𐑓 𐑕𐑳𐑐𐑼 𐑑-𐑥𐑪𐑮𐑴 𐑯𐑲𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑥𐑦𐑛-𐑢𐑪𐑗. ·𐑛'𐑘𐑰 𐑣𐑽? 𐑩𐑢𐑱 𐑿 𐑕𐑱𐑤, 𐑞𐑧𐑯.—𐑣𐑩𐑤𐑴! 𐑕𐑑𐑪𐑐! 𐑥𐑱𐑒 𐑩 𐑚𐑬 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑿 𐑜𐑴.—𐑩𐑝𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑰𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯! 𐑢𐑱𐑤-𐑚𐑷𐑤𐑟 𐑓 𐑚𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑓𐑩𐑕𐑑—𐑛𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑓𐑼𐑜𐑧𐑑.”

“𐑢𐑦𐑖, 𐑚𐑲 ·𐑜𐑹! 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑰𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥, '𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑛 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑰𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑤. 𐑲'𐑥 ·𐑚𐑮𐑰𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑓 𐑣𐑰 𐑱𐑯𐑑 𐑥𐑹 𐑝 𐑖𐑸𐑒 𐑛𐑨𐑯 ·𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑩 ·𐑖𐑸𐑒 𐑣𐑦𐑟𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓,” 𐑥𐑳𐑑𐑼𐑛 𐑞 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑥𐑨𐑯, 𐑤𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑢𐑱; 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑕𐑱𐑡 𐑦𐑡𐑨𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑥𐑩𐑒.

·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 65. 𐑞 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑨𐑟 𐑩 ·𐑛𐑦𐑖.

𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑹𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑓𐑰𐑛 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑰𐑗𐑼 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑓𐑰𐑛𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑤𐑨𐑥𐑐, 𐑯, 𐑤𐑲𐑒 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚, 𐑰𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑚𐑲 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑴𐑯 𐑤𐑲𐑑, 𐑨𐑟 𐑿 𐑥𐑱 𐑕𐑱; 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑟 𐑕𐑴 𐑬𐑑𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑖 𐑩 𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑯𐑰𐑛𐑟 𐑜𐑴 𐑩 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑦 𐑯 𐑓𐑦𐑤𐑪𐑕𐑩𐑓𐑦 𐑝 𐑦𐑑.

𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑹𐑛, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑗𐑼𐑦𐑟 𐑩𐑜𐑴 𐑞 𐑑𐑳𐑙 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑮𐑲𐑑 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑩 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑛𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑕𐑦 𐑦𐑯 ·𐑓𐑮𐑭𐑯𐑕, 𐑯 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑭𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑤𐑸𐑡 𐑐𐑮𐑲𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑞𐑺. 𐑷𐑤𐑕𐑴, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑯 ·𐑣𐑧𐑯𐑮𐑦 VIIIth's 𐑑𐑲𐑥, 𐑩 𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑒𐑫𐑒 𐑝 𐑞 𐑒𐑹𐑑 𐑩𐑚𐑑𐑱𐑯𐑛 𐑩 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑕𐑩𐑥 𐑮𐑦𐑢𐑹𐑛 𐑓 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑯 𐑨𐑛𐑥𐑼𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑷𐑕 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑰𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑚𐑸𐑚𐑩𐑒𐑘𐑵𐑛 𐑐𐑹𐑐𐑩𐑕𐑩𐑟, 𐑢𐑦𐑗, 𐑿 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑧𐑥𐑚𐑼, 𐑸 𐑩 𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑖𐑰𐑟 𐑝 𐑢𐑱𐑤. 𐑐𐑹𐑐𐑩𐑕𐑩𐑟, 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑰𐑛, 𐑸 𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑛𐑱 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑼𐑛 𐑓𐑲𐑯 𐑰𐑑𐑦𐑙. 𐑞 𐑥𐑰𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑚𐑷𐑤𐑟 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑲𐑟 𐑝 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑘𐑼𐑛 𐑚𐑷𐑤𐑟, 𐑯 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑧𐑤 𐑕𐑰𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑯 𐑕𐑐𐑲𐑕𐑑 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑓 𐑑𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑤-𐑚𐑷𐑤𐑟 𐑹 𐑝𐑰𐑤 𐑚𐑷𐑤𐑟. 𐑞 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑥𐑳𐑙𐑒𐑕 𐑝 ·𐑛𐑳𐑯𐑓𐑻𐑥𐑤𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑻 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑓𐑪𐑯𐑛 𐑝 𐑞𐑧𐑥. 𐑞𐑱 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑩 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑐𐑹𐑐𐑩𐑕 𐑜𐑮𐑭𐑯𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑬𐑯.

𐑞 𐑓𐑨𐑒𐑑 𐑦𐑟, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑟 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑰𐑕𐑑, 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑷𐑤 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑚𐑰 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑼𐑛 𐑩 𐑯𐑴𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑛𐑦𐑖, 𐑢𐑻 𐑞𐑺 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑴 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑥; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑿 𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑑 𐑕𐑦𐑑 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑩 𐑥𐑰𐑑-𐑐𐑲 𐑯𐑽𐑤𐑦 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑛 𐑓𐑰𐑑 𐑤𐑪𐑙, 𐑦𐑑 𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑕 𐑩𐑢𐑱 𐑘𐑹 𐑨𐑐𐑩𐑑𐑲𐑑. 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑞 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑳𐑯𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑡𐑩𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑 𐑝 𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑤𐑲𐑒 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚, 𐑯𐑬𐑩𐑛𐑱𐑟 𐑐𐑸𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑝 𐑒𐑫𐑒𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑧𐑕𐑒𐑦𐑥𐑴 𐑸 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑴 𐑓𐑩𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑛𐑾𐑕. 𐑢𐑰 𐑷𐑤 𐑯𐑴 𐑣𐑬 𐑞𐑱 𐑤𐑦𐑝 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟, 𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑮𐑺 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑝𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑡𐑩𐑟 𐑝 𐑐𐑮𐑲𐑥 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯 𐑶𐑤. ·𐑟𐑪𐑜𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑩, 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑞𐑺 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑓𐑱𐑥𐑩𐑕 𐑛𐑪𐑒𐑑𐑼𐑟, 𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑕 𐑝 𐑚𐑤𐑳𐑚𐑼 𐑓 𐑦𐑯𐑓𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕, 𐑨𐑟 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑰𐑛𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑡𐑵𐑕𐑦 𐑯 𐑯𐑳𐑮𐑦𐑖𐑦𐑙. 𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑲𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑥𐑰 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑯 ·𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑤𐑦𐑖𐑥𐑧𐑯, 𐑣𐑵 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑩𐑜𐑴 𐑢𐑻 𐑨𐑒𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑤𐑧𐑓𐑑 𐑦𐑯 ·𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑯𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑩 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑝𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑤—𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑨𐑒𐑗𐑵𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑤𐑦𐑝𐑛 𐑓 𐑕𐑧𐑝𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑥𐑳𐑯𐑔𐑕 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑥𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑦 𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑨𐑐𐑕 𐑝 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑤𐑧𐑓𐑑 𐑩𐑖𐑹 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑦𐑙 𐑬𐑑 𐑞 𐑚𐑤𐑳𐑚𐑼. 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑞 ·𐑛𐑳𐑗 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑨𐑐𐑕 𐑸 𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑛 “𐑓𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑼𐑟”; 𐑢𐑦𐑗, 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑰𐑛, 𐑞𐑱 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑧𐑥𐑚𐑩𐑤, 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑮𐑬𐑯 𐑯 𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑐, 𐑯 𐑕𐑥𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑴𐑤𐑛 ·𐑨𐑥𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑛𐑨𐑥 𐑣𐑬𐑕𐑢𐑲𐑝𐑟' 𐑛𐑴-𐑯𐑳𐑑𐑕 𐑹 𐑴𐑤𐑦-𐑒𐑫𐑒𐑕, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑖. 𐑞𐑱 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩𐑯 𐑰𐑑𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑤𐑫𐑒 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓-𐑛𐑦𐑯𐑲𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑼 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑣𐑸𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑰𐑐 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑪𐑓.

𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑓𐑻𐑞𐑼 𐑛𐑦𐑐𐑮𐑰𐑖𐑦𐑱𐑑𐑕 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑨𐑟 𐑩 𐑕𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑤𐑲𐑟𐑛 𐑛𐑦𐑖, 𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑰𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑮𐑦𐑗𐑯𐑩𐑕. 𐑣𐑰 𐑦𐑟 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑲𐑟 𐑪𐑒𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑰, 𐑑𐑵 𐑓𐑨𐑑 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑛𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑜𐑫𐑛. 𐑤𐑫𐑒 𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑳𐑥𐑐, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑚𐑰 𐑨𐑟 𐑓𐑲𐑯 𐑰𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑚𐑳𐑓𐑩𐑤𐑴'𐑟 (𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑩 𐑮𐑺 𐑛𐑦𐑖), 𐑢𐑻 𐑦𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩 𐑕𐑪𐑤𐑦𐑛 𐑐𐑦𐑮𐑩𐑥𐑦𐑛 𐑝 𐑓𐑨𐑑. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥𐑩𐑕𐑧𐑑𐑦 𐑦𐑑𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓, 𐑣𐑬 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑯 𐑒𐑮𐑰𐑥𐑦 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑟; 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑞 𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑕𐑐𐑨𐑮𐑩𐑯𐑑, 𐑣𐑭𐑓-𐑡𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑛, 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑥𐑰𐑑 𐑝 𐑩 𐑒𐑴𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑔𐑻𐑛 𐑥𐑳𐑯𐑔 𐑝 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑜𐑮𐑴𐑔, 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑓𐑸 𐑑𐑵 𐑮𐑦𐑗 𐑑 𐑕𐑩𐑐𐑤𐑲 𐑩 𐑕𐑳𐑚𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑑𐑿𐑑 𐑓 𐑚𐑳𐑑𐑼. 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼𐑞𐑩𐑤𐑧𐑕, 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑩 𐑥𐑧𐑔𐑩𐑛 𐑝 𐑩𐑚𐑕𐑹𐑚𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑕𐑳𐑚𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕, 𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑐𐑸𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑦𐑑. 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑑𐑮𐑲 𐑢𐑪𐑗𐑩𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑯𐑲𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑩 𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑓 𐑞 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑐 𐑞𐑺 𐑖𐑦𐑐-𐑚𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑣𐑿𐑡 𐑶𐑤-𐑐𐑪𐑑𐑕 𐑯 𐑤𐑧𐑑 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑓𐑮𐑲 𐑞𐑺 𐑩𐑢𐑲𐑤. 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑩 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑕𐑳𐑐𐑼 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑲 𐑞𐑳𐑕 𐑥𐑱𐑛.

𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑒𐑱𐑕 𐑝 𐑩 𐑕𐑥𐑷𐑤 ·𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑞 𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑟 𐑸 𐑩𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑩 𐑓𐑲𐑯 𐑛𐑦𐑖. 𐑞 𐑒𐑭𐑕𐑒𐑩𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑒𐑳𐑤 𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑮𐑴𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩𐑯 𐑨𐑒𐑕, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑑𐑵 𐑐𐑤𐑳𐑥𐑐, 𐑢𐑲𐑑𐑦𐑖 𐑤𐑴𐑚𐑟 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑛𐑮𐑷𐑯 (𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑲𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑧𐑥𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑑𐑵 𐑤𐑸𐑡 𐑐𐑫𐑛𐑦𐑙𐑟), 𐑞𐑱 𐑸 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑥𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑓𐑤𐑬𐑼, 𐑯 𐑒𐑫𐑒𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑩 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑥𐑧𐑕, 𐑦𐑯 𐑓𐑤𐑱𐑝𐑼 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑧𐑥𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑒𐑭𐑝𐑟' 𐑣𐑧𐑛, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑩 𐑛𐑦𐑖 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑧𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑟; 𐑯 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑯𐑴𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑘𐑳𐑙 𐑚𐑳𐑒𐑕 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑞 𐑧𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑟, 𐑚𐑲 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑿𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑲𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑒𐑭𐑝𐑟' 𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑟, 𐑚𐑲 𐑯 𐑚𐑲 𐑜𐑧𐑑 𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑩 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑞𐑺 𐑴𐑯, 𐑕𐑴 𐑨𐑟 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑱𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑑 𐑑𐑧𐑤 𐑩 𐑒𐑭𐑓'𐑕 𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞𐑺 𐑴𐑯 𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑟; 𐑢𐑦𐑗, 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑰𐑛, 𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑢𐑲𐑼𐑟 𐑳𐑯𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯. 𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑞 𐑮𐑰𐑟𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑲 𐑩 𐑘𐑳𐑙 𐑚𐑳𐑒 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑡𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑒𐑭𐑓'𐑕 𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑣𐑬 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑨𐑛𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑲𐑑𐑕 𐑿 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑕𐑰. 𐑞 𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑕 𐑩 𐑕𐑹𐑑 𐑝 𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑮𐑴𐑗𐑓𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩𐑯 “𐑧𐑑 𐑑𐑵 ·𐑚𐑮𐑵𐑑!” 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑯.

𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑, 𐑐𐑼𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑕, 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑲𐑼𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑪𐑟 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑴 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑧𐑕𐑦𐑝𐑤𐑦 𐑳𐑙𐑒𐑗𐑵𐑩𐑕 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑕𐑰𐑥 𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑜𐑸𐑛 𐑞 𐑰𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩𐑚𐑣𐑹𐑩𐑯𐑕; 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑩𐑐𐑽𐑟 𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑳𐑤𐑑, 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑢𐑱, 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑼𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑛: 𐑲𐑰 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑩 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑰𐑑 𐑩 𐑯𐑿𐑤𐑦 𐑥𐑻𐑛𐑼𐑛 𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑰, 𐑯 𐑰𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑑𐑵 𐑚𐑲 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑴𐑯 𐑤𐑲𐑑. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑯𐑴 𐑛𐑬𐑑 𐑞 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑥𐑻𐑛𐑼𐑛 𐑩𐑯 𐑪𐑒𐑕 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑮𐑦𐑜𐑸𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑨𐑟 𐑩 𐑥𐑻𐑛𐑼𐑼; 𐑐𐑼𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑕 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑣𐑳𐑙; 𐑯 𐑦𐑓 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑐𐑫𐑑 𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑩𐑤 𐑚𐑲 𐑪𐑒𐑕𐑩𐑯, 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑯; 𐑯 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑦𐑟𐑻𐑝𐑛 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑓 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑥𐑻𐑛𐑼𐑼 𐑛𐑳𐑟. 𐑜𐑴 𐑑 𐑞 𐑥𐑰𐑑-𐑥𐑸𐑒𐑩𐑑 𐑝 𐑩 𐑕𐑨𐑑𐑼𐑛𐑱 𐑯𐑲𐑑 𐑯 𐑕𐑰 𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑬𐑛𐑟 𐑝 𐑤𐑲𐑝 𐑚𐑲𐑐𐑧𐑛𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑺𐑦𐑙 𐑳𐑐 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑮𐑴𐑟 𐑝 𐑛𐑧𐑛 𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑐𐑧𐑛𐑟. 𐑛𐑳𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑲𐑑 𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑩 𐑑𐑵𐑔 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑚𐑩𐑤'𐑟 𐑡𐑷? 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑟? 𐑣𐑵 𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑩 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑚𐑩𐑤? 𐑲 𐑑𐑧𐑤 𐑿 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑚𐑰 𐑥𐑹 𐑑𐑪𐑤𐑼𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑓 𐑞 ·𐑝𐑧𐑡𐑰 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑷𐑤𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑩 𐑤𐑰𐑯 𐑥𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑼𐑦 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑼 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑩 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑨𐑥𐑦𐑯; 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑚𐑰 𐑥𐑹 𐑑𐑪𐑤𐑼𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑓 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑝𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑑 ·𐑝𐑧𐑡𐑰, 𐑲 𐑕𐑱, 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑛𐑱 𐑝 𐑡𐑳𐑡𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑, 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑓 𐑞𐑰, 𐑕𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑤𐑲𐑟𐑛 𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑤𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑜𐑫𐑼𐑥𐑭𐑯𐑛, 𐑣𐑵 𐑯𐑱𐑤𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑜𐑰𐑕 𐑑 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑯 𐑓𐑰𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑪𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑚𐑤𐑴𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑤𐑦𐑝𐑼𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑲 𐑐𐑨𐑑𐑱-𐑛𐑩-𐑓𐑢𐑭-𐑜𐑮𐑭.

𐑚𐑳𐑑 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚, 𐑣𐑰 𐑰𐑑𐑕 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑚𐑲 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑴𐑯 𐑤𐑲𐑑, 𐑛𐑳𐑟 𐑣𐑰? 𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑨𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑳𐑤𐑑 𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑡𐑼𐑦, 𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑑? 𐑤𐑫𐑒 𐑨𐑑 𐑘𐑹 𐑯𐑲𐑓-𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑤, 𐑞𐑺, 𐑥𐑲 𐑕𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑤𐑲𐑟𐑛 𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑤𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑜𐑫𐑼𐑥𐑭𐑯𐑛 𐑛𐑲𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑪𐑓 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑮𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑰𐑓, 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑤 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑝?—𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑚𐑮𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑝 𐑞 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑪𐑒𐑕 𐑿 𐑸 𐑰𐑑𐑦𐑙? 𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑛𐑵 𐑿 𐑐𐑦𐑒 𐑘𐑹 𐑑𐑰𐑔 𐑢𐑦𐑞, 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑛𐑦𐑝𐑬𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑓𐑨𐑑 𐑜𐑵𐑕? 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑓𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑓𐑬𐑤. 𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑧𐑒𐑮𐑩𐑑𐑼𐑦 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑩𐑕𐑲𐑩𐑑𐑦 𐑓 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑩𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 ·𐑒𐑮𐑵𐑩𐑤𐑑𐑦 𐑑 ·𐑜𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑟 𐑓𐑹𐑥𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑲𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑻𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑼𐑟? 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑥𐑳𐑯𐑔 𐑹 𐑑𐑵 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑩𐑕𐑲𐑩𐑑𐑦 𐑐𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑩 𐑮𐑧𐑟𐑩𐑤𐑵𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑑 𐑐𐑨𐑑𐑮𐑩𐑯𐑲𐑟 𐑯𐑳𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑰𐑤 𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑟.

·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 66. 𐑞 ·𐑖𐑸𐑒 ·𐑥𐑨𐑕𐑩𐑒𐑼.

𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑳𐑞𐑼𐑯 ·𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑼𐑦, 𐑩 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑗𐑼𐑛 ·𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑯 𐑢𐑽𐑦 𐑑𐑶𐑤, 𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑮𐑷𐑑 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑙𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑤𐑱𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑯𐑲𐑑, 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑, 𐑨𐑟 𐑩 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑰𐑕𐑑, 𐑒𐑳𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑥𐑼𐑦 𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑴𐑕𐑰𐑛 𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑕 𐑑 𐑞 𐑚𐑦𐑟𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑒𐑳𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑦𐑯. 𐑓 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑟𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑦𐑟 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑰𐑛𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑤𐑩𐑚𐑹𐑾𐑕 𐑢𐑳𐑯; 𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑕𐑵𐑯 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑰𐑑𐑩𐑛; 𐑯 𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑢𐑲𐑼𐑟 𐑷𐑤 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑑 𐑕𐑧𐑑 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑦𐑑. 𐑞𐑺𐑓𐑹, 𐑞 𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑿𐑕𐑦𐑡 𐑦𐑟 𐑑 𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑦𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑕𐑱𐑤; 𐑤𐑨𐑖 𐑞 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑥 𐑩'𐑤𐑰; 𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑴 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑥𐑩𐑒 𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑛𐑱𐑤𐑲𐑑, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑮𐑧𐑟𐑼𐑝𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑, 𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑑𐑲𐑥, 𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑼-𐑢𐑪𐑗𐑩𐑟 𐑖𐑨𐑤 𐑚𐑰 𐑒𐑧𐑐𐑑; 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑟, 𐑑𐑵 𐑯 𐑑𐑵 𐑓 𐑩𐑯 𐑬𐑼, 𐑰𐑗 𐑒𐑳𐑐𐑩𐑤, 𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑵 𐑦𐑯 𐑮𐑴𐑑𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑖𐑨𐑤 𐑥𐑬𐑯𐑑 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑒 𐑑 𐑕𐑰 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑜𐑴𐑟 𐑢𐑧𐑤.

𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟, 𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑤𐑲𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑩𐑕𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑒, 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑐𐑤𐑨𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑼 𐑨𐑑 𐑷𐑤; 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑨𐑤𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑣𐑴𐑕𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑖𐑸𐑒𐑕 𐑜𐑨𐑞𐑼 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑞 𐑥𐑫𐑼𐑛 𐑒𐑸𐑒𐑩𐑕, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑻 𐑣𐑰 𐑤𐑧𐑓𐑑 𐑕𐑴 𐑓 𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑕 𐑬𐑼𐑟, 𐑕𐑱, 𐑪𐑯 𐑩 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑧𐑗, 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑥𐑹 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑒𐑧𐑤𐑩𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑚𐑰 𐑝𐑦𐑟𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑚𐑲 𐑥𐑹𐑯𐑦𐑙. 𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑐𐑸𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯, 𐑣𐑬𐑧𐑝𐑼, 𐑢𐑺 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑓𐑦𐑖 𐑛𐑵 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑴 𐑤𐑸𐑡𐑤𐑦 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑯𐑛, 𐑞𐑺 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑕 𐑝𐑼𐑨𐑕𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑚𐑰 𐑨𐑑 𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑼𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑖𐑑, 𐑚𐑲 𐑝𐑦𐑜𐑼𐑩𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑑𐑻𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑳𐑐 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑖𐑸𐑐 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙-𐑕𐑐𐑱𐑛𐑟, 𐑩 𐑐𐑮𐑴𐑕𐑰𐑡𐑼 𐑯𐑪𐑑𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙, 𐑢𐑦𐑗, 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟, 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑟 𐑑 𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑𐑼 𐑨𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑑𐑦. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑞𐑳𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑒𐑱𐑕 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛'𐑟 𐑖𐑸𐑒𐑕; 𐑞𐑴, 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑖𐑫𐑼, 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑳𐑯𐑩𐑒𐑳𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑥𐑛 𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑕𐑲𐑑𐑕, 𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑑 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑣𐑻 𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑯𐑲𐑑, 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑔𐑷𐑑 𐑞 𐑣𐑴𐑤 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑕𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑣𐑿𐑡 𐑗𐑰𐑟, 𐑯 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑖𐑸𐑒𐑕 𐑞 𐑥𐑨𐑜𐑩𐑑𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑦𐑑.

𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼𐑞𐑩𐑤𐑧𐑕, 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚 𐑕𐑧𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑼-𐑢𐑪𐑗 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑳𐑐𐑼 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑒𐑤𐑵𐑛𐑩𐑛; 𐑯 𐑢𐑧𐑯, 𐑩𐑒𐑹𐑛𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦, ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜 𐑯 𐑩 𐑓𐑴𐑒𐑕𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑒𐑱𐑥 𐑪𐑯 𐑛𐑧𐑒, 𐑯𐑴 𐑕𐑥𐑷𐑤 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑲𐑑𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑞 𐑖𐑸𐑒𐑕; 𐑓 𐑦𐑥𐑰𐑛𐑾𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑩𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑒𐑳𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑡𐑩𐑟 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑞 𐑕𐑲𐑛, 𐑯 𐑤𐑴𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑯𐑟, 𐑕𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑱 𐑒𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑜𐑤𐑰𐑥𐑟 𐑝 𐑤𐑲𐑑 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑞 𐑑𐑻𐑚𐑦𐑛 𐑕𐑰, 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑑𐑵 𐑥𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑯𐑼𐑟, 𐑛𐑸𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑺 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙-𐑕𐑐𐑱𐑛𐑟, 𐑒𐑧𐑐𐑑 𐑳𐑐 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑥𐑻𐑛𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑞 𐑖𐑸𐑒𐑕,* 𐑚𐑲 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑒𐑰𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑰𐑤 𐑛𐑰𐑐 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞𐑺 𐑕𐑒𐑳𐑤𐑟, 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑞𐑺 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑝𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑐𐑸𐑑. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑴𐑥𐑦 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑓𐑿𐑠𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑞𐑺 𐑥𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑑 𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑜𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑴𐑕𐑑𐑕, 𐑞 𐑥𐑸𐑒𐑕𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑷𐑤𐑢𐑱𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑥𐑸𐑒; 𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑚𐑮𐑷𐑑 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑯𐑿 𐑮𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑓𐑼𐑪𐑕𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑝 𐑞 𐑓𐑴. 𐑞𐑱 𐑝𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑯𐑨𐑐𐑑, 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑨𐑑 𐑰𐑗 𐑳𐑞𐑼'𐑟 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑦𐑥𐑚𐑬𐑩𐑤𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑓𐑤𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑚𐑴𐑟, 𐑚𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛, 𐑯 𐑚𐑦𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑴𐑯; 𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑕𐑢𐑪𐑤𐑴𐑛 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑯 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑥𐑬𐑔, 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑪𐑐𐑩𐑟𐑦𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑝𐑶𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑜𐑱𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑵𐑯𐑛. 𐑯𐑹 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑷𐑤. 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑳𐑯𐑕𐑱𐑓 𐑑 𐑥𐑧𐑛𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑒𐑹𐑐𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑯 𐑜𐑴𐑕𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑒𐑮𐑰𐑗𐑼𐑟. 𐑩 𐑕𐑹𐑑 𐑝 𐑡𐑦𐑯𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑒 𐑹 ·𐑐𐑨𐑯𐑔𐑰𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑝𐑲𐑑𐑨𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑑 𐑤𐑻𐑒 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑡𐑶𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑯 𐑚𐑴𐑯𐑟, 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑛 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑡𐑵𐑩𐑤 𐑤𐑲𐑓 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑛𐑦𐑐𐑸𐑑𐑩𐑛. 𐑒𐑦𐑤𐑛 𐑯 𐑣𐑶𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑪𐑯 𐑛𐑧𐑒 𐑓 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑒 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑒𐑦𐑯, 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑖𐑸𐑒𐑕 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑑𐑫𐑒 𐑐𐑫𐑼 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜'𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑪𐑓, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑣𐑰 𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑛 𐑑 𐑖𐑳𐑑 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑛 𐑤𐑦𐑛 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑻𐑛𐑼𐑩𐑕 𐑡𐑷.

*𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙-𐑕𐑐𐑱𐑛 𐑿𐑟𐑛 𐑓 𐑒𐑳𐑑𐑦𐑙-𐑦𐑯 𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑝 𐑞 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑚𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑰𐑤; 𐑦𐑟 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑞 𐑚𐑦𐑜𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑩 𐑥𐑨𐑯'𐑟 𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛; 𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑖𐑱𐑐, 𐑒𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑪𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑑 𐑞 𐑜𐑸𐑛𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑦𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑱𐑥𐑛; 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑕𐑲𐑛𐑟 𐑸 𐑐𐑻𐑓𐑦𐑒𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑓𐑤𐑨𐑑, 𐑯 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑳𐑐𐑼 𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑼𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑯𐑼𐑴𐑼 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑞 𐑤𐑴𐑼. 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑧𐑐𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑟 𐑷𐑤𐑢𐑱𐑟 𐑒𐑧𐑐𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑖𐑸𐑐 𐑨𐑟 𐑐𐑪𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤; 𐑯 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑿𐑟𐑛 𐑦𐑟 𐑩𐑒𐑱𐑠𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑣𐑴𐑯𐑛, 𐑡𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑮𐑱𐑟𐑼. 𐑦𐑯 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑕𐑪𐑒𐑩𐑑, 𐑩 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑓 𐑐𐑴𐑤, 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑑𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑦 𐑑 𐑔𐑻𐑑𐑦 𐑓𐑰𐑑 𐑤𐑪𐑙, 𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑓 𐑩 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑤.

“·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜 𐑯𐑴 𐑒𐑺 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑜𐑪𐑛 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑖𐑸𐑒,” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑞 𐑕𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑡, 𐑨𐑜𐑩𐑯𐑲𐑟𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑤𐑦𐑓𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑳𐑐 𐑯 𐑛𐑬𐑯; “𐑢𐑧𐑛𐑼 ·𐑝𐑧𐑡𐑰 𐑜𐑪𐑛 𐑹 ·𐑯𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑑 𐑜𐑪𐑛; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑛𐑦 𐑜𐑪𐑛 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑖𐑸𐑒 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑛𐑨𐑥 ·𐑦𐑯𐑡𐑦𐑯.”

·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 67. 𐑒𐑳𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯.

𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩 𐑕𐑨𐑑𐑼𐑛𐑱 𐑯𐑲𐑑, 𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩 ·𐑕𐑨𐑚𐑩𐑔 𐑨𐑟 𐑓𐑪𐑤𐑴𐑛! 𐑧𐑒𐑕 𐑪𐑓𐑦𐑕𐑦𐑴 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑓𐑧𐑕𐑼𐑟 𐑝 ·𐑕𐑨𐑚𐑩𐑔 𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑸 𐑷𐑤 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑥𐑧𐑯. 𐑞 𐑲𐑝𐑼𐑦 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑩 𐑖𐑨𐑥𐑚𐑩𐑤; 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑼 𐑩 𐑚𐑫𐑗𐑼. 𐑿 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑔𐑷𐑑 𐑢𐑰 𐑢𐑻 𐑪𐑓𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑳𐑐 𐑑𐑧𐑯 𐑔𐑬𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑮𐑧𐑛 𐑪𐑒𐑕𐑩𐑯 𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑰 𐑜𐑪𐑛𐑟.

𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕, 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑹𐑥𐑩𐑕 𐑒𐑳𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑑𐑨𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑟, 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑐𐑪𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑩𐑕 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑮𐑲𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑒𐑤𐑳𐑕𐑑𐑼 𐑝 𐑚𐑤𐑪𐑒𐑕 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑱𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑯, 𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑯𐑴 𐑕𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑩𐑤 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑐𐑪𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑤𐑦𐑓𐑑—𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑝𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑳𐑯𐑗 𐑝 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑐𐑕 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑢𐑱𐑛 𐑳𐑐 𐑑 𐑞 𐑥𐑱𐑯-𐑑𐑪𐑐 𐑯 𐑓𐑻𐑥𐑤𐑦 𐑤𐑨𐑖𐑑 𐑑 𐑞 𐑤𐑴𐑼 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑-𐑣𐑧𐑛, 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑪𐑙𐑜𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑐𐑶𐑯𐑑 𐑧𐑯𐑦𐑢𐑺 𐑩𐑚𐑳𐑝 𐑩 𐑖𐑦𐑐'𐑕 𐑛𐑧𐑒. 𐑞 𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑝 𐑞 𐑣𐑷𐑟𐑼-𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑮𐑴𐑐 𐑢𐑲𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑕𐑦𐑟, 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑛𐑳𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑑 𐑞 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑤𐑩𐑕, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑣𐑿𐑡 𐑤𐑴𐑼 𐑚𐑤𐑪𐑒 𐑝 𐑞 𐑑𐑨𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑢𐑳𐑙 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤; 𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑚𐑤𐑪𐑒 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑚𐑤𐑳𐑚𐑼 𐑣𐑫𐑒, 𐑢𐑱𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑛 𐑐𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑟, 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩𐑑𐑨𐑗𐑑. 𐑯 𐑯𐑬 𐑕𐑩𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑡𐑩𐑟 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑞 𐑕𐑲𐑛, ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒 𐑯 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚, 𐑞 𐑥𐑱𐑑𐑕, 𐑸𐑥𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞𐑺 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑕𐑐𐑱𐑛𐑟, 𐑚𐑦𐑜𐑨𐑯 𐑒𐑳𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑣𐑴𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦 𐑓 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑻𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑣𐑫𐑒 𐑡𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑩𐑚𐑳𐑝 𐑞 𐑯𐑽𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑑𐑵 𐑕𐑲𐑛-𐑓𐑦𐑯𐑟. 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑛𐑳𐑯, 𐑩 𐑚𐑮𐑷𐑛, 𐑕𐑧𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑻𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑼 𐑤𐑲𐑯 𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑳𐑑 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑞 𐑣𐑴𐑤, 𐑞 𐑣𐑫𐑒 𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑛, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑥𐑱𐑯 𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦 𐑝 𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑵 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑳𐑐 𐑩 𐑢𐑲𐑤𐑛 𐑒𐑹𐑩𐑕, 𐑯𐑬 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑕 𐑣𐑰𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑛𐑧𐑯𐑕 𐑒𐑮𐑬𐑛 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑤𐑩𐑕. 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦, 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑲𐑼 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑒𐑼𐑰𐑯𐑟 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑻 𐑕𐑲𐑛; 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑚𐑴𐑤𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑻 𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑑𐑕 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑞 𐑯𐑱𐑤-𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑟 𐑝 𐑩𐑯 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑣𐑬𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑕𐑑𐑦 𐑢𐑧𐑞𐑼; 𐑖𐑰 𐑑𐑮𐑧𐑥𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑟, 𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑝𐑼𐑟, 𐑯 𐑯𐑪𐑛𐑟 𐑣𐑻 𐑓𐑮𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑-𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑟 𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑒𐑲. 𐑥𐑹 𐑯 𐑥𐑹 𐑖𐑰 𐑤𐑰𐑯𐑟 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑑 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑜𐑭𐑕𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑰𐑝 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑦𐑟 𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑼𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑩 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑰𐑝 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑴𐑟; 𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑, 𐑩 𐑕𐑢𐑦𐑓𐑑, 𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑯𐑨𐑐 𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑻𐑛; 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑕𐑢𐑭𐑖 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑮𐑴𐑤𐑟 𐑳𐑐𐑢𐑼𐑛𐑟 𐑯 𐑚𐑨𐑒𐑢𐑼𐑛𐑟 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑳𐑥𐑓𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑑𐑨𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑮𐑲𐑟𐑩𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑕𐑲𐑑 𐑛𐑮𐑨𐑜𐑦𐑙 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑦𐑑 𐑞 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑦𐑯𐑜𐑱𐑡𐑛 𐑕𐑧𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑻𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑼 𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑝 𐑞 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑐 𐑝 𐑚𐑤𐑳𐑚𐑼. 𐑯𐑬 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑚𐑤𐑳𐑚𐑼 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑧𐑤𐑩𐑐𐑕 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑲𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑮𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑛𐑳𐑟 𐑩𐑯 𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑯𐑡, 𐑕𐑴 𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑑 𐑪𐑓 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑲𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑨𐑟 𐑩𐑯 𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑯𐑡 𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑕𐑐𐑲𐑮𐑩𐑤𐑲𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑑. 𐑓 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑧𐑐𐑑 𐑳𐑐 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑿𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑰𐑐𐑕 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑮𐑴𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑯 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼, 𐑯 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑚𐑤𐑳𐑚𐑼 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑐 𐑿𐑯𐑦𐑓𐑹𐑥𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑰𐑤𐑟 𐑪𐑓 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑞 𐑤𐑲𐑯 𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑛 𐑞 “𐑕𐑒𐑸𐑓,” 𐑕𐑦𐑥𐑩𐑤𐑑𐑱𐑯𐑾𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑳𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑱𐑛𐑟 𐑝 ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒 𐑯 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚, 𐑞 𐑥𐑱𐑑𐑕; 𐑯 𐑡𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑓𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑞𐑳𐑕 𐑐𐑰𐑤𐑛 𐑪𐑓, 𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑰𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑨𐑒𐑑 𐑦𐑑𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓, 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑶𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑣𐑲𐑼 𐑯 𐑣𐑲𐑼 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑓𐑑 𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑳𐑐𐑼 𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑟𐑩𐑟 𐑞 𐑥𐑱𐑯-𐑑𐑪𐑐; 𐑞 𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑕𐑰𐑕 𐑣𐑰𐑝𐑦𐑙, 𐑯 𐑓 𐑩 𐑥𐑴𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑹 𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑛𐑦𐑡𐑩𐑕 𐑚𐑤𐑳𐑛-𐑛𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑨𐑕 𐑕𐑢𐑱𐑟 𐑑 𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑴 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑓 𐑤𐑧𐑑 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑕𐑒𐑲, 𐑯 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑣𐑰𐑛 𐑑 𐑛𐑪𐑡 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑢𐑦𐑙𐑟, 𐑧𐑤𐑕 𐑦𐑑 𐑥𐑱 𐑚𐑪𐑒𐑕 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑽𐑟 𐑯 𐑐𐑦𐑗 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑴𐑝𐑼𐑚𐑹𐑛.

𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑩𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑽𐑟 𐑯𐑬 𐑩𐑛𐑝𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑤𐑪𐑙, 𐑒𐑰𐑯 𐑢𐑧𐑐𐑩𐑯 𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑛 𐑩 𐑚𐑹𐑛𐑦𐑙-𐑕𐑹𐑛, 𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑗𐑭𐑯𐑕 𐑣𐑰 𐑛𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑩𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑤𐑲𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑬𐑑 𐑩 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑼𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑣𐑴𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑤𐑴𐑼 𐑐𐑸𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑢𐑱𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑨𐑕. 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑣𐑴𐑤, 𐑞 𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑧𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑷𐑤𐑑𐑼𐑯𐑱𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑑𐑨𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑟 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑣𐑫𐑒𐑑 𐑕𐑴 𐑨𐑟 𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑱𐑯 𐑩 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑤𐑳𐑚𐑼, 𐑦𐑯 𐑹𐑛𐑼 𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑺 𐑓 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑓𐑪𐑤𐑴𐑟. 𐑢𐑺𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯, 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑩𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑦𐑖𐑑 𐑕𐑹𐑛𐑟𐑥𐑩𐑯, 𐑢𐑹𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑷𐑤 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑪𐑓, 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑕 𐑥𐑹 𐑥𐑱𐑒𐑕 𐑩 𐑕𐑲𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑒 𐑛𐑨𐑖 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑥𐑨𐑕, 𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑓𐑿 𐑕𐑲𐑛𐑤𐑪𐑙, 𐑛𐑧𐑕𐑐𐑼𐑩𐑑, 𐑤𐑳𐑯𐑡𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑤𐑲𐑕𐑦𐑙𐑟, 𐑕𐑧𐑝𐑼𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑰𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑯 𐑑𐑢𐑱𐑯; 𐑕𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑞 𐑖𐑹𐑑 𐑤𐑴𐑼 𐑐𐑸𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑓𐑭𐑕𐑑, 𐑞 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑳𐑐𐑼 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑐, 𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑛 𐑩 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑩𐑑-𐑐𐑰𐑕, 𐑕𐑢𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑒𐑤𐑽, 𐑯 𐑦𐑟 𐑷𐑤 𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑦 𐑓 𐑤𐑴𐑼𐑦𐑙. 𐑞 𐑣𐑰𐑝𐑼𐑟 𐑓𐑹𐑢𐑼𐑛 𐑯𐑬 𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑿𐑥 𐑞𐑺 𐑕𐑪𐑙, 𐑯 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑞 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑑𐑨𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑰𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑯 𐑣𐑶𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑕𐑧𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑐 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑞 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑤𐑴𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑤𐑨𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑩𐑢𐑱, 𐑯 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑜𐑴𐑟 𐑞 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑐 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑞 𐑥𐑱𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑗𐑢𐑱 𐑮𐑲𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑯𐑰𐑔, 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑩𐑯 𐑳𐑯𐑓𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑖𐑑 𐑐𐑸𐑤𐑼 𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑛 𐑞 𐑚𐑤𐑳𐑚𐑼-𐑮𐑵𐑥. 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑑𐑢𐑲𐑤𐑲𐑑 𐑩𐑐𐑸𐑑𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑮𐑦 𐑯𐑦𐑥𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑒𐑰𐑐 𐑒𐑶𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑢𐑱 𐑞 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑩𐑑-𐑐𐑰𐑕 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑓 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑻 𐑩 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑤𐑲𐑝 𐑥𐑨𐑕 𐑝 𐑐𐑤𐑨𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑕𐑻𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕. 𐑯 𐑞𐑳𐑕 𐑞 𐑢𐑻𐑒 𐑐𐑮𐑴𐑕𐑰𐑛𐑟; 𐑞 𐑑𐑵 𐑑𐑨𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑣𐑶𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑯 𐑤𐑴𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑦𐑥𐑩𐑤𐑑𐑱𐑯𐑾𐑕𐑤𐑦; 𐑚𐑴𐑔 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑣𐑰𐑝𐑦𐑙, 𐑞 𐑣𐑰𐑝𐑼𐑟 𐑕𐑦𐑙𐑦𐑙, 𐑞 𐑚𐑤𐑳𐑚𐑼-𐑮𐑵𐑥 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑒𐑶𐑤𐑦𐑙, 𐑞 𐑥𐑱𐑑𐑕 𐑕𐑒𐑸𐑓𐑦𐑙, 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑦𐑙, 𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑕𐑢𐑺𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑒𐑱𐑠𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑤𐑦, 𐑚𐑲 𐑢𐑱 𐑝 𐑩𐑕𐑢𐑱𐑡𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑓𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯.

·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 68. 𐑞 ·𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑩𐑑.

𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑜𐑦𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑯𐑴 𐑕𐑥𐑷𐑤 𐑩𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑳𐑯𐑝𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑚𐑡𐑧𐑒𐑑, 𐑞 𐑕𐑒𐑦𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤. 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑩𐑝𐑻𐑕𐑦𐑟 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑽𐑾𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑩𐑓𐑤𐑴𐑑, 𐑯 𐑤𐑻𐑯𐑛 𐑯𐑨𐑗𐑼𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑕 𐑩𐑖𐑹. 𐑥𐑲 𐑼𐑦𐑡𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑩𐑐𐑦𐑯𐑘𐑩𐑯 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑱𐑯𐑟 𐑳𐑯𐑗𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑛; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑩𐑯 𐑩𐑐𐑦𐑯𐑘𐑩𐑯.

𐑞 𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑕𐑗𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑟, 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑯 𐑢𐑺 𐑦𐑟 𐑞 𐑕𐑒𐑦𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤? 𐑷𐑤𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑦 𐑿 𐑯𐑴 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑤𐑳𐑚𐑼 𐑦𐑟. 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑚𐑤𐑳𐑚𐑼 𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑞 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑝 𐑓𐑻𐑥, 𐑒𐑤𐑴𐑕-𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑛 𐑚𐑰𐑓, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑑𐑳𐑓𐑼, 𐑥𐑹 𐑦𐑤𐑨𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑯 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑨𐑒𐑑, 𐑯 𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑩𐑟 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑱𐑑 𐑹 𐑑𐑧𐑯 𐑑 𐑑𐑢𐑧𐑤𐑝 𐑯 𐑓𐑦𐑓𐑑𐑰𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑗𐑩𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑔𐑦𐑒𐑯𐑩𐑕.

𐑯𐑬, 𐑣𐑬𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑪𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑩𐑕 𐑦𐑑 𐑥𐑱 𐑨𐑑 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑥 𐑑 𐑑𐑷𐑒 𐑝 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑒𐑮𐑰𐑗𐑼'𐑟 𐑕𐑒𐑦𐑯 𐑨𐑟 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑹𐑑 𐑝 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑯 𐑔𐑦𐑒𐑯𐑩𐑕, 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑐𐑶𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑓𐑨𐑒𐑑 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑸 𐑯𐑴 𐑸𐑜𐑿𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑖𐑩𐑯; 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑪𐑟 𐑿 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑮𐑱𐑟 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑛𐑧𐑯𐑕 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑧𐑤𐑩𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑤𐑱𐑼 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤'𐑟 𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑚𐑤𐑳𐑚𐑼; 𐑯 𐑞 𐑬𐑑𐑼𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑧𐑤𐑩𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑤𐑱𐑼 𐑝 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑥𐑩𐑤, 𐑦𐑓 𐑮𐑰𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑧𐑯𐑕, 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑒𐑦𐑯? 𐑑𐑮𐑵, 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑳𐑯𐑥𐑸𐑛 𐑛𐑧𐑛 𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑿 𐑥𐑱 𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑱𐑐 𐑪𐑓 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑘𐑹 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑓𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑔𐑦𐑯, 𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑕𐑐𐑨𐑮𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑚𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕, 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑧𐑥𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑔𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑖𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑟 𐑝 𐑲𐑟𐑦𐑯𐑜𐑤𐑭𐑕, 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑓𐑤𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑯 𐑕𐑪𐑓𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑕𐑨𐑑𐑦𐑯; 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑟, 𐑐𐑮𐑰𐑝𐑾𐑕 𐑑 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑛𐑮𐑲𐑛, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑦𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑒𐑑𐑕 𐑯 𐑔𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑟, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑟 𐑮𐑭𐑞𐑼 𐑣𐑸𐑛 𐑯 𐑚𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤. 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑕𐑧𐑝𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑛𐑮𐑲𐑛 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑕, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑲 𐑿𐑟 𐑓 𐑥𐑸𐑒𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑲 𐑢𐑱𐑤-𐑚𐑫𐑒𐑕. 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑕𐑐𐑨𐑮𐑩𐑯𐑑, 𐑨𐑟 𐑲 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹; 𐑯 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑤𐑱𐑛 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑐𐑱𐑡, 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑐𐑤𐑰𐑟𐑛 𐑥𐑲𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑓𐑨𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑜𐑟𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑩 𐑥𐑨𐑜𐑯𐑦𐑓𐑲𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯𐑓𐑤𐑵𐑩𐑯𐑕. 𐑨𐑑 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑮𐑱𐑑, 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑤𐑧𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑑 𐑮𐑰𐑛 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑞𐑺 𐑴𐑯 𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑟, 𐑨𐑟 𐑿 𐑥𐑱 𐑕𐑱. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑲 𐑨𐑥 𐑛𐑮𐑲𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑽 𐑦𐑟 𐑞𐑦𐑕. 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑦𐑯𐑓𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑔𐑦𐑯, 𐑲𐑟𐑦𐑯𐑜𐑤𐑭𐑕 𐑕𐑳𐑚𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕, 𐑢𐑦𐑗, 𐑲 𐑩𐑛𐑥𐑦𐑑, 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑕 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑲𐑼 𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑴 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑮𐑦𐑜𐑸𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑕𐑒𐑦𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑰𐑗𐑼, 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑕𐑒𐑦𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑒𐑦𐑯, 𐑕𐑴 𐑑 𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑒; 𐑓 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑻 𐑕𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑦𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑑 𐑕𐑱, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑐𐑼 𐑕𐑒𐑦𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑕 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑦𐑟 𐑔𐑦𐑯𐑼 𐑯 𐑥𐑹 𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑒𐑦𐑯 𐑝 𐑩 𐑯𐑿-𐑚𐑹𐑯 𐑗𐑲𐑤𐑛. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑯𐑴 𐑥𐑹 𐑝 𐑞𐑦𐑕.

𐑩𐑕𐑿𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑚𐑤𐑳𐑚𐑼 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑞 𐑕𐑒𐑦𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤; 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑕𐑒𐑦𐑯, 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑒𐑱𐑕 𐑝 𐑩 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑤𐑸𐑡 ·𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑘𐑰𐑤𐑛 𐑞 𐑚𐑳𐑤𐑒 𐑝 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑨𐑮𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑝 𐑶𐑤; 𐑯, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑼𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑, 𐑦𐑯 𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑑𐑦, 𐑹 𐑮𐑭𐑞𐑼 𐑢𐑱𐑑, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑶𐑤, 𐑦𐑯 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑑, 𐑦𐑟 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑓𐑹𐑔𐑕, 𐑯 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑲𐑼 𐑕𐑳𐑚𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑒𐑴𐑑; 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑲𐑛𐑾 𐑥𐑱 𐑣𐑧𐑯𐑕 𐑚𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑝 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑹𐑥𐑩𐑕𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑥𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑥𐑨𐑕, 𐑩 𐑥𐑽 𐑐𐑸𐑑 𐑝 𐑣𐑵𐑟 𐑥𐑽 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑜𐑿𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑘𐑰𐑤𐑛𐑟 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩 𐑤𐑱𐑒 𐑝 𐑤𐑦𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑛 𐑨𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑. 𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑑𐑧𐑯 𐑚𐑨𐑮𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑑 𐑞 𐑑𐑳𐑯, 𐑿 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑑𐑧𐑯 𐑑𐑳𐑯𐑟 𐑓 𐑞 𐑯𐑧𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑑 𐑝 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑒𐑢𐑹𐑑𐑼𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑓 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤'𐑟 𐑕𐑒𐑦𐑯.

𐑦𐑯 𐑤𐑲𐑓, 𐑞 𐑝𐑦𐑟𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑻𐑓𐑦𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑞 𐑤𐑰𐑕𐑑 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑞 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑥𐑸𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑕. 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑺𐑾𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑷𐑤 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑴𐑚𐑤𐑰𐑒𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑮𐑪𐑕𐑑 𐑯 𐑮𐑰-𐑒𐑮𐑪𐑕𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑯𐑳𐑥𐑚𐑼𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑥𐑸𐑒𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑔𐑦𐑒 𐑼𐑱, 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑲𐑯𐑩𐑕𐑑 ·𐑦𐑑𐑨𐑤𐑾𐑯 𐑤𐑲𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑝𐑦𐑙𐑟. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑥𐑸𐑒𐑕 𐑛𐑵 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑥 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑲𐑟𐑦𐑯𐑜𐑤𐑭𐑕 𐑕𐑳𐑚𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑩𐑚𐑳𐑝 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑛, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑥 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑕𐑰𐑯 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑦𐑑, 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑓 𐑞𐑱 𐑢𐑻 𐑦𐑯𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑝𐑛 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦 𐑦𐑑𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓. 𐑯𐑹 𐑦𐑟 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑷𐑤. 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟, 𐑑 𐑞 𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑒, 𐑩𐑚𐑟𐑻𐑝𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑲, 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑤𐑦𐑯𐑽 𐑥𐑸𐑒𐑕, 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑯𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑝𐑦𐑙, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑩𐑓𐑹𐑛 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑓 𐑓𐑸 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟. 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑸 𐑣𐑲𐑮𐑩𐑜𐑤𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤; 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑟, 𐑦𐑓 𐑿 𐑒𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑽𐑾𐑕 𐑕𐑲𐑓𐑼𐑟 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑷𐑤𐑟 𐑝 𐑐𐑦𐑮𐑩𐑥𐑦𐑛𐑟 𐑣𐑲𐑮𐑩𐑜𐑤𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑒𐑕, 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑐𐑼 𐑢𐑻𐑛 𐑑 𐑿𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑧𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯. 𐑚𐑲 𐑥𐑲 𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑝 𐑥𐑧𐑥𐑼𐑦 𐑝 𐑞 𐑣𐑲𐑮𐑩𐑜𐑤𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑒𐑕 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯 ·𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑐𐑼𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑼, 𐑲 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑒 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑑 𐑮𐑧𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑴𐑤𐑛 ·𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑾𐑯 𐑒𐑨𐑮𐑩𐑒𐑑𐑼𐑟 𐑗𐑦𐑟𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑱𐑥𐑩𐑕 𐑣𐑲𐑮𐑩𐑜𐑤𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑒 𐑐𐑨𐑤𐑦𐑕𐑱𐑛𐑟 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑳𐑐𐑼 ·𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑦𐑕𐑦𐑐𐑦. 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑮𐑪𐑒𐑕, 𐑑𐑵, 𐑞 𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑒-𐑥𐑸𐑒𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑱𐑯𐑟 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑲𐑓𐑼𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤. 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑩𐑤𐑵𐑠𐑩𐑯 𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑾𐑯 𐑮𐑪𐑒𐑕 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑲𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑥𐑰 𐑝 𐑩𐑯𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑔𐑦𐑙. 𐑚𐑦𐑕𐑲𐑛𐑟 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑓𐑦𐑯𐑪𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑩 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑞 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑽𐑽 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕, 𐑣𐑰 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑛𐑩𐑥 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑟 𐑞 𐑚𐑨𐑒, 𐑯 𐑥𐑹 𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑤𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑕, 𐑦𐑓𐑱𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑐𐑸𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑮𐑧𐑜𐑿𐑤𐑼 𐑤𐑦𐑯𐑽 𐑩𐑐𐑽𐑩𐑯𐑕, 𐑚𐑲 𐑮𐑰𐑟𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑯𐑿𐑥𐑼𐑩𐑕 𐑮𐑵𐑛 𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑨𐑗𐑩𐑟, 𐑷𐑤𐑑𐑩𐑜𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑝 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑮𐑧𐑜𐑿𐑤𐑼, 𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑥 𐑨𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑. 𐑲 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑕𐑱 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑴𐑟 ·𐑯𐑿 ·𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑮𐑪𐑒𐑕 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑰-𐑒𐑴𐑕𐑑, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 ·𐑨𐑜𐑩𐑕𐑦 𐑦𐑥𐑨𐑡𐑦𐑯𐑟 𐑑 𐑚𐑺 𐑞 𐑥𐑸𐑒𐑕 𐑝 𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑱𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑨𐑒𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑝𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑓𐑤𐑴𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑲𐑕𐑚𐑻𐑜𐑟—𐑲 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑕𐑱, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑮𐑪𐑒𐑕 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑩 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑧𐑥𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑐𐑼𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑼. 𐑦𐑑 𐑷𐑤𐑕𐑴 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑟 𐑑 𐑥𐑰 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑨𐑗𐑩𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑸 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑚𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑣𐑪𐑕𐑑𐑲𐑤 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑨𐑒𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟; 𐑓 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑸𐑒𐑑 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑤𐑸𐑡, 𐑓𐑫𐑤-𐑜𐑮𐑴𐑯 𐑚𐑫𐑤𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑖𐑰𐑟.

𐑩 𐑢𐑻𐑛 𐑹 𐑑𐑵 𐑥𐑹 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑥𐑨𐑑𐑼 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑒𐑦𐑯 𐑹 𐑚𐑤𐑳𐑚𐑼 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤. 𐑦𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑷𐑤𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑦 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑕𐑧𐑛, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑦𐑯 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑐𐑰𐑕𐑩𐑟, 𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑛 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑩𐑑-𐑐𐑰𐑕𐑩𐑟. 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑰-𐑑𐑻𐑥𐑟, 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑦𐑟 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑦 𐑯 𐑕𐑦𐑜𐑯𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑. 𐑓 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑰𐑛 𐑮𐑨𐑐𐑑 𐑳𐑐 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑤𐑳𐑚𐑼 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑮𐑾𐑤 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑩𐑑 𐑹 𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑐𐑱𐑯; 𐑹, 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑚𐑧𐑑𐑼, 𐑩𐑯 ·𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑾𐑯 𐑐𐑪𐑯𐑗𐑴 𐑕𐑤𐑦𐑐𐑑 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑧𐑛, 𐑯 𐑕𐑒𐑻𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑧𐑥𐑦𐑑𐑦. 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑲 𐑮𐑰𐑟𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑒𐑴𐑟𐑦 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑩𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑱𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑑 𐑒𐑰𐑐 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑓𐑼𐑑𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑢𐑧𐑞𐑼𐑟, 𐑦𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑕𐑰𐑟, 𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟, 𐑯 𐑑𐑲𐑛𐑟. 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑝 𐑩 ·𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑯𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑕𐑱, 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑖𐑳𐑛𐑼𐑦𐑙, 𐑲𐑕𐑦 𐑕𐑰𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑯𐑹𐑔, 𐑦𐑓 𐑳𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑐𐑤𐑲𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑴𐑟𐑦 𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑬𐑑? 𐑑𐑮𐑵, 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑓𐑦𐑖 𐑸 𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑰𐑛𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑒 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑴𐑟 ·𐑣𐑲𐑐𐑼𐑚𐑹𐑾𐑯 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼𐑟; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞𐑰𐑟, 𐑚𐑰 𐑦𐑑 𐑩𐑚𐑟𐑻𐑝𐑛, 𐑸 𐑘𐑹 𐑒𐑴𐑤𐑛-𐑚𐑤𐑳𐑛𐑩𐑛, 𐑤𐑳𐑙𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑓𐑦𐑖, 𐑣𐑵𐑟 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑚𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑟 𐑸 𐑮𐑦𐑓𐑮𐑦𐑡𐑼𐑱𐑑𐑼𐑟; 𐑒𐑮𐑰𐑗𐑼𐑟, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑹𐑥 𐑞𐑧𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑝𐑟 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑞 𐑤𐑰 𐑝 𐑩𐑯 𐑲𐑕𐑚𐑻𐑜, 𐑨𐑟 𐑩 𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑼 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑚𐑭𐑕𐑒 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑓𐑲𐑼; 𐑢𐑺𐑨𐑟, 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑥𐑨𐑯, 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑤𐑳𐑙𐑟 𐑯 𐑢𐑹𐑥 𐑚𐑤𐑳𐑛. 𐑓𐑮𐑰𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑤𐑳𐑛, 𐑯 𐑣𐑰 𐑛𐑲𐑟. 𐑣𐑬 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑞𐑧𐑯—𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑧𐑐𐑑 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯—𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑥𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑼, 𐑑 𐑣𐑵𐑥 𐑒𐑹𐑐𐑹𐑾𐑤 𐑢𐑹𐑥𐑔 𐑦𐑟 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑑 𐑥𐑨𐑯; 𐑣𐑬 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑚𐑰 𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑴𐑥, 𐑦𐑥𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑤𐑦𐑐𐑕 𐑓 𐑤𐑲𐑓 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑴𐑟 ·𐑸𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼𐑟! 𐑢𐑺, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑓𐑷𐑤 𐑴𐑝𐑼𐑚𐑹𐑛, 𐑞𐑱 𐑸 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛, 𐑥𐑳𐑯𐑔𐑕 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼𐑢𐑼𐑛𐑟, 𐑐𐑻𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑼𐑤𐑦 𐑓𐑮𐑴𐑟𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑣𐑸𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑓𐑰𐑤𐑛𐑟 𐑝 𐑲𐑕, 𐑨𐑟 𐑩 𐑓𐑤𐑲 𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑜𐑤𐑵𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑨𐑥𐑚𐑼. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑥𐑹 𐑕𐑼𐑐𐑮𐑲𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑑 𐑯𐑴, 𐑨𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑐𐑮𐑵𐑝𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑚𐑤𐑳𐑛 𐑝 𐑩 ·𐑐𐑴𐑤𐑼 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑹𐑥𐑼 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑝 𐑩 ·𐑚𐑹𐑯𐑦𐑴 𐑯𐑰𐑜𐑮𐑴 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑼.

𐑦𐑑 𐑛𐑳𐑟 𐑕𐑰𐑥 𐑑 𐑥𐑰, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑽𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑰 𐑕𐑰 𐑞 𐑮𐑺 𐑝𐑻𐑗𐑵 𐑝 𐑩 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑪𐑙 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑡𐑵𐑩𐑤 𐑝𐑲𐑑𐑨𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑦, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑮𐑺 𐑝𐑻𐑗𐑵 𐑝 𐑔𐑦𐑒 𐑢𐑷𐑤𐑟, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑮𐑺 𐑝𐑻𐑗𐑵 𐑝 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑽𐑽 𐑕𐑐𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑕𐑯𐑩𐑕. 𐑴, 𐑥𐑨𐑯! 𐑩𐑛𐑥𐑲𐑼 𐑯 𐑥𐑪𐑛𐑩𐑤 𐑞𐑲𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤! 𐑛𐑵 𐑞𐑬, 𐑑𐑵, 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑱𐑯 𐑢𐑹𐑥 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑲𐑕. 𐑛𐑵 𐑞𐑬, 𐑑𐑵, 𐑤𐑦𐑝 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑦𐑑. 𐑚𐑰 𐑒𐑵𐑤 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑦𐑒𐑢𐑱𐑑𐑼; 𐑒𐑰𐑐 𐑞𐑲 𐑚𐑤𐑳𐑛 𐑓𐑤𐑵𐑦𐑛 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑴𐑤. 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑛𐑴𐑥 𐑝 ·𐑕𐑑 ·𐑐𐑰𐑑𐑼'𐑟, 𐑯 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑱𐑯, 𐑴 𐑥𐑨𐑯! 𐑦𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑕𐑰𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑩 𐑑𐑧𐑥𐑐𐑼𐑩𐑗𐑼 𐑝 𐑞𐑲𐑯 𐑴𐑯.

𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑣𐑬 𐑰𐑟𐑦 𐑯 𐑣𐑬 𐑣𐑴𐑐𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑑 𐑑𐑰𐑗 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑓𐑲𐑯 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑟! 𐑝 𐑦𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟, 𐑣𐑬 𐑓𐑿 𐑸 𐑛𐑴𐑥𐑛 𐑤𐑲𐑒 ·𐑕𐑑 ·𐑐𐑰𐑑𐑼'𐑟! 𐑝 𐑒𐑮𐑰𐑗𐑼𐑟, 𐑣𐑬 𐑓𐑿 𐑝𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤!

·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 69. 𐑞 ·𐑓𐑿𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑤.

“𐑣𐑷𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑗𐑱𐑯𐑟! 𐑤𐑧𐑑 𐑞 𐑒𐑸𐑒𐑩𐑕 𐑜𐑴 𐑩𐑕𐑑𐑻𐑯!”

𐑞 𐑝𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑑𐑨𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑯𐑬 𐑛𐑳𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑛𐑿𐑑𐑦. 𐑞 𐑐𐑰𐑤𐑛 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦 𐑝 𐑞 𐑚𐑦𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑓𐑤𐑨𐑖𐑩𐑟 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑥𐑸𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑧𐑐𐑩𐑤𐑒𐑼; 𐑞𐑴 𐑗𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑿, 𐑦𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑐𐑼𐑕𐑧𐑐𐑑𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑤𐑪𐑕𐑑 𐑧𐑯𐑦𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑚𐑳𐑤𐑒. 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑕𐑩𐑤. 𐑕𐑤𐑴𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑑 𐑓𐑤𐑴𐑑𐑕 𐑥𐑹 𐑯 𐑥𐑹 𐑩𐑢𐑱, 𐑞 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑑 𐑑𐑹𐑯 𐑯 𐑕𐑐𐑤𐑨𐑖𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑱𐑖𐑾𐑑 𐑖𐑸𐑒𐑕, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑺 𐑩𐑚𐑳𐑝 𐑝𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑮𐑩𐑐𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑕 𐑓𐑤𐑲𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑰𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑬𐑤𐑟, 𐑣𐑵𐑟 𐑚𐑰𐑒𐑕 𐑸 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑕𐑴 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑳𐑤𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑐𐑪𐑯𐑘𐑼𐑛𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤. 𐑞 𐑝𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑓𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑥 𐑓𐑤𐑴𐑑𐑕 𐑓𐑻𐑞𐑼 𐑯 𐑓𐑻𐑞𐑼 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐, 𐑯 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑮𐑪𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑴 𐑓𐑤𐑴𐑑𐑕, 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑥 𐑕𐑒𐑢𐑺 𐑮𐑵𐑛𐑟 𐑝 𐑖𐑸𐑒𐑕 𐑯 𐑒𐑿𐑚𐑦𐑒 𐑮𐑵𐑛𐑟 𐑝 𐑓𐑬𐑤𐑟, 𐑷𐑜𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑞 𐑥𐑻𐑛𐑼𐑩𐑕 𐑛𐑦𐑯. 𐑓 𐑬𐑼𐑟 𐑯 𐑬𐑼𐑟 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑼𐑦 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑛𐑾𐑕 𐑕𐑲𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑰𐑯. 𐑚𐑦𐑯𐑰𐑔 𐑞 𐑳𐑯𐑒𐑤𐑬𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑯 𐑥𐑲𐑤𐑛 𐑨𐑠𐑼 𐑕𐑒𐑲, 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑺 𐑓𐑱𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑐𐑤𐑧𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑕𐑰, 𐑢𐑪𐑓𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑡𐑶𐑩𐑕 𐑚𐑮𐑰𐑟𐑩𐑟, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑥𐑨𐑕 𐑝 𐑛𐑧𐑔 𐑓𐑤𐑴𐑑𐑕 𐑪𐑯 𐑯 𐑪𐑯, 𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑤𐑪𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑓𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑑 𐑐𐑼𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑝𐑟.

𐑞𐑺'𐑟 𐑩 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑛𐑴𐑤𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑯 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑥𐑪𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑿𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑤! 𐑞 𐑕𐑰-𐑝𐑳𐑤𐑗𐑼𐑟 𐑷𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑐𐑲𐑩𐑕 𐑥𐑹𐑯𐑦𐑙, 𐑞 𐑺-𐑖𐑸𐑒𐑕 𐑷𐑤 𐑐𐑳𐑙𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑤𐑾𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑯 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑒 𐑹 𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑛. 𐑦𐑯 𐑤𐑲𐑓 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑓𐑿 𐑝 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑐𐑑 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑲 𐑢𐑰𐑯, 𐑦𐑓 𐑐𐑻𐑩𐑛𐑝𐑧𐑯𐑗𐑼 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑯𐑰𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑑; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑢𐑩𐑑 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑿𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑞𐑱 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑐𐑲𐑩𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑵 𐑐𐑬𐑯𐑕. 𐑴, 𐑣𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑝𐑳𐑤𐑗𐑼𐑦𐑟𐑩𐑥 𐑝 𐑻𐑔! 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑞 𐑥𐑲𐑑𐑾𐑕𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑮𐑰.

𐑯𐑹 𐑦𐑟 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑞 𐑧𐑯𐑛. 𐑛𐑧𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑮𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦 𐑦𐑟, 𐑩 𐑝𐑧𐑯𐑡𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑜𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑼𐑝𐑲𐑝𐑟 𐑯 𐑣𐑪𐑝𐑼𐑟 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑦𐑑 𐑑 𐑕𐑒𐑺. 𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑲𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑑𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑛 𐑥𐑨𐑯-𐑝-𐑢𐑹 𐑹 𐑚𐑤𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑳𐑝𐑼𐑦-𐑝𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑤 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑩𐑓𐑸, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑞 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑩𐑚𐑕𐑒𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑕𐑢𐑹𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑬𐑤𐑟, 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼𐑞𐑩𐑤𐑧𐑕 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑖𐑴𐑟 𐑞 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑥𐑨𐑕 𐑓𐑤𐑴𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑯, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑱 𐑣𐑰𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑲 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑑; 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑑𐑢𐑱 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤'𐑟 𐑳𐑯𐑣𐑸𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑒𐑹𐑐𐑕, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑑𐑮𐑧𐑥𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑼𐑟 𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑧𐑑 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑤𐑪𐑜—𐑖𐑴𐑤𐑟, 𐑮𐑪𐑒𐑕, 𐑯 𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑒𐑼𐑟 𐑣𐑽𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑𐑕: 𐑚𐑦𐑢𐑺! 𐑯 𐑓 𐑘𐑽𐑟 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼𐑢𐑼𐑛𐑟, 𐑐𐑼𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑕, 𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑕 𐑖𐑳𐑯 𐑞 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕; 𐑤𐑰𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑦𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑕𐑦𐑤𐑦 𐑖𐑰𐑐 𐑤𐑰𐑐 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑩 𐑝𐑨𐑒𐑿𐑥, 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑪𐑟 𐑞𐑺 𐑤𐑰𐑛𐑼 𐑼𐑦𐑡𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑤𐑰𐑐𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑩 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑛. 𐑞𐑺'𐑟 𐑘𐑹 𐑤𐑷 𐑝 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕; 𐑞𐑺'𐑟 𐑘𐑹 𐑿𐑑𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑝 𐑑𐑮𐑩𐑛𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟; 𐑞𐑺'𐑟 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑹𐑦 𐑝 𐑘𐑹 𐑪𐑚𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑑 𐑕𐑼𐑝𐑲𐑝𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑰𐑓𐑕 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑚𐑪𐑑𐑩𐑥𐑛 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑻𐑔, 𐑯 𐑯𐑬 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑣𐑪𐑝𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑺! 𐑞𐑺'𐑟 𐑹𐑔𐑩𐑛𐑪𐑒𐑕𐑦!

𐑞𐑳𐑕, 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑤𐑲𐑓 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑤'𐑟 𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦 𐑥𐑱 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑩 𐑮𐑾𐑤 𐑑𐑧𐑮𐑼 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑴𐑟, 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑛𐑧𐑔 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑜𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑟 𐑩 𐑐𐑬𐑼𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑐𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑒 𐑑 𐑩 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛.

𐑸 𐑿 𐑩 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑰𐑝𐑼 𐑦𐑯 𐑜𐑴𐑕𐑑𐑕, 𐑥𐑲 𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑯𐑛? 𐑞𐑺 𐑸 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑜𐑴𐑕𐑑𐑕 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑒𐑪𐑒-·𐑤𐑱𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯, 𐑯 𐑓𐑸 𐑛𐑰𐑐𐑼 𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑯 ·𐑛𐑪𐑒𐑑𐑼 ·𐑡𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑯 𐑣𐑵 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑰𐑝 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑥.

·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 70. 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑓𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑕.

𐑦𐑑 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑴𐑥𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑰𐑝𐑾𐑕 𐑑 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑰𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦 𐑝 𐑞 𐑤𐑩𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑔𐑩𐑯, 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑚𐑦𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑩𐑛. 𐑯𐑬, 𐑞 𐑚𐑦𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑦𐑟 𐑩 𐑕𐑲𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑒 𐑨𐑯𐑩𐑑𐑪𐑥𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑓𐑰𐑑, 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑽𐑾𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑕𐑻𐑡𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑐𐑮𐑲𐑛 𐑞𐑧𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑝𐑟: 𐑯 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑 𐑮𐑰𐑟𐑩𐑯.

𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑼 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑯𐑳𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑐𐑼𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑰 𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑛 𐑩 𐑯𐑧𐑒; 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑺𐑦, 𐑢𐑺 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑯 𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦 𐑕𐑰𐑥 𐑑 𐑡𐑶𐑯, 𐑞𐑺, 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕, 𐑦𐑟 𐑞 𐑔𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑐𐑸𐑑 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑥. 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑧𐑥𐑚𐑼, 𐑷𐑤𐑕𐑴, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑻𐑡𐑩𐑯 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑪𐑐𐑼𐑱𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑩𐑚𐑳𐑝, 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑱𐑑 𐑹 𐑑𐑧𐑯 𐑓𐑰𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑝𐑰𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑢𐑰𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑳𐑚𐑡𐑧𐑒𐑑, 𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑚𐑡𐑧𐑒𐑑 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑳𐑤𐑼𐑛, 𐑮𐑴𐑤𐑦𐑙, 𐑯 𐑪𐑓𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑑𐑿𐑥𐑳𐑤𐑗𐑵𐑩𐑕 𐑯 𐑚𐑻𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑰. 𐑚𐑺 𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑲𐑯𐑛, 𐑑𐑵, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑳𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑢𐑹𐑛 𐑕𐑻𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑕 𐑑 𐑒𐑳𐑑 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑓𐑰𐑑 𐑛𐑰𐑐 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑤𐑧𐑖; 𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑚𐑑𐑼𐑱𐑯𐑾𐑕 𐑥𐑨𐑯𐑼, 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑 𐑕𐑴 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑨𐑟 𐑜𐑧𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑕𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑩𐑤 𐑐𐑰𐑐 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑧𐑝𐑼-𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑜𐑨𐑖 𐑞𐑳𐑕 𐑥𐑱𐑛, 𐑣𐑰 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑒𐑦𐑤𐑓𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑑𐑽 𐑒𐑤𐑽 𐑝 𐑷𐑤 𐑩𐑡𐑱𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑑, 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑐𐑸𐑑𐑕, 𐑯 𐑦𐑜𐑟𐑨𐑒𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑦𐑝𐑲𐑛 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑲𐑯 𐑨𐑑 𐑩 𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑐𐑶𐑯𐑑 𐑣𐑸𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑻𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑕𐑒𐑳𐑤. 𐑛𐑵 𐑿 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑥𐑸𐑝𐑩𐑤, 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑨𐑑 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚'𐑟 𐑚𐑴𐑕𐑑, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑛𐑦𐑥𐑭𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑑𐑧𐑯 𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑩 𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 𐑢𐑱𐑤?

𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑧𐑝𐑼𐑛, 𐑞 𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑦𐑟 𐑛𐑮𐑪𐑐𐑑 𐑩𐑕𐑑𐑻𐑯 𐑯 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑛 𐑞𐑺 𐑚𐑲 𐑩 𐑒𐑱𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑞 𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦 𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑑. 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑛𐑳𐑯, 𐑦𐑓 𐑦𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑑 𐑩 𐑕𐑥𐑷𐑤 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑶𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑪𐑯 𐑛𐑧𐑒 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑚𐑼𐑩𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑴𐑟𐑛 𐑝. 𐑚𐑳𐑑, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑓𐑫𐑤 𐑜𐑮𐑴𐑯 𐑤𐑩𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑔𐑩𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑪𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤; 𐑓 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 𐑢𐑱𐑤'𐑟 𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑦𐑥𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑯𐑽𐑤𐑦 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑔𐑻𐑛 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑲𐑼 𐑚𐑳𐑤𐑒, 𐑯 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑰𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑑 𐑕𐑩𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩 𐑚𐑻𐑛𐑩𐑯 𐑨𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑, 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑦𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑕 𐑑𐑨𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑝 𐑩 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑼, 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑻 𐑨𐑟 𐑝𐑱𐑯 𐑩 𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑨𐑟 𐑑 𐑩𐑑𐑧𐑥𐑐𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑦𐑙 𐑩 ·𐑛𐑳𐑗 𐑚𐑸𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑡𐑵𐑩𐑤𐑼𐑟' 𐑕𐑒𐑱𐑤𐑟.

𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛'𐑟 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑦𐑑𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑑, 𐑞 𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑣𐑶𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐'𐑕 𐑕𐑲𐑛—𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑣𐑭𐑓 𐑢𐑱 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑰, 𐑕𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑐𐑸𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑚𐑶𐑛 𐑳𐑐 𐑚𐑲 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑯𐑱𐑑𐑦𐑝 𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑. 𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑛 𐑒𐑮𐑭𐑓𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑰𐑐𐑤𐑦 𐑤𐑰𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑑 𐑦𐑑, 𐑚𐑲 𐑮𐑰𐑟𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑹𐑥𐑩𐑕 𐑛𐑬𐑯𐑢𐑼𐑛 𐑛𐑮𐑨𐑜 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑤𐑴𐑼 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑-𐑣𐑧𐑛, 𐑯 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑘𐑸𐑛-𐑸𐑥 𐑪𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑡𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑒𐑮𐑱𐑯 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑝𐑟; 𐑞𐑺, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑚𐑤𐑳𐑛-𐑛𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑣𐑳𐑙 𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛'𐑟 𐑢𐑱𐑕𐑑 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑞 𐑡𐑲𐑩𐑯𐑑 ·𐑣𐑪𐑤𐑩𐑓𐑻𐑯𐑟'𐑩𐑟 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑜𐑻𐑛𐑩𐑤 𐑝 ·𐑡𐑵𐑛𐑦𐑔.

𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑑𐑭𐑕𐑒 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑦𐑖𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑵𐑯, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑴 𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑛𐑦𐑯𐑼. 𐑕𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑛 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑞 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑑𐑿𐑥𐑳𐑤𐑗𐑵𐑩𐑕 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑯𐑬 𐑛𐑦𐑟𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑛𐑧𐑒. 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑕 𐑒𐑪𐑐𐑼 𐑒𐑭𐑥, 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑿𐑯𐑦𐑝𐑻𐑕𐑩𐑤 𐑘𐑧𐑤𐑴 𐑤𐑴𐑑𐑩𐑕, 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑥𐑹 𐑯 𐑥𐑹 𐑳𐑯𐑓𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑯𐑶𐑟𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑥𐑧𐑠𐑼𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑤𐑰𐑝𐑟 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑰.

𐑩 𐑖𐑹𐑑 𐑕𐑐𐑱𐑕 𐑦𐑤𐑨𐑐𐑕𐑑, 𐑯 𐑳𐑐 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑯𐑶𐑟𐑤𐑩𐑕𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑒𐑱𐑥 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑩𐑤𐑴𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑨𐑚𐑦𐑯. 𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑓𐑿 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑟 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑒𐑢𐑹𐑑𐑼-𐑛𐑧𐑒, 𐑣𐑰 𐑐𐑷𐑟𐑛 𐑑 𐑜𐑱𐑟 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑞 𐑕𐑲𐑛, 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑕𐑤𐑴𐑤𐑦 𐑜𐑧𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑥𐑱𐑯-𐑗𐑱𐑯𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑑𐑫𐑒 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚'𐑟 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑕𐑐𐑱𐑛—𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑱𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑺 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤'𐑟 𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑦𐑑𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯—𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑤𐑴𐑼 𐑐𐑸𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑣𐑭𐑓-𐑕𐑩𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑥𐑨𐑕, 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑒𐑮𐑳𐑗-𐑢𐑲𐑟 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑸𐑥, 𐑯 𐑕𐑴 𐑕𐑑𐑫𐑛 𐑤𐑰𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑲𐑟 𐑩𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑝𐑤𐑦 𐑓𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑑 𐑪𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑣𐑧𐑛.

𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑒 𐑯 𐑣𐑫𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑣𐑧𐑛; 𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑙𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑺 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑥𐑦𐑛𐑕𐑑 𐑝 𐑕𐑴 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑕 𐑩 𐑒𐑭𐑥, 𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑓𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑕'𐑩𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑟𐑼𐑑. “𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑒, 𐑞𐑬 𐑝𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑯 𐑝𐑧𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑣𐑧𐑛,” 𐑥𐑳𐑑𐑼𐑛 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚, “𐑢𐑦𐑗, 𐑞𐑴 𐑳𐑯𐑜𐑸𐑯𐑦𐑖𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑚𐑽𐑛, 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑣𐑽 𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑹𐑦 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑥𐑪𐑕𐑩𐑟; 𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑒, 𐑥𐑲𐑑𐑦 𐑣𐑧𐑛, 𐑯 𐑑𐑧𐑤 𐑳𐑕 𐑞 𐑕𐑰𐑒𐑮𐑩𐑑 𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑰. 𐑝 𐑷𐑤 𐑛𐑲𐑝𐑼𐑟, 𐑞𐑬 𐑣𐑨𐑕𐑑 𐑛𐑲𐑝𐑛 𐑞 𐑛𐑰𐑐𐑩𐑕𐑑. 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑞 𐑳𐑐𐑼 𐑕𐑳𐑯 𐑯𐑬 𐑜𐑤𐑰𐑥𐑟, 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑥𐑵𐑝𐑛 𐑩𐑥𐑦𐑛 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛'𐑟 𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟. 𐑢𐑺 𐑳𐑯𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑹𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑯𐑱𐑥𐑟 𐑯 𐑯𐑱𐑝𐑦𐑟 𐑮𐑳𐑕𐑑, 𐑯 𐑳𐑯𐑑𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑣𐑴𐑐𐑕 𐑯 𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑼𐑟 𐑮𐑪𐑑; 𐑢𐑺 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑻 𐑥𐑻𐑛𐑼𐑩𐑕 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑓𐑮𐑦𐑜𐑩𐑑 𐑻𐑔 𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑨𐑤𐑩𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑥𐑦𐑤𐑾𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑛𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛; 𐑞𐑺, 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑷𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼-𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛, 𐑞𐑺 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞𐑲 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑓𐑩𐑥𐑦𐑤𐑽 𐑣𐑴𐑥. 𐑞𐑬 𐑣𐑨𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑢𐑺 𐑚𐑧𐑤 𐑹 𐑛𐑲𐑝𐑼 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑑; 𐑣𐑨𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑤𐑧𐑐𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑩 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑼'𐑟 𐑕𐑲𐑛, 𐑢𐑺 𐑕𐑤𐑰𐑐𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑥𐑳𐑞𐑼𐑟 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑜𐑦𐑝 𐑞𐑺 𐑤𐑲𐑝𐑟 𐑑 𐑤𐑱 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑛𐑬𐑯. 𐑞𐑬 𐑕𐑷'𐑕𐑑 𐑞 𐑤𐑪𐑒𐑑 𐑤𐑳𐑝𐑼𐑟 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑤𐑰𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞𐑺 𐑓𐑤𐑱𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑖𐑦𐑐; 𐑣𐑸𐑑 𐑑 𐑣𐑸𐑑 𐑞𐑱 𐑕𐑨𐑙𐑒 𐑚𐑦𐑯𐑰𐑔 𐑞 𐑦𐑜𐑟𐑳𐑤𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑱𐑝; 𐑑𐑮𐑵 𐑑 𐑰𐑗 𐑳𐑞𐑼, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑣𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑓𐑷𐑤𐑕 𐑑 𐑞𐑧𐑥. 𐑞𐑬 𐑕𐑷'𐑕𐑑 𐑞 𐑥𐑻𐑛𐑼𐑛 𐑥𐑱𐑑 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑑𐑪𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑐𐑲𐑮𐑩𐑑𐑕 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑥𐑦𐑛𐑯𐑲𐑑 𐑛𐑧𐑒; 𐑓 𐑬𐑼𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑓𐑧𐑤 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑛𐑰𐑐𐑼 𐑥𐑦𐑛𐑯𐑲𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑱𐑖𐑾𐑑 𐑥𐑷; 𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑻𐑛𐑼𐑼𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑛 𐑪𐑯 𐑳𐑯𐑣𐑸𐑥𐑛—𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑕𐑢𐑦𐑓𐑑 𐑤𐑲𐑑𐑯𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑖𐑦𐑝𐑼𐑛 𐑞 𐑯𐑱𐑚𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑚𐑹𐑯 𐑩 𐑮𐑲𐑗𐑩𐑕 𐑣𐑳𐑟𐑚𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑑 𐑬𐑑𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑧𐑗𐑑, 𐑤𐑪𐑙𐑦𐑙 𐑸𐑥𐑟. 𐑴 𐑣𐑧𐑛! 𐑞𐑬 𐑣𐑨𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑳𐑓 𐑑 𐑕𐑐𐑤𐑦𐑑 𐑞 𐑐𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑩𐑑𐑕 𐑯 𐑥𐑱𐑒 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑓𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑤 𐑝 ·𐑱𐑚𐑮𐑩𐑣𐑨𐑥, 𐑯 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑕𐑦𐑤𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑟 𐑞𐑲𐑯!”

“𐑕𐑱𐑤 𐑣𐑴!” 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 𐑩 𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑳𐑥𐑓𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑝𐑶𐑕 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑥𐑱𐑯-𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑-𐑣𐑧𐑛.

“𐑲? 𐑢𐑧𐑤, 𐑯𐑬, 𐑞𐑨𐑑'𐑕 𐑗𐑽𐑦𐑙,” 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚, 𐑕𐑳𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓, 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑣𐑴𐑤 𐑔𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼-𐑒𐑤𐑬𐑛𐑟 𐑕𐑢𐑧𐑐𐑑 𐑩𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑮𐑬. “𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑲𐑝𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑮𐑲 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑛𐑧𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑭𐑥 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑝𐑻𐑑 𐑩 𐑚𐑧𐑑𐑼 𐑥𐑨𐑯.—𐑢𐑺 𐑩𐑢𐑱?”

“𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑐𐑶𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑼𐑛 𐑚𐑬, 𐑕𐑻, 𐑯 𐑚𐑮𐑦𐑙𐑦𐑙 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑣𐑻 𐑚𐑮𐑰𐑟 𐑑 𐑳𐑕!

“𐑚𐑧𐑑𐑼 𐑯 𐑚𐑧𐑑𐑼, 𐑥𐑨𐑯. 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑯𐑬 ·𐑕𐑑 ·𐑐𐑷𐑤 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑱, 𐑯 𐑑 𐑥𐑲 𐑚𐑮𐑰𐑟𐑤𐑩𐑕𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑚𐑮𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑮𐑰𐑟! 𐑴 ·𐑯𐑱𐑗𐑼, 𐑯 𐑴 𐑕𐑴𐑤 𐑝 𐑥𐑨𐑯! 𐑣𐑬 𐑓𐑸 𐑚𐑦𐑘𐑪𐑯𐑛 𐑷𐑤 𐑳𐑑𐑼𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑸 𐑘𐑹 𐑤𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑑 𐑩𐑯𐑨𐑤𐑩𐑡𐑦𐑟! 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑥𐑷𐑤𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑨𐑑𐑩𐑥 𐑕𐑑𐑻𐑟 𐑹 𐑤𐑲𐑝𐑟 𐑪𐑯 𐑥𐑨𐑑𐑼, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑒𐑳𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑛𐑿𐑐𐑤𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑲𐑯𐑛.”

·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 71. 𐑞 ·𐑡𐑧𐑮𐑩𐑚𐑴𐑩𐑥'𐑟 ·𐑕𐑑𐑹𐑦.

𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛, 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑯 𐑚𐑮𐑰𐑟 𐑚𐑤𐑵 𐑪𐑯; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞 𐑚𐑮𐑰𐑟 𐑒𐑱𐑥 𐑓𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑼 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐, 𐑯 𐑕𐑵𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛 𐑚𐑦𐑜𐑨𐑯 𐑑 𐑮𐑪𐑒.

𐑚𐑲 𐑯 𐑚𐑲, 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑞 𐑜𐑤𐑭𐑕 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑼'𐑟 𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕 𐑯 𐑥𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑-𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑟 𐑐𐑮𐑵𐑝𐑛 𐑣𐑻 𐑩 𐑢𐑱𐑤-𐑖𐑦𐑐. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑖𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑴 𐑓𐑸 𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑢𐑼𐑛, 𐑯 𐑖𐑵𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑲, 𐑩𐑐𐑨𐑮𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑥𐑱𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑐𐑨𐑕𐑦𐑡 𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑜𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛, 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑣𐑴𐑐 𐑑 𐑮𐑰𐑗 𐑣𐑻. 𐑕𐑴 𐑞 𐑕𐑦𐑜𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑧𐑑 𐑑 𐑕𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑪𐑯𐑕 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑚𐑰 𐑥𐑱𐑛.

𐑣𐑽 𐑚𐑰 𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑧𐑛, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑞 𐑝𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑝 𐑥𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑺𐑦 𐑥𐑼𐑰𐑯𐑟, 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑩𐑥𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑯 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤 ·𐑓𐑤𐑰𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑰𐑗 𐑩 𐑐𐑮𐑲𐑝𐑩𐑑 𐑕𐑦𐑜𐑯𐑩𐑤; 𐑷𐑤 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑕𐑦𐑜𐑯𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑚𐑫𐑒 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑯𐑱𐑥𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑝 𐑝𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑩𐑑𐑨𐑗𐑑, 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑝𐑲𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑦𐑑. 𐑞𐑺𐑚𐑲, 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑭𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑟 𐑸 𐑦𐑯𐑱𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑑 𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑩𐑜𐑯𐑲𐑟 𐑰𐑗 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯, 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑨𐑑 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑼𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑯𐑴 𐑕𐑥𐑷𐑤 𐑓𐑩𐑕𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑦.

𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛'𐑟 𐑕𐑦𐑜𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑪𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑼'𐑟 𐑕𐑧𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑻 𐑴𐑯; 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑐𐑮𐑵𐑝𐑛 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑞 ·𐑡𐑧𐑮𐑩𐑚𐑴𐑩𐑥 𐑝 ·𐑯𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑑. 𐑕𐑒𐑢𐑺𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑻 𐑘𐑸𐑛𐑟, 𐑖𐑰 𐑚𐑹 𐑛𐑬𐑯, 𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑛 𐑩𐑚𐑰𐑥 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛'𐑟 𐑤𐑰, 𐑯 𐑤𐑴𐑼𐑛 𐑩 𐑚𐑴𐑑; 𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑵𐑯 𐑛𐑮𐑵 𐑯𐑲; 𐑚𐑳𐑑, 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑕𐑲𐑛-𐑤𐑨𐑛𐑼 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑮𐑦𐑜𐑛 𐑚𐑲 ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒'𐑕 𐑹𐑛𐑼 𐑑 𐑩𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑛𐑱𐑑 𐑞 𐑝𐑦𐑟𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯, 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑼 𐑦𐑯 𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑕𐑗𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑱𐑝𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑴𐑑'𐑕 𐑕𐑑𐑻𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑑𐑴𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑴𐑕𐑰𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑲𐑼𐑤𐑦 𐑳𐑯𐑯𐑧𐑕𐑦𐑕𐑺𐑦. 𐑦𐑑 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑛 𐑬𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑡𐑧𐑮𐑩𐑚𐑴𐑩𐑥 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑩 𐑥𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑜𐑯𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑧𐑐𐑦𐑛𐑧𐑥𐑦𐑒 𐑪𐑯 𐑚𐑹𐑛, 𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 ·𐑥𐑱𐑣𐑿, 𐑣𐑻 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯, 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑓𐑽𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑦𐑯𐑓𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛'𐑟 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑦. 𐑓, 𐑞𐑴 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑯 𐑚𐑴𐑑'𐑕 𐑒𐑮𐑵 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑱𐑯𐑛 𐑳𐑯𐑑𐑱𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛, 𐑯 𐑞𐑴 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑣𐑭𐑓 𐑩 𐑮𐑲𐑓𐑩𐑤-𐑖𐑪𐑑 𐑪𐑓, 𐑯 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑼𐑳𐑐𐑑𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑰 𐑯 𐑺 𐑮𐑴𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑯 𐑓𐑤𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑢𐑰𐑯; 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑖𐑦𐑧𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑨𐑛𐑣𐑽𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑞 𐑑𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑛 𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑮𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑰𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛, 𐑣𐑰 𐑐𐑼𐑧𐑥𐑐𐑑𐑼𐑦𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑦𐑓𐑿𐑟𐑛 𐑑 𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑛𐑦𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑑 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑨𐑒𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛.

𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑯𐑴 𐑥𐑰𐑯𐑟 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑝𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑿𐑯𐑦𐑒𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟. 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑻𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑝𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑓𐑿 𐑘𐑸𐑛𐑟 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑢𐑰𐑯 𐑦𐑑𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑯 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐, 𐑞 ·𐑡𐑧𐑮𐑩𐑚𐑴𐑩𐑥'𐑟 𐑚𐑴𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑩𐑒𐑱𐑠𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑿𐑕 𐑝 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑹𐑟 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑝𐑛 𐑑 𐑒𐑰𐑐 𐑐𐑨𐑮𐑩𐑤𐑧𐑤 𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛, 𐑨𐑟 𐑖𐑰 𐑣𐑧𐑝𐑦𐑤𐑦 𐑓𐑹𐑡𐑛 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑞 𐑕𐑰 (𐑓 𐑚𐑲 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑦𐑑 𐑚𐑤𐑵 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑖), 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑻 𐑥𐑱𐑯-𐑑𐑪𐑐𐑕𐑱𐑤 𐑩𐑚𐑨𐑒; 𐑞𐑴, 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑰𐑛, 𐑨𐑑 𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑛𐑩𐑯 𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑧𐑑 𐑝 𐑩 𐑤𐑸𐑡 𐑮𐑴𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑱𐑝, 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑚𐑰 𐑐𐑫𐑖𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑢𐑱 𐑩𐑣𐑧𐑛; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑚𐑰 𐑕𐑵𐑯 𐑕𐑒𐑦𐑤𐑓𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑮𐑷𐑑 𐑑 𐑣𐑻 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑐𐑼 𐑚𐑺𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯. 𐑕𐑳𐑚𐑡𐑧𐑒𐑑 𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕, 𐑯 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑞 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑳𐑐𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑯𐑬 𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑩 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑝𐑼𐑕𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑩𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑯𐑛 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑢𐑰𐑯 𐑞 𐑑𐑵 𐑐𐑸𐑑𐑦𐑟; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑩𐑯𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑳𐑐𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑩 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑛𐑦𐑓𐑼𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑕𐑹𐑑.

𐑐𐑫𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑯 𐑹 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑡𐑧𐑮𐑩𐑚𐑴𐑩𐑥'𐑟 𐑚𐑴𐑑, 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑝 𐑩 𐑕𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑿𐑤𐑼 𐑩𐑐𐑽𐑩𐑯𐑕, 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑲𐑤𐑛 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑤𐑲𐑓 𐑢𐑺 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑡𐑵𐑩𐑤 𐑯𐑴𐑑𐑩𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑱𐑒 𐑳𐑐 𐑷𐑤 𐑑𐑴𐑑𐑨𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑟. 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩 𐑕𐑥𐑷𐑤, 𐑖𐑹𐑑, 𐑘𐑳𐑙𐑦𐑖 𐑥𐑨𐑯, 𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑷𐑤 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑱𐑕 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑟, 𐑯 𐑢𐑺𐑦𐑙 𐑮𐑦𐑛𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑘𐑧𐑤𐑴 𐑣𐑺. 𐑩 𐑤𐑪𐑙-𐑕𐑒𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑛, 𐑒𐑩𐑚𐑨𐑤𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑦-𐑒𐑳𐑑 𐑒𐑴𐑑 𐑝 𐑩 𐑓𐑱𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑷𐑤𐑯𐑳𐑑 𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑡 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑧𐑤𐑩𐑐𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥; 𐑞 𐑴𐑝𐑼𐑤𐑨𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑤𐑰𐑝𐑟 𐑝 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑢𐑻 𐑮𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑳𐑐 𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑕. 𐑩 𐑛𐑰𐑐, 𐑕𐑧𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑛, 𐑓𐑩𐑯𐑨𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑽𐑾𐑥 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑲𐑟.

𐑕𐑴 𐑕𐑵𐑯 𐑨𐑟 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑓𐑦𐑜𐑼 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛, ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑒𐑤𐑱𐑥𐑛—“𐑞𐑨𐑑'𐑕 𐑣𐑰! 𐑞𐑨𐑑'𐑕 𐑣𐑰!—𐑞 𐑤𐑪𐑙-𐑑𐑪𐑜𐑛 ·𐑕𐑒𐑨𐑮𐑩𐑥𐑬𐑗 𐑞 ·𐑑𐑬𐑯-·𐑣𐑴'𐑟 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑦 𐑑𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑳𐑕 𐑝!” 𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚 𐑣𐑽 𐑩𐑤𐑵𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑑 𐑩 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡 𐑕𐑑𐑹𐑦 𐑑𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑡𐑧𐑮𐑩𐑚𐑴𐑩𐑥, 𐑯 𐑩 𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑣𐑻 𐑒𐑮𐑵, 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑐𐑮𐑰𐑝𐑾𐑕 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛 𐑕𐑐𐑴𐑒 𐑞 ·𐑑𐑬𐑯-·𐑣𐑴. 𐑩𐑒𐑹𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑩𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑 𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑳𐑚𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑢𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑤𐑻𐑯𐑛, 𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑒𐑨𐑮𐑩𐑥𐑬𐑗 𐑦𐑯 𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑕𐑗𐑩𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑛 𐑩 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑩𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑡𐑧𐑮𐑩𐑚𐑴𐑩𐑥. 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑹𐑦 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞𐑦𐑕:

𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑼𐑦𐑡𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑯𐑻𐑗𐑼𐑛 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑱𐑟𐑦 𐑕𐑩𐑕𐑲𐑩𐑑𐑦 𐑝 ·𐑯𐑧𐑕𐑒𐑱𐑵𐑯𐑩 ·𐑖𐑱𐑒𐑼𐑟, 𐑢𐑺 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑩 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑓𐑩𐑑; 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑒𐑮𐑨𐑒𐑑, 𐑕𐑰𐑒𐑮𐑩𐑑 𐑥𐑰𐑑𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑧𐑝𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑣𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑢𐑱 𐑝 𐑩 𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑐-𐑛𐑹, 𐑩𐑯𐑬𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑛𐑦 𐑴𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑯𐑔 𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑤, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑝𐑧𐑕𐑑-𐑐𐑪𐑒𐑩𐑑; 𐑚𐑳𐑑, 𐑢𐑦𐑗, 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑛 𐑝 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑱𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑜𐑳𐑯𐑐𐑬𐑛𐑼, 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑩𐑐𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑗𐑸𐑡𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑤𐑷𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑥. 𐑩 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡, 𐑨𐑐𐑩𐑕𐑑𐑪𐑤𐑦𐑒 𐑢𐑦𐑥 𐑣𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑰𐑟𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑤𐑧𐑓𐑑 ·𐑯𐑧𐑕𐑒𐑱𐑵𐑯𐑩 𐑓 ·𐑯𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑑, 𐑢𐑺, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑒𐑳𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑽 𐑑 𐑒𐑮𐑱𐑟𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑕, 𐑣𐑰 𐑩𐑕𐑿𐑥𐑛 𐑩 𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑛𐑦, 𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑯-𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑕 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑽𐑽, 𐑯 𐑪𐑓𐑼𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑨𐑟 𐑩 𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑯-𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑑 𐑓 𐑞 ·𐑡𐑧𐑮𐑩𐑚𐑴𐑩𐑥'𐑟 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑝𐑶𐑦𐑡. 𐑞𐑱 𐑦𐑯𐑜𐑱𐑡𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑑𐑢𐑱 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐'𐑕 𐑜𐑧𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑕𐑲𐑑 𐑝 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛, 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑚𐑮𐑴𐑒 𐑬𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑑. 𐑣𐑰 𐑩𐑯𐑬𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑸𐑒𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑩𐑤 ·𐑜𐑭𐑚𐑮𐑦𐑧𐑤, 𐑯 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑭𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑞 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 𐑑 𐑡𐑳𐑥𐑐 𐑴𐑝𐑼𐑚𐑹𐑛. 𐑣𐑰 𐑐𐑳𐑚𐑤𐑦𐑖𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑓𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑴, 𐑢𐑺𐑚𐑲 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑧𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑓𐑹𐑔 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑝𐑼𐑼 𐑝 𐑞 𐑲𐑤𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑰 𐑯 𐑝𐑦𐑒𐑼-𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑷𐑤 ·𐑴𐑖𐑦𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑒𐑩. 𐑞 𐑳𐑯𐑓𐑤𐑦𐑯𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑻𐑯𐑩𐑕𐑑𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑣𐑰 𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑺𐑛 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑟;—𐑞 𐑛𐑸𐑒, 𐑛𐑺𐑦𐑙 𐑐𐑤𐑱 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑤𐑰𐑐𐑤𐑩𐑕, 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑥𐑨𐑡𐑦𐑯𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯, 𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑰𐑑𐑼𐑯𐑨𐑗𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑑𐑧𐑮𐑼𐑟 𐑝 𐑮𐑾𐑤 𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑽𐑾𐑥, 𐑿𐑯𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 ·𐑜𐑭𐑚𐑮𐑦𐑧𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑥𐑲𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑥𐑩𐑡𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑝 𐑞 𐑦𐑜𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑒𐑮𐑵, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩𐑯 𐑨𐑑𐑥𐑩𐑕𐑓𐑽 𐑝 𐑕𐑱𐑒𐑮𐑩𐑛𐑯𐑩𐑕. 𐑥𐑹𐑴𐑝𐑼, 𐑞𐑱 𐑢𐑻 𐑩𐑓𐑮𐑱𐑛 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑥. 𐑨𐑟 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩 𐑥𐑨𐑯, 𐑣𐑬𐑧𐑝𐑼, 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑝 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑐𐑮𐑨𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑿𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐, 𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑨𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑮𐑦𐑓𐑿𐑟𐑛 𐑑 𐑢𐑻𐑒 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑧𐑐𐑑 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑣𐑰 𐑐𐑤𐑰𐑟𐑛, 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑮𐑧𐑡𐑵𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑓𐑱𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑮𐑦𐑛 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑥; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑩𐑐𐑮𐑲𐑟𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑡𐑵𐑩𐑤'𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑑 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑝𐑰𐑯𐑾𐑯𐑑 𐑐𐑹𐑑, 𐑞 𐑸𐑒𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑩𐑤 𐑓𐑹𐑔𐑢𐑦𐑔 𐑴𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑷𐑤 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑰𐑤𐑟 𐑯 𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑤𐑟—𐑛𐑦𐑝𐑴𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑑 𐑳𐑯𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑐𐑼𐑛𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯, 𐑦𐑯 𐑒𐑱𐑕 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑒𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑛 𐑬𐑑. 𐑕𐑴 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑪𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑻𐑒 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑲𐑐𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑵, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦 𐑞𐑱 𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑑 𐑞 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 𐑯 𐑑𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑦𐑓 ·𐑜𐑭𐑚𐑮𐑦𐑧𐑤 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐, 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑩 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑝 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑱𐑯. 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞𐑺𐑓𐑹 𐑓𐑹𐑕𐑑 𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑖 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑤𐑨𐑯. 𐑯𐑹 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑞𐑱 𐑐𐑼𐑥𐑦𐑑 ·𐑜𐑭𐑚𐑮𐑦𐑧𐑤 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑢𐑱 𐑥𐑨𐑤𐑑𐑮𐑰𐑑𐑩𐑛, 𐑕𐑱 𐑹 𐑛𐑵 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑫𐑛; 𐑕𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑒𐑱𐑥 𐑑 𐑐𐑭𐑕 𐑞𐑨𐑑 ·𐑜𐑭𐑚𐑮𐑦𐑧𐑤 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑞 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑰𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑰𐑛𐑩𐑥 𐑝 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐. 𐑞 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑢𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑝 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑪𐑟, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑸𐑒𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑩𐑤 𐑒𐑺𐑛 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑹 𐑯𐑳𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑓 𐑞 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 𐑯 𐑥𐑱𐑑𐑕; 𐑯 𐑕𐑦𐑯𐑕 𐑞 𐑧𐑐𐑦𐑛𐑧𐑥𐑦𐑒 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑮𐑴𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑬𐑑, 𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑛 𐑩 𐑣𐑲𐑼 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑧𐑝𐑼; 𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑺𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑜, 𐑨𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑛 𐑦𐑑, 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑴𐑤 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑭𐑯𐑛; 𐑯𐑹 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑦𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑛 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑩𐑒𐑹𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑐𐑤𐑧𐑠𐑼. 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑼𐑟, 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑫𐑼 𐑛𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑟, 𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑯𐑡𐑛, 𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑝 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑓𐑷𐑯𐑛 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑣𐑦𐑥; 𐑦𐑯 𐑴𐑚𐑰𐑛𐑾𐑯𐑕 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟, 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑮𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑐𐑻𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑣𐑪𐑥𐑦𐑡, 𐑨𐑟 𐑑 𐑩 𐑜𐑪𐑛. 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑥𐑱 𐑕𐑰𐑥 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤; 𐑚𐑳𐑑, 𐑣𐑬𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑕, 𐑞𐑱 𐑸 𐑑𐑮𐑵. 𐑯𐑹 𐑦𐑟 𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑦 𐑝 𐑓𐑩𐑯𐑨𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑕 𐑣𐑭𐑓 𐑕𐑴 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑 𐑑 𐑞 𐑥𐑧𐑠𐑼𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓-𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑧𐑐𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑓𐑩𐑯𐑨𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓, 𐑨𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑧𐑠𐑼𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑐𐑬𐑼 𐑝 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑰𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑯 𐑚𐑦𐑛𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑴 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑳𐑞𐑼𐑟. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑻𐑯 𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛.

“𐑲 𐑓𐑽 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑞𐑲 𐑧𐑐𐑦𐑛𐑧𐑥𐑦𐑒, 𐑥𐑨𐑯,” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑚𐑫𐑤𐑢𐑼𐑒𐑕, 𐑑 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 ·𐑥𐑱𐑣𐑿, 𐑣𐑵 𐑕𐑑𐑫𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑'𐑕 𐑕𐑑𐑻𐑯; “𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑪𐑯 𐑚𐑹𐑛.”

𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑯𐑬 ·𐑜𐑭𐑚𐑮𐑦𐑧𐑤 𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑰𐑑.

“𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒, 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒 𐑝 𐑞 𐑓𐑰𐑝𐑼𐑟, 𐑘𐑧𐑤𐑴 𐑯 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑾𐑕! 𐑚𐑦𐑢𐑺 𐑝 𐑞 𐑣𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑜!”

“·𐑜𐑭𐑚𐑮𐑦𐑧𐑤! ·𐑜𐑭𐑚𐑮𐑦𐑧𐑤!” 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 ·𐑥𐑱𐑣𐑿; “𐑞𐑬 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑲𐑞𐑼—” 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑩 𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑢𐑱𐑝 𐑖𐑪𐑑 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑 𐑓𐑸 𐑩𐑣𐑧𐑛, 𐑯 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑕𐑰𐑞𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑛𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑷𐑤 𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑗.

“𐑣𐑨𐑕𐑑 𐑞𐑬 𐑕𐑰𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑢𐑲𐑑 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤?” 𐑛𐑦𐑥𐑭𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑 𐑛𐑮𐑦𐑓𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑨𐑒.

“𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒, 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒 𐑝 𐑞𐑲 𐑢𐑱𐑤-𐑚𐑴𐑑, 𐑕𐑑𐑴𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑙𐑒! 𐑚𐑦𐑢𐑺 𐑝 𐑞 𐑣𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑑𐑱𐑤!”

“𐑲 𐑑𐑧𐑤 𐑞𐑰 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯, ·𐑜𐑭𐑚𐑮𐑦𐑧𐑤, 𐑞𐑨𐑑—” 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑 𐑑𐑹 𐑩𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑓 𐑛𐑮𐑨𐑜𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑓𐑰𐑯𐑛𐑟. 𐑯𐑳𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑓 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑥𐑴𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑕, 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑩 𐑕𐑩𐑒𐑕𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑮𐑲𐑩𐑑𐑩𐑕 𐑢𐑱𐑝𐑟 𐑮𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑚𐑲, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑚𐑲 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑩𐑒𐑱𐑠𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑒𐑩𐑐𐑮𐑰𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑰𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑑𐑳𐑥𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙, 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑣𐑰𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑑. 𐑥𐑰𐑯𐑑𐑲𐑥, 𐑞 𐑣𐑶𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 𐑢𐑱𐑤'𐑟 𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑡𐑪𐑜𐑛 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦, 𐑯 ·𐑜𐑭𐑚𐑮𐑦𐑧𐑤 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑰𐑯 𐑲𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑮𐑭𐑞𐑼 𐑥𐑹 𐑨𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑣𐑧𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑝𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑸𐑒𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑩𐑤 𐑯𐑱𐑗𐑼 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑮𐑩𐑯𐑑.

𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑤𐑵𐑛 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑴𐑝𐑼, ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 ·𐑥𐑱𐑣𐑿 𐑚𐑦𐑜𐑨𐑯 𐑩 𐑛𐑸𐑒 𐑕𐑑𐑹𐑦 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑙 ·𐑥𐑪𐑚𐑦 ·𐑛𐑦𐑒; 𐑯𐑪𐑑, 𐑣𐑬𐑧𐑝𐑼, 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑳𐑐𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 ·𐑜𐑭𐑚𐑮𐑦𐑧𐑤, 𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑱𐑥 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑛, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑱𐑟𐑦 𐑕𐑰 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑤𐑰𐑜𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑥.

𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑡𐑧𐑮𐑩𐑚𐑴𐑩𐑥 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑤𐑧𐑓𐑑 𐑣𐑴𐑥, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑢𐑱𐑤-𐑖𐑦𐑐, 𐑣𐑻 𐑐𐑰𐑐𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑻 𐑮𐑦𐑤𐑲𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑩𐑐𐑮𐑲𐑟𐑛 𐑝 𐑞 𐑦𐑜𐑟𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑝 ·𐑥𐑪𐑚𐑦 ·𐑛𐑦𐑒, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑣𐑨𐑝𐑩𐑒 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑥𐑱𐑛. 𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑳𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑡𐑩𐑯𐑕, ·𐑜𐑭𐑚𐑮𐑦𐑧𐑤 𐑕𐑪𐑤𐑩𐑥𐑤𐑦 𐑢𐑹𐑯𐑛 𐑞 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑩𐑑𐑨𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑞 ·𐑢𐑲𐑑 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑦𐑯 𐑒𐑱𐑕 𐑞 𐑥𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑼 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑚𐑰 𐑕𐑰𐑯; 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑡𐑦𐑚𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑦, 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑯𐑬𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑞 ·𐑢𐑲𐑑 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑯𐑴 𐑤𐑧𐑕 𐑩 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑖𐑱𐑒𐑼 ·𐑜𐑪𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑸𐑯𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛; 𐑞 ·𐑖𐑱𐑒𐑼𐑟 𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑰𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑞 ·𐑚𐑲𐑚𐑩𐑤. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑧𐑯, 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑘𐑽 𐑹 𐑑𐑵 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼𐑢𐑼𐑛𐑟, ·𐑥𐑪𐑚𐑦 ·𐑛𐑦𐑒 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑓𐑺𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑-𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑟, ·𐑥𐑱𐑕𐑦, 𐑞 𐑗𐑰𐑓 𐑥𐑱𐑑, 𐑚𐑻𐑯𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑸𐑛𐑼 𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑼 𐑣𐑦𐑥; 𐑯 𐑞 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑳𐑯𐑢𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑤𐑧𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑞 𐑪𐑐𐑼𐑑𐑿𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑦, 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑲𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑸𐑒𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑩𐑤'𐑟 𐑛𐑦𐑯𐑳𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑯 𐑓𐑹𐑢𐑹𐑯𐑦𐑙𐑟, ·𐑥𐑱𐑕𐑦 𐑕𐑩𐑒𐑕𐑰𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑐𐑼𐑕𐑢𐑱𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑲𐑝 𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑑 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑴𐑑. 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑣𐑰 𐑐𐑫𐑖𐑑 𐑪𐑓; 𐑯, 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑢𐑽𐑦 𐑐𐑫𐑤𐑦𐑙, 𐑯 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑐𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑤𐑩𐑕, 𐑳𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑒𐑕𐑧𐑕𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑧𐑑𐑕, 𐑣𐑰 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑩𐑒𐑕𐑰𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑜𐑧𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑲𐑼𐑯 𐑓𐑭𐑕𐑑. 𐑥𐑰𐑯𐑑𐑲𐑥, ·𐑜𐑭𐑚𐑮𐑦𐑧𐑤, 𐑩𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑞 𐑥𐑱𐑯-𐑮𐑶𐑩𐑤 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑-𐑣𐑧𐑛, 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑑𐑪𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑸𐑥 𐑦𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑡𐑧𐑕𐑗𐑼𐑟, 𐑯 𐑣𐑻𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑹𐑔 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑓𐑩𐑕𐑦𐑟 𐑝 𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑛𐑦 𐑛𐑵𐑥 𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑨𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑡𐑩𐑕 𐑩𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑛𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑦. 𐑯𐑬, 𐑢𐑲𐑤 ·𐑥𐑱𐑕𐑦, 𐑞 𐑥𐑱𐑑, 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑳𐑐 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕 𐑚𐑬, 𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑧𐑯𐑼𐑡𐑦 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑚 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑝𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑲𐑤𐑛 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑒𐑤𐑩𐑥𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑯 𐑧𐑕𐑱𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑜𐑧𐑑 𐑩 𐑓𐑺 𐑗𐑭𐑯𐑕 𐑓 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑶𐑟𐑛 𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑕, 𐑤𐑴! 𐑩 𐑚𐑮𐑷𐑛 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑖𐑨𐑛𐑴 𐑮𐑴𐑟 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑕𐑰; 𐑚𐑲 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑒, 𐑓𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯, 𐑑𐑧𐑥𐑐𐑼𐑺𐑦𐑤𐑦 𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑚𐑮𐑧𐑔 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑹𐑟𐑥𐑧𐑯. 𐑯𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑, 𐑞 𐑤𐑳𐑒𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑥𐑱𐑑, 𐑕𐑴 𐑓𐑫𐑤 𐑝 𐑓𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑾𐑕 𐑤𐑲𐑓, 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑥𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑺, 𐑯 𐑥𐑱𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑸𐑒 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑑, 𐑓𐑧𐑤 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑕𐑰 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑝 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑓𐑦𐑓𐑑𐑦 𐑘𐑸𐑛𐑟. 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑩 𐑗𐑦𐑐 𐑝 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑣𐑸𐑥𐑛, 𐑯𐑹 𐑩 𐑣𐑺 𐑝 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑹𐑟𐑥𐑩𐑯'𐑟 𐑣𐑧𐑛; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞 𐑥𐑱𐑑 𐑓 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑕𐑨𐑙𐑒.

𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑧𐑤 𐑑 𐑐𐑼𐑧𐑯𐑔𐑩𐑕𐑲𐑟 𐑣𐑽, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑓𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑨𐑒𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥-·𐑢𐑱𐑤 ·𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑼𐑦, 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑒𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑼𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑕 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑓𐑮𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑧𐑯𐑦. 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟, 𐑯𐑳𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑡𐑼𐑛 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑣𐑵 𐑦𐑟 𐑞𐑳𐑕 𐑩𐑯𐑲𐑩𐑤𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛; 𐑪𐑓𐑩𐑯𐑼 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑'𐑕 𐑚𐑬 𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑒𐑑 𐑪𐑓, 𐑹 𐑞 𐑔𐑲-𐑚𐑹𐑛, 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑞 𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑟𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟, 𐑦𐑟 𐑑𐑹𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕 𐑯 𐑩𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑟 𐑞 𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑝 𐑷𐑤 𐑦𐑟 𐑞 𐑕𐑻𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑕, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑹 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑳𐑝𐑼𐑛, 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑩 𐑕𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑩𐑤 𐑥𐑸𐑒 𐑝 𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑦𐑟 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑻𐑯𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤; 𐑞 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑒 𐑛𐑧𐑛.

𐑞 𐑣𐑴𐑤 𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑨𐑥𐑦𐑑𐑦, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑓𐑷𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑹𐑥 𐑝 ·𐑥𐑱𐑕𐑦, 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐. 𐑮𐑱𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑐𐑽𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑖𐑮𐑰𐑒—“𐑞 𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑤! 𐑞 𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑤!” ·𐑜𐑭𐑚𐑮𐑦𐑧𐑤 𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑛 𐑪𐑓 𐑞 𐑑𐑧𐑮𐑼-𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑒𐑮𐑵 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑓𐑻𐑞𐑼 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤. 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑑𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑝𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑒𐑤𐑴𐑞𐑛 𐑞 𐑸𐑒𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑨𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑓𐑤𐑵𐑩𐑯𐑕; 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑪𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑮𐑧𐑡𐑵𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑲𐑐𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑰𐑝𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑕𐑐𐑩𐑕𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑦 𐑓𐑹-𐑩𐑯𐑬𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑑, 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑛 𐑝 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑥𐑱𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑓𐑩𐑕𐑦, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑛𐑳𐑯, 𐑯 𐑕𐑴 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑗𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑥𐑸𐑒𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑲𐑛 𐑥𐑸𐑡𐑦𐑯 𐑩𐑤𐑬𐑛. 𐑣𐑰 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑱𐑥 𐑩 𐑯𐑱𐑥𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑑𐑧𐑮𐑼 𐑑 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐.

·𐑥𐑱𐑣𐑿 𐑣𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑒𐑤𐑵𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑼𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯, ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑐𐑫𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑕𐑗𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑼 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑓𐑹𐑚𐑺 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑢𐑲𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑣𐑰 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑑 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑢𐑲𐑑 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑦𐑓 𐑪𐑐𐑼𐑑𐑿𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑪𐑓𐑼. 𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑗 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑼𐑛—“𐑲.” 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑑𐑢𐑱, 𐑞𐑧𐑯, ·𐑜𐑭𐑚𐑮𐑦𐑧𐑤 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑕 𐑥𐑹 𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑰𐑑, 𐑜𐑤𐑺𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑥𐑨𐑯, 𐑯 𐑝𐑾𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑒𐑤𐑱𐑥𐑛, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑛𐑬𐑯𐑢𐑼𐑛 𐑐𐑶𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑓𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑼—“𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒, 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒 𐑝 𐑞 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑕𐑓𐑰𐑥𐑼—𐑛𐑧𐑛, 𐑯 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑞𐑺!—𐑚𐑦𐑢𐑺 𐑝 𐑞 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑕𐑓𐑰𐑥𐑼'𐑟 𐑧𐑯𐑛!”

𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑕𐑑𐑪𐑤𐑦𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑛 𐑩𐑕𐑲𐑛; 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑑 ·𐑥𐑱𐑣𐑿, “𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯, 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑡𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑔𐑷𐑑 𐑥𐑰 𐑝 𐑥𐑲 𐑤𐑧𐑑𐑼-𐑚𐑨𐑜; 𐑞𐑺 𐑦𐑟 𐑩 𐑤𐑧𐑑𐑼 𐑓 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑞𐑲 𐑪𐑓𐑦𐑕𐑼𐑟, 𐑦𐑓 𐑲 𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑯𐑪𐑑. 𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒, 𐑤𐑫𐑒 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑞 𐑚𐑨𐑜.”

𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑢𐑱𐑤-𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑕 𐑬𐑑 𐑩 𐑜𐑫𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑯𐑳𐑥𐑚𐑼 𐑝 𐑤𐑧𐑑𐑼𐑟 𐑓 𐑝𐑺𐑾𐑕 𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑕, 𐑣𐑵𐑟 𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑝𐑼𐑦 𐑑 𐑞 𐑐𐑻𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑑 𐑣𐑵𐑥 𐑞𐑱 𐑥𐑱 𐑚𐑰 𐑩𐑛𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑑, 𐑛𐑦𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑥𐑽 𐑗𐑭𐑯𐑕 𐑝 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑹 𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟. 𐑞𐑳𐑕, 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑤𐑧𐑑𐑼𐑟 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑮𐑰𐑗 𐑞𐑺 𐑥𐑸𐑒; 𐑯 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑸 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑰𐑝𐑛 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑩𐑑𐑱𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑯 𐑱𐑡 𐑝 𐑑𐑵 𐑹 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑘𐑽𐑟 𐑹 𐑥𐑹.

𐑕𐑵𐑯 ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒 𐑮𐑩𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑤𐑧𐑑𐑼 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛. 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑹𐑤𐑦 𐑑𐑳𐑥𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑛, 𐑛𐑨𐑥𐑐, 𐑯 𐑒𐑳𐑝𐑼𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑛𐑳𐑤, 𐑕𐑐𐑪𐑑𐑩𐑛, 𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑯 𐑥𐑴𐑤𐑛, 𐑦𐑯 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑢𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑒𐑧𐑐𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑛𐑸𐑒 𐑤𐑪𐑒𐑼 𐑝 𐑞 𐑒𐑨𐑚𐑦𐑯. 𐑝 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩 𐑤𐑧𐑑𐑼, ·𐑛𐑧𐑔 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑢𐑧𐑤 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑞 𐑐𐑴𐑕𐑑-𐑚𐑶.

“𐑒𐑨𐑯'𐑕𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑮𐑰𐑛 𐑦𐑑?” 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚. “𐑜𐑦𐑝 𐑦𐑑 𐑥𐑰, 𐑥𐑨𐑯. 𐑲, 𐑲, 𐑦𐑑'𐑕 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑩 𐑛𐑦𐑥 𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑷𐑤;—𐑢𐑪𐑑'𐑕 𐑞𐑦𐑕?” 𐑨𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑛𐑦𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑑 𐑬𐑑, ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒 𐑑𐑫𐑒 𐑩 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑒𐑳𐑑𐑦𐑙-𐑕𐑐𐑱𐑛 𐑐𐑴𐑤, 𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑲𐑓 𐑕𐑤𐑲𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑐𐑤𐑦𐑑 𐑞 𐑧𐑯𐑛, 𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑻𐑑 𐑞 𐑤𐑧𐑑𐑼 𐑞𐑺, 𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑱, 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑑 𐑑 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑, 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑒𐑤𐑴𐑟𐑼 𐑑 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐.

𐑥𐑰𐑯𐑑𐑲𐑥, ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑤𐑧𐑑𐑼, 𐑥𐑳𐑑𐑼𐑛, “·𐑥𐑼 ·𐑣𐑸—𐑘𐑧𐑕, ·𐑥𐑼 ·𐑣𐑨𐑮𐑦—(𐑩 𐑢𐑫𐑥𐑩𐑯'𐑟 𐑐𐑦𐑯𐑦 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛,—𐑞 𐑥𐑨𐑯'𐑟 𐑢𐑲𐑓, 𐑲'𐑤 𐑢𐑱𐑡𐑼)—·𐑲—·𐑥𐑼 ·𐑣𐑨𐑮𐑦 ·𐑥𐑱𐑕𐑦, ·𐑖𐑦𐑐 ·𐑡𐑧𐑮𐑩𐑚𐑴𐑩𐑥;—𐑢𐑲 𐑦𐑑'𐑕 ·𐑥𐑱𐑕𐑦, 𐑯 𐑣𐑰'𐑟 𐑛𐑧𐑛!”

“𐑐𐑫𐑼 𐑓𐑧𐑤𐑴! 𐑐𐑫𐑼 𐑓𐑧𐑤𐑴! 𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑲𐑓,” 𐑕𐑲𐑛 ·𐑥𐑱𐑣𐑿; “𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑤𐑧𐑑 𐑥𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑦𐑑.”

“𐑯𐑱, 𐑒𐑰𐑐 𐑦𐑑 𐑞𐑲𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓,” 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 ·𐑜𐑭𐑚𐑮𐑦𐑧𐑤 𐑑 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚; “𐑞𐑬 𐑸𐑑 𐑕𐑵𐑯 𐑜𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑱.”

“𐑒𐑻𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑔𐑮𐑪𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑞𐑰!” 𐑘𐑧𐑤𐑛 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚. “𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 ·𐑥𐑱𐑣𐑿, 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑯𐑬 𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑰𐑝 𐑦𐑑”; 𐑯 𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑓𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑦𐑝 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒'𐑕 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟, 𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑷𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑤𐑦𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑐𐑴𐑤, 𐑯 𐑮𐑰𐑗𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑑𐑩𐑢𐑹𐑛𐑟 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑕𐑴, 𐑞 𐑹𐑟𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑦𐑟𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑮𐑴𐑦𐑙; 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑 𐑛𐑮𐑦𐑓𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑩 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑑𐑩𐑢𐑹𐑛𐑟 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐'𐑕 𐑕𐑑𐑻𐑯; 𐑕𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑, 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑓 𐑚𐑲 𐑥𐑨𐑡𐑦𐑒, 𐑞 𐑤𐑧𐑑𐑼 𐑕𐑳𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑛 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑢𐑦𐑞 ·𐑜𐑭𐑚𐑮𐑦𐑧𐑤'𐑟 𐑰𐑜𐑼 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛. 𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑤𐑳𐑗𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑, 𐑕𐑰𐑟𐑛 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑-𐑯𐑲𐑓, 𐑯 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑤𐑧𐑑𐑼 𐑪𐑯 𐑦𐑑, 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑞𐑳𐑕 𐑤𐑴𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑨𐑒 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐. 𐑦𐑑 𐑓𐑧𐑤 𐑨𐑑 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚'𐑟 𐑓𐑰𐑑. 𐑞𐑧𐑯 ·𐑜𐑭𐑚𐑮𐑦𐑧𐑤 𐑖𐑮𐑰𐑒𐑑 𐑬𐑑 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑮𐑱𐑛𐑟 𐑑 𐑜𐑦𐑝 𐑢𐑱 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞𐑺 𐑹𐑟, 𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑨𐑯𐑼 𐑞 𐑥𐑿𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑚𐑴𐑑 𐑮𐑨𐑐𐑦𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑖𐑪𐑑 𐑩𐑢𐑱 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛.

𐑨𐑟, 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑤𐑵𐑛, 𐑞 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑿𐑥𐑛 𐑞𐑺 𐑢𐑻𐑒 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑡𐑨𐑒𐑩𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑣𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑮𐑧𐑓𐑼𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑲𐑤𐑛 𐑩𐑓𐑺.

·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 72. 𐑞 ·𐑥𐑳𐑙𐑒𐑦-·𐑮𐑴𐑐.

𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑑𐑿𐑥𐑳𐑤𐑗𐑵𐑩𐑕 𐑚𐑦𐑟𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑒𐑳𐑑𐑦𐑙-𐑦𐑯 𐑯 𐑩𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑩 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑞𐑺 𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑮𐑳𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑨𐑒𐑢𐑼𐑛𐑟 𐑯 𐑓𐑹𐑢𐑼𐑛𐑟 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑵. 𐑯𐑬 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑸 𐑢𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑣𐑽, 𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑸 𐑢𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑞𐑺. 𐑞𐑺 𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑴 𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕; 𐑓 𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑨𐑕 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑛𐑳𐑯 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦𐑢𐑺. 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑣𐑵 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑧𐑝𐑼𐑟 𐑞 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑰𐑯. 𐑢𐑰 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑯𐑬 𐑮𐑰𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑕 𐑬𐑼 𐑢𐑱 𐑩 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤. 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑜𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤'𐑟 𐑚𐑨𐑒, 𐑞 𐑚𐑤𐑳𐑚𐑼-𐑣𐑫𐑒 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑼𐑦𐑡𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑣𐑴𐑤 𐑞𐑺 𐑒𐑳𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑱𐑛𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑥𐑱𐑑𐑕. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑣𐑬 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑕𐑴 𐑒𐑤𐑳𐑥𐑟𐑦 𐑯 𐑢𐑱𐑑𐑦 𐑩 𐑥𐑨𐑕 𐑨𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑣𐑫𐑒 𐑜𐑧𐑑 𐑓𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑴𐑤? 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑞𐑺 𐑚𐑲 𐑥𐑲 𐑐𐑼𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑼 𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑯𐑛 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜, 𐑣𐑵𐑟 𐑛𐑿𐑑𐑦 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟, 𐑨𐑟 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑽, 𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑥𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑼'𐑟 𐑚𐑨𐑒 𐑓 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑤 𐑐𐑻𐑐𐑩𐑕 𐑮𐑦𐑓𐑻𐑛 𐑑. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑒𐑱𐑕𐑩𐑟, 𐑕𐑻𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑢𐑲𐑼 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑽 𐑖𐑨𐑤 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑱𐑯 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑞 𐑣𐑴𐑤 𐑓𐑤𐑧𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑹 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑪𐑐𐑼𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑒𐑤𐑵𐑛𐑩𐑛. 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑚𐑰 𐑦𐑑 𐑩𐑚𐑟𐑻𐑝𐑛, 𐑤𐑲𐑟 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑲𐑼𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑥𐑻𐑡𐑛, 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑧𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑦𐑥𐑰𐑛𐑾𐑑 𐑐𐑸𐑑𐑕 𐑪𐑐𐑼𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯. 𐑕𐑴 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑞𐑺, 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑑𐑧𐑯 𐑓𐑰𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑴 𐑞 𐑤𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑒, 𐑞 𐑐𐑫𐑼 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑽 𐑓𐑤𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑟 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑, 𐑣𐑭𐑓 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑯 𐑣𐑭𐑓 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼, 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑝𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑥𐑨𐑕 𐑮𐑦𐑝𐑪𐑤𐑝𐑟 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑑𐑮𐑧𐑛-𐑥𐑦𐑤 𐑚𐑦𐑯𐑰𐑔 𐑣𐑦𐑥. 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑩𐑒𐑱𐑠𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑕𐑗𐑩𐑯, ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜 𐑓𐑦𐑜𐑼𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑣𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑒𐑪𐑕𐑑𐑿𐑥—𐑩 𐑖𐑻𐑑 𐑯 𐑕𐑪𐑒𐑕—𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑑 𐑥𐑲 𐑲𐑟, 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑰𐑕𐑑, 𐑣𐑰 𐑩𐑐𐑽𐑛 𐑑 𐑳𐑯𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑩𐑛𐑝𐑭𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑡; 𐑯 𐑯𐑴 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑩 𐑚𐑧𐑑𐑼 𐑗𐑭𐑯𐑕 𐑑 𐑩𐑚𐑟𐑻𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑨𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑰 𐑕𐑰𐑯.

𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑕𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑡'𐑩𐑟 𐑚𐑬𐑟𐑥𐑩𐑯, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑟, 𐑞 𐑐𐑻𐑕𐑩𐑯 𐑣𐑵 𐑐𐑫𐑤𐑛 𐑞 𐑚𐑬-𐑹 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑴𐑑 (𐑞 𐑕𐑧𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑓𐑹𐑢𐑼𐑛), 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑥𐑲 𐑗𐑽𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑛𐑿𐑑𐑦 𐑑 𐑩𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑸𐑛-𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑨𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑨𐑥𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑛 𐑢𐑱𐑤'𐑟 𐑚𐑨𐑒. 𐑿 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑕𐑰𐑯 ·𐑦𐑑𐑨𐑤𐑾𐑯 𐑹𐑜𐑩𐑯-𐑚𐑶𐑟 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑛𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑙-𐑱𐑐 𐑚𐑲 𐑩 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑒𐑹𐑛. 𐑡𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑴, 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐'𐑕 𐑕𐑑𐑰𐑐 𐑕𐑲𐑛, 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑲 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑰, 𐑚𐑲 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑑𐑧𐑒𐑯𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑼𐑦 𐑩 𐑥𐑳𐑙𐑒𐑦-𐑮𐑴𐑐, 𐑩𐑑𐑨𐑗𐑑 𐑑 𐑩 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑪𐑙 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑐 𐑝 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑝𐑩𐑕 𐑚𐑧𐑤𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑱𐑕𐑑.

𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩 𐑣𐑿𐑥𐑼𐑩𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑚𐑦𐑟𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑓 𐑚𐑴𐑔 𐑝 𐑳𐑕. 𐑓, 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑢𐑰 𐑐𐑮𐑴𐑕𐑰𐑛 𐑓𐑻𐑞𐑼, 𐑦𐑑 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑥𐑳𐑙𐑒𐑦-𐑮𐑴𐑐 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑓𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑚𐑴𐑔 𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑟; 𐑓𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑑 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜'𐑟 𐑚𐑮𐑷𐑛 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑝𐑩𐑕 𐑚𐑧𐑤𐑑, 𐑯 𐑓𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑑 𐑥𐑲 𐑯𐑼𐑴 𐑤𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑢𐑳𐑯. 𐑕𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑓 𐑚𐑧𐑑𐑼 𐑹 𐑓 𐑢𐑻𐑕, 𐑢𐑰 𐑑𐑵, 𐑓 𐑞 𐑑𐑲𐑥, 𐑢𐑻 𐑢𐑧𐑛𐑩𐑛; 𐑯 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑐𐑫𐑼 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜 𐑕𐑦𐑙𐑒 𐑑 𐑮𐑲𐑟 𐑯𐑴 𐑥𐑹, 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑚𐑴𐑔 𐑿𐑕𐑦𐑡 𐑯 𐑪𐑯𐑼 𐑛𐑦𐑥𐑭𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑛 𐑝 𐑒𐑳𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑒𐑹𐑛, 𐑦𐑑 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑛𐑮𐑨𐑜 𐑥𐑰 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑱𐑒. 𐑕𐑴, 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑩𐑯 𐑰𐑤𐑪𐑙𐑜𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 ·𐑕𐑲𐑩𐑥𐑰𐑟 𐑤𐑦𐑜𐑩𐑗𐑼 𐑿𐑯𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑳𐑕. ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑥𐑲 𐑴𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑧𐑐𐑼𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑑𐑢𐑦𐑯 𐑚𐑮𐑳𐑞𐑼; 𐑯𐑹 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑲 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑢𐑱 𐑜𐑧𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑛 𐑝 𐑞 𐑛𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑼𐑩𐑕 𐑤𐑲𐑩𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑞 𐑣𐑧𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑯 𐑚𐑪𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑱𐑤𐑛.

𐑕𐑴 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑪𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑯 𐑥𐑧𐑑𐑩𐑓𐑦𐑟𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑲 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑰𐑝 𐑝 𐑥𐑲 𐑕𐑦𐑗𐑵𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑻𐑯𐑩𐑕𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑢𐑪𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟, 𐑲 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑑 𐑐𐑼𐑕𐑰𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑲 𐑴𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑡𐑵𐑨𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑬 𐑥𐑻𐑡𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑡𐑶𐑯𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑪𐑒 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑦 𐑝 𐑑𐑵; 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑲 𐑓𐑮𐑰 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑰𐑝𐑛 𐑩 𐑥𐑹𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑵𐑯𐑛; 𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑩𐑯𐑳𐑞𐑼'𐑟 𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑹 𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑓𐑹𐑗𐑵𐑯 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑐𐑤𐑳𐑯𐑡 𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑥𐑰 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑳𐑯𐑥𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑛𐑦𐑟𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑼 𐑯 𐑛𐑧𐑔. 𐑞𐑺𐑓𐑹, 𐑲 𐑕𐑷 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑽 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩 𐑕𐑹𐑑 𐑝 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑮𐑧𐑜𐑯𐑩𐑥 𐑦𐑯 ·𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑝𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑕; 𐑓 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯-𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑧𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑕𐑴 𐑜𐑮𐑴𐑕 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑡𐑳𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑕. 𐑯 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑓𐑻𐑞𐑼 𐑐𐑪𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑦𐑙—𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑲 𐑡𐑻𐑒𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑯𐑬 𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑢𐑰𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑯 𐑖𐑦𐑐, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑔𐑮𐑧𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑑 𐑡𐑨𐑥 𐑣𐑦𐑥—𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑓𐑻𐑞𐑼 𐑐𐑪𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑦𐑙, 𐑲 𐑕𐑱, 𐑲 𐑕𐑷 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑕𐑦𐑗𐑵𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑥𐑲𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑲𐑕 𐑕𐑦𐑗𐑵𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑥𐑹𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑚𐑮𐑰𐑞𐑟; 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦, 𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑒𐑱𐑕𐑩𐑟, 𐑣𐑰, 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑢𐑱 𐑹 𐑳𐑞𐑼, 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑞𐑦𐑕 ·𐑕𐑲𐑩𐑥𐑰𐑟 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑧𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑐𐑤𐑫𐑼𐑨𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑝 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑥𐑹𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑟. 𐑦𐑓 𐑘𐑹 𐑚𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑼 𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑒𐑕, 𐑿 𐑕𐑯𐑨𐑐; 𐑦𐑓 𐑘𐑹 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑔𐑦𐑒𐑺𐑦 𐑚𐑲 𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑿 𐑐𐑶𐑟𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑘𐑹 𐑐𐑦𐑤𐑟, 𐑿 𐑛𐑲. 𐑑𐑮𐑵, 𐑿 𐑥𐑱 𐑕𐑱 𐑞𐑨𐑑, 𐑚𐑲 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑰𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑒𐑷𐑖𐑩𐑯, 𐑿 𐑥𐑱 𐑐𐑪𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑱𐑐 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑯 𐑞 𐑥𐑳𐑤𐑑𐑦𐑑𐑿𐑛𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑤 𐑗𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑝 𐑤𐑲𐑓. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑤 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜'𐑟 𐑥𐑳𐑙𐑒𐑦-𐑮𐑴𐑐 𐑣𐑰𐑛𐑓𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑨𐑟 𐑲 𐑢𐑫𐑛, 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑡𐑻𐑒𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑴, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑲 𐑒𐑱𐑥 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑯𐑽 𐑕𐑤𐑲𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑴𐑝𐑼𐑚𐑹𐑛. 𐑯𐑹 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑲 𐑐𐑪𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑓𐑼𐑜𐑧𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑, 𐑛𐑵 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑲 𐑢𐑫𐑛, 𐑲 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑞 𐑥𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑡𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑝 𐑦𐑑.*

*𐑞 𐑥𐑳𐑙𐑒𐑦-𐑮𐑴𐑐 𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑼𐑟; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑥𐑳𐑙𐑒𐑦 𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑼 𐑢𐑻 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑑𐑲𐑛 𐑑𐑩𐑜𐑧𐑞𐑼. 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑮𐑵𐑝𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑼𐑦𐑡𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑿𐑕𐑦𐑡 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑩𐑛𐑿𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑯𐑴 𐑤𐑧𐑕 𐑩 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑯 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚, 𐑦𐑯 𐑹𐑛𐑼 𐑑 𐑩𐑓𐑹𐑛 𐑞 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑤𐑛 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑽 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑪𐑙𐑜𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑐𐑪𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑜𐑨𐑮𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑰 𐑓 𐑞 𐑓𐑱𐑔𐑓𐑩𐑤𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑯 𐑝𐑦𐑡𐑦𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑳𐑙𐑒𐑦-𐑮𐑴𐑐 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑼.

𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑲 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑪𐑓𐑩𐑯 𐑡𐑻𐑒 𐑐𐑫𐑼 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑢𐑰𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑯 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐—𐑢𐑺 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑩𐑒𐑱𐑠𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑓𐑷𐑤, 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑮𐑴𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑯 𐑕𐑢𐑱𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑚𐑴𐑔. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑞 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑡𐑨𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑡𐑧𐑐𐑼𐑛𐑦 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑴𐑟𐑛 𐑑. 𐑳𐑯𐑩𐑐𐑷𐑤𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑥𐑨𐑕𐑩𐑒𐑼 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑛𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑯𐑲𐑑, 𐑞 𐑖𐑸𐑒𐑕 𐑯𐑬 𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑖𐑤𐑦 𐑯 𐑥𐑹 𐑒𐑰𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑩𐑤𐑫𐑼𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑚𐑤𐑳𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑚𐑦𐑜𐑨𐑯 𐑑 𐑓𐑤𐑴 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑒𐑸𐑒𐑩𐑕—𐑞 𐑮𐑱𐑚𐑦𐑛 𐑒𐑮𐑰𐑗𐑼𐑟 𐑕𐑢𐑹𐑥𐑛 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑑 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑚𐑰𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑚𐑰𐑣𐑲𐑝.

𐑯 𐑮𐑲𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑖𐑸𐑒𐑕 𐑢𐑪𐑟 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜; 𐑣𐑵 𐑪𐑓𐑩𐑯 𐑐𐑫𐑖𐑑 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑩𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑤𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑰𐑑. 𐑩 𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑷𐑤𐑑𐑩𐑜𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑻 𐑦𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑩𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑐𐑮𐑱 𐑨𐑟 𐑩 𐑛𐑧𐑛 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑞 𐑳𐑞𐑼𐑢𐑲𐑟 𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑩𐑤𐑱𐑯𐑾𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑸𐑯𐑦𐑝𐑼𐑩𐑕 𐑖𐑸𐑒 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑛𐑩𐑥 𐑑𐑳𐑗 𐑩 𐑥𐑨𐑯.

𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼𐑞𐑩𐑤𐑧𐑕, 𐑦𐑑 𐑥𐑱 𐑢𐑧𐑤 𐑚𐑰 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑰𐑝𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑦𐑯𐑕 𐑞𐑱 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩 𐑮𐑨𐑝𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑓𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑼 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑐𐑲, 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑛𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑲𐑟 𐑑 𐑤𐑫𐑒 𐑖𐑸𐑐 𐑑 𐑞𐑧𐑥. 𐑩𐑒𐑹𐑛𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦, 𐑚𐑦𐑕𐑲𐑛𐑟 𐑞 𐑥𐑳𐑙𐑒𐑦-𐑮𐑴𐑐, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑲 𐑯𐑬 𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑡𐑻𐑒𐑑 𐑞 𐑐𐑫𐑼 𐑓𐑧𐑤𐑴 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑑𐑵 𐑒𐑤𐑴𐑕 𐑩 𐑝𐑦𐑕𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑑 𐑞 𐑥𐑷 𐑝 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑩 𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑽𐑤𐑦 𐑓𐑼𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑕 𐑖𐑸𐑒—𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑝𐑲𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑩𐑯𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑑𐑧𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯. 𐑕𐑩𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑞 𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑡𐑩𐑟, ·𐑑𐑨𐑖𐑑𐑱𐑜𐑴 𐑯 ·𐑛𐑨𐑜𐑵 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑿𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑓𐑤𐑳𐑮𐑦𐑖𐑑 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑩 𐑒𐑳𐑐𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑒𐑰𐑯 𐑢𐑱𐑤-𐑕𐑐𐑱𐑛𐑟, 𐑢𐑺𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞𐑱 𐑕𐑤𐑷𐑑𐑼𐑛 𐑨𐑟 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑖𐑸𐑒𐑕 𐑨𐑟 𐑞𐑱 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑮𐑰𐑗. 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑐𐑮𐑴𐑕𐑰𐑡𐑼 𐑝 𐑞𐑺𐑟, 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑖𐑫𐑼, 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑩𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑯 𐑚𐑦𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑞𐑧𐑥. 𐑞𐑱 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜'𐑟 𐑚𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑕, 𐑲 𐑩𐑛𐑥𐑦𐑑; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑣𐑱𐑕𐑑𐑦 𐑟𐑰𐑤 𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑕𐑻𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑕 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑚𐑴𐑔 𐑣𐑰 𐑯 𐑞 𐑖𐑸𐑒𐑕 𐑢𐑻 𐑨𐑑 𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑣𐑭𐑓 𐑣𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑯 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑚𐑤𐑳𐑛-𐑥𐑳𐑛𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼, 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑰𐑑 𐑕𐑐𐑱𐑛𐑟 𐑝 𐑞𐑺𐑟 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑯𐑽𐑼 𐑨𐑥𐑐𐑿𐑑𐑱𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑤𐑧𐑜 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑩 𐑑𐑱𐑤. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑐𐑫𐑼 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜, 𐑲 𐑕𐑩𐑐𐑴𐑟, 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑯 𐑜𐑭𐑕𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑺 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑲𐑼𐑯 𐑣𐑫𐑒—𐑐𐑫𐑼 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜, 𐑲 𐑕𐑩𐑐𐑴𐑟, 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑮𐑱𐑛 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 ·𐑘𐑴𐑡𐑴, 𐑯 𐑜𐑱𐑝 𐑳𐑐 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑤𐑲𐑓 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑜𐑪𐑛𐑟.

𐑢𐑧𐑤, 𐑢𐑧𐑤, 𐑥𐑲 𐑛𐑽 𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑮𐑱𐑛 𐑯 𐑑𐑢𐑦𐑯-𐑚𐑮𐑳𐑞𐑼, 𐑔𐑷𐑑 𐑲, 𐑨𐑟 𐑲 𐑛𐑮𐑵 𐑦𐑯 𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑕𐑤𐑨𐑒𐑑 𐑪𐑓 𐑞 𐑮𐑴𐑐 𐑑 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑕𐑢𐑧𐑤 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑰—𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑥𐑨𐑑𐑼𐑟 𐑦𐑑, 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑷𐑤? 𐑸 𐑿 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑕 𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑡 𐑝 𐑰𐑗 𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑝 𐑳𐑕 𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛? 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑳𐑯𐑕𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑿 𐑜𐑭𐑕𐑐 𐑦𐑯, 𐑦𐑟 ·𐑤𐑲𐑓; 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑖𐑸𐑒𐑕, 𐑘𐑹 𐑓𐑴𐑟; 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑕𐑐𐑱𐑛𐑟, 𐑘𐑹 𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑟; 𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑢𐑰𐑯 𐑖𐑸𐑒𐑕 𐑯 𐑕𐑐𐑱𐑛𐑟 𐑿 𐑸 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑕𐑨𐑛 𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑯 𐑐𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑤, 𐑐𐑫𐑼 𐑤𐑨𐑛.

𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑒𐑳𐑮𐑦𐑡! 𐑞𐑺 𐑦𐑟 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑗𐑽 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑹 𐑓 𐑿, ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜. 𐑓 𐑯𐑬, 𐑨𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑚𐑤𐑵 𐑤𐑦𐑐𐑕 𐑯 𐑚𐑤𐑳𐑛-𐑖𐑪𐑑 𐑲𐑟 𐑞 𐑦𐑜𐑟𐑷𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑕𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑡 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑒𐑤𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑳𐑐 𐑞 𐑗𐑱𐑯𐑟 𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑷𐑤 𐑛𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑪𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑺𐑦𐑤𐑦 𐑑𐑮𐑧𐑥𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑞 𐑕𐑲𐑛; 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑿𐑼𐑛 𐑩𐑛𐑝𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟, 𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑚𐑦𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑑, 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑪𐑤𐑩𐑑𐑼𐑦 𐑜𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑕 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑥—𐑢𐑪𐑑? 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑣𐑪𐑑 ·𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑘𐑨𐑒? 𐑯𐑴! 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑘𐑰 𐑜𐑪𐑛𐑟! 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑩 𐑒𐑳𐑐 𐑝 𐑑𐑧𐑐𐑦𐑛 𐑡𐑦𐑯𐑡𐑼 𐑯 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼!

“𐑡𐑦𐑯𐑡𐑼? 𐑛𐑵 𐑲 𐑕𐑥𐑧𐑤 𐑡𐑦𐑯𐑡𐑼?” 𐑕𐑩𐑕𐑐𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑭𐑕𐑒𐑑 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚, 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑯𐑽. “𐑘𐑧𐑕, 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑡𐑦𐑯𐑡𐑼,” 𐑐𐑽𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑨𐑟 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑳𐑯𐑑𐑱𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑒𐑳𐑐. 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑓 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑮𐑧𐑡𐑵𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑓 𐑩 𐑢𐑲𐑤, 𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑭𐑥𐑤𐑦 𐑢𐑷𐑒𐑑 𐑑𐑩𐑢𐑹𐑛𐑟 𐑞 𐑩𐑕𐑑𐑪𐑯𐑦𐑖𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑿𐑼𐑛 𐑕𐑤𐑴𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑱𐑦𐑙, “𐑡𐑦𐑯𐑡𐑼? 𐑡𐑦𐑯𐑡𐑼? 𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑿 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑞 𐑜𐑫𐑛𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑑 𐑑𐑧𐑤 𐑥𐑰, ·𐑥𐑼 ·𐑛𐑴-·𐑚𐑶, 𐑢𐑺 𐑤𐑲𐑟 𐑞 𐑝𐑻𐑗𐑵 𐑝 𐑡𐑦𐑯𐑡𐑼? 𐑡𐑦𐑯𐑡𐑼! 𐑦𐑟 𐑡𐑦𐑯𐑡𐑼 𐑞 𐑕𐑹𐑑 𐑝 𐑓𐑿𐑩𐑤 𐑿 𐑿𐑟, ·𐑛𐑴-𐑚𐑶, 𐑑 𐑒𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑤 𐑩 𐑓𐑲𐑼 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑖𐑦𐑝𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑚𐑩𐑤? 𐑡𐑦𐑯𐑡𐑼!—𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑟 𐑡𐑦𐑯𐑡𐑼? 𐑕𐑰-𐑒𐑴𐑤? 𐑓𐑲𐑼𐑢𐑫𐑛?—𐑤𐑵𐑕𐑦𐑓𐑼 𐑥𐑨𐑗𐑩𐑟?—𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑼?—𐑜𐑳𐑯𐑐𐑬𐑛𐑼?—𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑟 𐑡𐑦𐑯𐑡𐑼, 𐑲 𐑕𐑱, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑿 𐑪𐑓𐑼 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑒𐑳𐑐 𐑑 𐑬𐑼 𐑐𐑫𐑼 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜 𐑣𐑽.”

“𐑞𐑺 𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑕𐑯𐑰𐑒𐑦𐑙 ·𐑑𐑧𐑥𐑐𐑼𐑩𐑯𐑕 ·𐑕𐑩𐑕𐑲𐑩𐑑𐑦 𐑥𐑵𐑝𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑚𐑦𐑟𐑯𐑩𐑕,” 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑳𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑨𐑛𐑩𐑛, 𐑯𐑬 𐑩𐑐𐑮𐑴𐑗𐑦𐑙 ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒, 𐑣𐑵 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑡𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑓𐑹𐑢𐑼𐑛. “𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑿 𐑤𐑫𐑒 𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 ·𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑩𐑒𐑦𐑯, 𐑕𐑻: 𐑕𐑥𐑧𐑤 𐑝 𐑦𐑑, 𐑦𐑓 𐑿 𐑐𐑤𐑰𐑟.” 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑥𐑱𐑑'𐑕 𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑯𐑕, 𐑣𐑰 𐑨𐑛𐑩𐑛, “𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑿𐑼𐑛, ·𐑥𐑼 ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒, 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑞 𐑓𐑱𐑕 𐑑 𐑪𐑓𐑼 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑒𐑨𐑤𐑩𐑥𐑧𐑤 𐑯 𐑗𐑩𐑤𐑨𐑐 𐑑 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜, 𐑞𐑺, 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑪𐑓 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤. 𐑦𐑟 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑿𐑼𐑛 𐑩𐑯 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑔𐑦𐑒𐑺𐑦, 𐑕𐑻? 𐑯 𐑥𐑱 𐑲 𐑭𐑕𐑒 𐑢𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑦𐑟 𐑞 𐑕𐑹𐑑 𐑝 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑼𐑟 𐑚𐑲 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑣𐑰 𐑚𐑤𐑴𐑟 𐑚𐑨𐑒 𐑞 𐑤𐑲𐑓 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑩 𐑣𐑭𐑓-𐑛𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑥𐑨𐑯?”

“𐑲 𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑑,” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒, “𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑫𐑼 𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑓 𐑦𐑯𐑳𐑓.”

“𐑲, 𐑲, 𐑕𐑑𐑿𐑼𐑛,” 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚, “𐑢𐑰'𐑤 𐑑𐑰𐑗 𐑿 𐑑 𐑛𐑮𐑳𐑜 𐑩 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑽; 𐑯𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑘𐑹 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑔𐑦𐑒𐑺𐑦'𐑟 𐑥𐑧𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑽; 𐑿 𐑢𐑪𐑯𐑑 𐑑 𐑐𐑶𐑟𐑩𐑯 𐑳𐑕, 𐑛𐑵 𐑘𐑰? 𐑿 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑜𐑪𐑑 𐑬𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑖𐑫𐑼𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑪𐑯 𐑬𐑼 𐑤𐑲𐑝𐑟 𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑯𐑑 𐑑 𐑥𐑻𐑛𐑼 𐑳𐑕 𐑷𐑤, 𐑯 𐑐𐑪𐑒𐑩𐑑 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑴𐑕𐑰𐑛𐑟, 𐑛𐑵 𐑘𐑰?”

“𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑥𐑰,” 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 ·𐑛𐑴-·𐑚𐑶, “𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 ·𐑭𐑯𐑑 ·𐑗𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑚𐑮𐑷𐑑 𐑞 𐑡𐑦𐑯𐑡𐑼 𐑪𐑯 𐑚𐑹𐑛; 𐑯 𐑚𐑨𐑛 𐑥𐑰 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑜𐑦𐑝 𐑞 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑽𐑟 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑕𐑐𐑦𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑕, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑡𐑦𐑯𐑡𐑼-𐑡𐑳𐑚—𐑕𐑴 𐑖𐑰 𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑛 𐑦𐑑.”

“𐑡𐑦𐑯𐑡𐑼-𐑡𐑳𐑚! 𐑿 𐑡𐑦𐑯𐑡𐑼𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑭𐑕𐑒𐑩𐑤! 𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑞𐑨𐑑! 𐑯 𐑮𐑳𐑯 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑘𐑰 𐑑 𐑞 𐑤𐑪𐑒𐑼𐑟, 𐑯 𐑜𐑧𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑧𐑑𐑼. 𐑲 𐑣𐑴𐑐 𐑲 𐑛𐑵 𐑯𐑴 𐑮𐑪𐑙, ·𐑥𐑼 ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒. 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑞 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯'𐑟 𐑹𐑛𐑼𐑟—𐑜𐑮𐑪𐑜 𐑓 𐑞 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑽 𐑪𐑯 𐑩 𐑢𐑱𐑤.”

“𐑦𐑯𐑳𐑓,” 𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑤𐑲𐑛 ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒, “𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯, 𐑚𐑳𐑑—”

“𐑴, 𐑲 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑣𐑻𐑑 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑲 𐑣𐑦𐑑, 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑧𐑐𐑑 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑲 𐑣𐑦𐑑 𐑩 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑹 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑹𐑑; 𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑓𐑧𐑤𐑴'𐑟 𐑩 ·𐑢𐑰𐑟𐑩𐑤. 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑢𐑻 𐑿 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑕𐑱𐑦𐑙, 𐑕𐑻?”

“𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑞𐑦𐑕: 𐑜𐑴 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑯 𐑜𐑧𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑞𐑬 𐑢𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑞𐑲𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓.”

𐑢𐑧𐑯 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚 𐑮𐑰𐑩𐑐𐑽𐑛, 𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑱𐑥 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑛𐑸𐑒 𐑓𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑒 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛, 𐑯 𐑩 𐑕𐑹𐑑 𐑝 𐑑𐑰-𐑒𐑨𐑛𐑦 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑳𐑞𐑼. 𐑞 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑱𐑯𐑛 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑪𐑙 𐑕𐑐𐑦𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑕, 𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑑 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜; 𐑞 𐑕𐑧𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑢𐑪𐑟 ·𐑭𐑯𐑑 ·𐑗𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑦'𐑟 𐑜𐑦𐑓𐑑, 𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑓𐑮𐑰𐑤𐑦 𐑜𐑦𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑑 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑝𐑟.

·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 73. 𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚 𐑯 ·𐑓𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑒 𐑒𐑦𐑤 𐑩 ·𐑮𐑲𐑑 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤; 𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑩 ·𐑑𐑷𐑒 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑣𐑦𐑥.

𐑦𐑑 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑚𐑹𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑢𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑩 ·𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤'𐑟 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑛𐑦𐑡𐑩𐑕 𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑙𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛'𐑟 𐑕𐑲𐑛. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑰 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑤𐑧𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑿 𐑣𐑨𐑙𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑺 𐑩 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑢𐑰 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑜𐑧𐑑 𐑩 𐑗𐑭𐑯𐑕 𐑑 𐑩𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑑 𐑦𐑑. 𐑓 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑥𐑨𐑑𐑼𐑟 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑕, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑢𐑰 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑛𐑵 𐑯𐑬 𐑓 𐑞 𐑣𐑧𐑛, 𐑦𐑟 𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑱 𐑣𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑞 𐑑𐑨𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑥𐑱 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛.

𐑯𐑬, 𐑛𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑐𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑯𐑲𐑑 𐑯 𐑓𐑹𐑯𐑵𐑯, 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑜𐑮𐑨𐑡𐑵𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑮𐑦𐑓𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑩 𐑕𐑰, 𐑢𐑦𐑗, 𐑚𐑲 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑩𐑒𐑱𐑠𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑐𐑨𐑗𐑩𐑟 𐑝 𐑘𐑧𐑤𐑴 ·𐑚𐑮𐑦𐑑, 𐑜𐑱𐑝 𐑳𐑯𐑿𐑠𐑵𐑩𐑤 𐑑𐑴𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑝𐑦𐑕𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑝 ·𐑮𐑲𐑑 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟, 𐑩 𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑖𐑰𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑤𐑩𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑔𐑩𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑓𐑿 𐑕𐑩𐑐𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑐𐑼𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑼 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑤𐑻𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑧𐑯𐑦𐑢𐑺 𐑯𐑽. 𐑯 𐑞𐑴 𐑷𐑤 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑛𐑱𐑯𐑛 𐑞 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑗𐑼 𐑝 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑓𐑽𐑽 𐑒𐑮𐑰𐑗𐑼𐑟; 𐑯 𐑞𐑴 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑑 𐑒𐑮𐑵𐑟 𐑓 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑨𐑑 𐑷𐑤, 𐑯 𐑞𐑴 𐑖𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑐𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑯𐑳𐑥𐑚𐑼𐑟 𐑝 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑯𐑽 𐑞 ·𐑒𐑮𐑴𐑟𐑧𐑑𐑕 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑 𐑤𐑴𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑚𐑴𐑑; 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑯𐑬 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑩 ·𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑚𐑮𐑷𐑑 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑙𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑯 𐑚𐑦𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑩𐑛, 𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑼𐑐𐑮𐑲𐑟 𐑝 𐑷𐑤, 𐑞 𐑩𐑯𐑬𐑯𐑕𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑩 ·𐑮𐑲𐑑 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑚𐑰 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑗𐑼𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑛𐑱, 𐑦𐑓 𐑪𐑐𐑼𐑑𐑿𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑪𐑓𐑼𐑛.

𐑯𐑹 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑢𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑙. 𐑑𐑷𐑤 𐑕𐑐𐑬𐑑𐑕 𐑢𐑻 𐑕𐑰𐑯 𐑑 𐑤𐑰𐑢𐑼𐑛; 𐑯 𐑑𐑵 𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕, ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚'𐑟 𐑯 ·𐑓𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑒'𐑕, 𐑢𐑻 𐑛𐑦𐑑𐑨𐑗𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑐𐑼𐑕𐑿𐑑. 𐑐𐑫𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑻𐑞𐑼 𐑯 𐑓𐑻𐑞𐑼 𐑩𐑢𐑱, 𐑞𐑱 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑱𐑥 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑦𐑟𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑑 𐑞 𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑-𐑣𐑧𐑛. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕, 𐑞𐑱 𐑕𐑷 𐑩 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑣𐑰𐑐 𐑝 𐑑𐑿𐑥𐑳𐑤𐑗𐑵𐑩𐑕 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼, 𐑯 𐑕𐑵𐑯 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑯𐑿𐑟 𐑒𐑱𐑥 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑓𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑹 𐑚𐑴𐑔 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑓𐑭𐑕𐑑. 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑝𐑩𐑤 𐑐𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕 𐑢𐑻 𐑦𐑯 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑯 𐑕𐑲𐑑, 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑨𐑒𐑑 𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑛𐑮𐑨𐑜𐑛 𐑮𐑲𐑑 𐑑𐑩𐑢𐑹𐑛𐑟 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑑𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑱𐑤. 𐑕𐑴 𐑒𐑤𐑴𐑕 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑞 𐑥𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑼 𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑑 𐑞 𐑣𐑳𐑤, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑓 𐑣𐑰 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑥𐑨𐑤𐑦𐑕; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑜𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑥𐑱𐑤𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑩𐑥, 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑦𐑯 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑮𐑪𐑛𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑐𐑤𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑕, 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑩𐑐𐑽𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑝𐑿, 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑓 𐑛𐑲𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑞 𐑒𐑰𐑤. “𐑒𐑳𐑑, 𐑒𐑳𐑑!” 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑲 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑑 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕, 𐑢𐑦𐑗, 𐑓 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑, 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑐𐑶𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑮𐑷𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑛𐑧𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑨𐑖 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑞 𐑝𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑤'𐑟 𐑕𐑲𐑛. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑐𐑤𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑦 𐑝 𐑤𐑲𐑯 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑑𐑳𐑚𐑟, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑮𐑨𐑐𐑦𐑛𐑤𐑦, 𐑞𐑱 𐑐𐑱𐑛 𐑬𐑑 𐑩𐑚𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑝 𐑮𐑴𐑐, 𐑯 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑐𐑫𐑤𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑺 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑕𐑴 𐑨𐑟 𐑑 𐑜𐑧𐑑 𐑩𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑝 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐. 𐑓 𐑩 𐑓𐑿 𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑜𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤; 𐑓 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑞𐑱 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑕𐑤𐑨𐑒𐑑 𐑬𐑑 𐑞 𐑑𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑤𐑲𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑛𐑦𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯, 𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑐𐑤𐑲𐑛 𐑞𐑺 𐑹𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑩𐑯𐑳𐑞𐑼, 𐑞 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯 𐑔𐑮𐑧𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑑 𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑩 𐑓𐑿 𐑓𐑰𐑑 𐑩𐑛𐑝𐑭𐑯𐑕 𐑞𐑱 𐑕𐑷𐑑 𐑑 𐑜𐑱𐑯. 𐑯 𐑞𐑱 𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑒 𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑞𐑱 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑜𐑱𐑯 𐑦𐑑; 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦, 𐑩 𐑕𐑢𐑦𐑓𐑑 𐑑𐑮𐑧𐑥𐑼 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑓𐑧𐑤𐑑 𐑮𐑳𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑤𐑲𐑑𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑞 𐑒𐑰𐑤, 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑛 𐑤𐑲𐑯, 𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑱𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑦𐑯𐑰𐑔 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐, 𐑕𐑳𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑴𐑟 𐑑 𐑝𐑿 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑣𐑻 𐑚𐑬𐑟, 𐑕𐑯𐑨𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑯 𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑝𐑼𐑦𐑙; 𐑯 𐑕𐑴 𐑓𐑤𐑦𐑙𐑦𐑙 𐑪𐑓 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑛𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑦𐑙𐑟, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑛𐑮𐑪𐑐𐑕 𐑓𐑧𐑤 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑚𐑮𐑴𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑜𐑤𐑭𐑕 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼, 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑚𐑦𐑘𐑪𐑯𐑛 𐑷𐑤𐑕𐑴 𐑮𐑴𐑟 𐑑 𐑕𐑲𐑑, 𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑕 𐑥𐑹 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕 𐑢𐑻 𐑓𐑮𐑰 𐑑 𐑓𐑤𐑲. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞 𐑓𐑨𐑜𐑛 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑩𐑚𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑛, 𐑯 𐑚𐑤𐑲𐑯𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑷𐑤𐑑𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑹𐑕, 𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑻𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑑𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑑𐑵 𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑕𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑱 𐑐𐑼𐑓𐑹𐑥𐑛 𐑩 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑰𐑑 𐑕𐑻𐑒𐑦𐑑.

𐑥𐑰𐑯𐑑𐑲𐑥, 𐑞𐑱 𐑣𐑷𐑤𐑛 𐑥𐑹 𐑯 𐑥𐑹 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑤𐑲𐑯𐑟, 𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑒𐑤𐑴𐑕 𐑓𐑤𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑪𐑯 𐑚𐑴𐑔 𐑕𐑲𐑛𐑟, ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚 𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑼𐑛 ·𐑓𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑒 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑕 𐑓 𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑕; 𐑯 𐑞𐑳𐑕 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑯 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛 𐑞 𐑚𐑨𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑑, 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑞 𐑥𐑳𐑤𐑑𐑦𐑑𐑿𐑛𐑟 𐑝 𐑖𐑸𐑒𐑕 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑕𐑢𐑳𐑥 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤'𐑟 𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦, 𐑮𐑳𐑖𐑑 𐑑 𐑞 𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑖 𐑚𐑤𐑳𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑐𐑦𐑤𐑛, 𐑔𐑻𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑮𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑨𐑑 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑯𐑿 𐑜𐑨𐑖, 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑰𐑜𐑼 ·𐑦𐑟𐑮𐑱𐑩𐑤𐑲𐑑𐑕 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑯𐑿 𐑚𐑻𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑐𐑹𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑕𐑥𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑮𐑪𐑒.

𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑐𐑬𐑑 𐑜𐑮𐑵 𐑔𐑦𐑒, 𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑓𐑮𐑲𐑑𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑮𐑴𐑤 𐑯 𐑝𐑪𐑥𐑦𐑑, 𐑣𐑰 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑛 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑨𐑒 𐑩 𐑒𐑹𐑐𐑕.

𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑞 𐑑𐑵 𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑟𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑢𐑻 𐑦𐑯𐑜𐑱𐑡𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑱𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑒𐑹𐑛𐑟 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑤𐑵𐑒𐑕, 𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑢𐑱𐑟 𐑜𐑧𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑥𐑨𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑓 𐑑𐑴𐑦𐑙, 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑝𐑼𐑕𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑿𐑛 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑢𐑰𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑥.

“𐑲 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑞 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑤𐑳𐑥𐑐 𐑝 𐑓𐑬𐑤 𐑤𐑸𐑛,” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚, 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑜𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑔𐑷𐑑 𐑝 𐑣𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑛𐑵 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑕𐑴 𐑦𐑜𐑯𐑴𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑩 𐑤𐑩𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑔𐑩𐑯.

“𐑢𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑦𐑑?” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 ·𐑓𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑒, 𐑒𐑶𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑕𐑐𐑺 𐑤𐑲𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑'𐑕 𐑚𐑬, “𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑿 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑣𐑽 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑕 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑩 ·𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤'𐑟 𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑣𐑶𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑻 𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑼𐑛 𐑕𐑲𐑛, 𐑯 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑩 ·𐑮𐑲𐑑 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤'𐑟 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑤𐑸𐑚𐑼𐑛; 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑿 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑣𐑽, ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼𐑢𐑼𐑛𐑟 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑕𐑲𐑟?”

“𐑢𐑲 𐑯𐑪𐑑?

“𐑲 𐑛𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑯𐑴, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑲 𐑣𐑻𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑜𐑨𐑥𐑚𐑴𐑠 𐑜𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑝 𐑩 ·𐑓𐑧𐑛𐑩𐑤𐑩 𐑕𐑱𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑴, 𐑯 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑟 𐑑 𐑯𐑴 𐑷𐑤 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑕' 𐑗𐑸𐑥𐑟. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑲 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒 𐑣𐑰'𐑤 𐑗𐑸𐑥 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑑 𐑯𐑴 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑. 𐑲 𐑛𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑣𐑭𐑓 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑗𐑨𐑐, ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚. 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑿 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑯𐑴𐑑𐑦𐑕 𐑣𐑬 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑑𐑳𐑕𐑒 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑟 𐑩 𐑕𐑹𐑑 𐑝 𐑒𐑸𐑝𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑩 𐑕𐑯𐑱𐑒'𐑕 𐑣𐑧𐑛, ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚?”

“𐑕𐑦𐑙𐑒 𐑣𐑦𐑥! 𐑲 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑤𐑫𐑒 𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑨𐑑 𐑷𐑤; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑓 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑲 𐑜𐑧𐑑 𐑩 𐑗𐑭𐑯𐑕 𐑝 𐑩 𐑛𐑸𐑒 𐑯𐑲𐑑, 𐑯 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑸𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑚𐑫𐑤𐑢𐑼𐑒𐑕, 𐑯 𐑯𐑴 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑚𐑲; 𐑤𐑫𐑒 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑞𐑺, ·𐑓𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑒”—𐑐𐑶𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑕𐑰 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑽 𐑥𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑚𐑴𐑔 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟—“𐑲, 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑲! 𐑓𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑒, 𐑲 𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑞𐑨𐑑 ·𐑓𐑧𐑛𐑩𐑤𐑩 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑜𐑲𐑟. 𐑛𐑵 𐑿 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑰𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑒𐑪𐑒 𐑯 𐑚𐑫𐑤 𐑕𐑑𐑹𐑦 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑴𐑛 𐑩𐑢𐑱 𐑪𐑯 𐑚𐑹𐑛 𐑖𐑦𐑐? 𐑣𐑰'𐑟 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑤, 𐑲 𐑕𐑱. 𐑞 𐑮𐑰𐑟𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑲 𐑿 𐑛𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑕𐑰 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑑𐑱𐑤, 𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑪𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑑𐑳𐑒𐑕 𐑦𐑑 𐑳𐑐 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑕𐑲𐑑; 𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑒𐑶𐑤𐑛 𐑩𐑢𐑱 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑪𐑒𐑩𐑑, 𐑲 𐑜𐑧𐑕. 𐑚𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥! 𐑯𐑬 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑲 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒 𐑝 𐑦𐑑, 𐑣𐑰'𐑟 𐑷𐑤𐑢𐑱𐑟 𐑢𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑴𐑒𐑩𐑥 𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑓 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑑𐑴𐑟 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑵𐑑𐑕.”

“𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑤𐑰𐑐𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑵𐑑𐑕, 𐑛𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑣𐑰? 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑜𐑪𐑑 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑣𐑨𐑥𐑩𐑒; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑲'𐑝 𐑕𐑰𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑤𐑱 𐑝 𐑯𐑲𐑑𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑒𐑶𐑤 𐑝 𐑮𐑦𐑜𐑦𐑙.”

“𐑯𐑴 𐑛𐑬𐑑, 𐑯 𐑦𐑑'𐑕 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑪𐑟 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑑𐑱𐑤; 𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑶𐑤𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑛𐑬𐑯, 𐑛𐑵 𐑘𐑰 𐑕𐑰, 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑲 𐑝 𐑞 𐑮𐑦𐑜𐑦𐑙.”

“𐑢𐑪𐑑'𐑕 𐑞 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑕𐑴 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑑 𐑛𐑵 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑓?”

“𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑳𐑐 𐑩 𐑕𐑢𐑪𐑐 𐑹 𐑩 𐑚𐑸𐑜𐑦𐑯, 𐑲 𐑕𐑩𐑐𐑴𐑟.”

“𐑚𐑸𐑜𐑦𐑯?—𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑑?”

“𐑢𐑲, 𐑛𐑵 𐑘𐑰 𐑕𐑰, 𐑞 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑸𐑛 𐑚𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑞𐑨𐑑 ·𐑢𐑲𐑑 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑤 𐑞𐑺 𐑦𐑟 𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑯 𐑜𐑧𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑑 𐑕𐑢𐑪𐑐 𐑩𐑢𐑱 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑦𐑤𐑝𐑼 𐑢𐑪𐑗, 𐑹 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑴𐑤, 𐑹 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑹𐑑, 𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑣𐑰'𐑤 𐑕𐑼𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑼 ·𐑥𐑪𐑚𐑦 ·𐑛𐑦𐑒.”

“𐑐𐑵! 𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚, 𐑿 𐑸 𐑕𐑒𐑲𐑤𐑸𐑒𐑦𐑙; 𐑣𐑬 𐑒𐑨𐑯 ·𐑓𐑧𐑛𐑩𐑤𐑩 𐑛𐑵 𐑞𐑨𐑑?”

“𐑲 𐑛𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑯𐑴, ·𐑓𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑒, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑟 𐑩 𐑒𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑾𐑕 𐑗𐑨𐑐, 𐑯 𐑩 𐑢𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑳𐑯, 𐑲 𐑑𐑧𐑤 𐑘𐑰. 𐑢𐑲, 𐑞𐑱 𐑕𐑱 𐑨𐑟 𐑣𐑬 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑩 𐑕𐑷𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑓𐑤𐑨𐑜-𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑕, 𐑕𐑢𐑦𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑑𐑱𐑤 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑛𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑖 𐑰𐑟𐑦 𐑯 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑲𐑒, 𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑢𐑲𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑓 𐑞 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑜𐑳𐑝𐑼𐑯𐑼 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑴𐑥. 𐑢𐑧𐑤, 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑴𐑥, 𐑯 𐑭𐑕𐑒𐑑 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛. 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑤, 𐑕𐑢𐑦𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑵𐑓𐑕, 𐑳𐑐 𐑯 𐑕𐑧𐑟, '𐑲 𐑢𐑪𐑯𐑑 ·𐑡𐑪𐑯.' '𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑓?' 𐑕𐑧𐑟 𐑞 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑜𐑳𐑝𐑼𐑯𐑼. '𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑟𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑦𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑝 𐑘𐑹𐑟,' 𐑕𐑧𐑟 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑤, 𐑜𐑧𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑨𐑛,—'𐑲 𐑢𐑪𐑯𐑑 𐑑 𐑿𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑥.' '𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑣𐑦𐑥,' 𐑕𐑧𐑟 𐑞 𐑜𐑳𐑝𐑼𐑯𐑼—𐑯 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 ·𐑤𐑹𐑛, ·𐑓𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑒, 𐑦𐑓 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑤 𐑛𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑜𐑦𐑝 ·𐑡𐑪𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑱𐑠𐑦𐑨𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑒𐑪𐑤𐑼𐑩 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑣𐑰 𐑜𐑪𐑑 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑲'𐑤 𐑰𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑥𐑬𐑔𐑓𐑫𐑤. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑤𐑫𐑒 𐑖𐑸𐑐—𐑱𐑯𐑑 𐑿 𐑷𐑤 𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑦 𐑞𐑺? 𐑢𐑧𐑤, 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑐𐑫𐑤 𐑩𐑣𐑧𐑛, 𐑯 𐑤𐑧𐑑'𐑕 𐑜𐑧𐑑 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑙𐑕𐑲𐑛.”

“𐑲 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒 𐑲 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑧𐑥𐑚𐑼 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑕𐑑𐑹𐑦 𐑨𐑟 𐑿 𐑢𐑻 𐑑𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑙,” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 ·𐑓𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑒, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑞 𐑑𐑵 𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕 𐑢𐑻 𐑕𐑤𐑴𐑤𐑦 𐑩𐑛𐑝𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞𐑺 𐑚𐑻𐑛𐑩𐑯 𐑑𐑩𐑢𐑹𐑛𐑟 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐, “𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑲 𐑒𐑭𐑯𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑧𐑥𐑚𐑼 𐑢𐑺.”

“𐑔𐑮𐑰 ·𐑕𐑐𐑨𐑯𐑘𐑼𐑛𐑟? 𐑩𐑛𐑝𐑧𐑯𐑗𐑼𐑟 𐑝 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑚𐑤𐑳𐑛𐑦-𐑥𐑲𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑕𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑱𐑛𐑴𐑟? 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑘𐑰 𐑮𐑰𐑛 𐑦𐑑 𐑞𐑺, ·𐑓𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑒? 𐑲 𐑜𐑧𐑕 𐑘𐑰 𐑛𐑦𐑛?”

“𐑯𐑴: 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑕𐑷 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩 𐑚𐑫𐑒; 𐑣𐑻𐑛 𐑝 𐑦𐑑, 𐑞𐑴. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑯𐑬, 𐑑𐑧𐑤 𐑥𐑰, ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚, 𐑛𐑵 𐑿 𐑕𐑩𐑐𐑴𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑛𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑤 𐑿 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑡𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑯𐑬, 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑿 𐑕𐑱 𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑬 𐑪𐑯 𐑚𐑹𐑛 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛?”

“𐑨𐑥 𐑲 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑐𐑑 𐑒𐑦𐑤 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑱𐑤? 𐑛𐑳𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑤 𐑤𐑲𐑝 𐑓 𐑧𐑝𐑼; 𐑣𐑵 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑣𐑻𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑛𐑧𐑛? 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑿 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑕𐑰 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑐𐑸𐑟𐑩𐑯 𐑩 𐑢𐑺𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑹𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑓 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑤? 𐑯 𐑦𐑓 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑤 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑩 𐑤𐑨𐑗-𐑒𐑰 𐑑 𐑜𐑧𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑨𐑛𐑥𐑼𐑩𐑤'𐑟 𐑒𐑨𐑚𐑦𐑯, 𐑛𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑿 𐑕𐑩𐑐𐑴𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑒𐑮𐑷𐑤 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑩 𐑐𐑹𐑑𐑣𐑴𐑤? 𐑑𐑧𐑤 𐑥𐑰 𐑞𐑨𐑑, ·𐑥𐑼 ·𐑓𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑒?”

“𐑣𐑬 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑛𐑵 𐑿 𐑕𐑩𐑐𐑴𐑟 ·𐑓𐑧𐑛𐑩𐑤𐑩 𐑦𐑟, ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚?”

“𐑛𐑵 𐑿 𐑕𐑰 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑱𐑯𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑞𐑺?” 𐑐𐑶𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐; “𐑢𐑧𐑤, 𐑞𐑨𐑑'𐑕 𐑞 𐑓𐑦𐑜𐑼 𐑢𐑳𐑯; 𐑯𐑬 𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑣𐑵𐑐𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛'𐑟 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛, 𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑮𐑴 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑, 𐑓 𐑷𐑑𐑕, 𐑛𐑵 𐑿 𐑕𐑰; 𐑢𐑧𐑤, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑫𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑜𐑦𐑯 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 ·𐑓𐑧𐑛𐑩𐑤𐑩'𐑟 𐑱𐑡. 𐑯𐑹 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑒𐑵𐑐𐑼𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑒𐑫𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑖𐑴 𐑣𐑵𐑐𐑕 𐑦𐑯𐑳𐑓 𐑑 𐑥𐑱𐑒 𐑷𐑑𐑕 𐑦𐑯𐑳𐑓.”

“𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑕𐑰 𐑣𐑽, ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚, 𐑲 𐑔𐑷𐑑 𐑿 𐑩 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑚𐑴𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑡𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑯𐑬, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑿 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑑 𐑜𐑦𐑝 ·𐑓𐑧𐑛𐑩𐑤𐑩 𐑩 𐑕𐑰-𐑑𐑪𐑕, 𐑦𐑓 𐑿 𐑜𐑪𐑑 𐑩 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑗𐑭𐑯𐑕. 𐑯𐑬, 𐑦𐑓 𐑣𐑰'𐑟 𐑕𐑴 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑨𐑟 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑣𐑵𐑐𐑕 𐑝 𐑘𐑹𐑟 𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑑, 𐑯 𐑦𐑓 𐑣𐑰 𐑦𐑟 𐑜𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑤𐑦𐑝 𐑓 𐑧𐑝𐑼, 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑦𐑑 𐑛𐑵 𐑑 𐑐𐑦𐑗 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑴𐑝𐑼𐑚𐑹𐑛—𐑑𐑧𐑤 𐑥𐑰 𐑞𐑨𐑑?

“𐑜𐑦𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑩 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑛𐑳𐑒𐑦𐑙, 𐑧𐑯𐑦𐑣𐑬.”

“𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑣𐑰'𐑛 𐑒𐑮𐑷𐑤 𐑚𐑨𐑒.”

“𐑛𐑳𐑒 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯; 𐑯 𐑒𐑰𐑐 𐑛𐑳𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑥.”

“𐑕𐑩𐑐𐑴𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑑 𐑛𐑳𐑒 𐑿, 𐑞𐑴—𐑘𐑧𐑕, 𐑯 𐑛𐑮𐑬𐑯 𐑿—𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑞𐑧𐑯?”

“𐑲 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑑 𐑕𐑰 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑑𐑮𐑲 𐑦𐑑; 𐑲'𐑛 𐑜𐑦𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩 𐑐𐑺 𐑝 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑒 𐑲𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑫𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑛𐑺 𐑑 𐑖𐑴 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑱𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑨𐑛𐑥𐑼𐑩𐑤'𐑟 𐑒𐑨𐑚𐑦𐑯 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯 𐑓 𐑩 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑢𐑲𐑤, 𐑤𐑧𐑑 𐑩𐑤𐑴𐑯 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑹𐑤𐑪𐑐 𐑞𐑺, 𐑢𐑺 𐑣𐑰 𐑤𐑦𐑝𐑟, 𐑯 𐑣𐑽𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑𐑕 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑳𐑐𐑼 𐑛𐑧𐑒𐑕 𐑢𐑺 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑯𐑰𐑒𐑕 𐑕𐑴 𐑥𐑳𐑗. 𐑛𐑨𐑥 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑤, ·𐑓𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑒; 𐑕𐑴 𐑿 𐑕𐑩𐑐𐑴𐑟 𐑲'𐑥 𐑩𐑓𐑮𐑱𐑛 𐑝 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑤? 𐑣𐑵'𐑟 𐑩𐑓𐑮𐑱𐑛 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑧𐑐𐑑 𐑞 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑜𐑳𐑝𐑼𐑯𐑼 𐑣𐑵 𐑛𐑺𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑒𐑨𐑗 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑯 𐑐𐑫𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑦𐑯 𐑛𐑳𐑚𐑩𐑤-𐑛𐑸𐑚𐑦𐑟, 𐑨𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑛𐑦𐑟𐑻𐑝𐑟, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑤𐑧𐑑𐑕 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑜𐑴 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑒𐑦𐑛𐑯𐑨𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑐𐑰𐑐𐑩𐑤; 𐑲, 𐑯 𐑕𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑩 𐑚𐑪𐑯𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑐𐑰𐑐𐑩𐑤 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑤 𐑒𐑦𐑛𐑯𐑨𐑐𐑑, 𐑣𐑰'𐑛 𐑮𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑓 𐑣𐑦𐑥? 𐑞𐑺'𐑟 𐑩 𐑜𐑳𐑝𐑼𐑯𐑼!”

“𐑛𐑵 𐑿 𐑕𐑩𐑐𐑴𐑟 ·𐑓𐑧𐑛𐑩𐑤𐑩 𐑢𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑑 𐑒𐑦𐑛𐑯𐑨𐑐 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚?”

“𐑛𐑵 𐑲 𐑕𐑩𐑐𐑴𐑟 𐑦𐑑? 𐑿'𐑤 𐑯𐑴 𐑦𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑤𐑪𐑙, ·𐑓𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑒. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑲 𐑨𐑥 𐑜𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑯𐑬 𐑑 𐑒𐑰𐑐 𐑩 𐑖𐑸𐑐 𐑤𐑫𐑒-𐑬𐑑 𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥; 𐑯 𐑦𐑓 𐑲 𐑕𐑰 𐑧𐑯𐑦𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑕𐑩𐑕𐑐𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑕 𐑜𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑪𐑯, 𐑲'𐑤 𐑡𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑯𐑱𐑐 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑧𐑒, 𐑯 𐑕𐑱—𐑤𐑫𐑒 𐑣𐑽, ·𐑚𐑰𐑧𐑤𐑟𐑦𐑚𐑳𐑚, 𐑿 𐑛𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑛𐑵 𐑦𐑑; 𐑯 𐑦𐑓 𐑣𐑰 𐑥𐑱𐑒𐑕 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑓𐑳𐑕, 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 ·𐑤𐑹𐑛 𐑲'𐑤 𐑥𐑱𐑒 𐑩 𐑜𐑮𐑨𐑚 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑪𐑒𐑩𐑑 𐑓 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑑𐑱𐑤, 𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑦𐑑 𐑑 𐑞 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯, 𐑯 𐑜𐑦𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩 𐑮𐑧𐑯𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑯 𐑣𐑰𐑝𐑦𐑙, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑑𐑱𐑤 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑖𐑹𐑑 𐑪𐑓 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑥𐑐—𐑛𐑵 𐑿 𐑕𐑰; 𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑲 𐑮𐑭𐑞𐑼 𐑜𐑧𐑕 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑣𐑰 𐑓𐑲𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑛𐑪𐑒𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑒𐑢𐑽 𐑓𐑨𐑖𐑩𐑯, 𐑣𐑰'𐑤 𐑕𐑯𐑰𐑒 𐑪𐑓 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑 𐑞 𐑐𐑫𐑼 𐑕𐑨𐑑𐑦𐑕𐑓𐑨𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑓𐑰𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑑𐑱𐑤 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑢𐑰𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑤𐑧𐑜𐑟.”

“𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑿 𐑛𐑵 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑑𐑱𐑤, ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚?”

“𐑛𐑵 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑦𐑑? 𐑕𐑧𐑤 𐑦𐑑 𐑓 𐑩𐑯 𐑪𐑒𐑕 𐑢𐑦𐑐 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑢𐑰 𐑜𐑧𐑑 𐑣𐑴𐑥;—𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑧𐑤𐑕?”

“𐑯𐑬, 𐑛𐑵 𐑿 𐑥𐑰𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑿 𐑕𐑱, 𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑕𐑱𐑦𐑙 𐑷𐑤 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑙, ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚?”

“𐑥𐑰𐑯 𐑹 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑥𐑰𐑯, 𐑣𐑽 𐑢𐑰 𐑸 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐.”

𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕 𐑢𐑻 𐑣𐑽 𐑣𐑱𐑤𐑛, 𐑑 𐑑𐑴 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑤𐑸𐑚𐑼𐑛 𐑕𐑲𐑛, 𐑢𐑺 𐑓𐑤𐑵𐑒 𐑗𐑱𐑯𐑟 𐑯 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑯𐑧𐑕𐑦𐑕𐑺𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑷𐑤𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑦 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑺𐑛 𐑓 𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑥.

“𐑛𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑲 𐑑𐑧𐑤 𐑿 𐑕𐑴?” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 ·𐑓𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑒; “𐑘𐑧𐑕, 𐑿'𐑤 𐑕𐑵𐑯 𐑕𐑰 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑮𐑲𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑤'𐑟 𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑣𐑶𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑳𐑐 𐑪𐑐𐑩𐑟𐑦𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 ·𐑐𐑸𐑥𐑩𐑕𐑧𐑑𐑦'𐑟.”

𐑦𐑯 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑑𐑲𐑥, ·𐑓𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑒'𐑕 𐑕𐑱𐑦𐑙 𐑐𐑮𐑵𐑝𐑛 𐑑𐑮𐑵. 𐑨𐑟 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹, 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛 𐑕𐑑𐑰𐑐𐑤𐑦 𐑤𐑰𐑯𐑛 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑑𐑩𐑢𐑹𐑛𐑟 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 𐑢𐑱𐑤'𐑟 𐑣𐑧𐑛, 𐑯𐑬, 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑐𐑶𐑟 𐑝 𐑚𐑴𐑔 𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑟, 𐑖𐑰 𐑮𐑦𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑛 𐑣𐑻 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑒𐑰𐑤; 𐑞𐑴 𐑕𐑹𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑛, 𐑿 𐑥𐑱 𐑢𐑧𐑤 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑰𐑝. 𐑕𐑴, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑪𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑿 𐑣𐑶𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯 ·𐑤𐑪𐑒'𐑕 𐑣𐑧𐑛, 𐑿 𐑜𐑴 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑱; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑯𐑬, 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑕𐑲𐑛, 𐑣𐑶𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯 ·𐑒𐑭𐑯𐑑'𐑕 𐑯 𐑿 𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑚𐑨𐑒 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑐𐑫𐑼 𐑐𐑤𐑲𐑑. 𐑞𐑳𐑕, 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑥𐑲𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑓 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑒𐑰𐑐 𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑴𐑑. 𐑴, 𐑘𐑰 𐑓𐑵𐑤𐑦𐑖! 𐑔𐑮𐑴 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑔𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼-𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑟 𐑴𐑝𐑼𐑚𐑹𐑛, 𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑿 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑓𐑤𐑴𐑑 𐑤𐑲𐑑 𐑯 𐑮𐑲𐑑.

𐑦𐑯 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑴𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑞 𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦 𐑝 𐑩 𐑮𐑲𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑚𐑮𐑷𐑑 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑙𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐, 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑼𐑦 𐑐𐑮𐑴𐑕𐑰𐑛𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑒𐑱𐑕 𐑝 𐑩 𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 𐑢𐑱𐑤; 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦, 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑤𐑨𐑑𐑼 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕, 𐑞 𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑳𐑑 𐑪𐑓 𐑣𐑴𐑤, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑹𐑥𐑼 𐑞 𐑤𐑦𐑐𐑕 𐑯 𐑑𐑳𐑙 𐑸 𐑕𐑧𐑐𐑼𐑩𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑵𐑝𐑛 𐑯 𐑣𐑶𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑪𐑯 𐑛𐑧𐑒, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑢𐑧𐑤 𐑯𐑴𐑯 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑒 𐑚𐑴𐑯 𐑩𐑑𐑨𐑗𐑑 𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑛 𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑬𐑯-𐑐𐑰𐑕. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑯𐑳𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑞𐑦𐑕, 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑒𐑱𐑕, 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑛𐑳𐑯. 𐑞 𐑒𐑸𐑒𐑩𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑝 𐑚𐑴𐑔 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑛𐑮𐑪𐑐𐑑 𐑩𐑕𐑑𐑻𐑯; 𐑯 𐑞 𐑣𐑧𐑛-𐑤𐑱𐑛𐑩𐑯 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑩 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑧𐑥𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑩 𐑥𐑿𐑤 𐑒𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑐𐑺 𐑝 𐑴𐑝𐑼𐑚𐑻𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑐𐑨𐑯𐑽𐑟.

𐑥𐑰𐑯𐑑𐑲𐑥, ·𐑓𐑧𐑛𐑩𐑤𐑩 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑒𐑭𐑥𐑤𐑦 𐑲𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑮𐑲𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑤'𐑟 𐑣𐑧𐑛, 𐑯 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑯 𐑩𐑯𐑪𐑯 𐑜𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑛𐑰𐑐 𐑮𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑞𐑺 𐑑 𐑞 𐑤𐑲𐑯𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑴𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛. 𐑯 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑗𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑴 𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑸𐑟𐑰 𐑪𐑒𐑿𐑐𐑲𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑖𐑨𐑛𐑴; 𐑢𐑲𐑤, 𐑦𐑓 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑸𐑟𐑰'𐑟 𐑖𐑨𐑛𐑴 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞𐑺 𐑨𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑑 𐑚𐑤𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞, 𐑯 𐑤𐑧𐑙𐑔𐑩𐑯 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚'𐑟. 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑵 𐑑𐑶𐑤𐑛 𐑪𐑯, ·𐑤𐑨𐑐𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑖 𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑚𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑞𐑧𐑥, 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑐𐑭𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑟.

·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 74. 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤'𐑟 ·𐑣𐑧𐑛—·𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛 ·𐑝𐑿.

𐑣𐑽, 𐑯𐑬, 𐑸 𐑑𐑵 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟, 𐑤𐑱𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑺 𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑟 𐑑𐑩𐑜𐑧𐑞𐑼; 𐑤𐑧𐑑 𐑳𐑕 𐑡𐑶𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑥, 𐑯 𐑤𐑱 𐑑𐑩𐑜𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑬𐑼 𐑴𐑯.

𐑝 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑹𐑛𐑼 𐑝 𐑓𐑴𐑤𐑦𐑴 𐑤𐑩𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑔𐑩𐑯𐑟, 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑮𐑲𐑑 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑸 𐑚𐑲 𐑓𐑸 𐑞 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑯𐑴𐑑𐑢𐑻𐑞𐑦. 𐑞𐑱 𐑸 𐑞 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑮𐑧𐑜𐑿𐑤𐑼𐑤𐑦 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑥𐑨𐑯. 𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑯𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑑𐑼, 𐑞𐑱 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑞 𐑑𐑵 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑰𐑥𐑟 𐑝 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑯𐑴𐑯 𐑝𐑼𐑲𐑩𐑑𐑦𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤. 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑛𐑦𐑓𐑼𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑢𐑰𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑱𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑩𐑚𐑟𐑻𐑝𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑟; 𐑯 𐑨𐑟 𐑩 𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑝 𐑰𐑗 𐑦𐑟 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑥𐑴𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑙𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛'𐑟 𐑕𐑲𐑛; 𐑯 𐑨𐑟 𐑢𐑰 𐑥𐑱 𐑓𐑮𐑰𐑤𐑦 𐑜𐑴 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑑 𐑞 𐑳𐑞𐑼, 𐑚𐑲 𐑥𐑽𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑒𐑮𐑪𐑕 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑒:—𐑢𐑺, 𐑲 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑑 𐑯𐑴, 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑿 𐑩𐑚𐑑𐑱𐑯 𐑩 𐑚𐑧𐑑𐑼 𐑗𐑭𐑯𐑕 𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑛𐑦 𐑐𐑮𐑨𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 ·𐑕𐑧𐑑𐑪𐑤𐑩𐑡𐑦 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑣𐑽?

𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕, 𐑿 𐑸 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑒 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑢𐑰𐑯 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑟. 𐑚𐑴𐑔 𐑸 𐑥𐑨𐑕𐑦𐑝 𐑦𐑯𐑳𐑓 𐑦𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑕; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑦𐑟 𐑩 𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑥𐑨𐑔𐑩𐑥𐑨𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑑𐑮𐑦 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤'𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑞 ·𐑮𐑲𐑑 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤'𐑟 𐑕𐑨𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑤𐑨𐑒𐑕. 𐑞𐑺 𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑹 𐑒𐑨𐑮𐑩𐑒𐑑𐑼 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤'𐑟 𐑣𐑧𐑛. 𐑨𐑟 𐑿 𐑚𐑦𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑦𐑑, 𐑿 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑪𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑺𐑦𐑤𐑦 𐑘𐑰𐑤𐑛 𐑞 𐑦𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑕 𐑕𐑵𐑐𐑽𐑦𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑦𐑯 𐑐𐑶𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑐𐑼𐑝𐑱𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑛𐑦𐑜𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑦. 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕, 𐑑𐑵, 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑛𐑦𐑜𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑐𐑧𐑐𐑼 𐑯 𐑕𐑷𐑤𐑑 𐑒𐑳𐑤𐑼 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑦𐑑, 𐑜𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑑𐑴𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑩𐑛𐑝𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑱𐑡 𐑯 𐑤𐑸𐑡 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑽𐑾𐑯𐑕. 𐑦𐑯 𐑖𐑹𐑑, 𐑣𐑰 𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑞 𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑼𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑑𐑧𐑒𐑯𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑷𐑤 𐑩 “𐑜𐑮𐑱-𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑱𐑤.”

𐑤𐑧𐑑 𐑳𐑕 𐑯𐑬 𐑯𐑴𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑤𐑰𐑕𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑤𐑼 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑟—𐑯𐑱𐑥𐑤𐑦, 𐑞 𐑑𐑵 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑹𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑹𐑜𐑩𐑯𐑟, 𐑞 𐑲 𐑯 𐑞 𐑽. 𐑓𐑸 𐑚𐑨𐑒 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑝 𐑞 𐑣𐑧𐑛, 𐑯 𐑤𐑴 𐑛𐑬𐑯, 𐑯𐑽 𐑞 𐑨𐑙𐑜𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑲𐑞𐑼 𐑢𐑱𐑤'𐑟 𐑡𐑷, 𐑦𐑓 𐑿 𐑯𐑼𐑴𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑻𐑗, 𐑿 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑰 𐑩 𐑤𐑨𐑖𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑲, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑿 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑓𐑨𐑯𐑕𐑦 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑩 𐑘𐑳𐑙 𐑒𐑴𐑤𐑑'𐑕 𐑲; 𐑕𐑴 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑷𐑤 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑐𐑹𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑑 𐑞 𐑥𐑨𐑜𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑿𐑛 𐑝 𐑞 𐑣𐑧𐑛.

𐑯𐑬, 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑽 𐑕𐑲𐑛𐑢𐑱 𐑐𐑩𐑟𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤'𐑟 𐑲𐑟, 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑕𐑰 𐑩𐑯 𐑪𐑚𐑡𐑧𐑒𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑜𐑟𐑨𐑒𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑩𐑣𐑧𐑛, 𐑯𐑴 𐑥𐑹 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑦𐑜𐑟𐑨𐑒𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑩𐑕𐑑𐑻𐑯. 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑢𐑻𐑛, 𐑞 𐑐𐑩𐑟𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤'𐑟 𐑲𐑟 𐑒𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑪𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑝 𐑩 𐑥𐑨𐑯'𐑟 𐑽𐑟; 𐑯 𐑿 𐑥𐑱 𐑓𐑨𐑯𐑕𐑦, 𐑓 𐑘𐑹𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓, 𐑣𐑬 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑓𐑺 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑿, 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑿 𐑕𐑲𐑛𐑢𐑱𐑟 𐑕𐑻𐑝𐑱 𐑪𐑚𐑡𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑕 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑘𐑹 𐑽𐑟. 𐑿 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑓𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑿 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑭𐑯𐑛 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑔𐑻𐑑𐑦 𐑛𐑦𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑟 𐑝 𐑝𐑦𐑠𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑩𐑛𐑝𐑭𐑯𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑕𐑲𐑛-𐑤𐑲𐑯 𐑝 𐑕𐑲𐑑; 𐑯 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑔𐑻𐑑𐑦 𐑥𐑹 𐑚𐑦𐑣𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑑. 𐑦𐑓 𐑘𐑹 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑼𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑓𐑴 𐑢𐑻 𐑢𐑷𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑑𐑩𐑢𐑹𐑛𐑟 𐑿, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑛𐑨𐑜𐑼 𐑳𐑐𐑤𐑦𐑓𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑚𐑮𐑷𐑛 𐑛𐑱, 𐑿 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑱𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑑 𐑕𐑰 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑥𐑹 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑦𐑓 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑻 𐑕𐑑𐑰𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑿 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑚𐑦𐑣𐑲𐑯𐑛. 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑢𐑻𐑛, 𐑿 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑑𐑵 𐑚𐑨𐑒𐑕, 𐑕𐑴 𐑑 𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑒; 𐑚𐑳𐑑, 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑑𐑲𐑥, 𐑷𐑤𐑕𐑴, 𐑑𐑵 𐑓𐑮𐑳𐑯𐑑𐑕 (𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑳𐑯𐑑𐑕): 𐑓 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑱𐑒𐑕 𐑞 𐑓𐑮𐑳𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑩 𐑥𐑨𐑯—𐑢𐑪𐑑, 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑰𐑛, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑲𐑟?

𐑥𐑹𐑴𐑝𐑼, 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑥𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑲 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑯𐑬 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒 𐑝, 𐑞 𐑲𐑟 𐑸 𐑕𐑴 𐑐𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑼𐑕𐑧𐑐𐑑𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑑 𐑚𐑤𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑞𐑺 𐑝𐑦𐑟𐑿𐑩𐑤 𐑐𐑬𐑼, 𐑕𐑴 𐑨𐑟 𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑛𐑿𐑕 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑗𐑼 𐑯 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑑𐑵 𐑑 𐑞 𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑯; 𐑞 𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑽 𐑐𐑩𐑟𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤'𐑟 𐑲𐑟, 𐑦𐑓𐑧𐑒𐑗𐑵𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑦𐑝𐑲𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑨𐑟 𐑞𐑱 𐑸 𐑚𐑲 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑒𐑿𐑚𐑦𐑒 𐑓𐑰𐑑 𐑝 𐑕𐑪𐑤𐑦𐑛 𐑣𐑧𐑛, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑑𐑬𐑼𐑟 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑢𐑰𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑥𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑕𐑧𐑐𐑼𐑱𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑑𐑵 𐑤𐑱𐑒𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑝𐑨𐑤𐑦𐑟; 𐑞𐑦𐑕, 𐑝 𐑒𐑹𐑕, 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑧𐑐𐑼𐑱𐑑 𐑞 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑰𐑗 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑹𐑜𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑸𐑑𐑕. 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑞𐑺𐑓𐑹, 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑰 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑑 𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑗𐑼 𐑪𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑕𐑲𐑛, 𐑯 𐑩𐑯𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑑 𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑗𐑼 𐑪𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑲𐑛; 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑷𐑤 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑢𐑰𐑯 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑛𐑸𐑒𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑯 𐑯𐑳𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥. 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑥𐑱, 𐑦𐑯 𐑦𐑓𐑧𐑒𐑑, 𐑚𐑰 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑑 𐑤𐑫𐑒 𐑬𐑑 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑩 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑦-𐑚𐑪𐑒𐑕 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑑𐑵 𐑡𐑶𐑯𐑛 𐑕𐑨𐑖𐑩𐑟 𐑓 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑴. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑑𐑵 𐑕𐑨𐑖𐑩𐑟 𐑸 𐑕𐑧𐑐𐑼𐑩𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑛, 𐑥𐑱𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑑𐑵 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑴𐑟, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑕𐑨𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑺𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑝𐑿. 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑦𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤'𐑟 𐑲𐑟 𐑦𐑟 𐑩 𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑷𐑤𐑢𐑱𐑟 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑚𐑹𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑼𐑦; 𐑯 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑧𐑥𐑚𐑼𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑮𐑰𐑛𐑼 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑕𐑳𐑚𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑢𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑯𐑟.

𐑩 𐑒𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑾𐑕 𐑯 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑐𐑳𐑟𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑕𐑗𐑩𐑯 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑝𐑦𐑟𐑿𐑩𐑤 𐑥𐑨𐑑𐑼 𐑨𐑟 𐑑𐑳𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑞 ·𐑤𐑩𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑔𐑩𐑯. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑲 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑣𐑦𐑯𐑑. 𐑕𐑴 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑨𐑟 𐑩 𐑥𐑨𐑯'𐑟 𐑲𐑟 𐑸 𐑴𐑐𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑤𐑲𐑑, 𐑞 𐑨𐑒𐑑 𐑝 𐑕𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑪𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑦; 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑟, 𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑐 𐑥𐑦𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑪𐑑𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑪𐑚𐑡𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑕 𐑸 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑣𐑦𐑥. 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼𐑞𐑩𐑤𐑧𐑕, 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑢𐑳𐑯'𐑟 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑽𐑾𐑯𐑕 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑑𐑰𐑗 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑴 𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑦𐑯 𐑩𐑯 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑱𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑢𐑰𐑐 𐑝 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑜𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑕, 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑪𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑓 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑩𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑝𐑤𐑦, 𐑯 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑰𐑑𐑤𐑦, 𐑑 𐑦𐑜𐑟𐑨𐑥𐑦𐑯 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑑𐑵 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑟—𐑣𐑬𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑤𐑸𐑡 𐑹 𐑣𐑬𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑕𐑥𐑷𐑤—𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑑𐑲𐑥; 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑥𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑓 𐑞𐑱 𐑤𐑲 𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑯 𐑑𐑳𐑗 𐑰𐑗 𐑳𐑞𐑼. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑓 𐑿 𐑯𐑬 𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑑 𐑕𐑧𐑐𐑼𐑱𐑑 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑑𐑵 𐑪𐑚𐑡𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑕, 𐑯 𐑕𐑼𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑰𐑗 𐑚𐑲 𐑩 𐑕𐑻𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑛𐑸𐑒𐑯𐑩𐑕; 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑦𐑯 𐑹𐑛𐑼 𐑑 𐑕𐑰 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑞𐑧𐑥, 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩 𐑥𐑨𐑯𐑼 𐑨𐑟 𐑑 𐑚𐑮𐑦𐑙 𐑘𐑹 𐑥𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑑 𐑚𐑺 𐑪𐑯 𐑦𐑑, 𐑞 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑚𐑰 𐑳𐑑𐑼𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑒𐑤𐑵𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑘𐑹 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑥𐑐𐑼𐑼𐑦 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑕𐑯𐑩𐑕. 𐑣𐑬 𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑑, 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤? 𐑑𐑮𐑵, 𐑚𐑴𐑔 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑲𐑟, 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑝𐑟, 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑦𐑥𐑩𐑤𐑑𐑱𐑯𐑾𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑨𐑒𐑑; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑯 𐑕𐑴 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑥𐑹 𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑣𐑧𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑝, 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑚𐑲𐑯𐑦𐑙, 𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑥𐑨𐑯'𐑟, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑥𐑴𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑩𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑝𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑜𐑟𐑨𐑥𐑦𐑯 𐑑𐑵 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑕, 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑪𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑦𐑯 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑜𐑟𐑨𐑒𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑪𐑐𐑩𐑟𐑦𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯? 𐑦𐑓 𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑨𐑯, 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑥𐑸𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑩 𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑓 𐑩 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑢𐑻 𐑱𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑦𐑥𐑩𐑤𐑑𐑱𐑯𐑾𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑑 𐑜𐑴 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑑𐑵 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑚𐑤𐑩𐑥𐑟 𐑦𐑯 ·𐑿𐑒𐑤𐑦𐑛. 𐑯𐑹, 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑜𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛, 𐑦𐑟 𐑞𐑺 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑪𐑙𐑜𐑮𐑵𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑩𐑯.

𐑦𐑑 𐑥𐑱 𐑚𐑰 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑩𐑯 𐑲𐑛𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑦𐑥, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑷𐑤𐑢𐑱𐑟 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑑 𐑥𐑰, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑹𐑛𐑦𐑯𐑼𐑦 𐑝𐑨𐑕𐑦𐑤𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑥𐑵𐑝𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑚𐑦𐑕𐑧𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑹 𐑓𐑹 𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕; 𐑞 𐑑𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑛𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑯 𐑤𐑲𐑩𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑑 𐑒𐑢𐑽 𐑓𐑮𐑲𐑑𐑕, 𐑕𐑴 𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟; 𐑲 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑮𐑴𐑕𐑰𐑛𐑟 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑐𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑐𐑼𐑐𐑤𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑝 𐑝𐑴𐑤𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯, 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑞𐑺 𐑛𐑦𐑝𐑲𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑯 𐑛𐑲𐑩𐑥𐑧𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑦 𐑪𐑐𐑩𐑟𐑦𐑑 𐑐𐑬𐑼𐑟 𐑝 𐑝𐑦𐑠𐑩𐑯 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑪𐑤𐑝 𐑞𐑧𐑥.

𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞 𐑽 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑫𐑤 𐑨𐑟 𐑒𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑾𐑕 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑲. 𐑦𐑓 𐑿 𐑸 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑲𐑼 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑼 𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑮𐑱𐑕, 𐑿 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑑 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑑𐑵 𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑟 𐑓 𐑬𐑼𐑟, 𐑯 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑳𐑝𐑼 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑹𐑜𐑩𐑯. 𐑞 𐑽 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑯𐑴 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑤𐑰𐑓 𐑢𐑪𐑑𐑧𐑝𐑼; 𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑣𐑴𐑤 𐑦𐑑𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑿 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑣𐑸𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑻𐑑 𐑩 𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑤, 𐑕𐑴 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑑. 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑤𐑪𐑡𐑛 𐑩 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑚𐑦𐑣𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑞 𐑲. 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑 𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑽𐑟, 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑹𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑓𐑼𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑦𐑟 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑩𐑚𐑟𐑻𐑝𐑛 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑢𐑰𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑯 𐑞 𐑮𐑲𐑑. 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑞 𐑽 𐑝 𐑞 𐑓𐑹𐑥𐑼 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑩𐑯 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑴𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑙, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑤𐑨𐑑𐑼 𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑲𐑼𐑤𐑦 𐑯 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑳𐑝𐑼𐑛 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑥𐑧𐑥𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑯, 𐑕𐑴 𐑨𐑟 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑒𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑼𐑕𐑧𐑐𐑑𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑.

𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑒𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑾𐑕, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑴 𐑝𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑩 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑕𐑰 𐑞 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑕𐑴 𐑕𐑥𐑷𐑤 𐑩𐑯 𐑲, 𐑯 𐑣𐑽 𐑞 𐑔𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑩𐑯 𐑽 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑥𐑷𐑤𐑼 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑩 𐑣𐑺'𐑟? 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑓 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑲𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑚𐑮𐑷𐑛 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑤𐑧𐑯𐑟 𐑝 ·𐑣𐑻𐑖𐑩𐑤'𐑟 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑑𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑴𐑐; 𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑽𐑟 𐑒𐑩𐑐𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑕 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑐𐑹𐑗𐑩𐑟 𐑝 𐑒𐑩𐑔𐑰𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑤𐑟; 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑱𐑒 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑤𐑪𐑙𐑜𐑼 𐑝 𐑕𐑲𐑑, 𐑹 𐑖𐑸𐑐𐑼 𐑝 𐑣𐑽𐑦𐑙? 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑷𐑤.—𐑢𐑲 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑛𐑵 𐑿 𐑑𐑮𐑲 𐑑 “𐑦𐑯𐑤𐑸𐑡” 𐑘𐑹 𐑥𐑲𐑯𐑛? 𐑕𐑳𐑚𐑑𐑦𐑤𐑲𐑟 𐑦𐑑.

𐑤𐑧𐑑 𐑳𐑕 𐑯𐑬 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑢𐑪𐑑𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑤𐑰𐑝𐑼𐑟 𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑰𐑥-𐑧𐑯𐑡𐑦𐑯𐑟 𐑢𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛, 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑑 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 𐑢𐑱𐑤'𐑟 𐑣𐑧𐑛, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑥𐑱 𐑤𐑲 𐑚𐑪𐑑𐑩𐑥 𐑳𐑐; 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑩𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑲 𐑩 𐑤𐑨𐑛𐑼 𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑦𐑑, 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑩 𐑐𐑰𐑐 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑞 𐑥𐑬𐑔; 𐑯 𐑢𐑻 𐑦𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦 𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑬 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑰𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑧𐑐𐑼𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑦𐑑, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑯 𐑢𐑰 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 ·𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑳𐑒𐑦 ·𐑥𐑨𐑥𐑩𐑔 ·𐑒𐑱𐑝 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑥𐑩𐑒. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑤𐑧𐑑 𐑳𐑕 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑽 𐑚𐑲 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑑𐑵𐑔, 𐑯 𐑤𐑫𐑒 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑳𐑕 𐑢𐑺 𐑢𐑰 𐑸. 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑩 𐑮𐑾𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑿𐑑𐑦𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑯 𐑗𐑱𐑕𐑑-𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑬𐑔! 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑓𐑤𐑹 𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑤𐑦𐑙, 𐑤𐑲𐑯𐑛, 𐑹 𐑮𐑭𐑞𐑼 𐑐𐑱𐑐𐑼𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑜𐑤𐑦𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑥𐑧𐑥𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑯, 𐑜𐑤𐑪𐑕𐑦 𐑨𐑟 𐑚𐑮𐑲𐑛𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑨𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑟.

𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑬𐑑 𐑯𐑬, 𐑯 𐑤𐑫𐑒 𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑐𐑹𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑕 𐑤𐑴𐑼 𐑡𐑷, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑟 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑞 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑯𐑼𐑴 𐑤𐑦𐑛 𐑝 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑕 𐑕𐑯𐑳𐑓-𐑚𐑪𐑒𐑕, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑯𐑡 𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑧𐑯𐑛, 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑛 𐑝 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑕𐑲𐑛. 𐑦𐑓 𐑿 𐑐𐑮𐑲 𐑦𐑑 𐑳𐑐, 𐑕𐑴 𐑨𐑟 𐑑 𐑜𐑧𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑴𐑝𐑼𐑣𐑧𐑛, 𐑯 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑴𐑟 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑮𐑴𐑟 𐑝 𐑑𐑰𐑔, 𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑟 𐑩 𐑑𐑼𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑒 𐑐𐑹𐑑𐑒𐑳𐑤𐑦𐑕; 𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑗, 𐑩𐑤𐑨𐑕! 𐑦𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑵𐑝𐑟 𐑑 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑩 𐑐𐑫𐑼 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑼𐑦, 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑵𐑥 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑕𐑐𐑲𐑒𐑕 𐑓𐑷𐑤 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑹𐑕. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑓𐑸 𐑥𐑹 𐑑𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑓𐑨𐑞𐑩𐑥𐑟 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑰, 𐑿 𐑕𐑰 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑕𐑳𐑤𐑒𐑦 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑓𐑤𐑴𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑺 𐑕𐑩𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑛𐑦𐑡𐑩𐑕 𐑡𐑷, 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑓𐑦𐑓𐑑𐑰𐑯 𐑓𐑰𐑑 𐑤𐑪𐑙, 𐑣𐑨𐑙𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑨𐑑 𐑮𐑲𐑑-𐑨𐑙𐑜𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦, 𐑓 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑖𐑦𐑐'𐑕 𐑡𐑦𐑚-𐑚𐑵𐑥. 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑛𐑧𐑛; 𐑣𐑰 𐑦𐑟 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑦𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑛; 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑕𐑹𐑑𐑕, 𐑐𐑼𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑕; 𐑣𐑲𐑐𐑴𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑛𐑮𐑦𐑨𐑒; 𐑯 𐑕𐑴 𐑕𐑵𐑐𐑲𐑯, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑯𐑡𐑩𐑟 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑡𐑷 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑮𐑦𐑤𐑨𐑒𐑕𐑑, 𐑤𐑰𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑞𐑺 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑳𐑯𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑹𐑑 𐑝 𐑐𐑤𐑲𐑑, 𐑩 𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑮𐑴𐑗 𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑚, 𐑣𐑵 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑, 𐑯𐑴 𐑛𐑬𐑑, 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑱𐑑 𐑤𐑪𐑒-𐑡𐑷𐑟 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥.

𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑒𐑱𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑤𐑴𐑼 𐑡𐑷—𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑰𐑟𐑦𐑤𐑦 𐑳𐑯𐑣𐑦𐑯𐑡𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑩 𐑐𐑮𐑨𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑕𐑑 𐑸𐑑𐑦𐑕𐑑—𐑦𐑟 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑦𐑯𐑜𐑱𐑡𐑛 𐑯 𐑣𐑶𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑪𐑯 𐑛𐑧𐑒 𐑓 𐑞 𐑐𐑻𐑐𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑲𐑝𐑼𐑦 𐑑𐑰𐑔, 𐑯 𐑓𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑖𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑕𐑩𐑐𐑤𐑲 𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑸𐑛 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑚𐑴𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑞 𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑼𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑓𐑨𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑕𐑹𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑒𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑾𐑕 𐑸𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑟, 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑤𐑵𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑒𐑱𐑯𐑟, 𐑳𐑥𐑚𐑮𐑧𐑤𐑩-𐑕𐑑𐑪𐑒𐑕, 𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑑 𐑮𐑲𐑛𐑦𐑙-𐑢𐑦𐑐𐑕.

𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑤𐑪𐑙, 𐑢𐑽𐑦 𐑣𐑶𐑕𐑑 𐑞 𐑡𐑷 𐑦𐑟 𐑛𐑮𐑨𐑜𐑛 𐑪𐑯 𐑚𐑹𐑛, 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑓 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑻 𐑩𐑯 𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑼; 𐑯 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑐𐑼 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑟—𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑓𐑿 𐑛𐑱𐑟 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑞 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑢𐑻𐑒—·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜, ·𐑛𐑨𐑜𐑵, 𐑯 ·𐑑𐑨𐑖𐑑𐑱𐑜𐑴, 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑷𐑤 𐑩𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑦𐑖𐑑 𐑛𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑕, 𐑸 𐑕𐑧𐑑 𐑑 𐑛𐑮𐑷𐑦𐑙 𐑑𐑰𐑔. 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑒𐑰𐑯 𐑒𐑳𐑑𐑦𐑙-𐑕𐑐𐑱𐑛, ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜 𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑞 𐑜𐑳𐑥𐑟; 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑞 𐑡𐑷 𐑦𐑟 𐑤𐑨𐑖𐑑 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑙𐑚𐑴𐑤𐑑𐑕, 𐑯 𐑩 𐑑𐑨𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑮𐑦𐑜𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑓𐑑, 𐑞𐑱 𐑛𐑮𐑨𐑜 𐑬𐑑 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑑𐑰𐑔, 𐑨𐑟 ·𐑥𐑦𐑖𐑦𐑜𐑩𐑯 𐑪𐑒𐑕𐑩𐑯 𐑛𐑮𐑨𐑜 𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑕 𐑝 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑴𐑒𐑕 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑢𐑲𐑤𐑛 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟. 𐑞𐑺 𐑸 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑓𐑹𐑑𐑦-𐑑𐑵 𐑑𐑰𐑔 𐑦𐑯 𐑷𐑤; 𐑦𐑯 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟, 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑢𐑹𐑯 𐑛𐑬𐑯, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑱𐑛; 𐑯𐑹 𐑓𐑦𐑤𐑛 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑬𐑼 𐑸𐑑𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑤 𐑓𐑨𐑖𐑩𐑯. 𐑞 𐑡𐑷 𐑦𐑟 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼𐑢𐑼𐑛𐑟 𐑕𐑷𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑕𐑤𐑨𐑚𐑟, 𐑯 𐑐𐑲𐑤𐑛 𐑩𐑢𐑱 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑡𐑶𐑕𐑑𐑕 𐑓 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑬𐑟𐑩𐑟.

·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 75. 𐑞 ·𐑮𐑲𐑑 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤'𐑟 ·𐑣𐑧𐑛—·𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛 ·𐑝𐑿.

𐑒𐑮𐑪𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑒, 𐑤𐑧𐑑 𐑳𐑕 𐑯𐑬 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑩 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑤𐑫𐑒 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑮𐑲𐑑 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤'𐑟 𐑣𐑧𐑛.

𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑖𐑱𐑐 𐑞 𐑯𐑴𐑚𐑩𐑤 ·𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤'𐑟 𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑥𐑱 𐑚𐑰 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑺𐑛 𐑑 𐑩 ·𐑮𐑴𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑹-𐑗𐑨𐑮𐑾𐑑 (𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑳𐑯𐑑, 𐑢𐑺 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑴 𐑚𐑮𐑷𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛); 𐑕𐑴, 𐑨𐑑 𐑩 𐑚𐑮𐑷𐑛 𐑝𐑿, 𐑞 ·𐑮𐑲𐑑 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤'𐑟 𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑚𐑺𐑟 𐑩 𐑮𐑭𐑞𐑼 𐑦𐑯𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑜𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑧𐑥𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑑 𐑩 𐑡𐑲𐑜𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑜𐑨𐑤𐑦𐑪𐑑-𐑑𐑴𐑛 𐑖𐑵. 𐑑𐑵 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑛 𐑘𐑽𐑟 𐑩𐑜𐑴 𐑩𐑯 𐑴𐑤𐑛 ·𐑛𐑳𐑗 𐑝𐑶𐑦𐑡𐑼 𐑤𐑲𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑖𐑱𐑐 𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑝 𐑩 𐑖𐑵𐑥𐑱𐑒𐑼'𐑟 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑. 𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑹 𐑖𐑵, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑢𐑫𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑯𐑻𐑕𐑼𐑦 𐑑𐑱𐑤, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑕𐑢𐑹𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑮𐑵𐑛, 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑓𐑼𐑑𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑰 𐑤𐑪𐑡𐑛, 𐑖𐑰 𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑣𐑻 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑡𐑩𐑯𐑦.

𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑿 𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑯𐑽𐑼 𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑦𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑜𐑦𐑯𐑟 𐑑 𐑩𐑕𐑿𐑥 𐑛𐑦𐑓𐑼𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑨𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑕, 𐑩𐑒𐑹𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑘𐑹 𐑐𐑶𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑝𐑿. 𐑦𐑓 𐑿 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑪𐑯 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑦𐑑 𐑯 𐑤𐑫𐑒 𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑑𐑵 F-𐑖𐑱𐑐𐑑 𐑕𐑐𐑬𐑑𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑟, 𐑿 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑞 𐑣𐑴𐑤 𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑓 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑹𐑥𐑩𐑕 𐑚𐑱𐑕-𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑤, 𐑯 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑕𐑐𐑦𐑮𐑩𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑟, 𐑞 𐑨𐑐𐑼𐑗𐑼𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑕𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙-𐑚𐑹𐑛. 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯, 𐑦𐑓 𐑿 𐑓𐑦𐑒𐑕 𐑘𐑹 𐑲 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡, 𐑒𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛, 𐑒𐑴𐑥-𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑮𐑳𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑑𐑪𐑐 𐑝 𐑞 𐑥𐑨𐑕—𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑯, 𐑚𐑸𐑯𐑩𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑔𐑦𐑙, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑞 ·𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑯𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑟 𐑒𐑷𐑤 𐑞 “𐑒𐑮𐑬𐑯,” 𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑳𐑞𐑼𐑯 𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑼𐑟 𐑞 “𐑚𐑪𐑯𐑩𐑑” 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑮𐑲𐑑 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤; 𐑓𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑘𐑹 𐑲𐑟 𐑕𐑴𐑤𐑦 𐑪𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕, 𐑿 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑞 𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑓 𐑞 𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑙𐑒 𐑝 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑣𐑿𐑡 𐑴𐑒, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑚𐑻𐑛'𐑟 𐑯𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑒𐑮𐑪𐑗. 𐑨𐑑 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑮𐑱𐑑, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑿 𐑢𐑪𐑗 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑤𐑲𐑝 𐑒𐑮𐑨𐑚𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑯𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑤 𐑣𐑽 𐑪𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑚𐑪𐑯𐑩𐑑, 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩𐑯 𐑲𐑛𐑾 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑚𐑰 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑖𐑫𐑼 𐑑 𐑩𐑒𐑻 𐑑 𐑿; 𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑧𐑕, 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑰𐑛, 𐑘𐑹 𐑓𐑨𐑯𐑕𐑦 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑓𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑑𐑧𐑒𐑯𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑑𐑻𐑥 “𐑒𐑮𐑬𐑯” 𐑷𐑤𐑕𐑴 𐑚𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑴𐑛 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑦𐑑; 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑒𐑱𐑕 𐑿 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑬 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑥𐑲𐑑𐑦 𐑥𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑼 𐑦𐑟 𐑨𐑒𐑗𐑵𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑩 𐑛𐑲𐑩𐑛𐑧𐑥𐑛 𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑰, 𐑣𐑵𐑟 𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑯 𐑒𐑮𐑬𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑐𐑫𐑑 𐑑𐑩𐑜𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑓 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑥𐑸𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑥𐑨𐑯𐑼. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑓 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑚𐑰 𐑩 𐑒𐑦𐑙, 𐑣𐑰 𐑦𐑟 𐑩 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑕𐑳𐑤𐑒𐑦 𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑧𐑤𐑴 𐑑 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑕 𐑩 𐑛𐑲𐑩𐑛𐑧𐑥. 𐑤𐑫𐑒 𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑙𐑦𐑙 𐑤𐑴𐑼 𐑤𐑦𐑐! 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑩 𐑣𐑿𐑡 𐑕𐑳𐑤𐑒 𐑯 𐑐𐑬𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑞𐑺! 𐑩 𐑕𐑳𐑤𐑒 𐑯 𐑐𐑬𐑑, 𐑚𐑲 𐑒𐑸𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑼'𐑟 𐑥𐑧𐑠𐑼𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑, 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑑𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑦 𐑓𐑰𐑑 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑯 𐑓𐑲𐑝 𐑓𐑰𐑑 𐑛𐑰𐑐; 𐑩 𐑕𐑳𐑤𐑒 𐑯 𐑐𐑬𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑘𐑰𐑤𐑛 𐑿 𐑕𐑳𐑥 500 𐑜𐑨𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑶𐑤 𐑯 𐑥𐑹.

𐑩 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑐𐑦𐑑𐑦, 𐑯𐑬, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑳𐑯𐑓𐑹𐑗𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑚𐑰 𐑣𐑺-𐑤𐑦𐑐𐑑. 𐑞 𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑼 𐑦𐑟 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑩 𐑓𐑫𐑑 𐑩𐑒𐑮𐑪𐑕. 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑚𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑞 𐑥𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑛𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑹𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑝𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑼𐑵𐑝𐑾𐑯 𐑒𐑴𐑕𐑑, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑻𐑔𐑒𐑢𐑱𐑒𐑕 𐑒𐑷𐑟𐑛 𐑞 𐑚𐑰𐑗 𐑑 𐑜𐑱𐑐. 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑤𐑦𐑐, 𐑨𐑟 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑩 𐑕𐑤𐑦𐑐𐑼𐑦 𐑔𐑮𐑧𐑖𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛, 𐑢𐑰 𐑯𐑬 𐑕𐑤𐑲𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑥𐑬𐑔. 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑥𐑲 𐑢𐑻𐑛 𐑢𐑻 𐑲 𐑨𐑑 ·𐑥𐑨𐑒𐑦𐑯𐑷, 𐑲 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑝 𐑩𐑯 ·𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑾𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑜𐑢𐑭𐑥. 𐑜𐑫𐑛 ·𐑤𐑹𐑛! 𐑦𐑟 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑞 𐑮𐑴𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 ·𐑡𐑴𐑯𐑩 𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑑? 𐑞 𐑮𐑵𐑓 𐑦𐑟 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑑𐑢𐑧𐑤𐑝 𐑓𐑰𐑑 𐑣𐑲, 𐑯 𐑮𐑳𐑯𐑟 𐑑 𐑩 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑖𐑸𐑐 𐑨𐑙𐑜𐑩𐑤, 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑓 𐑞𐑺 𐑢𐑻 𐑩 𐑮𐑧𐑜𐑿𐑤𐑼 𐑮𐑦𐑡-𐑐𐑴𐑤 𐑞𐑺; 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑮𐑦𐑚𐑛, 𐑸𐑗𐑑, 𐑣𐑺𐑦 𐑕𐑲𐑛𐑟, 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑳𐑕 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑕, 𐑣𐑭𐑓 𐑝𐑻𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤, ·𐑖𐑰𐑥𐑧𐑰𐑑𐑼-𐑖𐑱𐑐𐑑 𐑕𐑤𐑨𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑚𐑴𐑯, 𐑕𐑱 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑛 𐑪𐑯 𐑩 𐑕𐑲𐑛, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑛𐑦𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑳𐑐𐑼 𐑐𐑸𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑹 𐑒𐑮𐑬𐑯 𐑚𐑴𐑯, 𐑓𐑹𐑥 𐑞𐑴𐑟 ·𐑝𐑩𐑯𐑰𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑚𐑤𐑲𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑧𐑤𐑕𐑢𐑺 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑒𐑻𐑕𐑼𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑛. 𐑞 𐑧𐑡𐑩𐑟 𐑝 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑚𐑴𐑯𐑟 𐑸 𐑓𐑮𐑦𐑯𐑡𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑺𐑦 𐑓𐑲𐑚𐑼𐑟, 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑞 ·𐑮𐑲𐑑 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑟 𐑞 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼, 𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑵𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑕𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑱𐑯𐑟 𐑞 𐑕𐑥𐑷𐑤 𐑓𐑦𐑖, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑴𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑥𐑬𐑞𐑛 𐑣𐑰 𐑜𐑴𐑟 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑞 𐑕𐑰𐑟 𐑝 ·𐑚𐑮𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑓𐑰𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑑𐑲𐑥. 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑩𐑤 𐑚𐑤𐑲𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑝 𐑚𐑴𐑯, 𐑨𐑟 𐑞𐑱 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑯𐑨𐑗𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑹𐑛𐑼, 𐑞𐑺 𐑸 𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑒𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑾𐑕 𐑥𐑸𐑒𐑕, 𐑒𐑻𐑝𐑟, 𐑣𐑪𐑤𐑴𐑟, 𐑯 𐑮𐑦𐑡𐑩𐑟, 𐑢𐑺𐑚𐑲 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑒𐑨𐑤𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑱𐑑 𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑰𐑗𐑼'𐑟 𐑱𐑡, 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑱𐑡 𐑝 𐑩𐑯 𐑴𐑒 𐑚𐑲 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑕𐑻𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑼 𐑮𐑦𐑙𐑟. 𐑞𐑴 𐑞 𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑦 𐑝 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑑𐑽𐑾𐑯 𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑸 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑛𐑦𐑥𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤, 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑝𐑼 𐑝 𐑨𐑯𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑡𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑚𐑩𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑦. 𐑨𐑑 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑮𐑱𐑑, 𐑦𐑓 𐑢𐑰 𐑘𐑰𐑤𐑛 𐑑 𐑦𐑑, 𐑢𐑰 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑜𐑮𐑭𐑯𐑑 𐑩 𐑓𐑸 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑𐑼 𐑱𐑡 𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑮𐑲𐑑 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑨𐑑 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑜𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑕 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑕𐑰𐑥 𐑮𐑰𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤.

𐑦𐑯 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟, 𐑞𐑺 𐑕𐑰𐑥 𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑝𐑱𐑤𐑛 𐑞 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑒𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑾𐑕 𐑓𐑨𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑚𐑤𐑲𐑯𐑛𐑟. 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝𐑶𐑦𐑡𐑼 𐑦𐑯 ·𐑐𐑻𐑗𐑩𐑟 𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑟 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑞 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑕 “𐑢𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑼𐑟” 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤'𐑟 𐑥𐑬𐑔;* 𐑩𐑯𐑳𐑞𐑼, “𐑣𐑪𐑜𐑟' 𐑚𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑩𐑤𐑟”; 𐑩 𐑔𐑻𐑛 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯 ·𐑙𐑨𐑒𐑤𐑶𐑑 𐑿𐑟𐑩𐑟 𐑞 𐑓𐑪𐑤𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑜𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑤𐑨𐑙𐑜𐑢𐑦𐑡: “𐑞𐑺 𐑸 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑑𐑵 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑛 𐑯 𐑓𐑦𐑓𐑑𐑦 𐑓𐑦𐑯𐑟 𐑜𐑮𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑪𐑯 𐑰𐑗 𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑳𐑐𐑼 𐑗𐑪𐑐, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑸𐑗 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑑𐑳𐑙 𐑪𐑯 𐑰𐑗 𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑬𐑔.”

*𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑲𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑳𐑕 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑮𐑲𐑑 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑮𐑾𐑤𐑦 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑩 𐑕𐑹𐑑 𐑝 𐑢𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑼, 𐑹 𐑮𐑭𐑞𐑼 𐑩 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑𐑭𐑖, 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑩 𐑓𐑿 𐑕𐑒𐑨𐑑𐑼𐑛 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑣𐑺𐑟 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑳𐑐𐑼 𐑐𐑸𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑬𐑑𐑼 𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑝 𐑞 𐑤𐑴𐑼 𐑡𐑷. 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑑𐑳𐑓𐑑𐑕 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑸𐑑 𐑩 𐑮𐑭𐑞𐑼 𐑚𐑮𐑦𐑜𐑩𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑖 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑳𐑞𐑼𐑢𐑲𐑟 𐑕𐑪𐑤𐑩𐑥 𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑯𐑕.

𐑨𐑟 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑯𐑴𐑟, 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑕𐑱𐑥 “𐑣𐑪𐑜𐑟' 𐑚𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑩𐑤𐑟,” “𐑓𐑦𐑯𐑟,” “𐑢𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑼𐑟,” “𐑚𐑤𐑲𐑯𐑛𐑟,” 𐑹 𐑢𐑪𐑑𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑿 𐑐𐑤𐑰𐑟, 𐑓𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑖 𐑑 𐑞 𐑤𐑱𐑛𐑦𐑟 𐑞𐑺 𐑚𐑳𐑕𐑒𐑕 𐑯 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑓𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑝𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑐𐑼𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑼, 𐑞 𐑛𐑦𐑥𐑭𐑯𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑲𐑯. 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑦𐑯 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑯 ·𐑨𐑯'𐑟 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑜𐑤𐑹𐑦, 𐑞 𐑓𐑸𐑞𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑱𐑤 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑓𐑨𐑖𐑩𐑯. 𐑯 𐑨𐑟 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑱𐑯𐑗𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑛𐑱𐑥𐑟 𐑥𐑵𐑝𐑛 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑜𐑱𐑤𐑦, 𐑞𐑴 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑡𐑷𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑨𐑟 𐑿 𐑥𐑱 𐑕𐑱; 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑕𐑴, 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑖𐑬𐑼, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑔𐑷𐑑𐑤𐑩𐑕𐑯𐑩𐑕, 𐑛𐑵 𐑢𐑰 𐑯𐑬𐑩𐑛𐑱𐑟 𐑓𐑤𐑲 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑡𐑷𐑟 𐑓 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑑𐑧𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯; 𐑞 𐑳𐑥𐑚𐑮𐑧𐑤𐑩 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑛 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑚𐑴𐑯.

𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑯𐑬 𐑓𐑼𐑜𐑧𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑚𐑤𐑲𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑼𐑟 𐑓 𐑩 𐑥𐑴𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑, 𐑯, 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑮𐑲𐑑 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤'𐑟 𐑥𐑬𐑔, 𐑤𐑫𐑒 𐑼𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑿 𐑩𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑖. 𐑕𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑒𐑪𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑱𐑛𐑟 𐑝 𐑚𐑴𐑯 𐑕𐑴 𐑥𐑦𐑔𐑪𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑛 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑, 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑿 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒 𐑿 𐑢𐑻 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑝 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 ·𐑣𐑸𐑤𐑩𐑥 𐑹𐑜𐑩𐑯, 𐑯 𐑜𐑱𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑔𐑬𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑐𐑲𐑐𐑕? 𐑓 𐑩 𐑒𐑸𐑐𐑩𐑑 𐑑 𐑞 𐑹𐑜𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑩 𐑮𐑳𐑜 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑪𐑓𐑑𐑩𐑕𐑑 ·𐑑𐑻𐑒𐑦—𐑞 𐑑𐑳𐑙, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑦𐑟 𐑜𐑤𐑵𐑛, 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑻, 𐑑 𐑞 𐑓𐑤𐑹 𐑝 𐑞 𐑥𐑬𐑔. 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑓𐑨𐑑 𐑯 𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑼, 𐑯 𐑨𐑐𐑑 𐑑 𐑑𐑺 𐑦𐑯 𐑐𐑰𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑶𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑑 𐑪𐑯 𐑛𐑧𐑒. 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑐𐑼𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑼 𐑑𐑳𐑙 𐑯𐑬 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑳𐑕; 𐑨𐑑 𐑩 𐑐𐑭𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑜𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑕 𐑲 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑕𐑱 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩 𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑕-𐑚𐑨𐑮𐑩𐑤𐑼; 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑟, 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑘𐑰𐑤𐑛 𐑿 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑩𐑥𐑬𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑶𐑤.

𐑺 𐑞𐑦𐑕, 𐑿 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑰𐑯 𐑞 𐑑𐑮𐑵𐑔 𐑝 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑲 𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞—𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑮𐑲𐑑 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑲𐑼𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑦𐑓𐑼𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑟. 𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑳𐑐, 𐑞𐑧𐑯: 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑮𐑲𐑑 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤'𐑟 𐑞𐑺 𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑴 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑢𐑧𐑤 𐑝 𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥; 𐑯𐑴 𐑲𐑝𐑼𐑦 𐑑𐑰𐑔 𐑨𐑑 𐑷𐑤; 𐑯𐑴 𐑤𐑪𐑙, 𐑕𐑤𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑥𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑩 𐑤𐑴𐑼 𐑡𐑷, 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤'𐑟. 𐑯𐑹 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑸 𐑞𐑺 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑝 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑚𐑤𐑲𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑝 𐑚𐑴𐑯; 𐑯𐑴 𐑣𐑿𐑡 𐑤𐑴𐑼 𐑤𐑦𐑐; 𐑯 𐑕𐑒𐑺𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑧𐑯𐑦𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑩 𐑑𐑳𐑙. 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯, 𐑞 ·𐑮𐑲𐑑 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑑𐑵 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑐𐑬𐑑-𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑟, 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑢𐑳𐑯.

𐑤𐑫𐑒 𐑘𐑹 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑, 𐑯𐑬, 𐑪𐑯 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑝𐑧𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑣𐑫𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑟, 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑞𐑱 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑤𐑲 𐑑𐑩𐑜𐑧𐑞𐑼; 𐑓 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑕𐑵𐑯 𐑕𐑦𐑙𐑒, 𐑳𐑯𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑹𐑛𐑩𐑛, 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑰; 𐑞 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑓𐑪𐑤𐑴𐑦𐑙.

𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑿 𐑒𐑨𐑗 𐑞 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤'𐑟 𐑞𐑺? 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑣𐑰 𐑛𐑲𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞, 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑝 𐑞 𐑤𐑪𐑙𐑜𐑼 𐑮𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑛 𐑕𐑰𐑥 𐑯𐑬 𐑓𐑱𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑩𐑢𐑱. 𐑲 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑮𐑷𐑛 𐑚𐑮𐑬 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑓𐑫𐑤 𐑝 𐑩 𐑐𐑮𐑺𐑦-𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑐𐑤𐑩𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑦𐑑𐑦, 𐑚𐑹𐑯 𐑝 𐑩 𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑩𐑑𐑦𐑝 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑓𐑼𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑨𐑟 𐑑 𐑛𐑧𐑔. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑥𐑸𐑒 𐑞 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑣𐑧𐑛'𐑟 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑯. 𐑕𐑰 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑩𐑥𐑱𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑤𐑴𐑼 𐑤𐑦𐑐, 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑨𐑒𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑞 𐑝𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑤'𐑟 𐑕𐑲𐑛, 𐑕𐑴 𐑨𐑟 𐑓𐑻𐑥𐑤𐑦 𐑑 𐑦𐑥𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑕 𐑞 𐑡𐑷. 𐑛𐑳𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑣𐑴𐑤 𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑕𐑰𐑥 𐑑 𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑒 𐑝 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑹𐑥𐑩𐑕 𐑐𐑮𐑨𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑮𐑧𐑟𐑩𐑤𐑵𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑓𐑱𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑛𐑧𐑔? 𐑞𐑦𐑕 ·𐑮𐑲𐑑 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑲 𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑩 ·𐑕𐑑𐑴𐑦𐑒; 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑩 ·𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑑𐑴𐑯𐑾𐑯, 𐑣𐑵 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑳𐑐 ·𐑕𐑐𐑦𐑯𐑴𐑟𐑩 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑤𐑨𐑑𐑼 𐑘𐑽𐑟.

·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 76. 𐑞 ·𐑚𐑨𐑑𐑼𐑦𐑙-·𐑮𐑨𐑥.

𐑺 𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑙, 𐑓 𐑞 𐑯𐑪𐑯𐑕, 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤'𐑟 𐑣𐑧𐑛, 𐑲 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑿, 𐑨𐑟 𐑩 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑓𐑦𐑟𐑦𐑪𐑤𐑩𐑡𐑦𐑕𐑑, 𐑕𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑦—𐑐𐑼𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑼𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑸𐑒 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑓𐑮𐑳𐑯𐑑 𐑨𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑, 𐑦𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑨𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑛𐑯𐑩𐑕. 𐑲 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑿 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑜𐑱𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑯𐑬 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑕𐑴𐑤 𐑝𐑿 𐑝 𐑓𐑹𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑘𐑹𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑳𐑯𐑦𐑜𐑟𐑨𐑡𐑼𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛, 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑡𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑥𐑩𐑑 𐑝 𐑢𐑪𐑑𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑚𐑨𐑑𐑼𐑦𐑙-𐑮𐑨𐑥 𐑐𐑬𐑼 𐑥𐑱 𐑚𐑰 𐑤𐑪𐑡𐑛 𐑞𐑺. 𐑣𐑽 𐑦𐑟 𐑩 𐑝𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑐𐑶𐑯𐑑; 𐑓 𐑿 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑲𐑞𐑼 𐑕𐑨𐑑𐑦𐑕𐑓𐑨𐑒𐑑𐑼𐑦𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑧𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑥𐑨𐑑𐑼 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑘𐑹𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓, 𐑹 𐑓 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑱𐑯 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑓𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑤 𐑨𐑟 𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑩𐑐𐑷𐑤𐑦𐑙, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑞 𐑤𐑧𐑕 𐑑𐑮𐑵 𐑦𐑝𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑕, 𐑐𐑼𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑕 𐑧𐑯𐑦𐑢𐑺 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑹𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑦.

𐑿 𐑩𐑚𐑟𐑻𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑹𐑛𐑦𐑯𐑼𐑦 𐑕𐑢𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑐𐑩𐑟𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑞 𐑓𐑮𐑳𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑩𐑯 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑦 𐑝𐑻𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑯 𐑑 𐑞 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼; 𐑿 𐑩𐑚𐑟𐑻𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑤𐑴𐑼 𐑐𐑸𐑑 𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑳𐑯𐑑 𐑕𐑤𐑴𐑐𐑕 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑼𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑨𐑒𐑢𐑼𐑛𐑟, 𐑕𐑴 𐑨𐑟 𐑑 𐑓𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑖 𐑥𐑹 𐑝 𐑩 𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑮𐑰𐑑 𐑓 𐑞 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑕𐑪𐑒𐑩𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑰𐑝𐑟 𐑞 𐑚𐑵𐑥-𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑤𐑴𐑼 𐑡𐑷; 𐑿 𐑩𐑚𐑟𐑻𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑥𐑬𐑔 𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑲𐑼𐑤𐑦 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑞 𐑣𐑧𐑛, 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑢𐑱, 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑰𐑛, 𐑨𐑟 𐑞𐑴 𐑘𐑹 𐑴𐑯 𐑥𐑬𐑔 𐑢𐑻 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑲𐑼𐑤𐑦 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑘𐑹 𐑗𐑦𐑯. 𐑥𐑹𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑿 𐑩𐑚𐑟𐑻𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑯𐑴 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑯𐑴𐑟; 𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑯𐑴𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑟—𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑐𐑬𐑑 𐑣𐑴𐑤—𐑦𐑟 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑑𐑪𐑐 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑧𐑛; 𐑿 𐑩𐑚𐑟𐑻𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑲𐑟 𐑯 𐑽𐑟 𐑸 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑲𐑛𐑟 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑧𐑛, 𐑯𐑽𐑤𐑦 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑔𐑻𐑛 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑲𐑼 𐑤𐑧𐑙𐑔 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑓𐑮𐑳𐑯𐑑. 𐑢𐑺𐑓𐑹, 𐑿 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑯𐑬 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑐𐑼𐑕𐑰𐑝𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑓𐑮𐑳𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤'𐑟 𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑦𐑟 𐑩 𐑛𐑧𐑛, 𐑚𐑤𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑢𐑷𐑤, 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑 𐑩 𐑕𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑩𐑤 𐑹𐑜𐑩𐑯 𐑹 𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑝 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑕𐑹𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑑𐑕𐑴𐑧𐑝𐑼. 𐑓𐑻𐑞𐑼𐑥𐑹, 𐑿 𐑸 𐑯𐑬 𐑑 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑼 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑰𐑥, 𐑤𐑴𐑼, 𐑚𐑨𐑒𐑢𐑼𐑛 𐑕𐑤𐑴𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑐𐑸𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑓𐑮𐑳𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑣𐑧𐑛, 𐑦𐑟 𐑞𐑺 𐑞 𐑕𐑤𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑝𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑡 𐑝 𐑚𐑴𐑯; 𐑯 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑿 𐑜𐑧𐑑 𐑯𐑽 𐑑𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑦 𐑓𐑰𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑓𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑛 𐑛𐑵 𐑿 𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑑 𐑞 𐑓𐑫𐑤 𐑒𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑾𐑤 𐑛𐑦𐑝𐑧𐑤𐑩𐑐𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑. 𐑕𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑣𐑴𐑤 𐑦𐑯𐑹𐑥𐑩𐑕 𐑚𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑥𐑨𐑕 𐑦𐑟 𐑨𐑟 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑛. 𐑓𐑲𐑯𐑩𐑤𐑦, 𐑞𐑴, 𐑨𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑕𐑵𐑯 𐑚𐑰 𐑮𐑦𐑝𐑰𐑤𐑛, 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑐𐑸𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑮𐑲𐑟 𐑞 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑛𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑑 𐑶𐑤; 𐑘𐑧𐑑, 𐑿 𐑸 𐑯𐑬 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑩𐑐𐑮𐑲𐑟𐑛 𐑝 𐑞 𐑯𐑱𐑗𐑼 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑚𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑕𐑴 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑜𐑯𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑕 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑩𐑐𐑨𐑮𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑦𐑓𐑧𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑕𐑦. 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑐𐑮𐑰𐑝𐑾𐑕 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑚𐑛 𐑑 𐑿 𐑣𐑬 𐑞 𐑚𐑤𐑳𐑚𐑼 𐑮𐑨𐑐𐑕 𐑞 𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑮𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑮𐑨𐑐𐑕 𐑩𐑯 𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑯𐑡. 𐑡𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑴 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑣𐑧𐑛; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑛𐑦𐑓𐑼𐑩𐑯𐑕: 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑞 𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑧𐑯𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑴𐑐, 𐑞𐑴 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑴 𐑔𐑦𐑒, 𐑦𐑟 𐑝 𐑩 𐑚𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑑𐑳𐑓𐑯𐑩𐑕, 𐑦𐑯𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑥𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑚𐑲 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑣𐑵 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑦𐑑. 𐑞 𐑕𐑦𐑝𐑽𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑐𐑶𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯, 𐑞 𐑖𐑸𐑐𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑕 𐑛𐑸𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑪𐑙𐑜𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑿𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑸𐑥, 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑰𐑚𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑦𐑑. 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑨𐑟 𐑞𐑴 𐑞 𐑓𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑛 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑢𐑻 𐑐𐑱𐑝𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑹𐑕𐑩𐑟' 𐑣𐑵𐑓𐑕. 𐑲 𐑛𐑵 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑕𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑤𐑻𐑒𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑦𐑑.

𐑚𐑦𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒 𐑘𐑹𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑷𐑤𐑕𐑴 𐑝 𐑩𐑯𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑔𐑦𐑙. 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑑𐑵 𐑤𐑸𐑡, 𐑤𐑴𐑛𐑩𐑛 ·𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑾𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑗𐑭𐑯𐑕 𐑑 𐑒𐑮𐑬𐑛 𐑯 𐑒𐑮𐑳𐑖 𐑑𐑩𐑢𐑹𐑛𐑟 𐑰𐑗 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑛𐑪𐑒𐑕, 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑛𐑵 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑼𐑟 𐑛𐑵? 𐑞𐑱 𐑛𐑵 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑩𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑢𐑰𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑥, 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑐𐑶𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑨𐑒𐑑, 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑥𐑽𐑤𐑦 𐑣𐑸𐑛 𐑕𐑳𐑚𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕, 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑲𐑼𐑯 𐑹 𐑢𐑫𐑛. 𐑯𐑴, 𐑞𐑱 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑞𐑺 𐑩 𐑤𐑸𐑡, 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑢𐑪𐑛 𐑝 𐑑𐑴 𐑯 𐑒𐑹𐑒, 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑧𐑤𐑩𐑐𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑔𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑯 𐑑𐑳𐑓𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑝 𐑪𐑒𐑕-𐑣𐑲𐑛. 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑝𐑤𐑦 𐑯 𐑳𐑯𐑦𐑯𐑡𐑼𐑛 𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑕 𐑞 𐑡𐑨𐑥 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑕𐑯𐑨𐑐𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑺 𐑴𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑕𐑐𐑲𐑒𐑕 𐑯 𐑲𐑼𐑯 𐑒𐑮𐑴-𐑚𐑸𐑟. 𐑚𐑲 𐑦𐑑𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑕𐑩𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑤𐑳𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑑𐑕 𐑞 𐑪𐑚𐑝𐑾𐑕 𐑓𐑨𐑒𐑑 𐑲 𐑛𐑮𐑲𐑝 𐑨𐑑 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑐𐑤𐑦𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑦 𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕, 𐑦𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑣𐑲𐑐𐑪𐑔𐑧𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑦 𐑩𐑒𐑻𐑛 𐑑 𐑥𐑰, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑹𐑛𐑦𐑯𐑼𐑦 𐑓𐑦𐑖 𐑐𐑩𐑟𐑧𐑕 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑛 𐑩 𐑕𐑢𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑛𐑼 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑥, 𐑒𐑱𐑐𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤, 𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑤, 𐑝 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑹 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯; 𐑯 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑨𐑟 𐑓𐑸 𐑨𐑟 𐑲 𐑯𐑴, 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑯𐑴 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑝𐑦𐑠𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥; 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑼𐑦𐑙, 𐑑𐑵, 𐑞 𐑳𐑞𐑼𐑢𐑲𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑤𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑥𐑨𐑯𐑼 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑣𐑰 𐑯𐑬 𐑛𐑦𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑷𐑤𐑑𐑩𐑜𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑚𐑦𐑯𐑰𐑔 𐑞 𐑕𐑻𐑓𐑦𐑕, 𐑯 𐑩𐑯𐑪𐑯 𐑕𐑢𐑦𐑥𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑦𐑑 𐑣𐑲 𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑝𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼; 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑳𐑯𐑩𐑚𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑤𐑨𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑕𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑝 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑧𐑯𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑴𐑐; 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑿𐑯𐑰𐑒 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑽𐑽 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑧𐑛; 𐑦𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑣𐑲𐑐𐑪𐑔𐑧𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑦 𐑩𐑒𐑻𐑛 𐑑 𐑥𐑰, 𐑲 𐑕𐑱, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑤𐑳𐑙-𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑛 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑦𐑒𐑴𐑥𐑟 𐑞𐑺 𐑥𐑱 𐑐𐑪𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑣𐑦𐑞𐑼𐑑𐑵 𐑳𐑯𐑯𐑴𐑯 𐑯 𐑳𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑧𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑬𐑑𐑼 𐑺, 𐑕𐑴 𐑨𐑟 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑕𐑩𐑕𐑧𐑐𐑑𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑑 𐑨𐑑𐑥𐑩𐑕𐑓𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑒 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑯 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯. 𐑦𐑓 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑚𐑰 𐑕𐑴, 𐑓𐑨𐑯𐑕𐑦 𐑞 𐑦𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑲𐑑, 𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑞 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑨𐑤𐑐𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑯 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑝 𐑝 𐑷𐑤 𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑚𐑿𐑑𐑕.

𐑯𐑬, 𐑥𐑸𐑒. 𐑳𐑯𐑻𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑛𐑧𐑛, 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑜𐑯𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤, 𐑳𐑯𐑦𐑯𐑡𐑼𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑷𐑤, 𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑶𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑦𐑯; 𐑞𐑺 𐑕𐑢𐑦𐑥𐑟 𐑚𐑦𐑣𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑩 𐑥𐑨𐑕 𐑝 𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑕 𐑤𐑲𐑓, 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑨𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑢𐑩𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑥𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑨𐑟 𐑐𐑲𐑤𐑛 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑦𐑟—𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑒𐑹𐑛; 𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑴𐑚𐑰𐑛𐑾𐑯𐑑 𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝𐑴𐑤𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯, 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑕𐑥𐑷𐑤𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑧𐑒𐑑. 𐑕𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑲 𐑖𐑨𐑤 𐑣𐑽𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑛𐑰𐑑𐑱𐑤 𐑑 𐑿 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑖𐑦𐑨𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑟 𐑯 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑐𐑴𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦𐑢𐑺 𐑤𐑻𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑨𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑝 𐑥𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑼; 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑲 𐑖𐑨𐑤 𐑖𐑴 𐑿 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑹 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑼𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑰𐑑𐑕; 𐑲 𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑿 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑮𐑦𐑯𐑬𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑦𐑜𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑮𐑧𐑡𐑵𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑦, 𐑯 𐑚𐑰 𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑦 𐑑 𐑩𐑚𐑲𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑞𐑦𐑕; 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑴 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑕𐑑𐑴𐑝 𐑩 𐑐𐑨𐑕𐑦𐑡 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑞 ·𐑦𐑕𐑥𐑩𐑕 𐑝 ·𐑛𐑺𐑾𐑯, 𐑯 𐑥𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑩𐑑𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑩𐑕𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑒, 𐑿 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑝𐑱𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑣𐑺 𐑝 𐑘𐑹 𐑲-𐑚𐑮𐑬. 𐑓 𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑧𐑕 𐑿 𐑴𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑿 𐑸 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑩 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑝𐑦𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑤 𐑯 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯 ·𐑑𐑮𐑵𐑔. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑒𐑤𐑽 ·𐑑𐑮𐑵𐑔 𐑦𐑟 𐑩 𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑓 𐑕𐑨𐑤𐑩𐑥𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑡𐑲𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑼; 𐑣𐑬 𐑕𐑥𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑗𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑓 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑝𐑦𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑞𐑧𐑯? 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑧𐑤 𐑞 𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑿𐑔 𐑤𐑦𐑓𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑛𐑮𐑧𐑛 𐑜𐑪𐑛𐑧𐑕'𐑩𐑟 𐑝𐑱𐑤 𐑨𐑑 ·𐑤𐑭𐑦𐑕?

·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 77. 𐑞 ·𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 ·𐑣𐑲𐑛𐑩𐑤𐑚𐑼𐑩 ·𐑑𐑳𐑯.

𐑯𐑬 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑟 𐑞 ·𐑚𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑒𐑱𐑕. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑑 𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑣𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑑 𐑼𐑲𐑑, 𐑿 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑯𐑴 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑞 𐑒𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑾𐑕 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑒𐑗𐑼 𐑝 𐑞 𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑪𐑐𐑼𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯.

𐑮𐑦𐑜𐑸𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤'𐑟 𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑨𐑟 𐑩 𐑕𐑪𐑤𐑦𐑛 𐑪𐑚𐑤𐑪𐑙, 𐑿 𐑥𐑱, 𐑪𐑯 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑤𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑯, 𐑕𐑲𐑛𐑢𐑱𐑟 𐑛𐑦𐑝𐑲𐑛 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑑𐑵 𐑒𐑶𐑯𐑟,* 𐑢𐑺𐑪𐑝 𐑞 𐑤𐑴𐑼 𐑦𐑟 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑯𐑦 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑒𐑗𐑼, 𐑓𐑹𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑾𐑥 𐑯 𐑡𐑷𐑟, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑳𐑐𐑼 𐑩𐑯 𐑳𐑙𐑒𐑗𐑵𐑩𐑕 𐑥𐑨𐑕 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑦 𐑓𐑮𐑰 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑚𐑴𐑯𐑟; 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑚𐑮𐑷𐑛 𐑓𐑹𐑢𐑼𐑛 𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑓𐑹𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑝𐑻𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑩𐑐𐑨𐑮𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑓𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑛 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤. 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑥𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑞 𐑓𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑛 𐑣𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑳𐑚𐑛𐑦𐑝𐑲𐑛 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑳𐑐𐑼 𐑒𐑶𐑯, 𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑿 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑑𐑵 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑩𐑤 𐑐𐑸𐑑𐑕, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑢𐑻 𐑯𐑨𐑗𐑼𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑦𐑝𐑲𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑷𐑤 𐑝 𐑩 𐑔𐑦𐑒 𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑕𐑳𐑚𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕.

*𐑒𐑶𐑯 𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑩 ·𐑿𐑒𐑤𐑦𐑛𐑾𐑯 𐑑𐑻𐑥. 𐑦𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑪𐑙𐑟 𐑑 𐑞 𐑐𐑘𐑫𐑼 𐑯𐑷𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑥𐑨𐑔𐑩𐑥𐑨𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑕. 𐑲 𐑯𐑴 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑛𐑦𐑓𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹. 𐑩 𐑒𐑶𐑯 𐑦𐑟 𐑩 𐑕𐑪𐑤𐑦𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑛𐑦𐑓𐑼𐑟 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑩 𐑢𐑧𐑡 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑖𐑸𐑐 𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑓𐑹𐑥𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑰𐑐 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑤𐑦𐑯𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑕𐑲𐑛, 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑛 𐑝 𐑞 𐑥𐑿𐑗𐑵𐑩𐑤 𐑑𐑱𐑐𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑚𐑴𐑔 𐑕𐑲𐑛𐑟.

𐑞 𐑤𐑴𐑼 𐑕𐑳𐑚𐑛𐑦𐑝𐑲𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑐𐑸𐑑, 𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑛 𐑞 𐑡𐑳𐑙𐑒, 𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑦𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑕 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑦𐑒𐑴𐑥 𐑝 𐑶𐑤, 𐑓𐑹𐑥𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑪𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑯 𐑮𐑰𐑒𐑮𐑪𐑕𐑦𐑙, 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑑𐑧𐑯 𐑔𐑬𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑓𐑦𐑤𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑟, 𐑝 𐑑𐑳𐑓 𐑦𐑤𐑨𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑓𐑲𐑚𐑼𐑟 𐑔𐑮𐑵𐑬𐑑 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑣𐑴𐑤 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑑. 𐑞 𐑳𐑐𐑼 𐑐𐑸𐑑, 𐑯𐑴𐑯 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 ·𐑒𐑱𐑕, 𐑥𐑱 𐑚𐑰 𐑮𐑦𐑜𐑸𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 ·𐑣𐑲𐑛𐑩𐑤𐑚𐑼𐑩 ·𐑑𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤. 𐑯 𐑨𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑓𐑱𐑥𐑩𐑕 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑑𐑽𐑕 𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑸𐑝𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑳𐑯𐑑, 𐑕𐑴 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤'𐑟 𐑝𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑐𐑤𐑨𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑓𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑛 𐑓𐑹𐑥𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑿𐑥𐑼𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡 𐑛𐑦𐑝𐑲𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑓 𐑞 𐑧𐑥𐑚𐑤𐑩𐑥𐑨𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑩𐑛𐑹𐑯𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑕 𐑑𐑳𐑯. 𐑥𐑹𐑴𐑝𐑼, 𐑨𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑝 ·𐑣𐑲𐑛𐑩𐑤𐑚𐑼𐑩 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑷𐑤𐑢𐑱𐑟 𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑤𐑧𐑯𐑦𐑖𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑩𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑲𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑮𐑧𐑯𐑦𐑖 𐑝𐑨𐑤𐑦𐑟, 𐑕𐑴 𐑞 𐑑𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑱𐑯𐑟 𐑚𐑲 𐑓𐑸 𐑞 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑷𐑤 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑶𐑤𐑦 𐑝𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑡𐑩𐑟; 𐑯𐑱𐑥𐑤𐑦, 𐑞 𐑣𐑲𐑤𐑦-𐑐𐑮𐑲𐑟𐑛 𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥𐑩𐑕𐑧𐑑𐑦, 𐑦𐑯 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑨𐑚𐑕𐑩𐑤𐑵𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑘𐑫𐑼, 𐑤𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑦𐑛, 𐑯 𐑴𐑛𐑼𐑦𐑓𐑼𐑩𐑕 𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑑. 𐑯𐑹 𐑦𐑟 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑕 𐑕𐑳𐑚𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑳𐑯𐑩𐑤𐑶𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑐𐑸𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑰𐑗𐑼. 𐑞𐑴 𐑦𐑯 𐑤𐑲𐑓 𐑦𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑱𐑯𐑟 𐑐𐑻𐑓𐑦𐑒𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑓𐑤𐑵𐑦𐑛, 𐑘𐑧𐑑, 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑴𐑠𐑼 𐑑 𐑞 𐑺, 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑛𐑧𐑔, 𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑵𐑯 𐑚𐑦𐑜𐑦𐑯𐑟 𐑑 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑒𐑮𐑰𐑑; 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑹𐑔 𐑚𐑿𐑑𐑦𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑲𐑯 𐑖𐑵𐑑𐑕, 𐑨𐑟 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑔𐑦𐑯 𐑛𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑑 𐑲𐑕 𐑦𐑟 𐑡𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑓𐑹𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼. 𐑩 𐑤𐑸𐑡 𐑢𐑱𐑤'𐑟 𐑒𐑱𐑕 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑘𐑰𐑤𐑛𐑟 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑓𐑲𐑝 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑛 𐑜𐑨𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥, 𐑞𐑴 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑳𐑯𐑩𐑝𐑶𐑛𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑻𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟, 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑼𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑐𐑦𐑤𐑛, 𐑤𐑰𐑒𐑕, 𐑯 𐑛𐑮𐑦𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑩𐑢𐑱, 𐑹 𐑦𐑟 𐑳𐑞𐑼𐑢𐑲𐑟 𐑦𐑮𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑒𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑤𐑪𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑖 𐑚𐑦𐑟𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑿 𐑒𐑨𐑯.

𐑲 𐑯𐑴 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑓𐑲𐑯 𐑯 𐑒𐑪𐑕𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑥𐑩𐑑𐑽𐑾𐑤 𐑞 ·𐑣𐑲𐑛𐑩𐑤𐑚𐑼𐑩 ·𐑑𐑳𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑒𐑴𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑦𐑯, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑵𐑐𐑻𐑤𐑩𐑑𐑦𐑝 𐑮𐑦𐑗𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑒𐑴𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑐𐑪𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑺𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑕𐑦𐑤𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑐𐑻𐑤-𐑒𐑳𐑤𐑼𐑛 𐑥𐑧𐑥𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑯, 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑞 𐑤𐑲𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑩 𐑓𐑲𐑯 𐑐𐑧𐑤𐑰𐑕, 𐑓𐑹𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑼 𐑕𐑻𐑓𐑦𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤'𐑟 𐑒𐑱𐑕.

𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑕𐑰𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑣𐑲𐑛𐑩𐑤𐑚𐑼𐑩 ·𐑑𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑦𐑥𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑲𐑼 𐑤𐑧𐑙𐑔 𐑝 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑲𐑼 𐑑𐑪𐑐 𐑝 𐑞 𐑣𐑧𐑛; 𐑯 𐑕𐑦𐑯𐑕—𐑨𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑧𐑤𐑕𐑢𐑺 𐑕𐑧𐑑 𐑓𐑹𐑔—𐑞 𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑦𐑥𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑔𐑻𐑛 𐑝 𐑞 𐑣𐑴𐑤 𐑤𐑧𐑙𐑔 𐑝 𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑰𐑗𐑼, 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑕𐑧𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑧𐑙𐑔 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑨𐑑 𐑱𐑑𐑦 𐑓𐑰𐑑 𐑓 𐑩 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑕𐑲𐑟𐑛 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑿 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑥𐑹 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑑𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑦-𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑕 𐑓𐑰𐑑 𐑓 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑐𐑔 𐑝 𐑞 𐑑𐑳𐑯, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑤𐑧𐑙𐑔𐑢𐑲𐑟 𐑣𐑶𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑳𐑐 𐑯 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑩 𐑖𐑦𐑐'𐑕 𐑕𐑲𐑛.

𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑦𐑑𐑱𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑞 𐑪𐑐𐑼𐑱𐑑𐑼'𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑩𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑮𐑷𐑑 𐑒𐑤𐑴𐑕 𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑪𐑑 𐑢𐑺 𐑩𐑯 𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑳𐑚𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑢𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑓𐑹𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥𐑩𐑕𐑧𐑑𐑦 𐑥𐑨𐑜𐑩𐑟𐑰𐑯; 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑟, 𐑞𐑺𐑓𐑹, 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑳𐑯𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑣𐑰𐑛𐑓𐑩𐑤, 𐑤𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑩 𐑒𐑺𐑤𐑩𐑕, 𐑳𐑯𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑴𐑒 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑱𐑛 𐑞 𐑕𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑗𐑵𐑼𐑦 𐑯 𐑢𐑱𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑤𐑧𐑑 𐑬𐑑 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑨𐑤𐑿𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑕. 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑦𐑑𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑝 𐑞 𐑣𐑧𐑛, 𐑷𐑤𐑕𐑴, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑦𐑟 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑝𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼, 𐑯 𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑱𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑐𐑩𐑟𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑹𐑥𐑩𐑕 𐑒𐑳𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑑𐑨𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑟, 𐑣𐑵𐑟 𐑣𐑧𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑯 𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑚𐑦𐑯𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟, 𐑪𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑕𐑲𐑛, 𐑥𐑱𐑒 𐑒𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑩 𐑢𐑦𐑤𐑛𐑼𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑮𐑴𐑐𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑒𐑢𐑹𐑑𐑼.

𐑞𐑳𐑕 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑧𐑛, 𐑩𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑯𐑬, 𐑲 𐑐𐑮𐑱 𐑿, 𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑸𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑯—𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑐𐑼𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑼 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕—𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑓𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑪𐑐𐑼𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑺𐑚𐑲 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤'𐑟 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 ·𐑣𐑲𐑛𐑩𐑤𐑚𐑼𐑩 ·𐑑𐑳𐑯 𐑦𐑟 𐑑𐑨𐑐𐑑.

·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 78. 𐑕𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑯 𐑯 ·𐑚𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑑𐑕.

𐑯𐑦𐑥𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑨𐑟 𐑩 𐑒𐑨𐑑, ·𐑑𐑨𐑖𐑑𐑱𐑜𐑴 𐑥𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑓𐑑; 𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑 𐑷𐑤𐑑𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑑 𐑐𐑪𐑕𐑗𐑼, 𐑮𐑳𐑯𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑬𐑑 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑴𐑝𐑼𐑣𐑨𐑙𐑦𐑙 ·𐑥𐑱𐑯𐑘𐑸𐑛-𐑸𐑥, 𐑑 𐑞 𐑐𐑸𐑑 𐑢𐑺 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑜𐑟𐑨𐑒𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑡𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑕 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑞 𐑣𐑶𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛 ·𐑑𐑳𐑯. 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑒𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑩 𐑤𐑲𐑑 𐑑𐑨𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑛 𐑩 𐑢𐑦𐑐, 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑑𐑵 𐑐𐑸𐑑𐑕, 𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑩 𐑕𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑩𐑤-𐑖𐑰𐑝𐑛 𐑚𐑤𐑪𐑒. 𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑚𐑤𐑪𐑒, 𐑕𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑙𐑟 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑘𐑸𐑛-𐑸𐑥, 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑢𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑝 𐑞 𐑮𐑴𐑐, 𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑷𐑑 𐑯 𐑓𐑻𐑥𐑤𐑦 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑩 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑪𐑯 𐑛𐑧𐑒. 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛-𐑴𐑝𐑼-𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛, 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑞 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑐𐑸𐑑, 𐑞 ·𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑾𐑯 𐑛𐑮𐑪𐑐𐑕 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑞 𐑺, 𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑛𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑩𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑣𐑰 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑦𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑣𐑧𐑛. 𐑞𐑺—𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑣𐑲 𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑝𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑩𐑚𐑳𐑝 𐑞 𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑦, 𐑑 𐑣𐑵𐑥 𐑣𐑰 𐑝𐑦𐑝𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑟—𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑟 𐑕𐑳𐑥 ·𐑑𐑻𐑒𐑦𐑖 ·𐑥𐑵𐑧𐑟𐑦𐑯 𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑐𐑰𐑐𐑩𐑤 𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑱𐑼𐑟 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑑𐑪𐑐 𐑝 𐑩 𐑑𐑬𐑼. 𐑩 𐑖𐑹𐑑-𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑖𐑸𐑐 𐑕𐑐𐑱𐑛 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑳𐑐 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑣𐑰 𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑡𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑻𐑗𐑩𐑟 𐑓 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑐𐑼 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕 𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑜𐑦𐑯 𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 ·𐑑𐑳𐑯. 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑚𐑦𐑟𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑣𐑰 𐑐𐑮𐑴𐑕𐑰𐑛𐑟 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑣𐑰𐑛𐑓𐑩𐑤𐑦, 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑑𐑮𐑧𐑠𐑼-𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑑𐑼 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑣𐑬𐑕, 𐑕𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑢𐑷𐑤𐑟 𐑑 𐑓𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑢𐑺 𐑞 𐑜𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑱𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑯. 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑒𐑷𐑖𐑩𐑕 𐑕𐑻𐑗 𐑦𐑟 𐑴𐑝𐑼, 𐑩 𐑕𐑑𐑬𐑑 𐑲𐑼𐑯-𐑚𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑚𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑑, 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑲𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑢𐑧𐑤-𐑚𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑑, 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑩𐑑𐑨𐑗𐑑 𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑦𐑐; 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑞 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑧𐑯𐑛, 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑧𐑗𐑑 𐑩𐑒𐑮𐑪𐑕 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑒, 𐑦𐑟 𐑞𐑺 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑑𐑵 𐑹 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑩𐑤𐑻𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟. 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑯𐑬 𐑣𐑶𐑕𐑑 𐑞 𐑚𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑦𐑯 𐑜𐑮𐑭𐑕𐑐 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑾𐑯, 𐑑 𐑣𐑵𐑥 𐑩𐑯𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑐𐑻𐑕𐑩𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑮𐑰𐑗𐑑 𐑳𐑐 𐑩 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑐𐑴𐑤. 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑐𐑴𐑤 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑚𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑑, ·𐑑𐑨𐑖𐑑𐑱𐑜𐑴 𐑛𐑬𐑯𐑢𐑼𐑛 𐑜𐑲𐑛𐑟 𐑞 𐑚𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 ·𐑑𐑳𐑯, 𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑲𐑼𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑩𐑐𐑽𐑟; 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑜𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑢𐑻𐑛 𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑢𐑦𐑐, 𐑳𐑐 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑟 𐑞 𐑚𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑑 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯, 𐑷𐑤 𐑚𐑳𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑛𐑺𐑦-𐑥𐑱𐑛'𐑟 𐑐𐑱𐑤 𐑝 𐑯𐑿 𐑥𐑦𐑤𐑒. 𐑒𐑺𐑓𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑤𐑴𐑼𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑣𐑲𐑑, 𐑞 𐑓𐑫𐑤-𐑓𐑮𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑝𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑷𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑩𐑯 𐑩𐑐𐑶𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛, 𐑯 𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑦 𐑧𐑥𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑩 𐑤𐑸𐑡 𐑑𐑳𐑚. 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑮𐑰𐑥𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑓𐑑, 𐑦𐑑 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯 𐑜𐑴𐑟 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑞 𐑛𐑰𐑐 𐑕𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑘𐑰𐑤𐑛 𐑯𐑴 𐑥𐑹. 𐑑𐑩𐑢𐑹𐑛𐑟 𐑞 𐑧𐑯𐑛, ·𐑑𐑨𐑖𐑑𐑱𐑜𐑴 𐑣𐑨𐑕 𐑑 𐑮𐑨𐑥 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑐𐑴𐑤 𐑣𐑸𐑛𐑼 𐑯 𐑣𐑸𐑛𐑼, 𐑯 𐑛𐑰𐑐𐑼 𐑯 𐑛𐑰𐑐𐑼 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 ·𐑑𐑳𐑯, 𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑑𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑦 𐑓𐑰𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑐𐑴𐑤 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑜𐑪𐑯 𐑛𐑬𐑯.

𐑯𐑬, 𐑞 𐑐𐑰𐑐𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑚𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑱; 𐑕𐑧𐑝𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑑𐑳𐑚𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑓𐑦𐑤𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑓𐑮𐑱𐑜𐑮𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥; 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑕 𐑩 𐑒𐑢𐑽 𐑨𐑒𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑛. 𐑢𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 ·𐑑𐑨𐑖𐑑𐑱𐑜𐑴, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑲𐑤𐑛 ·𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑾𐑯, 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑴 𐑣𐑰𐑛𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑯 𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑨𐑟 𐑑 𐑤𐑧𐑑 𐑜𐑴 𐑓 𐑩 𐑥𐑴𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑳𐑯-𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑒𐑱𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑑𐑨𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑕𐑩𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑣𐑧𐑛; 𐑹 𐑢𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑞 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕 𐑢𐑺 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑑𐑫𐑛 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑴 𐑑𐑮𐑧𐑗𐑼𐑩𐑕 𐑯 𐑵𐑟𐑦; 𐑹 𐑢𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑞 ·𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑦𐑑 𐑑 𐑓𐑷𐑤 𐑬𐑑 𐑕𐑴, 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑼𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑼 𐑮𐑰𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑟; 𐑣𐑬 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑦𐑜𐑟𐑨𐑒𐑑𐑤𐑦, 𐑞𐑺 𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑴 𐑑𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑯𐑬; 𐑚𐑳𐑑, 𐑪𐑯 𐑩 𐑕𐑳𐑛𐑩𐑯, 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑱𐑑𐑾𐑔 𐑹 𐑯𐑲𐑯𐑑𐑾𐑔 𐑚𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑑 𐑒𐑱𐑥 𐑕𐑳𐑒𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑳𐑐—𐑥𐑲 ·𐑜𐑪𐑛! 𐑐𐑫𐑼 ·𐑑𐑨𐑖𐑑𐑱𐑜𐑴—𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑞 𐑑𐑢𐑦𐑯 𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑦𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑒𐑱𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑧𐑤, 𐑛𐑮𐑪𐑐𐑑 𐑣𐑧𐑛-𐑓𐑹𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 ·𐑑𐑳𐑯 𐑝 ·𐑣𐑲𐑛𐑩𐑤𐑚𐑼𐑩, 𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑣𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑶𐑤𐑦 𐑜𐑻𐑜𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙, 𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑒𐑤𐑰𐑯 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑕𐑲𐑑!

“𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑴𐑝𐑼𐑚𐑹𐑛!” 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 ·𐑛𐑨𐑜𐑵, 𐑣𐑵 𐑩𐑥𐑦𐑛 𐑞 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑯𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑒𐑱𐑥 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟. “𐑕𐑢𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑚𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑱!” 𐑯 𐑐𐑫𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑓𐑫𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑦𐑑, 𐑕𐑴 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑚𐑧𐑑𐑼 𐑑 𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑘𐑫𐑼 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑤𐑦𐑐𐑼𐑦 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛-𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑦𐑐 𐑦𐑑𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓, 𐑞 𐑣𐑶𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑟 𐑮𐑨𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑣𐑲 𐑳𐑐 𐑑 𐑞 𐑑𐑪𐑐 𐑝 𐑞 𐑣𐑧𐑛, 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 ·𐑑𐑨𐑖𐑑𐑱𐑜𐑴 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑮𐑰𐑗𐑑 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑽𐑽 𐑚𐑪𐑑𐑩𐑥. 𐑥𐑰𐑯𐑑𐑲𐑥, 𐑞𐑺 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩 𐑑𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑑𐑿𐑥𐑳𐑤𐑑. 𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑞 𐑕𐑲𐑛, 𐑞𐑱 𐑕𐑷 𐑞 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑤𐑲𐑓𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑔𐑮𐑪𐑚𐑦𐑙 𐑯 𐑣𐑰𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑡𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑴 𐑞 𐑕𐑻𐑓𐑦𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑰, 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑓 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑴𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑟𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑥𐑴𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑕 𐑲𐑛𐑾; 𐑢𐑺𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑞 𐑐𐑫𐑼 ·𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑾𐑯 𐑳𐑯𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑦𐑝𐑰𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑲 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑜𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑞 𐑐𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑛𐑧𐑐𐑔 𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑕𐑳𐑙𐑒.

𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑, 𐑢𐑲𐑤 ·𐑛𐑨𐑜𐑵, 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑦𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑣𐑧𐑛, 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑒𐑤𐑽𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑢𐑦𐑐—𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑣𐑬 𐑜𐑪𐑑 𐑓𐑬𐑤 𐑝 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑒𐑳𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑑𐑨𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑟—𐑩 𐑖𐑸𐑐 𐑒𐑮𐑨𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑯𐑶𐑟 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑣𐑻𐑛; 𐑯 𐑑 𐑞 𐑳𐑯𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑣𐑪𐑮𐑼 𐑝 𐑷𐑤, 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑑𐑵 𐑦𐑯𐑹𐑥𐑩𐑕 𐑣𐑫𐑒𐑕 𐑕𐑩𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑑𐑹 𐑬𐑑, 𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑝𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑝𐑲𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑹𐑥𐑩𐑕 𐑥𐑨𐑕 𐑕𐑲𐑛𐑢𐑱𐑟 𐑕𐑢𐑳𐑙, 𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑞 𐑛𐑮𐑳𐑙𐑒 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑮𐑰𐑤𐑛 𐑯 𐑖𐑫𐑒 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑓 𐑕𐑥𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑚𐑲 𐑩𐑯 𐑲𐑕𐑚𐑻𐑜. 𐑞 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑱𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑫𐑒, 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑲𐑼 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯 𐑯𐑬 𐑛𐑦𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛, 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑐𐑶𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑜𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑱; 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑝𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑥𐑹 𐑤𐑲𐑒𐑤𐑦 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑥𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑣𐑧𐑛.

“𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑛𐑬𐑯, 𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑛𐑬𐑯!” 𐑘𐑧𐑤𐑛 𐑞 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑑 ·𐑛𐑨𐑜𐑵, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑪𐑯 𐑑 𐑞 𐑣𐑧𐑝𐑦 𐑑𐑨𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑟, 𐑕𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑓 𐑞 𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑛𐑮𐑪𐑐, 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑱𐑯 𐑕𐑩𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛; 𐑞 𐑯𐑰𐑜𐑮𐑴 𐑣𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑒𐑤𐑽𐑛 𐑞 𐑓𐑬𐑤 𐑤𐑲𐑯, 𐑮𐑨𐑥𐑛 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑯𐑬 𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑨𐑐𐑕𐑑 𐑢𐑧𐑤, 𐑥𐑰𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑚𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑛 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑽 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑜𐑮𐑭𐑕𐑐 𐑦𐑑, 𐑯 𐑕𐑴 𐑚𐑰 𐑣𐑶𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑬𐑑.

“𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑯'𐑟 𐑯𐑱𐑥, 𐑥𐑨𐑯,” 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚, “𐑸 𐑿 𐑮𐑨𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑴𐑥 𐑩 𐑒𐑸𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑡 𐑞𐑺?—𐑩𐑝𐑭𐑕𐑑! 𐑣𐑬 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑐 𐑣𐑦𐑥; 𐑡𐑨𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑲𐑼𐑯-𐑚𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑚𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑑 𐑪𐑯 𐑑𐑪𐑐 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑧𐑛? 𐑩𐑝𐑭𐑕𐑑, 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑘𐑰!”

“𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑒𐑤𐑽 𐑝 𐑞 𐑑𐑨𐑒𐑩𐑤!” 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 𐑩 𐑝𐑶𐑕 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑞 𐑚𐑻𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑩 𐑮𐑪𐑒𐑩𐑑.

𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑔𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼-𐑚𐑵𐑥, 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑹𐑥𐑩𐑕 𐑥𐑨𐑕 𐑛𐑮𐑪𐑐𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑕𐑰, 𐑤𐑲𐑒 ·𐑯𐑲𐑨𐑜𐑼𐑩'𐑟 ·𐑑𐑱𐑚𐑩𐑤-·𐑮𐑪𐑒 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑐𐑵𐑤; 𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑦𐑤𐑰𐑝𐑛 𐑣𐑳𐑤 𐑮𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑩𐑢𐑱 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑦𐑑, 𐑑 𐑓𐑸 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑣𐑻 𐑜𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑒𐑪𐑐𐑼; 𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑒𐑷𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑚𐑮𐑧𐑔, 𐑨𐑟 𐑣𐑭𐑓 𐑕𐑢𐑦𐑙𐑦𐑙—𐑯𐑬 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑼𐑟' 𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑟, 𐑯 𐑯𐑬 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑞 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼—·𐑛𐑨𐑜𐑵, 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑩 𐑔𐑦𐑒 𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑑 𐑝 𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑱, 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑛𐑦𐑥𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑦𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑛 𐑒𐑤𐑦𐑙𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑞 𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑡𐑩𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑑𐑨𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑟, 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑐𐑫𐑼, 𐑚𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑛-𐑩𐑤𐑲𐑝 ·𐑑𐑨𐑖𐑑𐑱𐑜𐑴 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑳𐑑𐑼𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑑 𐑞 𐑚𐑪𐑑𐑩𐑥 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑰! 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑣𐑸𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑞 𐑚𐑤𐑲𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑝𐑱𐑐𐑼 𐑒𐑤𐑽𐑛 𐑩𐑢𐑱, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑩 𐑯𐑱𐑒𐑩𐑛 𐑓𐑦𐑜𐑼 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑚𐑹𐑛𐑦𐑙-𐑕𐑹𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛, 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑓 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑕𐑢𐑦𐑓𐑑 𐑥𐑴𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑯 𐑣𐑪𐑝𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑞 𐑚𐑫𐑤𐑢𐑼𐑒𐑕. 𐑞 𐑯𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑, 𐑩 𐑤𐑬𐑛 𐑕𐑐𐑤𐑨𐑖 𐑩𐑯𐑬𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑲 𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑝 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑛𐑲𐑝𐑛 𐑑 𐑞 𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑒𐑿. 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑐𐑨𐑒𐑑 𐑮𐑳𐑖 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑲𐑛, 𐑯 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑲 𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑩𐑤, 𐑨𐑟 𐑥𐑴𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑓𐑪𐑤𐑴𐑛 𐑥𐑴𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑, 𐑯 𐑯𐑴 𐑕𐑲𐑯 𐑝 𐑲𐑞𐑼 𐑞 𐑕𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑼 𐑹 𐑞 𐑛𐑲𐑝𐑼 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑚𐑰 𐑕𐑰𐑯. 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑯𐑬 𐑡𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑩 𐑚𐑴𐑑 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑙𐑕𐑲𐑛, 𐑯 𐑐𐑫𐑖𐑑 𐑩 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑪𐑓 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐.

“𐑣𐑭! 𐑣𐑭!” 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 ·𐑛𐑨𐑜𐑵, 𐑷𐑤 𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑕, 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑬 𐑒𐑢𐑲𐑩𐑑, 𐑕𐑢𐑦𐑙𐑦𐑙 𐑐𐑻𐑗 𐑴𐑝𐑼𐑣𐑧𐑛; 𐑯 𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑻𐑞𐑼 𐑪𐑓 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑕𐑲𐑛, 𐑢𐑰 𐑕𐑷 𐑩𐑯 𐑸𐑥 𐑔𐑮𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑳𐑐𐑮𐑲𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑚𐑤𐑵 𐑢𐑱𐑝𐑟; 𐑩 𐑕𐑲𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡 𐑑 𐑕𐑰, 𐑨𐑟 𐑩𐑯 𐑸𐑥 𐑔𐑮𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑓𐑹𐑔 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑭𐑕 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑩 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑝.

“𐑚𐑴𐑔! 𐑚𐑴𐑔!—𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑴𐑔!”—𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 ·𐑛𐑨𐑜𐑵 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑡𐑶𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑖𐑬𐑑; 𐑯 𐑕𐑵𐑯 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼, ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑰𐑯 𐑚𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑬𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛, 𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑒𐑤𐑳𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑣𐑺 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑾𐑯. 𐑛𐑮𐑷𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑴𐑑, 𐑞𐑱 𐑢𐑻 𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑮𐑷𐑑 𐑑 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑒; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 ·𐑑𐑨𐑖𐑑𐑱𐑜𐑴 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑑, 𐑯 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑤𐑫𐑒 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑚𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑒.

𐑯𐑬, 𐑣𐑬 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑯𐑴𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑒𐑿 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑩𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑦𐑖𐑑? 𐑢𐑲, 𐑛𐑲𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑞 𐑕𐑤𐑴𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑧𐑛, ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑰𐑯 𐑕𐑹𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑤𐑳𐑯𐑡𐑩𐑟 𐑯𐑽 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑚𐑪𐑑𐑩𐑥, 𐑕𐑴 𐑨𐑟 𐑑 𐑕𐑒𐑳𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑩 𐑤𐑸𐑡 𐑣𐑴𐑤 𐑞𐑺; 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑛𐑮𐑪𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑹𐑛, 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑔𐑮𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑸𐑥 𐑓𐑸 𐑦𐑯𐑢𐑼𐑛𐑟 𐑯 𐑳𐑐𐑢𐑼𐑛𐑟, 𐑯 𐑕𐑴 𐑣𐑷𐑤𐑛 𐑬𐑑 𐑐𐑫𐑼 ·𐑑𐑨𐑖 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑣𐑧𐑛. 𐑣𐑰 𐑩𐑝𐑻𐑛, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑔𐑮𐑳𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑓 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑩 𐑤𐑧𐑜 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑧𐑤 𐑯𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑷𐑑 𐑑 𐑚𐑰, 𐑯 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑩𐑒𐑱𐑠𐑩𐑯 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑚𐑩𐑤;—𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑔𐑮𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑨𐑒 𐑞 𐑤𐑧𐑜, 𐑯 𐑚𐑲 𐑩 𐑛𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑩𐑕 𐑣𐑰𐑝 𐑯 𐑑𐑪𐑕, 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑮𐑷𐑑 𐑩 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑼𐑕𐑧𐑑 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑾𐑯; 𐑕𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑯𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑 𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑩𐑤, 𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑱𐑥 𐑓𐑹𐑔 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑢𐑱—𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑓𐑹𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑. 𐑨𐑟 𐑓 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑦𐑑𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑛𐑵𐑦𐑙 𐑨𐑟 𐑢𐑧𐑤 𐑨𐑟 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑚𐑰 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑛.

𐑯 𐑞𐑳𐑕, 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑞 𐑒𐑳𐑮𐑦𐑡 𐑯 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑕𐑒𐑦𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑩𐑚𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑕 𐑝 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜, 𐑞 𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑝𐑼𐑩𐑯𐑕, 𐑹 𐑮𐑭𐑞𐑼, 𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑝𐑼𐑦 𐑝 ·𐑑𐑨𐑖𐑑𐑱𐑜𐑴, 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑩𐑒𐑕𐑧𐑕𐑓𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑩𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑦𐑖𐑑, 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑑𐑰𐑔, 𐑑𐑵, 𐑝 𐑞 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑳𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑢𐑹𐑛 𐑯 𐑩𐑐𐑨𐑮𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑣𐑴𐑐𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑧𐑛𐑦𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕; 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑦𐑟 𐑩 𐑤𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑯 𐑚𐑲 𐑯𐑴 𐑥𐑰𐑯𐑟 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑓𐑼𐑜𐑪𐑑𐑩𐑯. 𐑥𐑦𐑛𐑢𐑦𐑓𐑼𐑦 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑚𐑰 𐑑𐑷𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑒𐑹𐑕 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑓𐑧𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑯 𐑚𐑪𐑒𐑕𐑦𐑙, 𐑮𐑲𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑯 𐑮𐑴𐑦𐑙.

𐑲 𐑯𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑒𐑢𐑽 𐑩𐑛𐑝𐑧𐑯𐑗𐑼 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑜𐑱-·𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑼'𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑚𐑰 𐑖𐑫𐑼 𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑥 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟𐑥𐑧𐑯, 𐑞𐑴 𐑞𐑱 𐑞𐑧𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑝𐑟 𐑥𐑱 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑲𐑞𐑼 𐑕𐑰𐑯 𐑹 𐑣𐑻𐑛 𐑝 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑢𐑳𐑯'𐑟 𐑓𐑷𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑩 𐑕𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑯 𐑩𐑖𐑹; 𐑩𐑯 𐑨𐑒𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑛𐑩𐑥 𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑟, 𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑤𐑧𐑕 𐑮𐑰𐑟𐑩𐑯 𐑑𐑵 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑾𐑯'𐑟, 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑰𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑤𐑦𐑐𐑼𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑒𐑻𐑚 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤'𐑟 𐑢𐑧𐑤.

𐑚𐑳𐑑, 𐑐𐑻𐑩𐑛𐑝𐑧𐑯𐑗𐑼, 𐑦𐑑 𐑥𐑱 𐑚𐑰 𐑕𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑻𐑡𐑛, 𐑣𐑬 𐑦𐑟 𐑞𐑦𐑕? 𐑢𐑰 𐑔𐑷𐑑 𐑞 𐑑𐑦𐑖𐑿𐑛, 𐑦𐑯𐑓𐑦𐑤𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞 𐑤𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑯 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑒𐑹𐑒𐑦 𐑐𐑸𐑑 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥; 𐑯 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑞𐑬 𐑥𐑱𐑒𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑦𐑙𐑒 𐑦𐑯 𐑩𐑯 𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑩 𐑓𐑸 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑𐑼 𐑕𐑐𐑩𐑕𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑒 𐑜𐑮𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑦𐑑𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓. 𐑢𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑞𐑰 𐑞𐑺. 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑷𐑤, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑘𐑰; 𐑓 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑐𐑫𐑼 ·𐑑𐑨𐑖 𐑓𐑧𐑤 𐑦𐑯, 𐑞 𐑒𐑱𐑕 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑯𐑽𐑤𐑦 𐑧𐑥𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑛 𐑝 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑤𐑲𐑑𐑼 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑕, 𐑤𐑰𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑯𐑕 𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑢𐑷𐑤 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑧𐑤—𐑩 𐑛𐑳𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑧𐑤𐑛𐑩𐑛, 𐑣𐑨𐑥𐑼𐑛 𐑕𐑳𐑚𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕, 𐑨𐑟 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑕𐑧𐑛, 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑣𐑧𐑝𐑽 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑰 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼, 𐑯 𐑩 𐑤𐑳𐑥𐑐 𐑝 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑕𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑦𐑑 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑤𐑧𐑛 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞 𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦 𐑑 𐑮𐑨𐑐𐑦𐑛 𐑕𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑕𐑳𐑚𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑥𐑩𐑑𐑽𐑾𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑨𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑐𐑸𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑱𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑑𐑨𐑗𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑦𐑑, 𐑕𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑨𐑙𐑒 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑕𐑤𐑴𐑤𐑦 𐑯 𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑚𐑼𐑩𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑰𐑛, 𐑩𐑓𐑹𐑛𐑦𐑙 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜 𐑩 𐑓𐑺 𐑗𐑭𐑯𐑕 𐑓 𐑐𐑼𐑓𐑹𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑨𐑡𐑲𐑤 𐑩𐑚𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑕 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑮𐑳𐑯, 𐑨𐑟 𐑿 𐑥𐑱 𐑕𐑱. 𐑘𐑧𐑕, 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩 𐑮𐑳𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑝𐑼𐑦, 𐑕𐑴 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟.

𐑯𐑬, 𐑣𐑨𐑛 ·𐑑𐑨𐑖𐑑𐑱𐑜𐑴 𐑐𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑖𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑧𐑛, 𐑦𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑩 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑕 𐑐𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑖𐑦𐑙; 𐑕𐑥𐑳𐑞𐑼𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑢𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑯 𐑛𐑱𐑯𐑑𐑾𐑕𐑑 𐑝 𐑓𐑮𐑱𐑜𐑮𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥𐑩𐑕𐑧𐑑𐑦; 𐑒𐑪𐑓𐑦𐑯𐑛, 𐑣𐑻𐑕𐑑, 𐑯 𐑑𐑵𐑥𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑰𐑒𐑮𐑩𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑼 𐑗𐑱𐑥𐑚𐑼 𐑯 𐑕𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑥 𐑕𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑑𐑼𐑩𐑥 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤. 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑕𐑢𐑰𐑑𐑼 𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑰 𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑛—𐑞 𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑕 𐑛𐑧𐑔 𐑝 𐑩𐑯 ·𐑴𐑣𐑲𐑴 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑦-𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑑𐑼, 𐑣𐑵 𐑕𐑰𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑦 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑪𐑗 𐑝 𐑩 𐑣𐑪𐑤𐑴 𐑑𐑮𐑰, 𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑰𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑑𐑹 𐑝 𐑦𐑑, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑰𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑑𐑵 𐑓𐑸 𐑴𐑝𐑼, 𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑒𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑦𐑯, 𐑕𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑛𐑲𐑛 𐑦𐑥𐑚𐑭𐑥𐑛. 𐑣𐑬 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦, 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒 𐑘𐑰, 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑤𐑲𐑒𐑢𐑲𐑟 𐑓𐑷𐑤𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 ·𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑑𐑴'𐑟 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑦 𐑣𐑧𐑛, 𐑯 𐑕𐑢𐑰𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑖𐑑 𐑞𐑺?

·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 79. 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑮𐑺𐑦.

𐑑 𐑕𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑞 𐑤𐑲𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑱𐑕, 𐑹 𐑓𐑰𐑤 𐑞 𐑚𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑕 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑝 𐑞𐑦𐑕 ·𐑤𐑩𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑔𐑩𐑯; 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑦𐑟 𐑩 𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑯𐑴 ·𐑓𐑦𐑟𐑦𐑪𐑯𐑩𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑑 𐑹 ·𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑯𐑪𐑤𐑩𐑡𐑦𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑨𐑟 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑩𐑯. 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩𐑯 𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑐𐑮𐑲𐑟 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑕𐑰𐑥 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑣𐑴𐑐𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑨𐑟 𐑓 ·𐑤𐑱𐑝𐑱𐑑𐑼 𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑵𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑲𐑟𐑛 𐑞 𐑮𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑮𐑪𐑒 𐑝 ·𐑡𐑦𐑚𐑮𐑷𐑤𐑑𐑼, 𐑹 𐑓 ·𐑜𐑷𐑤 𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑥𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑩 𐑤𐑨𐑛𐑼 𐑯 𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑐𐑿𐑤𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑞 ·𐑛𐑴𐑥 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑨𐑯𐑔𐑾𐑯. 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤, 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑓𐑱𐑥𐑩𐑕 𐑢𐑻𐑒 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟, ·𐑤𐑱𐑝𐑱𐑑𐑼 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑑𐑮𐑰𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑝𐑺𐑾𐑕 𐑓𐑱𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑝 𐑥𐑧𐑯, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑷𐑤𐑕𐑴 𐑩𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑝𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑛𐑦𐑟 𐑞 𐑓𐑱𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑝 𐑣𐑹𐑕𐑩𐑟, 𐑚𐑻𐑛𐑟, 𐑕𐑻𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕, 𐑯 𐑓𐑦𐑖; 𐑯 𐑛𐑢𐑧𐑤𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑛𐑰𐑑𐑱𐑤 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑥𐑪𐑛𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑒𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑻𐑯𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑞𐑺𐑦𐑯. 𐑯𐑹 𐑣𐑨𐑝 ·𐑜𐑷𐑤 𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑲𐑐𐑩𐑤 ·𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑟𐑣𐑲𐑥 𐑓𐑱𐑤𐑛 𐑑 𐑔𐑮𐑴 𐑬𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑣𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑑𐑳𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑯𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑡𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑒𐑨𐑮𐑩𐑒𐑑𐑼𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑕 𐑝 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑥𐑨𐑯. 𐑞𐑺𐑓𐑹, 𐑞𐑴 𐑲 𐑨𐑥 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑤 𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑤𐑦𐑓𐑲𐑛 𐑓 𐑩 𐑐𐑲𐑩𐑯𐑽, 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑨𐑐𐑤𐑦𐑒𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑑𐑵 𐑕𐑧𐑥𐑦-𐑕𐑲𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑑 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑲 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑛𐑵 𐑥𐑲 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑧𐑝𐑼. 𐑲 𐑑𐑮𐑲 𐑷𐑤 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑟; 𐑲 𐑩𐑗𐑰𐑝 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑲 𐑒𐑨𐑯.

𐑓𐑦𐑟𐑦𐑪𐑜𐑯𐑩𐑥𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑦𐑜𐑸𐑛𐑩𐑛, 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑦𐑟 𐑩𐑯 𐑩𐑯𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑒𐑮𐑰𐑗𐑼. 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑯𐑴 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑐𐑼 𐑯𐑴𐑟. 𐑯 𐑕𐑦𐑯𐑕 𐑞 𐑯𐑴𐑟 𐑦𐑟 𐑞 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑩𐑤 𐑯 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑓𐑰𐑗𐑼𐑟; 𐑯 𐑕𐑦𐑯𐑕 𐑦𐑑 𐑐𐑼𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑕 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑥𐑪𐑛𐑦𐑓𐑲𐑟 𐑯 𐑓𐑲𐑯𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑴𐑤𐑟 𐑞𐑺 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑚𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑯; 𐑣𐑧𐑯𐑕 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑕𐑰𐑥 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑲𐑼 𐑨𐑚𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑕, 𐑨𐑟 𐑩𐑯 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑩𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑡, 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑤𐑸𐑡𐑤𐑦 𐑩𐑓𐑧𐑒𐑑 𐑞 𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤. 𐑓 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑕𐑒𐑱𐑐 𐑜𐑸𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑙, 𐑩 𐑕𐑐𐑲𐑼, 𐑒𐑿𐑐𐑩𐑤𐑩, 𐑥𐑪𐑯𐑿𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑, 𐑹 𐑑𐑬𐑼 𐑝 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑕𐑹𐑑, 𐑦𐑟 𐑛𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑑 𐑞 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑰𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑰𐑯; 𐑕𐑴 𐑯𐑴 𐑓𐑱𐑕 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑚𐑰 𐑓𐑦𐑟𐑦𐑪𐑜𐑯𐑩𐑥𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑯 𐑒𐑰𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑 𐑞 𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑝𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑴𐑐𐑩𐑯-𐑢𐑻𐑒 𐑚𐑧𐑤𐑓𐑮𐑦 𐑝 𐑞 𐑯𐑴𐑟. 𐑛𐑨𐑖 𐑞 𐑯𐑴𐑟 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 ·𐑓𐑦𐑛𐑾𐑕'𐑩𐑟 𐑥𐑸𐑚𐑩𐑤 ·𐑡𐑴𐑝, 𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑩 𐑕𐑪𐑮𐑦 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑱𐑯𐑛𐑼! 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼𐑞𐑩𐑤𐑧𐑕, ·𐑤𐑩𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑔𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑟 𐑝 𐑕𐑴 𐑥𐑲𐑑𐑦 𐑩 𐑥𐑨𐑜𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑿𐑛, 𐑷𐑤 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑐𐑹𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑸 𐑕𐑴 𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑑𐑤𐑦, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑛𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑒𐑳𐑤𐑐𐑗𐑼𐑛 ·𐑡𐑴𐑝 𐑢𐑻 𐑣𐑦𐑛𐑾𐑕, 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑴 𐑚𐑤𐑧𐑥𐑦𐑖 𐑨𐑑 𐑷𐑤. 𐑯𐑱, 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑩𐑯 𐑨𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑜𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑡𐑼. 𐑩 𐑯𐑴𐑟 𐑑 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑻𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑯𐑑. 𐑨𐑟 𐑪𐑯 𐑘𐑹 𐑓𐑦𐑟𐑦𐑪𐑜𐑯𐑩𐑥𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑝𐑶𐑦𐑡 𐑿 𐑕𐑱𐑤 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑝𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑘𐑹 𐑡𐑪𐑤𐑦-𐑚𐑴𐑑, 𐑘𐑹 𐑯𐑴𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑧𐑐𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑸 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑳𐑤𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑮𐑦𐑓𐑤𐑧𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑩 𐑯𐑴𐑟 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑐𐑫𐑤𐑛. 𐑩 𐑐𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑰𐑑, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑕𐑴 𐑪𐑓𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑕𐑑 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑩𐑚𐑑𐑮𐑵𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑚𐑦𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑥𐑲𐑑𐑾𐑕𐑑 𐑮𐑶𐑩𐑤 𐑚𐑰𐑛𐑩𐑤 𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑔𐑮𐑴𐑯.

𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑐𐑼𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑼𐑟, 𐑐𐑼𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑕 𐑞 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑴𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑦𐑟𐑦𐑪𐑜𐑯𐑩𐑥𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑝𐑿 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑦𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑓𐑫𐑤 𐑓𐑮𐑳𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑧𐑛. 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑨𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑲𐑥.

𐑦𐑯 𐑔𐑷𐑑, 𐑩 𐑓𐑲𐑯 𐑣𐑿𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑚𐑮𐑬 𐑦𐑟 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑞 ·𐑰𐑕𐑑 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑥𐑹𐑯𐑦𐑙. 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑴𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑐𐑭𐑕𐑗𐑼, 𐑞 𐑒𐑻𐑤𐑛 𐑚𐑮𐑬 𐑝 𐑞 𐑚𐑫𐑤 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑩 𐑑𐑳𐑗 𐑝 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑦𐑑. 𐑐𐑫𐑖𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑧𐑝𐑦 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑩𐑯 𐑳𐑐 𐑥𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑛𐑦𐑓𐑲𐑤𐑟, 𐑞 𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑓𐑩𐑯𐑑'𐑕 𐑚𐑮𐑬 𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑩𐑡𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑒. 𐑣𐑿𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑹 𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑥𐑩𐑤, 𐑞 𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑚𐑮𐑬 𐑦𐑟 𐑨𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑜𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑩𐑯 𐑕𐑰𐑤 𐑩𐑓𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 ·𐑡𐑻𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑧𐑥𐑐𐑼𐑼𐑟 𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑮𐑰𐑟. 𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑦𐑜𐑯𐑦𐑓𐑲𐑟—“𐑜𐑪𐑛: 𐑛𐑳𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑛𐑱 𐑚𐑲 𐑥𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛.” 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑒𐑮𐑰𐑗𐑼𐑟, 𐑯𐑱 𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓, 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑪𐑓𐑩𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑮𐑬 𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑩 𐑥𐑽 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑐 𐑝 𐑨𐑤𐑐𐑲𐑯 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑤𐑲𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑞 𐑕𐑯𐑴 𐑤𐑲𐑯. 𐑓𐑿 𐑸 𐑞 𐑓𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑛𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑤𐑲𐑒 ·𐑖𐑱𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑽'𐑟 𐑹 ·𐑥𐑧𐑤𐑨𐑒𐑔𐑪𐑯'𐑟 𐑮𐑲𐑟 𐑕𐑴 𐑣𐑲, 𐑯 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑕𐑴 𐑤𐑴, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑲𐑟 𐑞𐑧𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑝𐑟 𐑕𐑰𐑥 𐑒𐑤𐑽, 𐑦𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑩𐑤, 𐑑𐑲𐑛𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑥𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑤𐑱𐑒𐑕; 𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑩𐑚𐑳𐑝 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑛'𐑟 𐑮𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑟, 𐑿 𐑕𐑰𐑥 𐑑 𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑒 𐑞 𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑼𐑛 𐑔𐑷𐑑𐑕 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑺 𐑑 𐑛𐑮𐑦𐑙𐑒, 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 ·𐑣𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑟 𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑒 𐑞 𐑕𐑯𐑴 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑛𐑽. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 ·𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑣𐑲 𐑯 𐑥𐑲𐑑𐑦 𐑜𐑪𐑛-𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑛𐑦𐑜𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑦𐑯𐑣𐑧𐑮𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑮𐑬 𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑴 𐑦𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑨𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑦𐑓𐑲𐑛, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑜𐑱𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑪𐑯 𐑦𐑑, 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑓𐑫𐑤 𐑓𐑮𐑳𐑯𐑑 𐑝𐑿, 𐑿 𐑓𐑰𐑤 𐑞 ·𐑛𐑰𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑯 𐑞 𐑛𐑮𐑧𐑛 𐑐𐑬𐑼𐑟 𐑥𐑹 𐑓𐑹𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑚𐑦𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑪𐑚𐑡𐑧𐑒𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑤𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑯𐑱𐑗𐑼. 𐑓 𐑿 𐑕𐑰 𐑯𐑴 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑐𐑶𐑯𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑲𐑕𐑤𐑦; 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑑 𐑓𐑰𐑗𐑼 𐑦𐑟 𐑮𐑦𐑝𐑰𐑤𐑛; 𐑯𐑴 𐑯𐑴𐑟, 𐑲𐑟, 𐑽𐑟, 𐑹 𐑥𐑬𐑔; 𐑯𐑴 𐑓𐑱𐑕; 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑯𐑳𐑯, 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑐𐑼; 𐑯𐑳𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑚𐑮𐑷𐑛 𐑓𐑻𐑥𐑩𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑩 𐑓𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑛, 𐑐𐑤𐑰𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑮𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑤𐑟; 𐑛𐑳𐑥𐑤𐑦 𐑤𐑴𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑛𐑵𐑥 𐑝 𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕, 𐑯 𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑕, 𐑯 𐑥𐑧𐑯. 𐑯𐑹, 𐑦𐑯 𐑐𐑮𐑴𐑓𐑲𐑤, 𐑛𐑳𐑟 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑕 𐑚𐑮𐑬 𐑛𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑖; 𐑞𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑱 𐑝𐑿𐑛 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑜𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑡𐑼 𐑛𐑳𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑛𐑪𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑽 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑿 𐑕𐑴. 𐑦𐑯 𐑐𐑮𐑴𐑓𐑲𐑤, 𐑿 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑼𐑕𐑰𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤, 𐑕𐑧𐑥𐑦-𐑒𐑮𐑧𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑛𐑦𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑛'𐑟 𐑥𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑤, 𐑢𐑦𐑗, 𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑨𐑯, 𐑦𐑟 ·𐑤𐑱𐑝𐑱𐑑𐑼'𐑟 𐑥𐑸𐑒 𐑝 𐑡𐑰𐑯𐑾𐑕.

𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑣𐑬? 𐑡𐑰𐑯𐑾𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤? 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑩 𐑚𐑫𐑒, 𐑕𐑐𐑴𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑩 𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑗? 𐑯𐑴, 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑡𐑰𐑯𐑾𐑕 𐑦𐑟 𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑺𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑛𐑵𐑦𐑙 𐑯𐑳𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑐𐑼𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑼 𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑵𐑝 𐑦𐑑. 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑹𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑺𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑦𐑮𐑩𐑥𐑦𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑕. 𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑲𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑥𐑰 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 ·𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑯𐑴𐑯 𐑑 𐑞 𐑘𐑳𐑙 ·𐑹𐑦𐑧𐑯𐑑 ·𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛, 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑛𐑰𐑦𐑓𐑲𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑞𐑺 𐑗𐑲𐑤𐑛-𐑥𐑱𐑡𐑾𐑯 𐑔𐑷𐑑𐑕. 𐑞𐑱 𐑛𐑰𐑦𐑓𐑲𐑛 𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑪𐑒𐑩𐑛𐑲𐑤 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑯𐑲𐑤, 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑪𐑟 𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑪𐑒𐑩𐑛𐑲𐑤 𐑦𐑟 𐑑𐑳𐑙𐑤𐑩𐑕; 𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑯𐑴 𐑑𐑳𐑙, 𐑹 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑰𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑴 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑰𐑛𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑥𐑷𐑤, 𐑨𐑟 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑱𐑐𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑐𐑮𐑴𐑑𐑮𐑵𐑠𐑩𐑯. 𐑦𐑓 𐑣𐑽𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑣𐑲𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑳𐑤𐑗𐑼𐑛, 𐑐𐑴𐑧𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑯𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑖𐑨𐑤 𐑤𐑫𐑼 𐑚𐑨𐑒 𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑚𐑻𐑔-𐑮𐑲𐑑, 𐑞 𐑥𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑥𐑱-𐑛𐑱 𐑜𐑪𐑛𐑟 𐑝 𐑴𐑤𐑛; 𐑯 𐑤𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑯𐑔𐑮𐑴𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑯𐑬 𐑰𐑜𐑴𐑑𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑒𐑲; 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑯𐑬 𐑳𐑯𐑣𐑷𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑤; 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑚𐑰 𐑖𐑫𐑼, 𐑦𐑜𐑟𐑷𐑤𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑑 ·𐑡𐑴𐑝'𐑟 𐑣𐑲 𐑕𐑰𐑑, 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 ·𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑖𐑨𐑤 𐑤𐑹𐑛 𐑦𐑑.

·𐑖𐑭𐑥𐑐𐑴𐑤𐑦𐑴𐑯 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑲𐑓𐑼𐑛 𐑞 𐑮𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑜𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑑 𐑣𐑲𐑮𐑩𐑜𐑤𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑒𐑕. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑴 ·𐑖𐑭𐑥𐑐𐑴𐑤𐑦𐑴𐑯 𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑲𐑓𐑼 𐑞 ·𐑰𐑡𐑦𐑐𐑑 𐑝 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑥𐑨𐑯'𐑟 𐑯 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙'𐑟 𐑓𐑱𐑕. 𐑓𐑦𐑟𐑦𐑪𐑯𐑩𐑥𐑦, 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑣𐑿𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑕𐑲𐑩𐑯𐑕, 𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑩 𐑐𐑭𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑱𐑚𐑩𐑤. 𐑦𐑓 𐑞𐑧𐑯, ·𐑕𐑻 ·𐑢𐑦𐑤𐑾𐑥 ·𐑡𐑴𐑯𐑟, 𐑣𐑵 𐑮𐑰𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑔𐑻𐑑𐑦 𐑤𐑨𐑙𐑜𐑢𐑦𐑡𐑩𐑟, 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑮𐑰𐑛 𐑞 𐑕𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑤𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑐𐑧𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑑'𐑕 𐑓𐑱𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑯 𐑥𐑹 𐑕𐑳𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑥𐑰𐑯𐑦𐑙𐑟, 𐑣𐑬 𐑥𐑱 𐑳𐑯𐑤𐑧𐑑𐑼𐑛 ·𐑦𐑖𐑥𐑱𐑩𐑤 𐑣𐑴𐑐 𐑑 𐑮𐑰𐑛 𐑞 𐑷𐑓𐑩𐑤 ·𐑗𐑭𐑤𐑛𐑰 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤'𐑟 𐑚𐑮𐑬? 𐑲 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑐𐑫𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑚𐑮𐑬 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑿. 𐑮𐑰𐑛 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑓 𐑿 𐑒𐑨𐑯.

·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 80. 𐑞 ·𐑯𐑳𐑑.

𐑦𐑓 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑚𐑰 𐑓𐑦𐑟𐑦𐑪𐑜𐑯𐑩𐑥𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑦 𐑩 ·𐑕𐑓𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑕, 𐑑 𐑞 𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑯𐑪𐑤𐑩𐑡𐑦𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑯 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑡𐑾𐑥𐑧𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑻𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑪𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑑 𐑕𐑒𐑢𐑺.

𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑫𐑤-𐑜𐑮𐑴𐑯 𐑒𐑮𐑰𐑗𐑼 𐑞 𐑕𐑒𐑳𐑤 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑥𐑧𐑠𐑼 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑰𐑕𐑑 𐑑𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑦 𐑓𐑰𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑤𐑧𐑙𐑔. 𐑳𐑯𐑣𐑦𐑯𐑡 𐑞 𐑤𐑴𐑼 𐑡𐑷, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑝𐑿 𐑝 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑕𐑒𐑳𐑤 𐑦𐑟 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑝 𐑩 𐑥𐑪𐑛𐑼𐑩𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑤𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑯 𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑔𐑮𐑵𐑬𐑑 𐑪𐑯 𐑩 𐑤𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑤 𐑚𐑱𐑕. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑤𐑲𐑓—𐑨𐑟 𐑢𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑧𐑤𐑕𐑢𐑺 𐑕𐑰𐑯—𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑤𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑯 𐑦𐑟 𐑨𐑙𐑜𐑿𐑤𐑼𐑤𐑦 𐑓𐑦𐑤𐑛 𐑳𐑐, 𐑯 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑒𐑢𐑺𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑹𐑥𐑩𐑕 𐑕𐑵𐑐𐑼𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑚𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑥𐑨𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑡𐑳𐑙𐑒 𐑯 𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥. 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑣𐑲 𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑞 𐑕𐑒𐑳𐑤 𐑓𐑹𐑥𐑟 𐑩 𐑒𐑮𐑱𐑑𐑼 𐑑 𐑚𐑧𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑐𐑸𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑥𐑨𐑕; 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑞 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑓𐑤𐑹 𐑝 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑒𐑮𐑱𐑑𐑼—𐑦𐑯 𐑩𐑯𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑒𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑛𐑩𐑥 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑰𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑑𐑧𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑗𐑩𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑤𐑧𐑙𐑔 𐑯 𐑨𐑟 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑦𐑯 𐑛𐑧𐑐𐑔—𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑴𐑟𐑩𐑟 𐑞 𐑥𐑽 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑓𐑫𐑤 𐑝 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑥𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑼'𐑟 𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑯. 𐑞 𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑯 𐑦𐑟 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑰𐑕𐑑 𐑑𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑦 𐑓𐑰𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑩𐑐𐑨𐑮𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑓𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑤𐑲𐑓; 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑯 𐑩𐑢𐑱 𐑚𐑦𐑣𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑝𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑬𐑑𐑢𐑻𐑒𐑕, 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑼𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑛𐑧𐑤 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑨𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑦𐑓𐑲𐑛 𐑓𐑹𐑑𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑒𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑝 ·𐑒𐑢𐑩𐑚𐑧𐑒. 𐑕𐑴 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑗𐑶𐑕 𐑒𐑭𐑕𐑒𐑩𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑮𐑰𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑯𐑴𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑣𐑵 𐑐𐑼𐑧𐑥𐑐𐑑𐑼𐑦𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑦𐑯𐑲 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑐𐑨𐑤𐑐𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑧𐑥𐑚𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑝 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑓𐑹𐑥𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑒𐑿𐑚𐑦𐑒-𐑘𐑸𐑛𐑟 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 𐑥𐑨𐑜𐑩𐑟𐑰𐑯. 𐑤𐑲𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡 𐑓𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑟, 𐑒𐑹𐑕𐑩𐑟, 𐑯 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑵𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟, 𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑨𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑣𐑧𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟, 𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑟 𐑥𐑹 𐑦𐑯 𐑒𐑰𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑲𐑛𐑾 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑜𐑸𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑐𐑸𐑑 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑕𐑰𐑑 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑡𐑩𐑯𐑕.

𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑯, 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑯𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑡𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑦 𐑞 𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑝 𐑞𐑦𐑕 ·𐑤𐑩𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑔𐑩𐑯, 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑰𐑗𐑼'𐑟 𐑤𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑨𐑒𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑑, 𐑦𐑟 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑲𐑼 𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑵𐑠𐑩𐑯. 𐑨𐑟 𐑓 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑑𐑮𐑵 𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑯, 𐑿 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑕𐑰 𐑯𐑴 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑦𐑑, 𐑯𐑹 𐑓𐑰𐑤 𐑧𐑯𐑦. 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑷𐑤 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑸 𐑥𐑲𐑑𐑦, 𐑢𐑺𐑟 𐑩 𐑓𐑷𐑤𐑕 𐑚𐑮𐑬 𐑑 𐑞 𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛.

𐑦𐑓 𐑿 𐑳𐑯𐑤𐑴𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑒𐑳𐑤 𐑝 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥𐑦 𐑣𐑰𐑐𐑕 𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑩 𐑮𐑽 𐑝𐑿 𐑝 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑮𐑽 𐑧𐑯𐑛, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑦𐑟 𐑞 𐑣𐑲 𐑧𐑯𐑛, 𐑿 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑚𐑰 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑒 𐑚𐑲 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑧𐑥𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑑 𐑞 𐑣𐑿𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑕𐑒𐑳𐑤, 𐑚𐑦𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑕𐑦𐑗𐑵𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯, 𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑐𐑶𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑝𐑿. 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑰𐑛, 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑮𐑦𐑝𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑒𐑳𐑤 (𐑕𐑒𐑱𐑤𐑛 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑑 𐑞 𐑣𐑿𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑥𐑨𐑜𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑿𐑛) 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑩 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑑 𐑝 𐑥𐑧𐑯'𐑟 𐑕𐑒𐑳𐑤𐑟, 𐑯 𐑿 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑪𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑺𐑦𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞𐑧𐑥; 𐑯 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑸𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑛𐑦𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑪𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑐𐑸𐑑 𐑝 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑦𐑑, 𐑦𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑯𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑡𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑓𐑮𐑱𐑟 𐑿 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑕𐑱—𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑯𐑴 𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓-𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑰𐑥, 𐑯 𐑯𐑴 𐑝𐑧𐑯𐑼𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯. 𐑯 𐑚𐑲 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑯𐑧𐑜𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟, 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑼𐑛 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑩𐑓𐑻𐑥𐑩𐑑𐑦𐑝 𐑓𐑨𐑒𐑑 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑛𐑦𐑡𐑩𐑕 𐑚𐑳𐑤𐑒 𐑯 𐑐𐑬𐑼, 𐑿 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑚𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑓𐑹𐑥 𐑑 𐑘𐑹𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑞 𐑑𐑮𐑵𐑩𐑕𐑑, 𐑞𐑴 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑞 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑜𐑟𐑦𐑤𐑼𐑱𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑧𐑐𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑞 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑜𐑟𐑷𐑤𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑐𐑴𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦 𐑦𐑟.

𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑓 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑨𐑮𐑩𐑑𐑦𐑝 𐑛𐑦𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤'𐑟 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑐𐑼 𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑯, 𐑿 𐑛𐑰𐑥 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑱𐑐𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑨𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑢𐑩𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑗𐑸𐑑𐑩𐑛, 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑩𐑯𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑲𐑛𐑾 𐑓 𐑿. 𐑦𐑓 𐑿 𐑩𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑝𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑦𐑜𐑸𐑛 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑐𐑧𐑛'𐑟 𐑕𐑐𐑲𐑯, 𐑿 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑚𐑰 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑒 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑧𐑥𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑝 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑝𐑻𐑑𐑦𐑚𐑮𐑦 𐑑 𐑩 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑙 𐑯𐑧𐑒𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑛𐑢𐑹𐑓𐑑 𐑕𐑒𐑳𐑤𐑟, 𐑷𐑤 𐑚𐑺𐑦𐑙 𐑮𐑵𐑛𐑦𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑧𐑥𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑒𐑳𐑤 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑐𐑼. 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑩 ·𐑡𐑻𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑰𐑑, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑝𐑻𐑑𐑦𐑚𐑮𐑦 𐑸 𐑨𐑚𐑕𐑩𐑤𐑵𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑝𐑧𐑤𐑩𐑐𐑑 𐑕𐑒𐑳𐑤𐑟. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞 𐑒𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑾𐑕 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑧𐑥𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑕, 𐑲 𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑦𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑡𐑻𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑞 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑑 𐑐𐑼𐑕𐑰𐑝. 𐑩 𐑓𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑕 𐑐𐑶𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑑 𐑬𐑑 𐑑 𐑥𐑰, 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑒𐑧𐑤𐑩𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑩 𐑓𐑴 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑕𐑤𐑱𐑯, 𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑝𐑻𐑑𐑦𐑚𐑮𐑦 𐑝 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑤𐑱𐑦𐑙, 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑕𐑹𐑑 𐑝 𐑚𐑨𐑕𐑴-𐑮𐑦𐑤𐑰𐑝𐑴, 𐑞 𐑚𐑰𐑒𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑬 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑵. 𐑯𐑬, 𐑲 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑼 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑯𐑪𐑤𐑩𐑡𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑕 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑴𐑥𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑹𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑐𐑫𐑖𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑺 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑜𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑕𐑧𐑮𐑩𐑚𐑧𐑤𐑩𐑥 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑲𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑨𐑤. 𐑓 𐑲 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑰𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑝 𐑩 𐑥𐑨𐑯'𐑟 𐑒𐑨𐑮𐑩𐑒𐑑𐑼 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑚𐑰 𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑴𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑨𐑒𐑚𐑴𐑯. 𐑲 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑮𐑭𐑞𐑼 𐑓𐑰𐑤 𐑘𐑹 𐑕𐑐𐑲𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑘𐑹 𐑕𐑒𐑳𐑤, 𐑣𐑵𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑿 𐑸. 𐑩 𐑔𐑦𐑯 𐑡𐑶𐑕𐑑 𐑝 𐑩 𐑕𐑐𐑲𐑯 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑳𐑐𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑛 𐑩 𐑓𐑫𐑤 𐑯 𐑯𐑴𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑴𐑤. 𐑲 𐑮𐑦𐑡𐑶𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑲 𐑕𐑐𐑲𐑯, 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑻𐑥 𐑷𐑛𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑕 𐑕𐑑𐑭𐑓 𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑓𐑤𐑨𐑜 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑲 𐑓𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑭𐑓 𐑬𐑑 𐑑 𐑞 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛.

𐑩𐑐𐑤𐑲 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑕𐑐𐑲𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑚𐑮𐑭𐑯𐑗 𐑝 𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑯𐑪𐑤𐑩𐑡𐑦 𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤. 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑾𐑤 𐑒𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑿𐑩𐑕 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑯𐑧𐑒-𐑝𐑻𐑑𐑦𐑚𐑮𐑩; 𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑝𐑻𐑑𐑦𐑚𐑮𐑩 𐑞 𐑚𐑪𐑑𐑩𐑥 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑲𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑨𐑤 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑥𐑧𐑠𐑼 𐑑𐑧𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑗𐑩𐑟 𐑩𐑒𐑮𐑪𐑕, 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑱𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑲𐑑, 𐑯 𐑝 𐑩 𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑨𐑙𐑜𐑿𐑤𐑼 𐑓𐑦𐑜𐑼 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑚𐑱𐑕 𐑛𐑬𐑯𐑢𐑼𐑛𐑟. 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑐𐑭𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑞 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑱𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑝𐑻𐑑𐑦𐑚𐑮𐑦 𐑞 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑨𐑤 𐑑𐑱𐑐𐑼𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑲𐑟, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑓 𐑩 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑼𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑱𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑤𐑸𐑡 𐑒𐑩𐑐𐑨𐑕𐑦𐑑𐑦. 𐑯𐑬, 𐑝 𐑒𐑹𐑕, 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑨𐑤 𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑦𐑤𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑤𐑦 𐑓𐑲𐑚𐑮𐑩𐑕 𐑕𐑳𐑚𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕—𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑲𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑒𐑹𐑛—𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑯; 𐑯 𐑛𐑦𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑿𐑯𐑦𐑒𐑱𐑑𐑕 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑯. 𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑥𐑹, 𐑓 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑓𐑰𐑑 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑦𐑥𐑻𐑡𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑯'𐑟 𐑒𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑑𐑦, 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑲𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑒𐑹𐑛 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑱𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑩𐑯 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑮𐑰𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑜𐑻𐑔, 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑩𐑤 𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑯. 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑕𐑻𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟, 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑦𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑳𐑯𐑮𐑰𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑑 𐑕𐑻𐑝𐑱 𐑯 𐑥𐑨𐑐 𐑬𐑑 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤'𐑟 𐑕𐑐𐑲𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑯𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑡𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑦? 𐑓, 𐑝𐑿𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑤𐑲𐑑, 𐑞 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑨𐑮𐑩𐑑𐑦𐑝 𐑕𐑥𐑷𐑤𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑯 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑐𐑼 𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑹 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑐𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑨𐑮𐑩𐑑𐑦𐑝 𐑥𐑨𐑜𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑿𐑛 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑐𐑲𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑒𐑹𐑛.

𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑤𐑰𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑣𐑦𐑯𐑑 𐑑 𐑪𐑐𐑼𐑱𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑥𐑱 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑯𐑪𐑤𐑩𐑡𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑕, 𐑲 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑥𐑽𐑤𐑦 𐑩𐑕𐑿𐑥 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑲𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑔𐑽𐑦 𐑓 𐑩 𐑥𐑴𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑, 𐑦𐑯 𐑮𐑧𐑓𐑼𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤'𐑟 𐑣𐑳𐑥𐑐. 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑷𐑜𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑳𐑥𐑐, 𐑦𐑓 𐑲 𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑯𐑪𐑑, 𐑮𐑲𐑟𐑩𐑟 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑤𐑸𐑡𐑼 𐑝𐑻𐑑𐑦𐑚𐑮𐑦, 𐑯 𐑦𐑟, 𐑞𐑺𐑓𐑹, 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑕𐑹𐑑, 𐑞 𐑬𐑑𐑼 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑝𐑧𐑒𐑕 𐑥𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑝 𐑦𐑑. 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑮𐑧𐑤𐑩𐑑𐑦𐑝 𐑕𐑦𐑗𐑵𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑲 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑒𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑣𐑲 𐑣𐑳𐑥𐑐 𐑞 𐑹𐑜𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑓𐑻𐑥𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑹 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑪𐑥𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤. 𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑥𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑼 𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑪𐑥𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤, 𐑿 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑮𐑰𐑟𐑩𐑯 𐑑 𐑯𐑴.

·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 81. 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛 ·𐑥𐑰𐑑𐑕 𐑞 ·𐑝𐑻𐑡𐑦𐑯.

𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑰𐑛𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑛𐑱 𐑼𐑲𐑝𐑛, 𐑯 𐑢𐑰 𐑛𐑵𐑤𐑦 𐑥𐑧𐑑 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐 ·𐑿𐑙𐑓𐑮𐑬, ·𐑛𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑒 ·𐑛𐑦 ·𐑛𐑽, 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑼, 𐑝 ·𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑥𐑩𐑯.

𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑐𐑰𐑐𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛, 𐑞 ·𐑛𐑳𐑗 𐑯 ·𐑡𐑻𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑸 𐑯𐑬 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑞 𐑤𐑰𐑕𐑑; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑣𐑽 𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑨𐑑 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑢𐑲𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑝 𐑤𐑨𐑑𐑦𐑑𐑿𐑛 𐑯 𐑤𐑪𐑯𐑜𐑦𐑑𐑿𐑛, 𐑿 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑩𐑒𐑱𐑠𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑥𐑰𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞𐑺 𐑓𐑤𐑨𐑜 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑩𐑕𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑒.

𐑓 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑮𐑰𐑟𐑩𐑯, 𐑞 ·𐑿𐑙𐑓𐑮𐑬 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑒𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑰𐑜𐑼 𐑑 𐑐𐑱 𐑣𐑻 𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑕. 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛, 𐑖𐑰 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑑, 𐑯 𐑛𐑮𐑪𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑚𐑴𐑑, 𐑣𐑻 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑧𐑤𐑛 𐑑𐑩𐑢𐑹𐑛𐑟 𐑳𐑕, 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑬𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑛 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑻𐑯.

“𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑞𐑺?” 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒, 𐑐𐑶𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑱𐑝𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 ·𐑡𐑻𐑥𐑩𐑯. “𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑪𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤!—𐑩 𐑤𐑨𐑥𐑐-𐑓𐑰𐑛𐑼!”

“𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑,” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚, “𐑯𐑴, 𐑯𐑴, 𐑦𐑑'𐑕 𐑩 𐑒𐑪𐑓𐑦-𐑐𐑪𐑑, ·𐑥𐑼 ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒; 𐑣𐑰'𐑟 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑪𐑓 𐑑 𐑥𐑱𐑒 𐑳𐑕 𐑬𐑼 𐑒𐑪𐑓𐑦, 𐑦𐑟 𐑞 ·𐑘𐑸𐑥𐑩𐑯; 𐑛𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑿 𐑕𐑰 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑜 𐑑𐑦𐑯 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑙𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑥?—𐑞𐑨𐑑'𐑕 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑶𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼. 𐑴! 𐑣𐑰'𐑟 𐑷𐑤 𐑮𐑲𐑑, 𐑦𐑟 𐑞 ·𐑘𐑸𐑥𐑩𐑯.”

“𐑜𐑴 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑿,” 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 ·𐑓𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑒, “𐑦𐑑'𐑕 𐑩 𐑤𐑨𐑥𐑐-𐑓𐑰𐑛𐑼 𐑯 𐑩𐑯 𐑶𐑤-𐑒𐑨𐑯. 𐑣𐑰'𐑟 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑶𐑤, 𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑩-𐑚𐑧𐑜𐑦𐑙.”

𐑣𐑬𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑒𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑾𐑕 𐑦𐑑 𐑥𐑱 𐑕𐑰𐑥 𐑓 𐑩𐑯 𐑶𐑤-𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑚𐑪𐑮𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑶𐑤 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤-𐑜𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛, 𐑯 𐑣𐑬𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑦𐑑 𐑥𐑱 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑩𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑑 𐑞 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑝𐑻𐑚 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑒𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑦𐑙 𐑒𐑴𐑤𐑟 𐑑 ·𐑯𐑿𐑒𐑭𐑕𐑩𐑤, 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩 𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑮𐑾𐑤𐑦 𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑟; 𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑒𐑱𐑕 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 ·𐑛𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑒 ·𐑛𐑦 ·𐑛𐑽 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑿𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑛𐑳𐑒𐑑 𐑩 𐑤𐑨𐑥𐑐-𐑓𐑰𐑛𐑼 𐑨𐑟 ·𐑓𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑒 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑺.

𐑨𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑥𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑒, ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑩𐑚𐑮𐑳𐑐𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑩𐑒𐑪𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑣𐑰𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑮𐑴𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑤𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑴, 𐑞 ·𐑡𐑻𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑕𐑵𐑯 𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑰𐑑 𐑦𐑜𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑢𐑲𐑑 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤; 𐑦𐑥𐑰𐑛𐑾𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑝𐑼𐑕𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑤𐑨𐑥𐑐-𐑓𐑰𐑛𐑼 𐑯 𐑶𐑤 𐑒𐑨𐑯, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑸𐑒𐑕 𐑑𐑳𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑑𐑻𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑥𐑩𐑒 𐑨𐑑 𐑯𐑲𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑛𐑸𐑒𐑯𐑩𐑕—𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑛𐑮𐑪𐑐 𐑝 ·𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑶𐑤 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑜𐑪𐑯, 𐑯 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑩 𐑕𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑩𐑤 𐑓𐑤𐑲𐑦𐑙-𐑓𐑦𐑖 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑗𐑼𐑛 𐑑 𐑕𐑩𐑐𐑤𐑲 𐑞 𐑛𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦; 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑒𐑤𐑵𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑲 𐑣𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑰𐑛 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑼𐑦 𐑦𐑟 𐑑𐑧𐑒𐑯𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑛 𐑩 𐑒𐑤𐑰𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯 (𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑟, 𐑩𐑯 𐑧𐑥𐑐𐑑𐑦 𐑢𐑳𐑯), 𐑢𐑧𐑤 𐑛𐑦𐑟𐑻𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑯𐑱𐑥 𐑝 ·𐑿𐑙𐑓𐑮𐑬 𐑹 𐑞 ·𐑝𐑻𐑡𐑦𐑯.

𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑦𐑕𐑧𐑕𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑩𐑐𐑤𐑲𐑛, ·𐑛𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑒 𐑛𐑦𐑐𐑸𐑑𐑩𐑛; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑖𐑦𐑐'𐑕 𐑕𐑲𐑛, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑦𐑥𐑩𐑤𐑑𐑱𐑯𐑾𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑱𐑟𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑-𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑟 𐑝 𐑚𐑴𐑔 𐑝𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑤𐑟; 𐑯 𐑕𐑴 𐑰𐑜𐑼 𐑓 𐑞 𐑗𐑱𐑕 𐑢𐑪𐑟 ·𐑛𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑒, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑 𐑐𐑷𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑐𐑫𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑶𐑤-𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑯 𐑤𐑨𐑥𐑐-𐑓𐑰𐑛𐑼 𐑩𐑚𐑹𐑛, 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑤𐑵𐑛 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑴𐑑 𐑯 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑞 𐑤𐑩𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑔𐑩𐑯 𐑤𐑨𐑥𐑐-𐑓𐑰𐑛𐑼𐑟.

𐑯𐑬, 𐑞 𐑜𐑱𐑥 𐑣𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑩𐑯 𐑑 𐑤𐑰𐑢𐑼𐑛, 𐑣𐑰 𐑯 𐑞 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑔𐑮𐑰 ·𐑡𐑻𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑵𐑯 𐑓𐑪𐑤𐑴𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑼𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛'𐑟 𐑒𐑰𐑤𐑟. 𐑞𐑺 𐑢𐑻 𐑱𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟, 𐑩𐑯 𐑨𐑝𐑼𐑦𐑡 𐑐𐑪𐑛. 𐑩𐑢𐑺 𐑝 𐑞𐑺 𐑛𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑼, 𐑞𐑱 𐑢𐑻 𐑜𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑷𐑤 𐑩𐑚𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑛 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑞 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛, 𐑮𐑳𐑚𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑺 𐑓𐑤𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑕 𐑨𐑟 𐑒𐑤𐑴𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑨𐑟 𐑕𐑴 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑕𐑐𐑨𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑣𐑹𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑸𐑯𐑩𐑕. 𐑞𐑱 𐑤𐑧𐑓𐑑 𐑩 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑, 𐑢𐑲𐑛 𐑢𐑱𐑒, 𐑨𐑟 𐑞𐑴 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑿𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑳𐑯𐑮𐑴𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑢𐑲𐑛 𐑐𐑸𐑗𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑰.

𐑓𐑫𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑮𐑨𐑐𐑦𐑛 𐑢𐑱𐑒, 𐑯 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑓𐑨𐑞𐑩𐑥𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑮𐑽, 𐑕𐑢𐑨𐑥 𐑩 𐑣𐑿𐑡, 𐑣𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑑 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑚𐑫𐑤, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑚𐑲 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑨𐑮𐑩𐑑𐑦𐑝𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑤𐑴 𐑐𐑮𐑴𐑜𐑮𐑧𐑕, 𐑨𐑟 𐑢𐑧𐑤 𐑨𐑟 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑳𐑯𐑿𐑠𐑵𐑩𐑤 𐑘𐑧𐑤𐑴𐑦𐑖 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑮𐑳𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑴𐑝𐑼𐑜𐑮𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑩𐑓𐑤𐑦𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑡𐑷𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑕, 𐑹 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑦𐑯𐑓𐑻𐑥𐑦𐑑𐑦. 𐑢𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑪𐑙𐑛 𐑑 𐑞 𐑐𐑪𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑩𐑛𐑝𐑭𐑯𐑕, 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑕𐑗𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤; 𐑓 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑒𐑳𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑥𐑼𐑦 𐑓 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑝𐑧𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑤𐑩𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑔𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑨𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑕𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑤. 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼𐑞𐑩𐑤𐑧𐑕, 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑒 𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑢𐑱𐑒, 𐑞𐑴 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑰𐑛 𐑞𐑺 𐑚𐑨𐑒 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑸𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑪𐑟 𐑞 𐑢𐑲𐑑-𐑚𐑴𐑯 𐑹 𐑕𐑢𐑧𐑤 𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑮𐑷𐑛 𐑥𐑳𐑟𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩 𐑛𐑨𐑖𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯, 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑞 𐑕𐑢𐑧𐑤 𐑓𐑹𐑥𐑛 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑑𐑵 𐑣𐑪𐑕𐑑𐑲𐑤 𐑒𐑳𐑮𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑥𐑰𐑑. 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑐𐑬𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑖𐑹𐑑, 𐑕𐑤𐑴, 𐑯 𐑤𐑩𐑚𐑹𐑾𐑕; 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑹𐑔 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑗𐑴𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑹𐑑 𐑝 𐑜𐑳𐑖, 𐑯 𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑑𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑦𐑯 𐑑𐑹𐑯 𐑖𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑟, 𐑓𐑪𐑤𐑴𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡 𐑕𐑳𐑚𐑑𐑼𐑱𐑯𐑾𐑯 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑰𐑜𐑮𐑧𐑕 𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑚𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑛 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑧𐑥𐑦𐑑𐑦, 𐑒𐑷𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼𐑟 𐑚𐑦𐑣𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑑 𐑳𐑐𐑚𐑳𐑚𐑩𐑤.

“𐑣𐑵'𐑟 𐑜𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑐𐑨𐑮𐑩𐑜𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑒?” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚, “𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑥𐑩𐑒-𐑱𐑒, 𐑲'𐑥 𐑩𐑓𐑮𐑱𐑛. 𐑤𐑹𐑛, 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒 𐑝 𐑣𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑭𐑓 𐑩𐑯 𐑱𐑒𐑼 𐑝 𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑥𐑩𐑒-𐑱𐑒! 𐑨𐑛𐑝𐑻𐑕 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑸 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑨𐑛 ·𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑥𐑩𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑚𐑶𐑟. 𐑦𐑑'𐑕 𐑞 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑓𐑬𐑤 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛 𐑲 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑯𐑿 𐑑 𐑚𐑤𐑴 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑩𐑕𐑑𐑻𐑯; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑤𐑫𐑒, 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑘𐑷 𐑕𐑴 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹? 𐑦𐑑 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑰, 𐑣𐑰'𐑟 𐑤𐑪𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑑𐑦𐑤𐑼.”

𐑨𐑟 𐑩𐑯 𐑴𐑝𐑼𐑤𐑱𐑛𐑩𐑯 ·𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑾𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑚𐑺𐑦𐑙 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑣𐑲𐑯𐑛𐑴𐑕𐑑𐑭𐑯 𐑒𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑛𐑧𐑒 𐑤𐑴𐑛 𐑝 𐑓𐑮𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑣𐑹𐑕𐑩𐑟, 𐑒𐑼𐑰𐑯𐑟, 𐑚𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑟, 𐑮𐑴𐑤𐑟, 𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑤𐑴𐑟 𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑻 𐑢𐑱; 𐑕𐑴 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑣𐑰𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑱𐑡𐑛 𐑚𐑳𐑤𐑒, 𐑯 𐑯𐑬 𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑐𐑸𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑚𐑮𐑩𐑕 𐑮𐑦𐑚-𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑟, 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑴𐑟 𐑞 𐑒𐑷𐑟 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑛𐑰𐑝𐑾𐑕 𐑢𐑱𐑒 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑳𐑯𐑯𐑨𐑗𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑥𐑐 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑼𐑛 𐑓𐑦𐑯. 𐑢𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑤𐑪𐑕𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑓𐑦𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑚𐑨𐑑𐑩𐑤, 𐑹 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑚𐑹𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑 𐑦𐑑, 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑻 𐑣𐑸𐑛 𐑑 𐑕𐑱.

“𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑢𐑱𐑑 𐑩 𐑚𐑦𐑑, 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑗𐑨𐑐, 𐑯 𐑲'𐑤 𐑜𐑦𐑝 𐑘𐑰 𐑩 𐑕𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑓 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑵𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑸𐑥,” 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 𐑒𐑮𐑵𐑩𐑤 ·𐑓𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑒, 𐑐𐑶𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤-𐑤𐑲𐑯 𐑯𐑽 𐑣𐑦𐑥.

“𐑥𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑣𐑰 𐑛𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑕𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑰 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑦𐑑,” 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒. “𐑜𐑦𐑝 𐑢𐑱, 𐑹 𐑞 ·𐑡𐑻𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑥.”

𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑚𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑮𐑲𐑝𐑩𐑤 𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕 𐑢𐑻 𐑐𐑶𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑓 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑓𐑦𐑖, 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑞 𐑤𐑸𐑡𐑩𐑕𐑑, 𐑯 𐑞𐑺𐑓𐑹 𐑞 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑝𐑨𐑤𐑿𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑽𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑑 𐑞𐑧𐑥, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑜𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑝𐑦𐑤𐑪𐑕𐑦𐑑𐑦, 𐑥𐑹𐑴𐑝𐑼, 𐑨𐑟 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑓𐑲 𐑐𐑼𐑕𐑿𐑑 𐑓 𐑞 𐑑𐑲𐑥. 𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑡𐑳𐑙𐑒𐑗𐑼 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛'𐑟 𐑒𐑰𐑤𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑖𐑪𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑔𐑮𐑰 ·𐑡𐑻𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑤𐑴𐑼𐑛; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑛, ·𐑛𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑒'𐑕 𐑚𐑴𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑤𐑧𐑛 𐑞 𐑗𐑱𐑕, 𐑞𐑴 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑥𐑴𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑯𐑽𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑯 𐑮𐑲𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑟. 𐑞 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑱 𐑓𐑽𐑛, 𐑢𐑪𐑟, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑷𐑤𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑦 𐑕𐑴 𐑯𐑲 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑸𐑒, 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑚𐑰 𐑦𐑯𐑱𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑑 𐑛𐑸𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑲𐑼𐑯 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑞𐑱 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑰𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑴𐑝𐑼𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑯 𐑐𐑭𐑕 𐑣𐑦𐑥. 𐑨𐑟 𐑓 ·𐑛𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑒, 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑒𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑓𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑚𐑰 𐑞 𐑒𐑱𐑕, 𐑯 𐑩𐑒𐑱𐑠𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑛𐑦𐑮𐑲𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑡𐑧𐑕𐑗𐑼 𐑖𐑫𐑒 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑤𐑨𐑥𐑐-𐑓𐑰𐑛𐑼 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕.

“𐑞 𐑳𐑯𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑕 𐑯 𐑳𐑯𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑛𐑪𐑜!” 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒; “𐑣𐑰 𐑥𐑪𐑒𐑕 𐑯 𐑛𐑺𐑟 𐑥𐑰 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑐𐑫𐑼-𐑚𐑪𐑒𐑕 𐑲 𐑓𐑦𐑤𐑛 𐑓 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑓𐑲𐑝 𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑩𐑜𐑴!”—𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑕 𐑢𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑼—“𐑜𐑦𐑝 𐑢𐑱, 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑣𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑟! 𐑛𐑪𐑜 𐑑 𐑦𐑑!”

“𐑲 𐑑𐑧𐑤 𐑘𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟, 𐑥𐑧𐑯”—𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑮𐑵—“𐑦𐑑'𐑕 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑥𐑲 𐑮𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑡𐑩𐑯 𐑑 𐑜𐑧𐑑 𐑥𐑨𐑛; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑲'𐑛 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑑 𐑰𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑝𐑦𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑕 ·𐑘𐑸𐑥𐑩𐑯—·𐑐𐑫𐑤—𐑢𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑘𐑰? 𐑸 𐑘𐑰 𐑜𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑤𐑧𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑮𐑭𐑕𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑚𐑰𐑑 𐑘𐑰? 𐑛𐑵 𐑘𐑰 𐑤𐑳𐑝 𐑚𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑦? 𐑩 𐑣𐑪𐑜𐑟𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑝 𐑚𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑦, 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑑 𐑞 𐑚𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑥𐑨𐑯. 𐑒𐑳𐑥, 𐑢𐑲 𐑛𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑝 𐑘𐑰 𐑚𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑩 𐑚𐑤𐑳𐑛-𐑝𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑤? 𐑣𐑵'𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑛𐑮𐑪𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑯 𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑼 𐑴𐑝𐑼𐑚𐑹𐑛—𐑢𐑰 𐑛𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑚𐑳𐑡 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑗—𐑢𐑰'𐑼 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑭𐑥𐑛. 𐑣𐑩𐑤𐑵, 𐑣𐑽'𐑟 𐑜𐑮𐑭𐑕 𐑜𐑮𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑'𐑕 𐑚𐑪𐑑𐑩𐑥—𐑯 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 ·𐑤𐑹𐑛, 𐑞 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑞𐑺'𐑟 𐑚𐑳𐑛𐑦𐑙. 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑛𐑵, 𐑚𐑶𐑟. 𐑤𐑫𐑒 𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 ·𐑘𐑸𐑥𐑩𐑯! 𐑞 𐑖𐑹𐑑 𐑯 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑝 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟, 𐑥𐑧𐑯, 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑘𐑰 𐑕𐑐𐑦𐑑 𐑓𐑲𐑼 𐑹 𐑯𐑪𐑑?”

“𐑴! 𐑕𐑰 𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑛𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑥𐑱𐑒𐑕!” 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 ·𐑓𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑒, 𐑛𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑳𐑐 𐑯 𐑛𐑬𐑯—“𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑩 𐑣𐑳𐑥𐑐—𐑴, 𐑛𐑵 𐑐𐑲𐑤 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑰𐑓—𐑤𐑱𐑟 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑤𐑪𐑜! 𐑴! 𐑥𐑲 𐑤𐑨𐑛𐑟, 𐑛𐑵 𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑙—𐑕𐑤𐑨𐑐-𐑡𐑨𐑒𐑕 𐑯 𐑒𐑢𐑭𐑣𐑪𐑜𐑟 𐑓 𐑕𐑳𐑐𐑼, 𐑿 𐑯𐑴, 𐑥𐑲 𐑤𐑨𐑛𐑟—𐑚𐑱𐑒𐑑 𐑒𐑤𐑨𐑥𐑟 𐑯 𐑥𐑳𐑓𐑦𐑯𐑟—𐑴, 𐑛𐑵, 𐑛𐑵, 𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑙,—𐑣𐑰'𐑟 𐑩 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑨𐑮𐑩𐑤𐑼—𐑛𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑤𐑵𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑯𐑬—𐑛𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑴, 𐑛𐑴𐑯𐑑!—𐑕𐑰 𐑞𐑨𐑑 ·𐑘𐑸𐑥𐑩𐑯—𐑴, 𐑢𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑘𐑰 𐑐𐑫𐑤 𐑓 𐑘𐑹 𐑛𐑳𐑓, 𐑥𐑲 𐑤𐑨𐑛𐑟—𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩 𐑕𐑪𐑜! 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩 𐑕𐑪𐑜𐑼! 𐑛𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑘𐑰 𐑤𐑳𐑝 𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥? 𐑞𐑺 𐑜𐑴𐑟 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑔𐑬𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑛𐑪𐑤𐑼𐑟, 𐑥𐑧𐑯!—𐑩 𐑚𐑨𐑙𐑒!—𐑩 𐑣𐑴𐑤 𐑚𐑨𐑙𐑒! 𐑞 𐑚𐑨𐑙𐑒 𐑝 ·𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛!—𐑴, 𐑛𐑵, 𐑛𐑵, 𐑛𐑵!—𐑢𐑪𐑑'𐑕 𐑞𐑨𐑑 ·𐑘𐑸𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑯𐑬?”

𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑥𐑴𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑 ·𐑛𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑒 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑨𐑒𐑑 𐑝 𐑐𐑦𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑤𐑨𐑥𐑐-𐑓𐑰𐑛𐑼 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑩𐑛𐑝𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕, 𐑯 𐑷𐑤𐑕𐑴 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑶𐑤-𐑒𐑨𐑯; 𐑐𐑼𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑕 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑛𐑳𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑝𐑿 𐑝 𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑸𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑮𐑲𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑟' 𐑢𐑱, 𐑯 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑰𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑪𐑥𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑦 𐑩𐑒𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑼𐑱𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑴𐑯 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑥𐑴𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑦 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑚𐑨𐑒𐑢𐑼𐑛 𐑑𐑪𐑕.

“𐑞 𐑳𐑯𐑥𐑨𐑯𐑼𐑤𐑦 ·𐑛𐑳𐑗 𐑛𐑪𐑜𐑼!” 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚. “𐑐𐑫𐑤 𐑯𐑬, 𐑥𐑧𐑯, 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑓𐑦𐑓𐑑𐑦 𐑔𐑬𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑤𐑲𐑯-𐑝-𐑚𐑨𐑑𐑩𐑤-𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑤𐑴𐑛𐑟 𐑝 𐑮𐑧𐑛-𐑣𐑺𐑛 𐑛𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑟. 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑛'𐑘𐑰 𐑕𐑱, ·𐑑𐑨𐑖𐑑𐑱𐑜𐑴; 𐑸 𐑿 𐑞 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑑 𐑕𐑯𐑨𐑐 𐑘𐑹 𐑕𐑐𐑲𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑑𐑵-𐑯-𐑑𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑦 𐑐𐑰𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑓 𐑞 𐑪𐑯𐑼 𐑝 𐑴𐑤𐑛 ·𐑜𐑱𐑣𐑧𐑛? 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑛'𐑘𐑰 𐑕𐑱?”

“𐑲 𐑕𐑱, 𐑐𐑫𐑤 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑜𐑪𐑛-𐑛𐑨𐑥,”—𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 𐑞 ·𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑾𐑯.

𐑓𐑽𐑕𐑤𐑦, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑑𐑷𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑡𐑻𐑥𐑩𐑯, 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛'𐑟 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕 𐑯𐑬 𐑚𐑦𐑜𐑨𐑯 𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑦𐑙 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑩𐑚𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑑; 𐑯, 𐑕𐑴 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑴𐑟𐑛, 𐑥𐑴𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑺𐑦𐑤𐑦 𐑯𐑽𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥. 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑓𐑲𐑯, 𐑤𐑵𐑕, 𐑖𐑦𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑮𐑩𐑕 𐑨𐑑𐑦𐑑𐑿𐑛 𐑝 𐑞 𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑟𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑛𐑮𐑷𐑦𐑙 𐑯𐑽 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑮𐑱, 𐑞 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑥𐑱𐑑𐑕 𐑕𐑑𐑫𐑛 𐑳𐑐 𐑐𐑮𐑬𐑛𐑤𐑦, 𐑩𐑒𐑱𐑠𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑨𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑹𐑟𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑜𐑟𐑦𐑤𐑼𐑱𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑒𐑮𐑲 𐑝, “𐑞𐑺 𐑖𐑰 𐑕𐑤𐑲𐑛𐑟, 𐑯𐑬! 𐑣𐑼𐑭 𐑓 𐑞 𐑢𐑲𐑑-𐑨𐑖 𐑚𐑮𐑰𐑟! 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 ·𐑘𐑸𐑥𐑩𐑯! 𐑕𐑱𐑤 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑣𐑦𐑥!”

𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑕𐑴 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑲𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑩𐑯 𐑼𐑦𐑡𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑛 ·𐑛𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑒 𐑣𐑨𐑛, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑐𐑲𐑑 𐑝 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑺 𐑜𐑨𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑦, 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑐𐑮𐑵𐑝𐑛 𐑞 𐑝𐑦𐑒𐑑𐑼 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑮𐑱𐑕, 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑩 𐑮𐑲𐑗𐑩𐑕 𐑡𐑳𐑡𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑒𐑮𐑨𐑚 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑒𐑷𐑑 𐑞 𐑚𐑤𐑱𐑛 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑦𐑛𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑹𐑟𐑥𐑩𐑯. 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑒𐑤𐑳𐑥𐑟𐑦 𐑤𐑳𐑚𐑼 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑰 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑲𐑑-𐑨𐑖, 𐑯 𐑢𐑲𐑤, 𐑦𐑯 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑢𐑩𐑯𐑕, ·𐑛𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑒'𐑕 𐑚𐑴𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑲 𐑑 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑕𐑲𐑟𐑦𐑙, 𐑯 𐑣𐑰 𐑔𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑢𐑱 𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑥𐑲𐑑𐑦 𐑮𐑱𐑡;—𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑓 ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒, ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚, 𐑯 ·𐑓𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑒. 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑖𐑬𐑑, 𐑞𐑱 𐑑𐑫𐑒 𐑩 𐑥𐑹𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑑 𐑓𐑹𐑢𐑼𐑛𐑟, 𐑯 𐑕𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑛 𐑳𐑐 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑡𐑻𐑥𐑩𐑯'𐑟 𐑒𐑢𐑹𐑑𐑼. 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑥𐑹, 𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑓𐑹 𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕 𐑢𐑻 𐑛𐑲𐑨𐑜𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤'𐑟 𐑦𐑥𐑰𐑛𐑾𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑒, 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑧𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞𐑧𐑥, 𐑪𐑯 𐑚𐑴𐑔 𐑕𐑲𐑛𐑟, 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞 𐑓𐑴𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑢𐑧𐑤 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑥𐑱𐑛.

𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩 𐑑𐑼𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑒, 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑐𐑦𐑑𐑾𐑚𐑩𐑤, 𐑯 𐑥𐑨𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑲𐑑. 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑬 𐑜𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑬𐑑, 𐑯 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑐𐑬𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑿𐑩𐑤 𐑑𐑹𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑡𐑧𐑑; 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑐𐑫𐑼 𐑓𐑦𐑯 𐑚𐑰𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑩𐑯 𐑨𐑜𐑩𐑯𐑦 𐑝 𐑓𐑮𐑲𐑑. 𐑯𐑬 𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛, 𐑯𐑬 𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑, 𐑣𐑰 𐑘𐑷𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑷𐑤𐑑𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑤𐑲𐑑, 𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑨𐑑 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑚𐑮𐑴𐑒, 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑐𐑨𐑟𐑥𐑪𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑨𐑙𐑒 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑰, 𐑹 𐑕𐑲𐑛𐑢𐑱𐑟 𐑮𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑑𐑩𐑢𐑹𐑛𐑟 𐑞 𐑕𐑒𐑲 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑚𐑰𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑦𐑯. 𐑕𐑴 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑲 𐑕𐑰𐑯 𐑩 𐑚𐑻𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑒𐑤𐑦𐑐𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑱𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑓𐑮𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑮𐑴𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑕𐑻𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑺, 𐑝𐑱𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑱𐑐 𐑞 𐑐𐑲𐑮𐑨𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑣𐑷𐑒𐑕. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞 𐑚𐑻𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑩 𐑝𐑶𐑕, 𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑝 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑥𐑱𐑒 𐑯𐑴𐑯 𐑣𐑻 𐑓𐑽; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞 𐑓𐑽 𐑝 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑝𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑛𐑳𐑥 𐑚𐑮𐑵𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑰, 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑗𐑱𐑯𐑛 𐑳𐑐 𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑗𐑭𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥; 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑯𐑴 𐑝𐑶𐑕, 𐑕𐑱𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑗𐑴𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑐𐑼𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑐𐑦𐑮𐑩𐑒𐑩𐑤, 𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑞 𐑕𐑲𐑑 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑳𐑯𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑦𐑑𐑾𐑚𐑩𐑤; 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤, 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑩𐑥𐑱𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑳𐑤𐑒, 𐑐𐑹𐑑𐑒𐑳𐑤𐑦𐑕 𐑡𐑷, 𐑯 𐑪𐑥𐑯𐑦𐑐𐑩𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑑𐑱𐑤, 𐑞𐑺 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑳𐑓 𐑑 𐑩𐑐𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑬𐑑𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑣𐑵 𐑕𐑴 𐑐𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑛.

𐑕𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑯𐑬 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑩 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑓𐑿 𐑥𐑴𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑥𐑹 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑜𐑦𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛'𐑟 𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕 𐑞 𐑩𐑛𐑝𐑭𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑡, 𐑯 𐑮𐑭𐑞𐑼 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑚𐑰 𐑞𐑳𐑕 𐑓𐑶𐑤𐑛 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑜𐑱𐑥, ·𐑛𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑒 𐑗𐑴𐑟 𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑟𐑼𐑛 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑩 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑳𐑯𐑿𐑠𐑵𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑛𐑸𐑑, 𐑺 𐑞 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑗𐑭𐑯𐑕 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑓 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑱𐑐.

𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑯𐑴 𐑕𐑵𐑯𐑼 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑽 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑳𐑐 𐑓 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑴𐑒, 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑑𐑲𐑜𐑼𐑟—·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜, ·𐑑𐑨𐑖𐑑𐑱𐑜𐑴, ·𐑛𐑨𐑜𐑵—𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑝𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑨𐑙 𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑓𐑰𐑑, 𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑛𐑲𐑨𐑜𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑮𐑴, 𐑕𐑦𐑥𐑩𐑤𐑑𐑱𐑯𐑾𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑶𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑞𐑺 𐑚𐑸𐑚𐑟; 𐑯 𐑛𐑸𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑞 𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑡𐑻𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑽, 𐑞𐑺 𐑔𐑮𐑰 ·𐑯𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑑 𐑲𐑼𐑯𐑟 𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑛 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤. 𐑚𐑤𐑲𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑝𐑱𐑐𐑼𐑟 𐑝 𐑓𐑴𐑥 𐑯 𐑢𐑲𐑑-𐑓𐑲𐑼! 𐑞 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕, 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑓𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑦 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤'𐑟 𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑮𐑳𐑖, 𐑚𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑡𐑻𐑥𐑩𐑯'𐑟 𐑩𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑓𐑹𐑕, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑚𐑴𐑔 ·𐑛𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑒 𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑨𐑓𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑽 𐑢𐑻 𐑕𐑐𐑦𐑤𐑛 𐑬𐑑, 𐑯 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑛 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑓𐑤𐑲𐑦𐑙 𐑒𐑰𐑤𐑟.

“𐑛𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑩𐑓𐑮𐑱𐑛, 𐑥𐑲 𐑚𐑳𐑑𐑼-𐑚𐑪𐑒𐑕𐑩𐑟,” 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚, 𐑒𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑐𐑭𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑜𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑕 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑨𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑖𐑪𐑑 𐑚𐑲; “𐑘𐑰'𐑤 𐑚𐑰 𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑑 𐑳𐑐 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦—𐑷𐑤 𐑮𐑲𐑑—𐑲 𐑕𐑷 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑖𐑸𐑒𐑕 𐑩𐑕𐑑𐑻𐑯—·𐑕𐑑 ·𐑚𐑻𐑯𐑸𐑛'𐑟 𐑛𐑪𐑜𐑟, 𐑿 𐑯𐑴—𐑮𐑦𐑤𐑰𐑝 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑼𐑟. 𐑣𐑼𐑭! 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑦𐑟 𐑞 𐑢𐑱 𐑑 𐑕𐑱𐑤 𐑯𐑬. 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑒𐑰𐑤 𐑩 𐑕𐑳𐑯𐑚𐑰𐑥! 𐑣𐑼𐑭!—𐑣𐑽 𐑢𐑰 𐑜𐑴 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑑𐑦𐑯 𐑒𐑧𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑑𐑱𐑤 𐑝 𐑩 𐑥𐑨𐑛 𐑒𐑵𐑜𐑼! 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑐𐑫𐑑𐑕 𐑥𐑰 𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑝 𐑓𐑭𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑩𐑯 𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑓𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑑𐑦𐑤𐑚𐑼𐑦 𐑪𐑯 𐑩 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑯—𐑥𐑱𐑒𐑕 𐑞 𐑢𐑰𐑤-𐑕𐑐𐑴𐑒𐑕 𐑓𐑤𐑲, 𐑚𐑶𐑟, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑿 𐑓𐑭𐑕𐑩𐑯 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑱; 𐑯 𐑞𐑺'𐑟 𐑛𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑼 𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑐𐑦𐑗𐑑 𐑬𐑑 𐑑𐑵, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑿 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑣𐑦𐑤. 𐑣𐑼𐑭! 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑦𐑟 𐑞 𐑢𐑱 𐑩 𐑓𐑧𐑤𐑴 𐑓𐑰𐑤𐑟 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑣𐑰'𐑟 𐑜𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑑 ·𐑛𐑱𐑝𐑦 ·𐑡𐑴𐑯𐑟—𐑷𐑤 𐑩 𐑮𐑳𐑖 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑩𐑯 𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑤𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑯! 𐑣𐑼𐑭! 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑒𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑟 𐑞 𐑧𐑝𐑼𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑱𐑤!”

𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞 𐑥𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑼'𐑟 𐑮𐑳𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩 𐑚𐑮𐑰𐑓 𐑢𐑳𐑯. 𐑜𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑕𐑳𐑛𐑩𐑯 𐑜𐑭𐑕𐑐, 𐑣𐑰 𐑑𐑿𐑥𐑳𐑤𐑗𐑵𐑩𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛. 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑮𐑳𐑖, 𐑞 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑤𐑲𐑯𐑟 𐑓𐑤𐑵 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑞 𐑤𐑪𐑜𐑼𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩 𐑓𐑹𐑕 𐑨𐑟 𐑑 𐑜𐑬𐑡 𐑛𐑰𐑐 𐑜𐑮𐑵𐑝𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑥; 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑕𐑴 𐑓𐑽𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑻 𐑞 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑽𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑮𐑨𐑐𐑦𐑛 𐑕𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑕𐑵𐑯 𐑦𐑜𐑟𐑷𐑕𐑑 𐑞 𐑤𐑲𐑯𐑟, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑿𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑺 𐑛𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑩𐑕 𐑥𐑲𐑑, 𐑞𐑱 𐑒𐑷𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑰𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑕𐑥𐑴𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑮𐑴𐑐 𐑑 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑪𐑯; 𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑—𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑞 𐑐𐑻𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑼 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑤𐑧𐑛-𐑤𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑗𐑪𐑒𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕, 𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑕 𐑞 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑮𐑴𐑐𐑕 𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑚𐑤𐑵—𐑞 𐑜𐑳𐑯𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑚𐑬𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼, 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑞 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑕𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑟 𐑑𐑦𐑤𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑣𐑲 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑺. 𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑕𐑵𐑯 𐑕𐑰𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑕𐑬𐑯𐑛, 𐑓 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑞𐑱 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑱𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑨𐑑𐑦𐑑𐑿𐑛, 𐑓𐑽𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑹 𐑤𐑲𐑯, 𐑞𐑴 𐑞 𐑐𐑩𐑟𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑖. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞𐑴 𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑯 𐑤𐑪𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑱, 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑞𐑦𐑕 “𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑪𐑯,” 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑛; 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑣𐑫𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑳𐑐 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑖𐑸𐑐 𐑚𐑸𐑚𐑟 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑤𐑲𐑝 𐑓𐑤𐑧𐑖 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑚𐑨𐑒; 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑪𐑓𐑩𐑯 𐑑𐑹𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑞 ·𐑤𐑩𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑔𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑕𐑵𐑯 𐑮𐑲𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯 𐑑 𐑥𐑰𐑑 𐑞 𐑖𐑸𐑐 𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑕 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑴𐑟. 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑑 𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑒 𐑝 𐑞 𐑐𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑤 𐑝 𐑞 𐑔𐑦𐑙, 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑛𐑬𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑒𐑹𐑕 𐑦𐑟 𐑷𐑤𐑢𐑱𐑟 𐑞 𐑚𐑧𐑕𐑑; 𐑓 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑮𐑰𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑿𐑥, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑤𐑪𐑙𐑜𐑼 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑟 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼, 𐑞 𐑥𐑹 𐑣𐑰 𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑜𐑟𐑷𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛. 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑪𐑟, 𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑹𐑥𐑩𐑕 𐑕𐑻𐑓𐑦𐑕 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑥—𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑓𐑫𐑤 𐑜𐑮𐑴𐑯 𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑤𐑧𐑕 𐑞𐑨𐑯 2000 𐑕𐑒𐑢𐑺 𐑓𐑰𐑑—𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑖𐑼 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼 𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑕. 𐑢𐑰 𐑷𐑤 𐑯𐑴 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑩𐑯 𐑩𐑕𐑑𐑪𐑯𐑦𐑖𐑦𐑙 𐑨𐑑𐑥𐑩𐑕𐑓𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑒 𐑢𐑱𐑑 𐑢𐑰 𐑬𐑼𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑝𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑳𐑐 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼; 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑣𐑽, 𐑩𐑚𐑳𐑝-𐑜𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛, 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑺; 𐑣𐑬 𐑝𐑭𐑕𐑑, 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑞 𐑚𐑻𐑛𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑩 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑚𐑺𐑦𐑙 𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑨𐑒 𐑩 𐑒𐑪𐑤𐑩𐑥 𐑝 𐑑𐑵 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑛 𐑓𐑨𐑞𐑩𐑥𐑟 𐑝 𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯! 𐑦𐑑 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑰𐑕𐑑 𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑩𐑤 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑑 𐑝 𐑓𐑦𐑓𐑑𐑦 𐑨𐑑𐑥𐑩𐑕𐑓𐑽𐑟. 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑥𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑑 𐑝 𐑑𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑦 𐑤𐑲𐑯-𐑝-𐑚𐑨𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑕, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑺 𐑜𐑳𐑯𐑟, 𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑹𐑟, 𐑯 𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑪𐑯 𐑚𐑹𐑛.

𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕 𐑤𐑱 𐑞𐑺 𐑪𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑴𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑰, 𐑜𐑱𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑦𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑚𐑤𐑵 𐑯𐑵𐑯; 𐑯 𐑨𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑩 𐑕𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑩𐑤 𐑜𐑮𐑴𐑯 𐑹 𐑒𐑮𐑲 𐑝 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑕𐑹𐑑, 𐑯𐑱, 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑴 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑨𐑟 𐑩 𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑩𐑤 𐑹 𐑩 𐑚𐑳𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑒𐑱𐑥 𐑳𐑐 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑛𐑧𐑐𐑔𐑕; 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑔𐑷𐑑, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑯𐑰𐑔 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑯 𐑐𐑤𐑩𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑦𐑑𐑦, 𐑞 𐑳𐑑𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑥𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑼 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑰𐑟 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑮𐑲𐑞𐑦𐑙 𐑯 𐑮𐑧𐑯𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑨𐑜𐑩𐑯𐑦! 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑱𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑗𐑩𐑟 𐑝 𐑐𐑻𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑼 𐑮𐑴𐑐 𐑢𐑻 𐑝𐑦𐑟𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑚𐑬𐑟. 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑒𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑔𐑦𐑯 𐑔𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑟 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 ·𐑤𐑩𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑔𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑩𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑞 𐑚𐑦𐑜 𐑢𐑱𐑑 𐑑 𐑩𐑯 𐑱𐑑 𐑛𐑱 𐑒𐑤𐑪𐑒. 𐑕𐑩𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛? 𐑯 𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑑? 𐑑 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑚𐑹𐑛. 𐑦𐑟 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑰𐑗𐑼 𐑝 𐑣𐑵𐑥 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑕 𐑕𐑴 𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑳𐑥𐑓𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑧𐑛—“𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑞𐑬 𐑓𐑦𐑤 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑒𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑚𐑸𐑚𐑛 𐑲𐑼𐑯𐑟? 𐑹 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑓𐑦𐑖-𐑕𐑐𐑽𐑟? 𐑞 𐑕𐑹𐑛 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑱𐑩𐑔 𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛, 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑽, 𐑞 𐑛𐑸𐑑, 𐑯𐑹 𐑞 𐑣𐑨𐑚𐑼𐑡𐑩𐑯: 𐑣𐑰 𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑰𐑥𐑩𐑔 𐑲𐑼𐑯 𐑨𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑷; 𐑞 𐑨𐑮𐑴 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑥𐑱𐑒 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑓𐑤𐑰; 𐑛𐑸𐑑𐑕 𐑸 𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑨𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚𐑩𐑤; 𐑣𐑰 𐑤𐑭𐑓𐑩𐑔 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑖𐑱𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑩 𐑕𐑐𐑽!” 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑰𐑗𐑼? 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑣𐑰? 𐑴! 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑳𐑯𐑓𐑫𐑤𐑓𐑦𐑤𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑓𐑪𐑤𐑴 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑓𐑩𐑑𐑕. 𐑓 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑧𐑙𐑔 𐑝 𐑩 𐑔𐑬𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑔𐑲𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑑𐑱𐑤, ·𐑤𐑩𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑔𐑩𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑮𐑳𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑞 𐑥𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑰, 𐑑 𐑣𐑲𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛'𐑟 𐑓𐑦𐑖-𐑕𐑐𐑽𐑟!

𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑤𐑴𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼𐑯𐑵𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑯𐑤𐑲𐑑, 𐑞 𐑖𐑨𐑛𐑴𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑚𐑦𐑯𐑰𐑔 𐑞 𐑕𐑻𐑓𐑦𐑕, 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑦𐑯𐑳𐑓 𐑯 𐑚𐑮𐑷𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑳𐑓 𐑑 𐑖𐑱𐑛 𐑣𐑭𐑓 ·𐑟𐑻𐑒𐑕𐑰𐑟' 𐑸𐑥𐑦. 𐑣𐑵 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑑𐑧𐑤 𐑣𐑬 𐑩𐑐𐑷𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑞 𐑢𐑵𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑣𐑿𐑡 𐑓𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑥𐑟 𐑓𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑧𐑛!

“𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑚𐑲, 𐑥𐑧𐑯; 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑑𐑻𐑟,” 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒, 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑤𐑲𐑯𐑟 𐑕𐑳𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑝𐑲𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼, 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑛𐑳𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑳𐑐𐑢𐑼𐑛𐑟 𐑑 𐑞𐑧𐑥, 𐑨𐑟 𐑚𐑲 𐑥𐑨𐑜𐑯𐑧𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑢𐑲𐑼𐑟, 𐑞 𐑤𐑲𐑓 𐑯 𐑛𐑧𐑔 𐑔𐑮𐑪𐑚𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑕𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑹𐑟𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑓𐑧𐑤𐑑 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑰𐑑. 𐑞 𐑯𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑 𐑥𐑴𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑, 𐑮𐑦𐑤𐑰𐑝𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑐𐑸𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑛𐑬𐑯𐑢𐑼𐑛 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑚𐑬𐑟, 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕 𐑜𐑱𐑝 𐑩 𐑕𐑳𐑛𐑩𐑯 𐑚𐑬𐑯𐑕 𐑳𐑐𐑢𐑼𐑛𐑟, 𐑨𐑟 𐑩 𐑕𐑥𐑷𐑤 𐑲𐑕𐑓𐑰𐑤𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑤, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑩 𐑛𐑧𐑯𐑕 𐑣𐑻𐑛 𐑝 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑚𐑺𐑟 𐑸 𐑕𐑒𐑺𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑕𐑰.

“𐑣𐑷𐑤 𐑦𐑯! 𐑣𐑷𐑤 𐑦𐑯!” 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯; “𐑣𐑰'𐑟 𐑮𐑲𐑟𐑦𐑙.”

𐑞 𐑤𐑲𐑯𐑟, 𐑝 𐑢𐑦𐑗, 𐑣𐑸𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹, 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛'𐑟 𐑚𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑔 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑛, 𐑢𐑻 𐑯𐑬 𐑦𐑯 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑒 𐑒𐑶𐑤𐑟 𐑓𐑤𐑳𐑙 𐑚𐑨𐑒 𐑷𐑤 𐑛𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕, 𐑯 𐑕𐑵𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑚𐑮𐑴𐑒 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑦𐑯 𐑑𐑵 𐑖𐑦𐑐'𐑕 𐑤𐑧𐑙𐑔𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑟.

𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑦𐑯𐑴𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑰𐑥 𐑦𐑜𐑟𐑷𐑕𐑗𐑩𐑯. 𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑥𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑞𐑺 𐑸 𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑝𐑨𐑤𐑝𐑟 𐑹 𐑓𐑤𐑳𐑛-𐑜𐑱𐑑𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑝 𐑞𐑺 𐑝𐑱𐑯𐑟, 𐑢𐑺𐑚𐑲 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑢𐑵𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛, 𐑞 𐑚𐑤𐑳𐑛 𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑛𐑦𐑜𐑮𐑰 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑰𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑖𐑳𐑑 𐑪𐑓 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑛𐑦𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟. 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑴 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤; 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑣𐑵𐑟 𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑦𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑲𐑼 𐑯𐑪𐑯-𐑝𐑨𐑤𐑝𐑿𐑤𐑼 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑒𐑗𐑼 𐑝 𐑞 𐑚𐑤𐑳𐑛-𐑝𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑤𐑟, 𐑕𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑐𐑽𐑕𐑑 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑚𐑲 𐑕𐑴 𐑕𐑥𐑷𐑤 𐑩 𐑐𐑶𐑯𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑩 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯, 𐑩 𐑛𐑧𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑮𐑱𐑯 𐑦𐑟 𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑕 𐑚𐑦𐑜𐑳𐑯 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑴𐑤 𐑸𐑑𐑽𐑾𐑤 𐑕𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑥; 𐑯 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑹𐑛𐑦𐑯𐑼𐑦 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑖𐑼 𐑝 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼 𐑨𐑑 𐑩 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑴 𐑞 𐑕𐑻𐑓𐑦𐑕, 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑤𐑲𐑓 𐑥𐑱 𐑚𐑰 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑑 𐑐𐑹 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑦𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑰𐑥𐑟. 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑕𐑴 𐑝𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑞 𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑝 𐑚𐑤𐑳𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑯 𐑕𐑴 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑯 𐑯𐑿𐑥𐑼𐑩𐑕 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑽𐑽 𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑟, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑒𐑰𐑐 𐑞𐑳𐑕 𐑚𐑤𐑰𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑯 𐑚𐑤𐑰𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑓 𐑩 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑼𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑐𐑽𐑾𐑛; 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑛𐑮𐑬𐑑 𐑩 𐑮𐑦𐑝𐑼 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑓𐑤𐑴, 𐑣𐑵𐑟 𐑕𐑹𐑕 𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑧𐑤-𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑝 𐑓𐑸-𐑪𐑓 𐑯 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑻𐑯𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑣𐑦𐑤𐑟. 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑯𐑬, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕 𐑐𐑫𐑤𐑛 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑯 𐑐𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑤𐑩𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑮𐑵 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑢𐑱𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑤𐑵𐑒𐑕, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑛𐑸𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑞𐑱 𐑢𐑻 𐑓𐑪𐑤𐑴𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑛𐑦 𐑡𐑧𐑑𐑕 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑯𐑿 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑢𐑵𐑯𐑛, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑒𐑧𐑐𐑑 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑿𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑦𐑙, 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑞 𐑯𐑨𐑗𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑐𐑬𐑑-𐑣𐑴𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑟, 𐑣𐑬𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑮𐑨𐑐𐑦𐑛, 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑩𐑓𐑮𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑥𐑶𐑕𐑗𐑼 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑺. 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑝𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑯𐑴 𐑚𐑤𐑳𐑛 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑒𐑱𐑥, 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑴 𐑝𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑐𐑸𐑑 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑞𐑳𐑕 𐑓𐑸 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑒. 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑤𐑲𐑓, 𐑨𐑟 𐑞𐑱 𐑕𐑦𐑜𐑯𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑷𐑤 𐑦𐑑, 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑳𐑯𐑑𐑳𐑗𐑑.

𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕 𐑯𐑬 𐑥𐑹 𐑒𐑤𐑴𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑼𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑞 𐑣𐑴𐑤 𐑳𐑐𐑼 𐑐𐑸𐑑 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑹𐑥, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑝 𐑦𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑹𐑛𐑦𐑯𐑺𐑦𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑥𐑻𐑡𐑛, 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑦𐑝𐑰𐑤𐑛. 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑲𐑟, 𐑹 𐑮𐑭𐑞𐑼 𐑞 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑢𐑺 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑲𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑰𐑯, 𐑢𐑻 𐑚𐑦𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑛. 𐑨𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡 𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑜𐑮𐑴𐑯 𐑥𐑨𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑜𐑨𐑞𐑼 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑯𐑪𐑑-𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑯𐑴𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑴𐑒𐑕 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑑, 𐑕𐑴 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑐𐑶𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤'𐑟 𐑲𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑕 𐑪𐑒𐑿𐑐𐑲𐑛, 𐑯𐑬 𐑐𐑮𐑴𐑑𐑮𐑵𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑤𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑚𐑳𐑤𐑚𐑟, 𐑣𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑦𐑑𐑾𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑑 𐑕𐑰. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑐𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑞𐑺 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑳𐑯. 𐑓 𐑷𐑤 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑱𐑡, 𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑸𐑥, 𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑤𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑲𐑟, 𐑣𐑰 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑛𐑲 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑔 𐑯 𐑚𐑰 𐑥𐑻𐑛𐑼𐑛, 𐑦𐑯 𐑹𐑛𐑼 𐑑 𐑤𐑲𐑑 𐑞 𐑜𐑱 𐑚𐑮𐑲𐑛𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑯 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑥𐑧𐑮𐑦-𐑥𐑱𐑒𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑝 𐑥𐑧𐑯, 𐑯 𐑷𐑤𐑕𐑴 𐑑 𐑦𐑤𐑵𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑱𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑪𐑤𐑩𐑥 𐑗𐑻𐑗𐑩𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑰𐑗 𐑳𐑯𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑓𐑧𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑝𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑚𐑲 𐑷𐑤 𐑑 𐑷𐑤. 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑮𐑴𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑤𐑳𐑛, 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑐𐑸𐑖𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑤𐑴𐑟𐑛 𐑩 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑳𐑤𐑼𐑛 𐑚𐑳𐑯𐑗 𐑹 𐑐𐑮𐑴𐑑𐑿𐑚𐑼𐑩𐑯𐑕, 𐑞 𐑕𐑲𐑟 𐑝 𐑩 𐑚𐑫𐑖𐑩𐑤, 𐑤𐑴 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑤𐑨𐑙𐑒.

“𐑩 𐑯𐑲𐑕 𐑕𐑐𐑪𐑑,” 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 ·𐑓𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑒; “𐑡𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑤𐑧𐑑 𐑥𐑰 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑒 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑞𐑺 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑕.”

“𐑩𐑝𐑭𐑕𐑑!” 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒, “𐑞𐑺'𐑟 𐑯𐑴 𐑯𐑰𐑛 𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑!”

𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑣𐑿𐑥𐑱𐑯 ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑑𐑵 𐑤𐑱𐑑. 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑛𐑸𐑑 𐑩𐑯 𐑳𐑤𐑕𐑼𐑩𐑕 𐑡𐑧𐑑 𐑖𐑪𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑒𐑮𐑵𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑵𐑯𐑛, 𐑯 𐑜𐑴𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑥𐑹 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑓𐑼𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑨𐑙𐑜𐑢𐑦𐑖, 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑯𐑬 𐑕𐑐𐑬𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑔𐑦𐑒 𐑚𐑤𐑳𐑛, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑕𐑢𐑦𐑓𐑑 𐑓𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑦 𐑚𐑤𐑲𐑯𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑸𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑭𐑓𐑑, 𐑚𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑨𐑑𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑜𐑤𐑹𐑦𐑦𐑙 𐑒𐑮𐑵𐑟 𐑷𐑤 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑖𐑬𐑼𐑟 𐑝 𐑜𐑹, 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑕𐑲𐑟𐑦𐑙 ·𐑓𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑒'𐑕 𐑚𐑴𐑑 𐑯 𐑥𐑸𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑚𐑬𐑟. 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑛𐑧𐑔 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑴𐑒. 𐑓, 𐑚𐑲 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑑𐑲𐑥, 𐑕𐑴 𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑚𐑲 𐑤𐑪𐑕 𐑝 𐑚𐑤𐑳𐑛, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑐𐑤𐑩𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑩𐑢𐑱 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑮𐑧𐑒 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑥𐑱𐑛; 𐑤𐑱 𐑐𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑲𐑛, 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑓𐑤𐑨𐑐𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑑 𐑓𐑦𐑯, 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑯 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑕𐑤𐑴𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑦𐑝𐑪𐑤𐑝𐑛 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑢𐑱𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛; 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑛 𐑳𐑐 𐑞 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑒𐑮𐑩𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑧𐑤𐑦; 𐑤𐑱 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑤𐑪𐑜, 𐑯 𐑛𐑲𐑛. 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑐𐑦𐑑𐑾𐑕, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑲𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑐𐑬𐑑. 𐑨𐑟 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑚𐑲 𐑳𐑯𐑕𐑰𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑞 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼 𐑦𐑟 𐑜𐑮𐑨𐑡𐑵𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑮𐑷𐑯 𐑪𐑓 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑥𐑲𐑑𐑦 𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑯, 𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑭𐑓-𐑕𐑑𐑲𐑓𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑥𐑧𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑒𐑪𐑤𐑦 𐑜𐑻𐑜𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑱-𐑒𐑪𐑤𐑩𐑥 𐑤𐑴𐑼𐑟 𐑯 𐑤𐑴𐑼𐑟 𐑑 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛—𐑕𐑴 𐑞 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑛𐑲𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑐𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤.

𐑕𐑵𐑯, 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑵𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑩𐑢𐑱𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑼𐑲𐑝𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐, 𐑞 𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦 𐑖𐑴𐑛 𐑕𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑑𐑩𐑥𐑟 𐑝 𐑕𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑷𐑤 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑑𐑮𐑧𐑠𐑼𐑟 𐑳𐑯𐑮𐑲𐑓𐑩𐑤𐑛. 𐑦𐑥𐑰𐑛𐑾𐑑𐑤𐑦, 𐑚𐑲 ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒'𐑕 𐑹𐑛𐑼𐑟, 𐑤𐑲𐑯𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑛 𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑓𐑼𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑐𐑶𐑯𐑑𐑕, 𐑕𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑺 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑚𐑴𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩 𐑚𐑶; 𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑙𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑩𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑩 𐑓𐑿 𐑦𐑯𐑗𐑩𐑟 𐑚𐑦𐑯𐑰𐑔 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑒𐑹𐑛𐑟. 𐑚𐑲 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑣𐑰𐑛𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑥𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑡𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑛𐑮𐑵 𐑯𐑲, 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑕𐑓𐑻𐑛 𐑑 𐑣𐑻 𐑕𐑲𐑛, 𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑪𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑛 𐑞𐑺 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑓𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑓𐑤𐑵𐑒-𐑗𐑱𐑯𐑟, 𐑓 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑧𐑕 𐑸𐑑𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑳𐑐𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑛, 𐑞 𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑕 𐑕𐑦𐑙𐑒 𐑑 𐑞 𐑚𐑪𐑑𐑩𐑥.

𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑴 𐑗𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑒𐑳𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑱𐑛, 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑲𐑼 𐑤𐑧𐑙𐑔 𐑝 𐑩 𐑒𐑼𐑴𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑥𐑚𐑧𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑤𐑧𐑖, 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑤𐑴𐑼 𐑐𐑸𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑚𐑳𐑯𐑗 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑚𐑛. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑕 𐑝 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑟 𐑸 𐑓𐑮𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑛 𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦𐑟 𐑝 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑗𐑼𐑛 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑓𐑤𐑧𐑖 𐑐𐑻𐑓𐑦𐑒𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑣𐑰𐑤𐑛 𐑼𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑞𐑧𐑥, 𐑯 𐑯𐑴 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑝 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑒𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑯𐑴𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕; 𐑞𐑺𐑓𐑹, 𐑞𐑺 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑯𐑰𐑛𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑳𐑯𐑯𐑴𐑯 𐑮𐑰𐑟𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑒𐑱𐑕 𐑓𐑫𐑤𐑦 𐑑 𐑩𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑 𐑓 𐑞 𐑳𐑤𐑕𐑼𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑩𐑤𐑵𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑑. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑥𐑹 𐑒𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑾𐑕 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞 𐑓𐑨𐑒𐑑 𐑝 𐑩 𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑕-𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑝 𐑕𐑑𐑴𐑯 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑓𐑸 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑚𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑛 𐑲𐑼𐑯, 𐑞 𐑓𐑤𐑧𐑖 𐑐𐑻𐑓𐑦𐑒𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑓𐑻𐑥 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑦𐑑. 𐑣𐑵 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑛𐑸𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑴𐑯 𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑕? 𐑯 𐑢𐑧𐑯? 𐑦𐑑 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑛𐑸𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑕𐑳𐑥 ·𐑯𐑹' ·𐑢𐑧𐑕𐑑 ·𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑾𐑯 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 ·𐑩𐑥𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑩 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑳𐑝𐑼𐑛.

𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑥𐑸𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑮𐑳𐑥𐑦𐑡𐑛 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑥𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑩𐑕 𐑒𐑨𐑚𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑴 𐑑𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑙. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑩 𐑕𐑳𐑛𐑩𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑪𐑐 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑐𐑫𐑑 𐑑 𐑓𐑻𐑞𐑼 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑳𐑝𐑼𐑦𐑟, 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐'𐑕 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑳𐑯𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑮𐑨𐑜𐑛 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑕𐑲𐑛𐑢𐑱𐑟 𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑰, 𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑞 𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦'𐑟 𐑦𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑮𐑰𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦 𐑑 𐑕𐑦𐑙𐑒. 𐑣𐑬𐑧𐑝𐑼, ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒, 𐑣𐑵 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑞 𐑹𐑛𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑩𐑓𐑺𐑟, 𐑣𐑳𐑙 𐑪𐑯 𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑑 𐑞 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑; 𐑣𐑳𐑙 𐑪𐑯 𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑴 𐑮𐑧𐑟𐑩𐑤𐑵𐑑𐑤𐑦, 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑰𐑛, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑧𐑙𐑔 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑕𐑲𐑟𐑛, 𐑦𐑓 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑐𐑼𐑕𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑤𐑪𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑸𐑥𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦; 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑞 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑭𐑯𐑛 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑜𐑦𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑑 𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑒 𐑒𐑤𐑽 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑦𐑑, 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞 𐑦𐑥𐑵𐑝𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑑𐑦𐑥𐑚𐑼-𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑟 𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑞 𐑓𐑤𐑵𐑒-𐑗𐑱𐑯𐑟 𐑯 𐑒𐑱𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑓𐑭𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑛, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑪𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑑 𐑒𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑪𐑓. 𐑥𐑰𐑯𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩𐑕𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑑. 𐑑 𐑒𐑮𐑪𐑕 𐑑 𐑞 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑝 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑒 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑢𐑷𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑳𐑐 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑰𐑐 𐑜𐑱𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑮𐑵𐑓 𐑝 𐑩 𐑣𐑬𐑕. 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑜𐑮𐑴𐑯𐑛 𐑯 𐑜𐑭𐑕𐑐𐑑. 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑝 𐑞 𐑲𐑝𐑼𐑦 𐑦𐑯𐑤𐑱𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑝 𐑣𐑻 𐑚𐑫𐑤𐑢𐑼𐑒𐑕 𐑯 𐑒𐑨𐑚𐑦𐑯𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞𐑺 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕𐑩𐑟, 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑳𐑯𐑯𐑨𐑗𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑤𐑴𐑒𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯. 𐑦𐑯 𐑝𐑱𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑕𐑐𐑲𐑒𐑕 𐑯 𐑒𐑮𐑴𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑚𐑮𐑷𐑑 𐑑 𐑚𐑺 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑦𐑥𐑵𐑝𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑓𐑤𐑵𐑒-𐑗𐑱𐑯𐑟, 𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑲 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑩𐑛𐑮𐑦𐑓𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑑𐑦𐑥𐑚𐑼𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑟; 𐑯 𐑕𐑴 𐑤𐑴 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑯𐑬 𐑕𐑧𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑥𐑻𐑡𐑛 𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑨𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑩𐑐𐑮𐑴𐑗𐑑, 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑥𐑴𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑣𐑴𐑤 𐑑𐑳𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑐𐑪𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑪𐑕𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑨𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑳𐑤𐑒, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑐𐑶𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑜𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑴𐑝𐑼.

“𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑪𐑯, 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑪𐑯, 𐑢𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑘𐑰?” 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚 𐑑 𐑞 𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦, “𐑛𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩 𐑛𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑩 𐑣𐑳𐑮𐑦 𐑑 𐑕𐑦𐑙𐑒! 𐑚𐑲 𐑔𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼, 𐑥𐑧𐑯, 𐑢𐑰 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑛𐑵 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑹 𐑜𐑴 𐑓 𐑦𐑑. 𐑯𐑴 𐑿𐑕 𐑐𐑮𐑲𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑺; 𐑩𐑝𐑭𐑕𐑑, 𐑲 𐑕𐑱 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑘𐑹 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑕𐑐𐑲𐑒𐑕, 𐑯 𐑮𐑳𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑘𐑰 𐑓 𐑩 𐑐𐑮𐑱𐑼 𐑚𐑫𐑒 𐑯 𐑩 𐑐𐑧𐑯-𐑯𐑲𐑓, 𐑯 𐑒𐑳𐑑 𐑞 𐑚𐑦𐑜 𐑗𐑱𐑯𐑟.”

“𐑯𐑲𐑓? 𐑲, 𐑲,” 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜, 𐑯 𐑕𐑰𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑒𐑸𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑼'𐑟 𐑣𐑧𐑝𐑦 𐑣𐑨𐑗𐑩𐑑, 𐑣𐑰 𐑤𐑰𐑯𐑛 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑩 𐑐𐑹𐑑𐑣𐑴𐑤, 𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑰𐑤 𐑑 𐑲𐑼𐑯, 𐑚𐑦𐑜𐑨𐑯 𐑕𐑤𐑨𐑖𐑦𐑙 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑤𐑸𐑡𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑓𐑤𐑵𐑒-𐑗𐑱𐑯𐑟. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑩 𐑓𐑿 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑴𐑒𐑕, 𐑓𐑫𐑤 𐑝 𐑕𐑐𐑸𐑒𐑕, 𐑢𐑻 𐑜𐑦𐑝𐑩𐑯, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑞 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑰𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯 𐑦𐑓𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑞 𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑑. 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑑𐑼𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑒 𐑕𐑯𐑨𐑐, 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑓𐑭𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑩𐑛𐑮𐑦𐑓𐑑; 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑮𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑛, 𐑞 𐑒𐑸𐑒𐑩𐑕 𐑕𐑨𐑙𐑒.

𐑯𐑬, 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑩𐑒𐑱𐑠𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑞 𐑮𐑰𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑦𐑤𐑛 ·𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑦𐑟 𐑩 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑒𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑾𐑕 𐑔𐑦𐑙; 𐑯𐑹 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑼𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑨𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑢𐑩𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑩𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑓 𐑦𐑑. 𐑿𐑠𐑵𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑛 ·𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑓𐑤𐑴𐑑𐑕 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑚𐑶𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑹 𐑚𐑧𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑼𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑝𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑩𐑚𐑳𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑻𐑓𐑦𐑕. 𐑦𐑓 𐑞 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑳𐑕 𐑕𐑨𐑙𐑒 𐑢𐑻 𐑴𐑤𐑛, 𐑥𐑰𐑜𐑼, 𐑯 𐑚𐑮𐑴𐑒𐑩𐑯-𐑣𐑸𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑒𐑮𐑰𐑗𐑼𐑟, 𐑞𐑺 𐑐𐑨𐑛𐑟 𐑝 𐑤𐑸𐑛 𐑛𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑖𐑑 𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑺 𐑚𐑴𐑯𐑟 𐑣𐑧𐑝𐑦 𐑯 𐑮𐑵𐑥𐑨𐑑𐑦𐑒; 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑿 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑮𐑰𐑟𐑩𐑯 𐑩𐑕𐑻𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑕𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑷𐑟𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑩𐑯 𐑳𐑯𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑕𐑐𐑩𐑕𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑒 𐑜𐑮𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑦𐑖 𐑕𐑴 𐑕𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑦𐑙, 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑢𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑨𐑚𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑝 𐑚𐑶𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑥𐑨𐑑𐑼 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑴. 𐑓 𐑘𐑳𐑙 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟, 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑣𐑲𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑔, 𐑯 𐑕𐑢𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑯𐑴𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑨𐑕𐑐𐑼𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟, 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑥𐑩𐑗𐑫𐑼𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑳𐑑 𐑪𐑓 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑹𐑥 𐑓𐑤𐑳𐑖 𐑯 𐑥𐑱 𐑝 𐑤𐑲𐑓, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑺 𐑐𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑤𐑸𐑛 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑞𐑧𐑥; 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑚𐑮𐑷𐑯𐑦, 𐑚𐑶𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑣𐑽𐑴𐑟 𐑛𐑵 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑕𐑦𐑙𐑒.

𐑚𐑰 𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑧𐑛, 𐑣𐑬𐑧𐑝𐑼, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑸 𐑤𐑧𐑕 𐑤𐑲𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑨𐑒𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑖𐑰𐑟. 𐑢𐑺 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑹𐑑 𐑜𐑴 𐑛𐑬𐑯, 𐑑𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑦 ·𐑮𐑲𐑑 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑛𐑵. 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑛𐑦𐑓𐑼𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑖𐑰𐑟 𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑴 𐑛𐑬𐑑 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑿𐑑𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑯𐑴 𐑕𐑥𐑷𐑤 𐑛𐑦𐑜𐑮𐑰 𐑑 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑𐑼 𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑝 𐑚𐑴𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑮𐑲𐑑 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤; 𐑣𐑦𐑟 ·𐑝𐑩𐑯𐑰𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑚𐑤𐑲𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑩𐑤𐑴𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑢𐑱𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑹 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑩 𐑑𐑳𐑯; 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑚𐑮𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑦 𐑓𐑮𐑰. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑸 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑢𐑺, 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑞 𐑤𐑨𐑐𐑕 𐑝 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑬𐑼𐑟 𐑹 𐑕𐑧𐑝𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑛𐑱𐑟, 𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑙𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯 𐑮𐑲𐑟𐑩𐑟, 𐑥𐑹 𐑚𐑶𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑤𐑲𐑓. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞 𐑮𐑰𐑟𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑦𐑟 𐑪𐑚𐑝𐑾𐑕. 𐑜𐑨𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑸 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑼𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥; 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑢𐑧𐑤𐑟 𐑑 𐑩 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑛𐑦𐑡𐑩𐑕 𐑥𐑨𐑜𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑿𐑛; 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑟 𐑩 𐑕𐑹𐑑 𐑝 𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑥𐑩𐑤 𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑵𐑯. 𐑩 𐑤𐑲𐑯-𐑝-𐑚𐑨𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑣𐑸𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑰𐑐 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑞𐑧𐑯. 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑖𐑹 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙, 𐑪𐑯 𐑕𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙𐑟, 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑞 ·𐑚𐑱𐑟 𐑝 ·𐑯𐑿 ·𐑟𐑰𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑩 ·𐑮𐑲𐑑 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑜𐑦𐑝𐑟 𐑑𐑴𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑕𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑦𐑙, 𐑞𐑱 𐑓𐑭𐑕𐑩𐑯 𐑚𐑶𐑟 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑐𐑤𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑦 𐑝 𐑮𐑴𐑐; 𐑕𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑜𐑪𐑯 𐑛𐑬𐑯, 𐑞𐑱 𐑯𐑴 𐑢𐑺 𐑑 𐑤𐑫𐑒 𐑓 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑦𐑑 𐑖𐑨𐑤 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑩𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯.

𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑞 𐑕𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑞 𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑩 𐑒𐑮𐑲 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑣𐑻𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛'𐑟 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑-𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑟, 𐑩𐑯𐑬𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑿𐑙𐑓𐑮𐑬 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯 𐑤𐑴𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑻 𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕; 𐑞𐑴 𐑞 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑐𐑬𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑲𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑝 𐑩 ·𐑓𐑦𐑯-𐑚𐑨𐑒, 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑪𐑙𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑖𐑰𐑟 𐑝 𐑳𐑯𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑗𐑼𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟, 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑪𐑟 𐑝 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑐𐑬𐑼 𐑝 𐑕𐑢𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑙. 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼𐑞𐑩𐑤𐑧𐑕, 𐑞 ·𐑓𐑦𐑯-𐑚𐑨𐑒'𐑕 𐑕𐑐𐑬𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑴 𐑕𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑤𐑼 𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤'𐑟, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑳𐑯𐑕𐑒𐑦𐑤𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑼𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑪𐑓𐑩𐑯 𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑓 𐑦𐑑. 𐑯 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑢𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 ·𐑛𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑒 𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑢𐑻 𐑯𐑬 𐑦𐑯 𐑝𐑨𐑤𐑾𐑯𐑑 𐑗𐑱𐑕 𐑝 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑳𐑯𐑯𐑽𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑚𐑮𐑵𐑑. 𐑞 ·𐑝𐑻𐑡𐑦𐑯 𐑒𐑮𐑬𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑷𐑤 𐑕𐑱𐑤, 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑣𐑻 𐑓𐑹 𐑘𐑳𐑙 𐑒𐑰𐑤𐑟, 𐑯 𐑞𐑳𐑕 𐑞𐑱 𐑷𐑤 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑩𐑐𐑽𐑛 𐑓𐑸 𐑑 𐑤𐑰𐑢𐑼𐑛, 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑚𐑴𐑤𐑛, 𐑣𐑴𐑐𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑗𐑱𐑕.

𐑴! 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑸 𐑞 ·𐑓𐑦𐑯-·𐑚𐑨𐑒𐑕, 𐑯 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑸 𐑞 ·𐑛𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑕, 𐑥𐑲 𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑯𐑛.

·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 82. 𐑞 ·𐑪𐑯𐑼 𐑯 ·𐑜𐑤𐑹𐑦 𐑝 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙.

𐑞𐑺 𐑸 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑐𐑮𐑲𐑟𐑩𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑩 𐑒𐑺𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑹𐑛𐑼𐑤𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑦𐑟 𐑞 𐑑𐑮𐑵 𐑥𐑧𐑔𐑩𐑛.

𐑞 𐑥𐑹 𐑲 𐑛𐑲𐑝 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑥𐑨𐑑𐑼 𐑝 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙, 𐑯 𐑐𐑫𐑖 𐑥𐑲 𐑮𐑰𐑕𐑻𐑗𐑩𐑟 𐑳𐑐 𐑑 𐑞 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑙-𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑝 𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑴 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑞 𐑥𐑹 𐑨𐑥 𐑲 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑪𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑯 𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑑𐑦; 𐑯 𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑲 𐑓𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑕𐑴 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑛𐑧𐑥𐑦-𐑜𐑪𐑛𐑟 𐑯 𐑣𐑽𐑴𐑟, 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑓𐑩𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑷𐑤 𐑕𐑹𐑑𐑕, 𐑣𐑵 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑢𐑱 𐑹 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑖𐑧𐑛 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑦𐑑, 𐑲 𐑨𐑥 𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑕𐑐𐑹𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑮𐑦𐑓𐑤𐑧𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑲 𐑥𐑲𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑪𐑙, 𐑞𐑴 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑹𐑛𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑑𐑤𐑦, 𐑑 𐑕𐑴 𐑦𐑥𐑚𐑤𐑱𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑩 𐑓𐑮𐑩𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑦.

𐑞 𐑜𐑨𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑑 ·𐑐𐑻𐑕𐑾𐑕, 𐑩 𐑕𐑳𐑯 𐑝 ·𐑡𐑵𐑐𐑦𐑑𐑼, 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑥𐑩𐑯; 𐑯 𐑑 𐑞 𐑦𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑪𐑯𐑼 𐑝 𐑬𐑼 𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑰 𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑧𐑛, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑩𐑑𐑨𐑒𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑬𐑼 𐑚𐑮𐑳𐑞𐑼𐑣𐑫𐑛 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑒𐑦𐑤𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑕𐑹𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑑. 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑞 𐑯𐑲𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑱𐑟 𐑝 𐑬𐑼 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑓𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑯, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑢𐑰 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑹 𐑸𐑥𐑟 𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑒𐑼 𐑞 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑑, 𐑯 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑑 𐑓𐑦𐑤 𐑥𐑧𐑯'𐑟 𐑤𐑨𐑥𐑐-𐑓𐑰𐑛𐑼𐑟. 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑯𐑴𐑟 𐑞 𐑓𐑲𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑹𐑦 𐑝 ·𐑐𐑻𐑕𐑾𐑕 𐑯 ·𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑮𐑪𐑥𐑦𐑛𐑩; 𐑣𐑬 𐑞 𐑤𐑳𐑝𐑤𐑦 ·𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑮𐑪𐑥𐑦𐑛𐑩, 𐑞 𐑛𐑷𐑑𐑼 𐑝 𐑩 𐑒𐑦𐑙, 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑑𐑲𐑛 𐑑 𐑩 𐑮𐑪𐑒 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑰-𐑒𐑴𐑕𐑑, 𐑯 𐑨𐑟 ·𐑤𐑩𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑔𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑨𐑒𐑑 𐑝 𐑒𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑻 𐑪𐑓, ·𐑐𐑻𐑕𐑾𐑕, 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑯𐑕 𐑝 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑥𐑧𐑯, 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑧𐑐𐑦𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑩𐑛𐑝𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑙, 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑛 𐑞 𐑥𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑼, 𐑯 𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑝𐑼𐑛 𐑯 𐑥𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑛 𐑞 𐑥𐑱𐑛. 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩𐑯 𐑨𐑛𐑥𐑼𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑸𐑑𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑤𐑶𐑑, 𐑮𐑺𐑤𐑦 𐑩𐑗𐑰𐑝𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑚𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑽𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑛𐑱; 𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑟𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑨𐑟 𐑞𐑦𐑕 ·𐑤𐑩𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑔𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑤𐑱𐑯 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑛𐑸𐑑. 𐑯 𐑤𐑧𐑑 𐑯𐑴 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑛𐑬𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 ·𐑸𐑒𐑲𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑹𐑦; 𐑓 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑱𐑯𐑗𐑩𐑯𐑑 ·𐑡𐑪𐑐𐑩, 𐑯𐑬 ·𐑡𐑨𐑓𐑩, 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑦𐑮𐑾𐑯 𐑒𐑴𐑕𐑑, 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑱𐑜𐑩𐑯 𐑑𐑧𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑤𐑟, 𐑞𐑺 𐑕𐑑𐑫𐑛 𐑓 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑱𐑡𐑩𐑟 𐑞 𐑝𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑒𐑧𐑤𐑩𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑩 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑞 𐑕𐑦𐑑𐑦'𐑟 𐑤𐑧𐑡𐑩𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑣𐑨𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑩𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑞 𐑲𐑛𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑚𐑴𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑥𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑼 𐑞𐑨𐑑 ·𐑐𐑻𐑕𐑾𐑕 𐑕𐑤𐑵. 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑮𐑴𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑑𐑫𐑒 ·𐑡𐑪𐑐𐑩, 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑕𐑒𐑧𐑤𐑩𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑒𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑛 𐑑 ·𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑯 𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑳𐑥𐑓. 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑟 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑿𐑤𐑼 𐑯 𐑕𐑩𐑡𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑝𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑹𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑕𐑑𐑹𐑦, 𐑦𐑟 𐑞𐑦𐑕: 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 ·𐑡𐑪𐑐𐑩 𐑞𐑨𐑑 ·𐑡𐑴𐑯𐑩 𐑕𐑧𐑑 𐑕𐑱𐑤.

𐑩𐑒𐑦𐑯 𐑑 𐑞 𐑩𐑛𐑝𐑧𐑯𐑗𐑼 𐑝 ·𐑐𐑻𐑕𐑾𐑕 𐑯 ·𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑮𐑪𐑥𐑦𐑛𐑩—𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑰𐑛, 𐑚𐑲 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑕𐑩𐑐𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑦𐑮𐑲𐑝𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑦𐑑—𐑦𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑓𐑱𐑥𐑩𐑕 𐑕𐑑𐑹𐑦 𐑝 ·𐑕𐑑 ·𐑡𐑹𐑡 𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑛𐑮𐑨𐑜𐑩𐑯; 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑛𐑮𐑨𐑜𐑩𐑯 𐑲 𐑥𐑱𐑯𐑑𐑱𐑯 𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑩 𐑢𐑱𐑤; 𐑓 𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑒𐑮𐑪𐑯𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑯 𐑛𐑮𐑨𐑜𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑸 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑤𐑦 𐑡𐑳𐑥𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑑𐑩𐑜𐑧𐑞𐑼, 𐑯 𐑪𐑓𐑩𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑓 𐑰𐑗 𐑳𐑞𐑼. “𐑞𐑬 𐑸𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑩 𐑤𐑲𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼𐑟, 𐑯 𐑨𐑟 𐑩 𐑛𐑮𐑨𐑜𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑰,” 𐑕𐑧𐑔 ·𐑦𐑟𐑰𐑒𐑾𐑤; 𐑣𐑽𐑚𐑲, 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑥𐑰𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑢𐑱𐑤; 𐑦𐑯 𐑑𐑮𐑵𐑔, 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑝𐑻𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑚𐑲𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑿𐑕 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑻𐑛 𐑦𐑑𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓. 𐑚𐑦𐑕𐑲𐑛𐑟, 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑒𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑜𐑤𐑹𐑦 𐑝 𐑞 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑤𐑶𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑛 ·𐑕𐑑 ·𐑡𐑹𐑡 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑛 𐑩 𐑒𐑮𐑷𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑮𐑧𐑐𐑑𐑲𐑤 𐑝 𐑞 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛, 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑛 𐑝 𐑛𐑵𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑨𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑥𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑼 𐑝 𐑞 𐑛𐑰𐑐. 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑥𐑱 𐑒𐑦𐑤 𐑩 𐑕𐑯𐑱𐑒, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑩 ·𐑐𐑻𐑕𐑾𐑕, 𐑩 ·𐑕𐑑 ·𐑡𐑹𐑡, 𐑩 ·𐑒𐑪𐑓𐑦𐑯, 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑞 𐑣𐑸𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑑 𐑥𐑸𐑗 𐑚𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑳𐑐 𐑑 𐑩 𐑢𐑱𐑤.

𐑤𐑧𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑞 𐑥𐑪𐑛𐑼𐑯 𐑐𐑱𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑝 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑕𐑰𐑯 𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑤𐑰𐑛 𐑳𐑕; 𐑓 𐑞𐑴 𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑰𐑗𐑼 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑝𐑨𐑤𐑾𐑯𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑦𐑟 𐑝𐑱𐑜𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑧𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑝 𐑩 𐑜𐑮𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑯-𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑖𐑱𐑐, 𐑯 𐑞𐑴 𐑞 𐑚𐑨𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑟 𐑛𐑦𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑪𐑯 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑯𐑑 𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑹𐑕𐑚𐑨𐑒, 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑦𐑜𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑝 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑞 𐑑𐑮𐑵 𐑓𐑹𐑥 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑳𐑯𐑯𐑴𐑯 𐑑 𐑸𐑑𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑕; 𐑯 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑯 ·𐑐𐑻𐑕𐑾𐑕' 𐑒𐑱𐑕, ·𐑕𐑑 ·𐑡𐑹𐑡'𐑩𐑟 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑒𐑮𐑷𐑤𐑛 𐑳𐑐 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑰 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑰𐑗; 𐑯 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑥𐑩𐑤 𐑮𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑯 𐑚𐑲 ·𐑕𐑑 ·𐑡𐑹𐑡 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑩 𐑤𐑸𐑡 𐑕𐑰𐑤, 𐑹 𐑕𐑰-𐑣𐑹𐑕; 𐑚𐑺𐑦𐑙 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑲𐑯𐑛, 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑩𐑐𐑽 𐑷𐑤𐑑𐑩𐑜𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑨𐑑𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑒𐑮𐑩𐑛 𐑤𐑧𐑡𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑯 𐑞 𐑱𐑯𐑗𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑛𐑮𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑰𐑯, 𐑑 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑕𐑴-𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑛 𐑛𐑮𐑨𐑜𐑩𐑯 𐑯𐑴 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 ·𐑤𐑩𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑔𐑩𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓. 𐑦𐑯 𐑓𐑨𐑒𐑑, 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑑 𐑯 𐑐𐑽𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑑𐑮𐑵𐑔, 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑣𐑴𐑤 𐑕𐑑𐑹𐑦 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑓𐑺 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑓𐑦𐑖, 𐑓𐑤𐑧𐑖, 𐑯 𐑓𐑬𐑤 𐑲𐑛𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑓𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑲𐑯𐑟, ·𐑛𐑨𐑜𐑩𐑯 𐑚𐑲 𐑯𐑱𐑥; 𐑣𐑵 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑐𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑞 𐑸𐑒 𐑝 ·𐑦𐑟𐑮𐑱𐑩𐑤, 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑹𐑕'𐑩𐑟 𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑯 𐑚𐑴𐑔 𐑞 𐑐𐑭𐑥𐑟 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑓𐑧𐑤 𐑪𐑓 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑯 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑥𐑐 𐑹 𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑦 𐑐𐑸𐑑 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑱𐑯𐑛. 𐑞𐑳𐑕, 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑬𐑼 𐑴𐑯 𐑯𐑴𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑥𐑐, 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑩 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑥𐑩𐑯, 𐑦𐑟 𐑞 𐑑𐑿𐑑𐑦𐑤𐑼𐑦 𐑜𐑸𐑛𐑾𐑯 𐑝 ·𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛; 𐑯 𐑚𐑲 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑮𐑲𐑑𐑕, 𐑢𐑰 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑽𐑟 𐑝 ·𐑯𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑑 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑚𐑰 𐑦𐑯𐑮𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑯𐑴𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑹𐑛𐑼 𐑝 ·𐑕𐑑 ·𐑡𐑹𐑡. 𐑯 𐑞𐑺𐑓𐑹, 𐑤𐑧𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑞 𐑯𐑲𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑪𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑦 (𐑯𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑣𐑵𐑥, 𐑲 𐑝𐑧𐑯𐑗𐑼 𐑑 𐑕𐑱, 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑑 𐑛𐑵 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑞𐑺 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑐𐑱𐑑𐑮𐑩𐑯), 𐑤𐑧𐑑 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑲 𐑩 ·𐑯𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑑𐑼 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑛𐑱𐑯, 𐑕𐑦𐑯𐑕 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑬𐑼 𐑢𐑫𐑤𐑩𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑒𐑕 𐑯 𐑑𐑸𐑛 𐑑𐑮𐑴𐑟𐑼𐑟 𐑢𐑰 𐑸 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑚𐑧𐑑𐑼 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑑 ·𐑕𐑑 ·𐑡𐑹𐑡'𐑩𐑟 𐑛𐑧𐑒𐑼𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑞𐑱.

𐑢𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑑 𐑩𐑛𐑥𐑦𐑑 ·𐑣𐑻𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑰𐑟 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑳𐑕 𐑹 𐑯𐑪𐑑, 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑲 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑱𐑯𐑛 𐑛𐑿𐑚𐑾𐑕: 𐑓 𐑞𐑴 𐑩𐑒𐑹𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑒 𐑥𐑦𐑔𐑪𐑤𐑩𐑡𐑦𐑟, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑰𐑒 ·𐑒𐑮𐑪𐑒𐑦𐑑 𐑯 ·𐑒𐑦𐑑 ·𐑒𐑸𐑕𐑩𐑯—𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑚𐑮𐑷𐑯𐑦 𐑛𐑵𐑼 𐑝 𐑮𐑦𐑡𐑶𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑛𐑰𐑛𐑟, 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑢𐑪𐑤𐑴𐑛 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑯 𐑔𐑮𐑴𐑯 𐑳𐑐 𐑚𐑲 𐑩 𐑢𐑱𐑤; 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤, 𐑢𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑥𐑱𐑒𐑕 𐑩 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑥𐑵𐑑𐑩𐑛. 𐑦𐑑 𐑯𐑴𐑢𐑺 𐑩𐑐𐑽𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑨𐑒𐑗𐑵𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑦𐑖, 𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑧𐑕, 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑰𐑛, 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑲𐑛. 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼𐑞𐑩𐑤𐑧𐑕, 𐑣𐑰 𐑥𐑱 𐑚𐑰 𐑛𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑩 𐑕𐑹𐑑 𐑝 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑪𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑦 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑥𐑩𐑯; 𐑨𐑑 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑒𐑷𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑦𐑓 𐑣𐑰 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤. 𐑲 𐑒𐑤𐑱𐑥 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑓 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑬𐑼 𐑒𐑤𐑨𐑯.

𐑚𐑳𐑑, 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑚𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑩𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑑𐑼𐑦 𐑷𐑔𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑟, 𐑞𐑦𐑕 ·𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑹𐑦 𐑝 ·𐑣𐑻𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑰𐑟 𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑼𐑛 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑛𐑦𐑮𐑲𐑝𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑥𐑹 𐑱𐑯𐑗𐑩𐑯𐑑 ·𐑣𐑰𐑚𐑮𐑵 𐑕𐑑𐑹𐑦 𐑝 ·𐑡𐑴𐑯𐑩 𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤; 𐑯 𐑝𐑲𐑕 𐑝𐑻𐑕𐑩; 𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑞𐑱 𐑸 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑕𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑤𐑼. 𐑦𐑓 𐑲 𐑒𐑤𐑱𐑥 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑥𐑦-𐑜𐑪𐑛 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑢𐑲 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑓𐑩𐑑?

𐑯𐑹 𐑛𐑵 𐑣𐑽𐑴𐑟, 𐑕𐑱𐑯𐑑𐑕, 𐑛𐑧𐑥𐑦𐑜𐑪𐑛𐑟, 𐑯 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑓𐑩𐑑𐑕 𐑩𐑤𐑴𐑯 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑮𐑲𐑟 𐑞 𐑣𐑴𐑤 𐑮𐑴𐑤 𐑝 𐑬𐑼 𐑹𐑛𐑼. 𐑬𐑼 𐑜𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑼 𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑯𐑱𐑥𐑛; 𐑓 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑮𐑶𐑩𐑤 𐑒𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑝 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟, 𐑢𐑰 𐑓𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑞 𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼𐑟 𐑝 𐑬𐑼 𐑓𐑮𐑩𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑦𐑯 𐑯𐑳𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑖𐑹𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑜𐑪𐑛𐑟 𐑞𐑧𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑝𐑟. 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑕 ·𐑹𐑦𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑑𐑹𐑦 𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑬 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑮𐑦𐑣𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 ·𐑖𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑼, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑜𐑦𐑝𐑟 𐑳𐑕 𐑞 𐑛𐑮𐑧𐑛 ·𐑝𐑦𐑖𐑯𐑵, 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑐𐑻𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑜𐑪𐑛𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑣𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑵𐑟; 𐑜𐑦𐑝𐑟 𐑳𐑕 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑛𐑦𐑝𐑲𐑯 ·𐑝𐑦𐑖𐑯𐑵 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑓 𐑬𐑼 ·𐑤𐑹𐑛;—·𐑝𐑦𐑖𐑯𐑵, 𐑣𐑵, 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑑𐑧𐑯 𐑻𐑔𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑸𐑯𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟, 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑓 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑕𐑧𐑑 𐑩𐑐𐑸𐑑 𐑯 𐑕𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑓𐑲𐑛 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤. 𐑢𐑧𐑯 ·𐑚𐑮𐑭𐑥𐑩, 𐑹 𐑞 ·𐑜𐑪𐑛 𐑝 ·𐑜𐑪𐑛𐑟, 𐑕𐑧𐑔 𐑞 ·𐑖𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑼, 𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑪𐑤𐑝𐑛 𐑑 𐑮𐑰𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑱𐑑 𐑞 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑐𐑽𐑦𐑪𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑩𐑤𐑵𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟, 𐑣𐑰 𐑜𐑱𐑝 𐑚𐑻𐑔 𐑑 ·𐑝𐑦𐑖𐑯𐑵, 𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑲𐑛 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑞 𐑢𐑻𐑒; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑝𐑧𐑛𐑩𐑟, 𐑹 𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑚𐑫𐑒𐑕, 𐑣𐑵𐑟 𐑐𐑼𐑵𐑟𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑕𐑰𐑥 𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑑 ·𐑝𐑦𐑖𐑯𐑵 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑚𐑦𐑜𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯, 𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑞𐑺𐑓𐑹 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑱𐑯𐑛 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑖𐑱𐑐 𐑝 𐑐𐑮𐑨𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑣𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑑 𐑘𐑳𐑙 𐑸𐑒𐑦𐑑𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑕, 𐑞𐑰𐑟 ·𐑝𐑧𐑛𐑩𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑤𐑲𐑦𐑙 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑚𐑪𐑑𐑩𐑥 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼𐑟; 𐑕𐑴 ·𐑝𐑦𐑖𐑯𐑵 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑱𐑥 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑸𐑯𐑩𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑯 𐑕𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑑 𐑞 𐑳𐑑𐑼𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑛𐑧𐑐𐑔𐑕, 𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑒𐑿𐑛 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑒𐑮𐑩𐑛 𐑝𐑪𐑤𐑿𐑥𐑟. 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 ·𐑝𐑦𐑖𐑯𐑵 𐑩 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑥𐑩𐑯, 𐑞𐑧𐑯? 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑨𐑟 𐑩 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑣𐑵 𐑮𐑲𐑛𐑟 𐑩 𐑣𐑹𐑕 𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑛 𐑩 𐑣𐑹𐑕𐑥𐑩𐑯?

𐑐𐑻𐑕𐑾𐑕, ·𐑕𐑑 ·𐑡𐑹𐑡, ·𐑣𐑻𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑰𐑟, ·𐑡𐑴𐑯𐑩, 𐑯 ·𐑝𐑦𐑖𐑯𐑵! 𐑞𐑺'𐑟 𐑩 𐑥𐑧𐑥𐑚𐑼-𐑮𐑴𐑤 𐑓 𐑿! 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑒𐑤𐑳𐑚 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑥𐑩𐑯'𐑟 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑪𐑓 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑞𐑨𐑑?

·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 83. ·𐑡𐑴𐑯𐑩 ·𐑣𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑦 ·𐑮𐑦𐑜𐑸𐑛𐑩𐑛.

𐑮𐑧𐑓𐑼𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑑 𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑑𐑹𐑦 𐑝 ·𐑡𐑴𐑯𐑩 𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑰𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼. 𐑯𐑬 𐑕𐑳𐑥 ·𐑯𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑑𐑼𐑟 𐑮𐑭𐑞𐑼 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑣𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑑𐑹𐑦 𐑝 ·𐑡𐑴𐑯𐑩 𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑢𐑻 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑕𐑒𐑧𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 ·𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑒𐑕 𐑯 ·𐑮𐑴𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑟, 𐑣𐑵, 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑬𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑹𐑔𐑩𐑛𐑪𐑒𐑕 𐑐𐑱𐑜𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑞𐑺 𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟, 𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑬𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑹𐑦 𐑝 ·𐑣𐑻𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑰𐑟 𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑯 ·𐑸𐑾𐑯 𐑯 𐑞 𐑛𐑪𐑤𐑓𐑦𐑯; 𐑯 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑛𐑬𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑑𐑮𐑩𐑛𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑥𐑱𐑒 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑑𐑮𐑩𐑛𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑑 𐑞 𐑤𐑧𐑕 𐑓𐑨𐑒𐑑𐑕, 𐑓 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑨𐑑.

𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑴𐑤𐑛 ·𐑕𐑨𐑜-·𐑣𐑸𐑚𐑼 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑥𐑩𐑯'𐑟 𐑗𐑰𐑓 𐑮𐑰𐑟𐑩𐑯 𐑓 𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑕𐑗𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑞 ·𐑣𐑰𐑚𐑮𐑵 𐑕𐑑𐑹𐑦 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞𐑦𐑕:—𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑒𐑢𐑱𐑯𐑑 𐑴𐑤𐑛-𐑓𐑨𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑛 ·𐑚𐑲𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑟, 𐑦𐑥𐑚𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑖𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑒𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑾𐑕, 𐑳𐑯𐑕𐑲𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑒 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑑𐑕; 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑮𐑧𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 ·𐑡𐑴𐑯𐑩'𐑟 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑑𐑵 𐑕𐑐𐑬𐑑𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑧𐑛—𐑩 𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑦𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑑𐑮𐑵 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑 𐑑 𐑩 𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑖𐑰𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑤𐑩𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑔𐑩𐑯 (𐑞 ·𐑮𐑲𐑑 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑝𐑼𐑲𐑩𐑑𐑦𐑟 𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑹𐑛𐑼), 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑞 𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑼𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑕𐑱𐑦𐑙, “𐑩 𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑮𐑴𐑤 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑗𐑴𐑒 𐑣𐑦𐑥”; 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑢𐑪𐑤𐑴 𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑴 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑕𐑥𐑷𐑤. 𐑚𐑳𐑑, 𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕, ·𐑚𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑐 ·𐑡𐑧𐑚'𐑟 𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑕𐑦𐑐𐑩𐑑𐑦𐑝 𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑼 𐑦𐑟 𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑦. 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑯𐑧𐑕𐑦𐑕𐑺𐑦, 𐑣𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑞 ·𐑚𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑐, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑰 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑼 ·𐑡𐑴𐑯𐑩 𐑨𐑟 𐑑𐑵𐑥𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤'𐑟 𐑚𐑧𐑤𐑦, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑑𐑧𐑥𐑐𐑼𐑺𐑦𐑤𐑦 𐑤𐑪𐑡𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑐𐑸𐑑 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑬𐑔. 𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑟 𐑮𐑰𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑯𐑳𐑓 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑜𐑫𐑛 ·𐑚𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑐. 𐑓 𐑑𐑮𐑵𐑤𐑦, 𐑞 ·𐑮𐑲𐑑 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤'𐑟 𐑥𐑬𐑔 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑩𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑛𐑱𐑑 𐑩 𐑒𐑳𐑐𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑢𐑦𐑕𐑑-𐑑𐑱𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑟, 𐑯 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑓𐑼𐑑𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑰𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑼𐑟. 𐑐𐑪𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑦, 𐑑𐑵, ·𐑡𐑴𐑯𐑩 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑣𐑪𐑤𐑴 𐑑𐑵𐑔; 𐑚𐑳𐑑, 𐑪𐑯 𐑕𐑧𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑔𐑷𐑑𐑕, 𐑞 ·𐑮𐑲𐑑 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑦𐑟 𐑑𐑵𐑔𐑤𐑩𐑕.

𐑩𐑯𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑮𐑰𐑟𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑗 ·𐑕𐑨𐑜-·𐑣𐑸𐑚𐑼 (𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑯𐑱𐑥) 𐑻𐑡𐑛 𐑓 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑪𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑓𐑱𐑔 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑥𐑨𐑑𐑼 𐑝 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑓𐑩𐑑, 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑚𐑕𐑒𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑯 𐑮𐑧𐑓𐑼𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑸𐑕𐑼𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦 𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤'𐑟 𐑜𐑨𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑒 𐑡𐑵𐑕𐑩𐑟. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑩𐑚𐑡𐑧𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑤𐑲𐑒𐑢𐑲𐑟 𐑓𐑷𐑤𐑟 𐑑 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛, 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑪𐑟 𐑩 ·𐑡𐑻𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑦𐑡𐑰𐑑𐑦𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑩𐑐𐑴𐑟𐑩𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 ·𐑡𐑴𐑯𐑩 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑮𐑧𐑓𐑿𐑡 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑤𐑴𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦 𐑝 𐑩 𐑛𐑧𐑛 𐑢𐑱𐑤—𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 ·𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑯𐑗 𐑕𐑴𐑤𐑡𐑼𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑮𐑳𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑒𐑨𐑥𐑐𐑱𐑯 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑛 𐑞𐑺 𐑛𐑧𐑛 𐑣𐑹𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑕, 𐑯 𐑒𐑮𐑷𐑤𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞𐑧𐑥. 𐑚𐑦𐑕𐑲𐑛𐑟, 𐑦𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑛𐑦𐑝𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑱𐑑𐑼𐑟, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑧𐑯 ·𐑡𐑴𐑯𐑩 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑔𐑮𐑴𐑯 𐑴𐑝𐑼𐑚𐑹𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 ·𐑡𐑪𐑐𐑩 𐑖𐑦𐑐, 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑑𐑢𐑱 𐑦𐑓𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑱𐑐 𐑑 𐑩𐑯𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑝𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑤 𐑯𐑽 𐑚𐑲, 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑝𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑓 𐑩 𐑓𐑦𐑜𐑼-𐑣𐑧𐑛; 𐑯, 𐑲 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑨𐑛, 𐑐𐑪𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑛 “𐑞 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤,” 𐑨𐑟 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑒𐑮𐑭𐑓𐑑 𐑸 𐑯𐑬𐑩𐑛𐑱𐑟 𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑞 “𐑖𐑸𐑒,” 𐑞 “𐑜𐑳𐑤,” 𐑞 “𐑰𐑜𐑩𐑤.” 𐑯𐑹 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑞𐑺 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑤𐑻𐑯𐑛 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑦𐑡𐑰𐑑𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑕 𐑣𐑵 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑩𐑐𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑫𐑒 𐑝 ·𐑡𐑴𐑯𐑩 𐑥𐑽𐑤𐑦 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑩 𐑤𐑲𐑓-𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑻𐑝𐑼—𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑓𐑤𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑨𐑜 𐑝 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛—𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑼𐑛 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑓𐑩𐑑 𐑕𐑢𐑨𐑥 𐑑, 𐑯 𐑕𐑴 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑱𐑝𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑩 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼𐑦 𐑛𐑵𐑥. 𐑐𐑫𐑼 ·𐑕𐑨𐑜-·𐑣𐑸𐑚𐑼, 𐑞𐑺𐑓𐑹, 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑟 𐑢𐑫𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑷𐑤 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑩𐑯𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑮𐑰𐑟𐑩𐑯 𐑓 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑪𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑓𐑱𐑔. 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞𐑦𐑕, 𐑦𐑓 𐑲 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑧𐑥𐑚𐑼 𐑮𐑲𐑑: ·𐑡𐑴𐑯𐑩 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑢𐑪𐑤𐑴𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑥𐑧𐑛𐑦𐑑𐑼𐑱𐑯𐑾𐑯 ·𐑕𐑰, 𐑯 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑛𐑱𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑝𐑪𐑥𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑳𐑐 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑢𐑺 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑦𐑯 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑛𐑱𐑟' 𐑡𐑻𐑯𐑦 𐑝 ·𐑯𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑝𐑩, 𐑩 𐑕𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑑𐑲𐑜𐑮𐑦𐑕, 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑥𐑹 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑛𐑱𐑟' 𐑡𐑻𐑯𐑦 𐑩𐑒𐑮𐑪𐑕 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑯𐑽𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑐𐑶𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑥𐑧𐑛𐑦𐑑𐑼𐑱𐑯𐑾𐑯 𐑒𐑴𐑕𐑑. 𐑣𐑬 𐑦𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑?

𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞𐑺 𐑯𐑴 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑢𐑱 𐑓 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑑 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑓𐑩𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑖𐑹𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑝 ·𐑯𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑝𐑩? 𐑘𐑧𐑕. 𐑣𐑰 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑒𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑢𐑱 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑒𐑱𐑐 𐑝 𐑜𐑫𐑛 ·𐑣𐑴𐑐. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑑 𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑒 𐑝 𐑞 𐑐𐑨𐑕𐑦𐑡 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑞 𐑣𐑴𐑤 𐑤𐑧𐑙𐑔 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑥𐑧𐑛𐑦𐑑𐑼𐑱𐑯𐑾𐑯, 𐑯 𐑩𐑯𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑐𐑨𐑕𐑦𐑡 𐑳𐑐 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑻𐑖𐑩𐑯 ·𐑜𐑳𐑤𐑓 𐑯 ·𐑮𐑧𐑛 ·𐑕𐑰, 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩 𐑕𐑳𐑐𐑩𐑟𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑪𐑤𐑝 𐑞 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑰𐑑 𐑕𐑻𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑯𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑜𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑷𐑤 ·𐑨𐑓𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑩 𐑦𐑯 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑛𐑱𐑟, 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑑 𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑒 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑑𐑲𐑜𐑮𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼𐑟, 𐑯𐑽 𐑞 𐑕𐑲𐑑 𐑝 ·𐑯𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑝𐑩, 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑑𐑵 𐑖𐑨𐑤𐑴 𐑓 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑑 𐑕𐑢𐑦𐑥 𐑦𐑯. 𐑚𐑦𐑕𐑲𐑛𐑟, 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑲𐑛𐑾 𐑝 ·𐑡𐑴𐑯𐑩'𐑟 𐑢𐑧𐑞𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑞 ·𐑒𐑱𐑐 𐑝 𐑜𐑫𐑛 ·𐑣𐑴𐑐 𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑴 𐑻𐑤𐑦 𐑩 𐑛𐑱 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑞 𐑪𐑯𐑼 𐑝 𐑞 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑳𐑝𐑼𐑦 𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 ·𐑚𐑸𐑔𐑪𐑤𐑩𐑥𐑿 ·𐑛𐑾𐑟, 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑿𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑳𐑝𐑼𐑼, 𐑯 𐑕𐑴 𐑥𐑱𐑒 𐑥𐑪𐑛𐑼𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑦 𐑩 𐑤𐑲𐑼.

𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑓𐑵𐑤𐑦𐑖 𐑸𐑜𐑿𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑴𐑤𐑛 ·𐑕𐑨𐑜-·𐑣𐑸𐑚𐑼 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑵𐑤𐑦𐑖 𐑐𐑮𐑲𐑛 𐑝 𐑮𐑰𐑟𐑩𐑯—𐑩 𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑥𐑹 𐑮𐑧𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑣𐑧𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑕𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑤𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑧𐑐𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑑 𐑳𐑐 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑯 𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑰. 𐑲 𐑕𐑱 𐑦𐑑 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑖𐑴𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑵𐑤𐑦𐑖, 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑲𐑩𐑕 𐑐𐑮𐑲𐑛, 𐑯 𐑩𐑚𐑪𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤, 𐑛𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑖 𐑮𐑦𐑚𐑧𐑤𐑘𐑩𐑯 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑞 𐑮𐑧𐑝𐑼𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑒𐑤𐑻𐑡𐑦. 𐑓 𐑚𐑲 𐑩 ·𐑐𐑹𐑗𐑩𐑜𐑰𐑟 ·𐑒𐑨𐑔𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑒 𐑐𐑮𐑰𐑕𐑑, 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑲𐑛𐑾 𐑝 ·𐑡𐑴𐑯𐑩'𐑟 𐑜𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑑 ·𐑯𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑝𐑩 𐑝𐑲𐑩 𐑞 ·𐑒𐑱𐑐 𐑝 𐑜𐑫𐑛 ·𐑣𐑴𐑐 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩𐑛𐑝𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑩 𐑕𐑦𐑜𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑥𐑨𐑜𐑯𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑒𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑥𐑦𐑮𐑩𐑒𐑩𐑤. 𐑯 𐑕𐑴 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟. 𐑚𐑦𐑕𐑲𐑛𐑟, 𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑛𐑱, 𐑞 𐑣𐑲𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑯𐑤𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑛 ·𐑑𐑻𐑒𐑕 𐑛𐑦𐑝𐑬𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑰𐑝 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑑𐑹𐑦 𐑝 ·𐑡𐑴𐑯𐑩. 𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑗𐑼𐑦𐑟 𐑩𐑜𐑴, 𐑩𐑯 ·𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑤𐑦𐑖 𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑼 𐑦𐑯 𐑴𐑤𐑛 ·𐑣𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑕'𐑩𐑟 ·𐑝𐑶𐑦𐑡𐑩𐑟, 𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑕 𐑝 𐑩 ·𐑑𐑻𐑒𐑦𐑖 ·𐑥𐑪𐑕𐑒 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑪𐑯𐑼 𐑝 ·𐑡𐑴𐑯𐑩, 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑗 ·𐑥𐑪𐑕𐑒 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩 𐑥𐑦𐑮𐑨𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑤𐑨𐑥𐑐 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑚𐑻𐑯𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑶𐑤.

·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 84. 𐑐𐑦𐑗𐑐𐑴𐑤𐑦𐑙.

𐑑 𐑥𐑱𐑒 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑮𐑳𐑯 𐑰𐑟𐑦𐑤𐑦 𐑯 𐑕𐑢𐑦𐑓𐑑𐑤𐑦, 𐑞 𐑨𐑒𐑕𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑝 𐑒𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑡𐑩𐑟 𐑸 𐑩𐑯𐑶𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛; 𐑯 𐑓 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑐𐑻𐑐𐑩𐑕, 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑼𐑟 𐑐𐑼𐑓𐑹𐑥 𐑩𐑯 𐑩𐑯𐑨𐑤𐑩𐑜𐑩𐑕 𐑪𐑐𐑼𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑚𐑴𐑑; 𐑞𐑱 𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑕 𐑞 𐑚𐑪𐑑𐑩𐑥. 𐑯𐑹 𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑛𐑬𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩 𐑐𐑮𐑴𐑕𐑰𐑡𐑼 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑛𐑵 𐑯𐑴 𐑣𐑸𐑥, 𐑦𐑑 𐑥𐑱 𐑐𐑪𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑰 𐑝 𐑯𐑴 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑥𐑐𐑑𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑩𐑛𐑝𐑭𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑡; 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑶𐑤 𐑯 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼 𐑸 𐑣𐑪𐑕𐑑𐑲𐑤; 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑶𐑤 𐑦𐑟 𐑩 𐑕𐑤𐑲𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑔𐑦𐑙, 𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑪𐑚𐑡𐑧𐑒𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑝𐑿 𐑦𐑟 𐑑 𐑥𐑱𐑒 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑 𐑕𐑤𐑲𐑛 𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑝𐑤𐑦. ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑰𐑝𐑛 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑪𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑯 𐑩𐑯𐑶𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑴𐑑, 𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑥𐑹𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑞 ·𐑡𐑻𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑖𐑦𐑐 ·𐑿𐑙𐑓𐑮𐑬 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑩𐑐𐑽𐑛, 𐑑𐑫𐑒 𐑥𐑹 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑒𐑳𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑥𐑼𐑦 𐑐𐑱𐑯𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑪𐑒𐑿𐑐𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯; 𐑒𐑮𐑷𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑚𐑪𐑑𐑩𐑥, 𐑢𐑺 𐑦𐑑 𐑣𐑳𐑙 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑞 𐑕𐑲𐑛, 𐑯 𐑮𐑳𐑚𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑳𐑙𐑒𐑗𐑵𐑩𐑕𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑨𐑟 𐑞𐑴 𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑡𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑰𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑖𐑫𐑼 𐑩 𐑒𐑮𐑪𐑐 𐑝 𐑣𐑺 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑭𐑓𐑑'𐑕 𐑚𐑷𐑤𐑛 𐑒𐑰𐑤. 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑢𐑻𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑴𐑚𐑰𐑛𐑾𐑯𐑕 𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑐𐑼𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑼 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑. 𐑯𐑹 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑦𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑱𐑯 𐑳𐑯𐑢𐑪𐑮𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑦𐑝𐑧𐑯𐑑.

𐑑𐑩𐑢𐑹𐑛𐑟 𐑯𐑵𐑯 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑮𐑱𐑟𐑛; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑕𐑴 𐑕𐑵𐑯 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑛 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑑 𐑞𐑧𐑥, 𐑞𐑱 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑛 𐑯 𐑓𐑤𐑧𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑕𐑢𐑦𐑓𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑦𐑐𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦; 𐑩 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑹𐑛𐑼𐑛 𐑓𐑤𐑲𐑑, 𐑨𐑟 𐑝 ·𐑒𐑤𐑦𐑴𐑐𐑨𐑑𐑮𐑩'𐑟 𐑚𐑸𐑡𐑩𐑟 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 ·𐑨𐑒𐑑𐑾𐑥.

𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼𐑞𐑩𐑤𐑧𐑕, 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕 𐑐𐑼𐑕𐑿𐑛, 𐑯 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚'𐑟 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑓𐑹𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑. 𐑚𐑲 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑦𐑜𐑟𐑻𐑖𐑩𐑯, ·𐑑𐑨𐑖𐑑𐑱𐑜𐑴 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑩𐑒𐑕𐑰𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑐𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑲𐑼𐑯; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑕𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙, 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑿𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑓𐑤𐑲𐑑, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑨𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑓𐑤𐑰𐑑𐑯𐑩𐑕. 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑳𐑯𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑥𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑐𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑲𐑼𐑯 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑵𐑯𐑼 𐑹 𐑤𐑱𐑑𐑼 𐑦𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑒𐑑 𐑦𐑑. 𐑦𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑱𐑥 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑧𐑮𐑩𐑑𐑦𐑝 𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑕 𐑞 𐑓𐑤𐑲𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑹 𐑚𐑰 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑑 𐑤𐑵𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑥. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑑 𐑣𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑 𐑳𐑐 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑤𐑨𐑙𐑒 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑪𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤, 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑢𐑨𐑥 𐑕𐑴 𐑓𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑯 𐑓𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑾𐑕. 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑱𐑯𐑛?

𐑝 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑕 𐑛𐑦𐑝𐑲𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑯 𐑛𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑟, 𐑞 𐑕𐑤𐑲𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑯 𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑕𐑳𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑑𐑦𐑟, 𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑞 𐑝𐑧𐑑𐑼𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑴 𐑪𐑓𐑩𐑯 𐑓𐑹𐑕𐑑, 𐑯𐑳𐑯 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑰𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑓𐑲𐑯 𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑵𐑝𐑼 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑕 𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑛 𐑐𐑦𐑗𐑐𐑴𐑤𐑦𐑙. 𐑕𐑥𐑷𐑤 𐑕𐑹𐑛, 𐑹 𐑚𐑮𐑷𐑛 𐑕𐑹𐑛, 𐑦𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑼𐑕𐑲𐑟𐑩𐑟 𐑚𐑴𐑕𐑑𐑕 𐑯𐑳𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑦𐑑. 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑧𐑑𐑼𐑩𐑑 𐑮𐑳𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑱𐑤; 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑜𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑓𐑨𐑒𐑑 𐑯 𐑓𐑰𐑗𐑼 𐑦𐑟 𐑞 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑞 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑕 𐑦𐑟 𐑨𐑒𐑘𐑼𐑩𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑸𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑩 𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑪𐑒𐑦𐑙, 𐑡𐑻𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑴𐑑, 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑰𐑥 𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑢𐑱. 𐑕𐑑𐑰𐑤 𐑯 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑤𐑵𐑛𐑩𐑛, 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑲𐑼 𐑕𐑐𐑽 𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑑𐑧𐑯 𐑹 𐑑𐑢𐑧𐑤𐑝 𐑓𐑰𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑤𐑧𐑙𐑔; 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑭𐑓 𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑕𐑤𐑲𐑑𐑼 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯, 𐑯 𐑷𐑤𐑕𐑴 𐑝 𐑩 𐑤𐑲𐑑𐑼 𐑥𐑩𐑑𐑽𐑾𐑤—𐑐𐑲𐑯. 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑖𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑕𐑥𐑷𐑤 𐑮𐑴𐑐 𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑛 𐑩 𐑢𐑹𐑐, 𐑝 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑼𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑤𐑧𐑙𐑔, 𐑚𐑲 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑦𐑑 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑚𐑰 𐑣𐑷𐑤𐑛 𐑚𐑨𐑒 𐑑 𐑞 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑛𐑸𐑑𐑦𐑙.

𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑜𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑻𐑞𐑼, 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑹𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑑 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑣𐑽, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑴 𐑞 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯 𐑥𐑱 𐑚𐑰 𐑐𐑦𐑗𐑐𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑢𐑱 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑕, 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑛𐑩𐑥 𐑛𐑳𐑯; 𐑯 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑛𐑳𐑯, 𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑤𐑧𐑕 𐑓𐑮𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑩𐑒𐑕𐑧𐑕𐑓𐑩𐑤, 𐑪𐑯 𐑩𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑𐑼 𐑢𐑱𐑑 𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑓𐑽𐑽 𐑤𐑧𐑙𐑔 𐑝 𐑞 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯 𐑨𐑟 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑺𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑕, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑦𐑯 𐑦𐑓𐑧𐑒𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑕𐑽𐑾𐑕 𐑛𐑮𐑷𐑚𐑨𐑒𐑕. 𐑨𐑟 𐑩 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑔𐑦𐑙, 𐑞𐑺𐑓𐑹, 𐑿 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑜𐑧𐑑 𐑓𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑑 𐑩 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑐𐑦𐑗𐑐𐑴𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑐𐑤𐑱.

𐑤𐑫𐑒 𐑯𐑬 𐑨𐑑 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚; 𐑩 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑣𐑵 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑿𐑥𐑼𐑩𐑕, 𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑚𐑼𐑩𐑑 𐑒𐑵𐑤𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑯 𐑧𐑒𐑢𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑛𐑲𐑼𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑥𐑻𐑡𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑟, 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑤𐑦𐑓𐑲𐑛 𐑑 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑧𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑐𐑦𐑗𐑐𐑴𐑤𐑦𐑙. 𐑤𐑫𐑒 𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥; 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑳𐑐𐑮𐑲𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑑𐑪𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑬 𐑝 𐑞 𐑓𐑤𐑲𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑴𐑑; 𐑮𐑨𐑐𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑓𐑤𐑰𐑕𐑦 𐑓𐑴𐑥, 𐑞 𐑑𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑹𐑑𐑦 𐑓𐑰𐑑 𐑩𐑣𐑧𐑛. 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑕 𐑤𐑲𐑑𐑤𐑦, 𐑜𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑑𐑢𐑲𐑕 𐑹 𐑔𐑮𐑲𐑕 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑤𐑧𐑙𐑔 𐑑 𐑕𐑰 𐑦𐑓 𐑦𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑦𐑜𐑟𐑨𐑒𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑑, ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚 𐑢𐑦𐑕𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑜𐑨𐑞𐑼𐑟 𐑳𐑐 𐑞 𐑒𐑶𐑤 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑹𐑐 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛, 𐑕𐑴 𐑨𐑟 𐑑 𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑘𐑫𐑼 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑓𐑮𐑰 𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑜𐑮𐑭𐑕𐑐, 𐑤𐑰𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑳𐑯𐑩𐑚𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑛. 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑕 𐑓𐑫𐑤 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑱𐑕𐑑𐑚𐑨𐑯𐑛'𐑟 𐑥𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑤, 𐑣𐑰 𐑤𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤; 𐑢𐑧𐑯, 𐑒𐑳𐑝𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑦𐑑, 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑦𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑞 𐑚𐑳𐑑-𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛, 𐑞𐑺𐑚𐑲 𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑝𐑱𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑐𐑶𐑯𐑑 𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑞 𐑢𐑧𐑐𐑩𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑓𐑺𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑨𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑭𐑥, 𐑓𐑦𐑓𐑑𐑰𐑯 𐑓𐑰𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑺. 𐑣𐑰 𐑥𐑲𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑿 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑝 𐑩 𐑡𐑳𐑜𐑩𐑤𐑼, 𐑚𐑨𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑕𐑑𐑭𐑓 𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑗𐑦𐑯. 𐑯𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑 𐑥𐑴𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑮𐑨𐑐𐑦𐑛, 𐑯𐑱𐑥𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑳𐑤𐑕, 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑕𐑵𐑐𐑻𐑚 𐑤𐑪𐑓𐑑𐑦 𐑸𐑗 𐑞 𐑚𐑮𐑲𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑰𐑤 𐑕𐑐𐑨𐑯𐑟 𐑞 𐑓𐑴𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕, 𐑯 𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑝𐑼𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑤𐑲𐑓 𐑕𐑐𐑪𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤. 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑛 𐑝 𐑕𐑐𐑸𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼, 𐑣𐑰 𐑯𐑬 𐑕𐑐𐑬𐑑𐑕 𐑮𐑧𐑛 𐑚𐑤𐑳𐑛.

“𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑛𐑮𐑴𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑦𐑜𐑩𐑑 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑥!” 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚. “'𐑑𐑦𐑟 𐑡𐑩𐑤𐑲'𐑟 𐑦𐑥𐑹𐑑𐑩𐑤 ·𐑓𐑹𐑔; 𐑷𐑤 𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑮𐑳𐑯 𐑢𐑲𐑯 𐑑𐑩𐑛𐑱! 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑯𐑬, 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑻 𐑴𐑤𐑛 ·𐑹𐑤𐑰𐑯𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑦, 𐑹 𐑴𐑤𐑛 ·𐑴𐑣𐑲𐑴, 𐑹 𐑳𐑯𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑴𐑤𐑛 ·𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑪𐑙𐑜𐑭𐑰𐑤𐑩! 𐑞𐑧𐑯, ·𐑑𐑨𐑖𐑑𐑱𐑜𐑴, 𐑤𐑨𐑛, 𐑲'𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑘𐑰 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑩 𐑒𐑱𐑯𐑩𐑒𐑦𐑯 𐑑 𐑞 𐑡𐑧𐑑, 𐑯 𐑢𐑰'𐑛 𐑛𐑮𐑦𐑙𐑒 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑑! 𐑘𐑱, 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑤𐑦, 𐑣𐑸𐑑𐑕 𐑩𐑤𐑲𐑝, 𐑢𐑰'𐑛 𐑚𐑮𐑵 𐑗𐑶𐑕 𐑐𐑳𐑯𐑗 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑛 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑐𐑬𐑑-𐑣𐑴𐑤 𐑞𐑺, 𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑲𐑝 𐑐𐑳𐑯𐑗-𐑚𐑴𐑤 𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑓 𐑞 𐑤𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑓.”

𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯 𐑯 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯 𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑜𐑱𐑥𐑕𐑩𐑥 𐑑𐑷𐑒, 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑩𐑕 𐑛𐑸𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑰𐑑𐑩𐑛, 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑽 𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑼 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑣𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑒𐑦𐑤𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑤𐑰𐑖. 𐑞 𐑨𐑜𐑩𐑯𐑲𐑟𐑛 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑜𐑴𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑤𐑳𐑮𐑦; 𐑞 𐑑𐑴-𐑤𐑲𐑯 𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑤𐑨𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑛, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑐𐑦𐑗𐑐𐑴𐑤𐑼 𐑛𐑮𐑪𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑕𐑑𐑻𐑯, 𐑓𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟, 𐑯 𐑥𐑿𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑢𐑪𐑗𐑩𐑟 𐑞 𐑥𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑼 𐑛𐑲.

·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 85. 𐑞 ·𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑯.

𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑓 𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑕 𐑔𐑬𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑘𐑽𐑟—𐑯 𐑯𐑴 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑯𐑴𐑟 𐑣𐑬 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑥𐑦𐑤𐑾𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑱𐑡𐑩𐑟 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹—𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑕𐑐𐑬𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑷𐑤 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑞 𐑕𐑰, 𐑯 𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑯 𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑓𐑲𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑜𐑸𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑛𐑰𐑐, 𐑨𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑕𐑴 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑹 𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑓𐑲𐑦𐑙 𐑐𐑪𐑑𐑕; 𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑓 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑗𐑼𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑨𐑒, 𐑔𐑬𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑝 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑟 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑒𐑤𐑴𐑕 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑢𐑪𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑯 𐑕𐑐𐑬𐑑𐑦𐑙𐑟—𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑚𐑰, 𐑯 𐑘𐑧𐑑, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑚𐑤𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑑 (𐑓𐑦𐑓𐑑𐑰𐑯 𐑯 𐑩 𐑒𐑢𐑹𐑑𐑼 𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑐𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑴'𐑒𐑤𐑪𐑒 P.M. 𐑝 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑰𐑯𐑔 𐑛𐑱 𐑝 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑧𐑥𐑚𐑼, ⸰𐑱𐑛 1851), 𐑦𐑑 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑱𐑯 𐑩 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑚𐑤𐑩𐑥, 𐑢𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑕𐑐𐑬𐑑𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑸, 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑷𐑤, 𐑮𐑾𐑤𐑦 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼, 𐑹 𐑯𐑳𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑝𐑱𐑐𐑼—𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑦𐑟 𐑖𐑫𐑼𐑤𐑦 𐑩 𐑯𐑴𐑑𐑢𐑻𐑞𐑦 𐑔𐑦𐑙.

𐑤𐑧𐑑 𐑳𐑕, 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑤𐑫𐑒 𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑥𐑨𐑑𐑼, 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑩𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑥𐑟 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑡𐑩𐑯𐑑. 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑯𐑴𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑽 𐑒𐑳𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑞𐑺 𐑜𐑦𐑤𐑟, 𐑞 𐑓𐑦𐑯𐑦 𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑚𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑚𐑮𐑰𐑞 𐑞 𐑺 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑨𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑚𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑞𐑱 𐑕𐑢𐑦𐑥; 𐑣𐑧𐑯𐑕, 𐑩 𐑣𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑙 𐑹 𐑩 𐑒𐑪𐑛 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑤𐑦𐑝 𐑩 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑗𐑼𐑦, 𐑯 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑕 𐑮𐑱𐑟 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑩𐑚𐑳𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑻𐑓𐑦𐑕. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑸𐑒𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑒𐑗𐑼 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑜𐑦𐑝𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑮𐑧𐑜𐑿𐑤𐑼 𐑤𐑳𐑙𐑟, 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑣𐑿𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙'𐑟, 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑤𐑦𐑝 𐑚𐑲 𐑦𐑯𐑣𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑦𐑯𐑜𐑱𐑡𐑛 𐑺 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑴𐑐𐑩𐑯 𐑨𐑑𐑥𐑩𐑕𐑓𐑽. 𐑢𐑺𐑓𐑹 𐑞 𐑯𐑦𐑕𐑧𐑕𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑓 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑽𐑦𐑪𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑝𐑦𐑟𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑑 𐑞 𐑳𐑐𐑼 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑛𐑦𐑜𐑮𐑰 𐑚𐑮𐑰𐑞 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑬𐑔, 𐑓, 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑹𐑛𐑦𐑯𐑼𐑦 𐑨𐑑𐑦𐑑𐑿𐑛, 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤'𐑟 𐑥𐑬𐑔 𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑛 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑰𐑕𐑑 𐑱𐑑 𐑓𐑰𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑯𐑰𐑔 𐑞 𐑕𐑻𐑓𐑦𐑕; 𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑥𐑹, 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑐𐑲𐑐 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑯𐑴 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑧𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑬𐑔. 𐑯𐑴, 𐑣𐑰 𐑚𐑮𐑰𐑞𐑟 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑐𐑦𐑮𐑩𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑩𐑤𐑴𐑯; 𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑦𐑟 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑑𐑪𐑐 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑧𐑛.

𐑦𐑓 𐑲 𐑕𐑱, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑒𐑮𐑰𐑗𐑼 𐑚𐑮𐑰𐑞𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑟 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑩 𐑓𐑳𐑙𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑑 𐑝𐑲𐑑𐑨𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑦, 𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑟𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑛𐑮𐑷𐑟 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑺 𐑩 𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑳𐑚𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑢𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑮𐑷𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑨𐑒𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑚𐑤𐑳𐑛 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑸𐑑𐑕 𐑑 𐑞 𐑚𐑤𐑳𐑛 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑝𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑓𐑲𐑦𐑙 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑐𐑩𐑤, 𐑲 𐑛𐑵 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒 𐑲 𐑖𐑨𐑤 𐑻; 𐑞𐑴 𐑲 𐑥𐑱 𐑐𐑪𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑿𐑟 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑕𐑵𐑐𐑻𐑓𐑤𐑵𐑩𐑕 𐑕𐑲𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑒 𐑢𐑻𐑛𐑟. 𐑩𐑕𐑿𐑥 𐑦𐑑, 𐑯 𐑦𐑑 𐑓𐑪𐑤𐑴𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑓 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑚𐑤𐑳𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑚𐑰 𐑺𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑚𐑮𐑧𐑔, 𐑣𐑰 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑕𐑰𐑤 𐑳𐑐 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑯 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑓𐑧𐑗 𐑩𐑯𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑓 𐑩 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑼𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑑𐑲𐑥. 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑑 𐑕𐑱, 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑤𐑦𐑝 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑 𐑚𐑮𐑰𐑞𐑦𐑙. 𐑩𐑯𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑥𐑱 𐑕𐑰𐑥, 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑲𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑞 𐑒𐑱𐑕 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑣𐑵 𐑕𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑥𐑨𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑦 𐑤𐑦𐑝𐑟, 𐑚𐑲 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑟, 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑫𐑤 𐑬𐑼 𐑯 𐑥𐑹 (𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑚𐑪𐑑𐑩𐑥) 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑 𐑛𐑮𐑷𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑕𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑩𐑤 𐑚𐑮𐑧𐑔, 𐑹 𐑕𐑴 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑢𐑱 𐑦𐑯𐑣𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑐𐑸𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑺; 𐑓, 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑧𐑥𐑚𐑼, 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑯𐑴 𐑜𐑦𐑤𐑟. 𐑣𐑬 𐑦𐑟 𐑞𐑦𐑕? 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑢𐑰𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑮𐑦𐑚𐑟 𐑯 𐑪𐑯 𐑰𐑗 𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑐𐑲𐑯 𐑣𐑰 𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑩𐑐𐑤𐑲𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑸𐑒𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑪𐑤𐑝𐑛 ·𐑒𐑮𐑰𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑤𐑨𐑚𐑼𐑦𐑯𐑔 𐑝 𐑝𐑻𐑥𐑦𐑗𐑧𐑤𐑦-𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑝𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑤𐑟, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑝𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑤𐑟, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑞 𐑕𐑻𐑓𐑦𐑕, 𐑸 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑰𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑪𐑒𐑕𐑦𐑡𐑩𐑯𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑤𐑳𐑛. 𐑕𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑓 𐑩𐑯 𐑬𐑼 𐑹 𐑥𐑹, 𐑩 𐑔𐑬𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑓𐑨𐑞𐑩𐑥𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑰, 𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑟 𐑩 𐑕𐑻𐑐𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑕𐑑𐑪𐑒 𐑝 𐑝𐑲𐑑𐑨𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑡𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑒𐑨𐑥𐑩𐑤 𐑒𐑮𐑪𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑛𐑧𐑟𐑼𐑑 𐑒𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑟 𐑩 𐑕𐑻𐑐𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑕𐑩𐑐𐑤𐑲 𐑝 𐑛𐑮𐑦𐑙𐑒 𐑓 𐑓𐑿𐑗𐑼 𐑿𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑓𐑹 𐑕𐑳𐑐𐑤𐑦𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑦 𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑥𐑩𐑒𐑕. 𐑞 𐑨𐑯𐑩𐑑𐑪𐑥𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑓𐑨𐑒𐑑 𐑝 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑤𐑨𐑚𐑼𐑦𐑯𐑔 𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑿𐑑𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤; 𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑐𐑩𐑟𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑮𐑰𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑯 𐑑𐑮𐑵, 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑟 𐑞 𐑥𐑹 𐑒𐑴𐑡𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑑 𐑥𐑰, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑲 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑼 𐑞 𐑳𐑞𐑼𐑢𐑲𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑤𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑪𐑚𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑕𐑦 𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑩𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑔𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑐𐑬𐑑𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑬𐑑, 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑼𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑱𐑟 𐑦𐑑. 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑲 𐑥𐑰𐑯. 𐑦𐑓 𐑳𐑯𐑥𐑩𐑤𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛, 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑮𐑲𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑻𐑓𐑦𐑕, 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑿 𐑞𐑺 𐑓 𐑩 𐑐𐑽𐑾𐑛 𐑝 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑦𐑜𐑟𐑨𐑒𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑿𐑯𐑦𐑓𐑹𐑥 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑷𐑤 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑳𐑯𐑥𐑩𐑤𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑮𐑲𐑟𐑦𐑙𐑟. 𐑕𐑱 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑟 𐑦𐑤𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑕, 𐑯 𐑡𐑧𐑑𐑕 𐑕𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑦 𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑟, 𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑲𐑼𐑟 𐑕𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑦 𐑚𐑮𐑧𐑔𐑕; 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑣𐑰 𐑮𐑲𐑟𐑩𐑟 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯, 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑚𐑰 𐑖𐑫𐑼 𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑦 𐑚𐑮𐑧𐑔𐑕 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯, 𐑑 𐑩 𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑑. 𐑯𐑬, 𐑦𐑓 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑣𐑰 𐑓𐑧𐑗𐑩𐑟 𐑩 𐑓𐑿 𐑚𐑮𐑧𐑔𐑕 𐑿 𐑩𐑤𐑸𐑥 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑕𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑟, 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑚𐑰 𐑷𐑤𐑢𐑱𐑟 𐑛𐑪𐑡𐑦𐑙 𐑳𐑐 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯 𐑑 𐑥𐑱𐑒 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑮𐑧𐑜𐑿𐑤𐑼 𐑩𐑤𐑬𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑝 𐑺. 𐑯 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑕𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑦 𐑚𐑮𐑧𐑔𐑕 𐑸 𐑑𐑴𐑤𐑛, 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑣𐑰 𐑓𐑲𐑯𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑜𐑴 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑱 𐑬𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑫𐑤 𐑑𐑻𐑥 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑴. 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑸𐑒, 𐑣𐑬𐑧𐑝𐑼, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑛𐑦𐑓𐑼𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑡𐑵𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑮𐑱𐑑𐑕 𐑸 𐑛𐑦𐑓𐑼𐑩𐑯𐑑; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑞𐑱 𐑸 𐑩𐑤𐑲𐑒. 𐑯𐑬, 𐑢𐑲 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑞𐑳𐑕 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑕𐑑 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑐𐑬𐑑𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑬𐑑, 𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑧𐑕 𐑦𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑤𐑧𐑯𐑦𐑖 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑮𐑧𐑟𐑼𐑝𐑢𐑸 𐑝 𐑺, 𐑺 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑓 𐑜𐑫𐑛? 𐑣𐑬 𐑪𐑚𐑝𐑾𐑕 𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑑, 𐑑𐑵, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑯𐑦𐑕𐑧𐑕𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑓 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤'𐑟 𐑮𐑲𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑴𐑟𐑩𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑓𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑣𐑨𐑟𐑼𐑛𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑗𐑱𐑕. 𐑓 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑣𐑫𐑒 𐑹 𐑚𐑲 𐑯𐑧𐑑 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑝𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑤𐑩𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑔𐑩𐑯 𐑚𐑰 𐑒𐑷𐑑, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑔𐑬𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑓𐑨𐑞𐑩𐑥𐑟 𐑚𐑦𐑯𐑰𐑔 𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑯𐑤𐑲𐑑. 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑴 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑞𐑲 𐑕𐑒𐑦𐑤, 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑴 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑑𐑼, 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑯𐑦𐑕𐑧𐑕𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑒 𐑞 𐑝𐑦𐑒𐑑𐑼𐑦 𐑑 𐑞𐑰!

𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑨𐑯, 𐑚𐑮𐑰𐑞𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑜𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑪𐑯—𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑚𐑮𐑧𐑔 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑻𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑓 𐑑𐑵 𐑹 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑐𐑳𐑤𐑕𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟; 𐑕𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑑𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑚𐑦𐑟𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑕 𐑑 𐑩𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑑, 𐑢𐑱𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑹 𐑕𐑤𐑰𐑐𐑦𐑙, 𐑚𐑮𐑰𐑞 𐑣𐑰 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑, 𐑹 𐑛𐑲 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑦𐑤. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑮𐑰𐑞𐑟 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑕𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑯𐑔 𐑹 𐑕𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑱 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑑𐑲𐑥.

𐑦𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑮𐑰𐑞𐑟 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑐𐑬𐑑-𐑣𐑴𐑤; 𐑦𐑓 𐑦𐑑 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑑𐑮𐑵𐑔𐑓𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑰 𐑨𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑐𐑬𐑑𐑕 𐑸 𐑥𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼, 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑲 𐑩𐑐𐑲𐑯 𐑢𐑰 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑚𐑰 𐑓𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑖𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑮𐑰𐑟𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑲 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑕 𐑝 𐑕𐑥𐑧𐑤 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑟 𐑴𐑚𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑼𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥; 𐑓 𐑞 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑼𐑟 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑴𐑟 𐑦𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑲𐑛𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑐𐑬𐑑-𐑣𐑴𐑤; 𐑯 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑴 𐑒𐑤𐑪𐑜𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑑𐑵 𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕, 𐑦𐑑 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑞 𐑐𐑬𐑼 𐑝 𐑕𐑥𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑙. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑞 𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑦 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑬𐑑—𐑢𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑦𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼 𐑹 𐑢𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑦𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑝𐑱𐑐𐑼—𐑯𐑴 𐑨𐑚𐑕𐑩𐑤𐑵𐑑 𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑦 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑨𐑟 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑼𐑲𐑝𐑛 𐑨𐑑 𐑪𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑣𐑧𐑛. 𐑖𐑫𐑼 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟, 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼𐑞𐑩𐑤𐑧𐑕, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑯𐑴 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑐𐑼 𐑪𐑤𐑓𐑨𐑒𐑑𐑼𐑦𐑟. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑛𐑳𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑞𐑧𐑥? 𐑯𐑴 𐑮𐑴𐑟𐑩𐑟, 𐑯𐑴 𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑤𐑩𐑑𐑕, 𐑯𐑴 ·𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑴𐑯-𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑰.

𐑓𐑻𐑞𐑼𐑥𐑹, 𐑨𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑐𐑲𐑐 𐑕𐑴𐑤𐑦 𐑴𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑑𐑿𐑚 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑐𐑬𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑨𐑤, 𐑯 𐑨𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑨𐑤—𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑛 ·𐑽𐑦 ·𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑨𐑤—𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑖𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑕𐑹𐑑 𐑝 𐑤𐑪𐑒𐑕 (𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑴𐑐𐑩𐑯 𐑯 𐑖𐑳𐑑) 𐑓 𐑞 𐑛𐑬𐑯𐑢𐑼𐑛 𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑺 𐑹 𐑞 𐑳𐑐𐑢𐑼𐑛 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑒𐑤𐑵𐑠𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼, 𐑞𐑺𐑓𐑹 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑯𐑴 𐑝𐑶𐑕; 𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑧𐑕 𐑿 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑳𐑤𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑚𐑲 𐑕𐑱𐑦𐑙, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑴 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑳𐑥𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑟, 𐑣𐑰 𐑑𐑷𐑒𐑕 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑴𐑟. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯, 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑑 𐑕𐑱? 𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑛𐑩𐑥 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑲 𐑯𐑴𐑯 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑧𐑯𐑦𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑕𐑱 𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛, 𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑧𐑕 𐑓𐑹𐑕𐑑 𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑥𐑼 𐑬𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑲 𐑢𐑱 𐑝 𐑜𐑧𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑤𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑙. 𐑴! 𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑦 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛 𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩𐑯 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑩𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑤𐑦𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑼!

𐑯𐑬, 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑬𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑨𐑤 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑗𐑰𐑓𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑓 𐑞 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑝𐑱𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑝 𐑺, 𐑯 𐑓 𐑕𐑧𐑝𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑓𐑰𐑑 𐑤𐑱𐑛 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑙, 𐑣𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑦, 𐑡𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑯𐑰𐑔 𐑞 𐑳𐑐𐑼 𐑕𐑻𐑓𐑦𐑕 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑧𐑛, 𐑯 𐑩 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑕𐑲𐑛; 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑒𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑾𐑕 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑨𐑤 𐑦𐑟 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑜𐑨𐑕-𐑐𐑲𐑐 𐑤𐑱𐑛 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑕𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑪𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑝 𐑩 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑰𐑑. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞 𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑕𐑗𐑩𐑯 𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑟 𐑢𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑜𐑨𐑕-𐑐𐑲𐑐 𐑦𐑟 𐑷𐑤𐑕𐑴 𐑩 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼-𐑐𐑲𐑐; 𐑦𐑯 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑢𐑻𐑛𐑟, 𐑢𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑦𐑟 𐑞 𐑥𐑽 𐑝𐑱𐑐𐑼 𐑝 𐑞 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑣𐑱𐑤𐑛 𐑚𐑮𐑧𐑔, 𐑹 𐑢𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑣𐑱𐑤𐑛 𐑚𐑮𐑧𐑔 𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼 𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑥𐑬𐑔, 𐑯 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑗𐑸𐑡𐑛 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑦𐑮𐑩𐑒𐑩𐑤. 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑥𐑬𐑔 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑿𐑯𐑦𐑒𐑱𐑑𐑕 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑬𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑨𐑤; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑐𐑮𐑵𐑝𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑦𐑟 𐑓 𐑞 𐑐𐑻𐑐𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑗𐑸𐑡𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑦𐑮𐑩𐑒𐑩𐑤. 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑪𐑟 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑯𐑦𐑕𐑧𐑕𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑓 𐑕𐑴 𐑛𐑵𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑕𐑰𐑥 𐑑 𐑚𐑰, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑓𐑰𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑰 𐑨𐑒𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤'𐑟 𐑓𐑵𐑛 𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑸 𐑚𐑦𐑯𐑰𐑔 𐑞 𐑕𐑻𐑓𐑦𐑕, 𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑐𐑬𐑑 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑓 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑫𐑛. 𐑚𐑦𐑕𐑲𐑛𐑟, 𐑦𐑓 𐑿 𐑮𐑦𐑜𐑸𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑒𐑤𐑴𐑕𐑤𐑦, 𐑯 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑘𐑹 𐑢𐑪𐑗, 𐑿 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑓𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑳𐑯𐑥𐑩𐑤𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛, 𐑞𐑺 𐑦𐑟 𐑩𐑯 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑰𐑝𐑦𐑱𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑮𐑲𐑥 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑢𐑰𐑯 𐑞 𐑐𐑽𐑾𐑛𐑟 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑡𐑧𐑑𐑕 𐑯 𐑞 𐑹𐑛𐑦𐑯𐑼𐑦 𐑐𐑽𐑾𐑛𐑟 𐑝 𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑐𐑼𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯.

𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑲 𐑐𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑼 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑮𐑰𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑚𐑡𐑧𐑒𐑑? 𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑒 𐑬𐑑! 𐑿 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑕𐑰𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑕𐑐𐑬𐑑; 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑺 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑬𐑑 𐑦𐑟; 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑿 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑑𐑧𐑤 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑺? 𐑥𐑲 𐑛𐑽 𐑕𐑻, 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑴 𐑰𐑟𐑦 𐑑 𐑕𐑧𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑯 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑟. 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑘𐑹 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑯 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑞 𐑯𐑪𐑑𐑾𐑕𐑑 𐑝 𐑷𐑤. 𐑯 𐑨𐑟 𐑓 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑕𐑐𐑬𐑑, 𐑿 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑦𐑑, 𐑯 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑲𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑨𐑟 𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑲𐑕𐑤𐑦.

𐑞 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑩𐑤 𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦 𐑝 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑯𐑴𐑦 𐑕𐑐𐑸𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑧𐑤𐑩𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑑; 𐑯 𐑣𐑬 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑿 𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑑𐑧𐑤 𐑢𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼 𐑓𐑷𐑤𐑟 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑦𐑑, 𐑢𐑧𐑯, 𐑷𐑤𐑢𐑱𐑟, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑿 𐑸 𐑒𐑤𐑴𐑕 𐑦𐑯𐑳𐑓 𐑑 𐑩 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑑 𐑜𐑧𐑑 𐑩 𐑒𐑤𐑴𐑕 𐑝𐑿 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑐𐑬𐑑, 𐑣𐑰 𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑛𐑦𐑡𐑩𐑕 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯, 𐑞 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼 𐑒𐑨𐑕𐑒𐑱𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑷𐑤 𐑼𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥. 𐑯 𐑦𐑓 𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑿 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑿 𐑮𐑾𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑼𐑕𐑰𐑝𐑛 𐑛𐑮𐑪𐑐𐑕 𐑝 𐑥𐑶𐑕𐑗𐑼 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑬𐑑, 𐑣𐑬 𐑛𐑵 𐑿 𐑯𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑱 𐑸 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑥𐑽𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑛𐑧𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑝𐑱𐑐𐑼; 𐑹 𐑣𐑬 𐑛𐑵 𐑿 𐑯𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑱 𐑸 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑲𐑛𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑛𐑮𐑪𐑐𐑕 𐑕𐑵𐑐𐑼𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑤𐑪𐑡𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑬𐑑-𐑣𐑴𐑤 𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑼, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑕𐑳𐑙𐑒 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑦𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤'𐑟 𐑣𐑧𐑛? 𐑓 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑢𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑞 𐑥𐑦𐑛-𐑛𐑱 𐑕𐑰 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑒𐑭𐑥, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑝𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑣𐑳𐑥𐑐 𐑕𐑳𐑯-𐑛𐑮𐑲𐑛 𐑨𐑟 𐑩 𐑛𐑮𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑛𐑼𐑦'𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑟𐑼𐑑; 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑷𐑤𐑢𐑱𐑟 𐑒𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑟 𐑩 𐑕𐑥𐑷𐑤 𐑚𐑱𐑕𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼 𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑧𐑛, 𐑨𐑟 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑩 𐑚𐑤𐑱𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑳𐑯 𐑿 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑕𐑰 𐑩 𐑒𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑮𐑪𐑒 𐑓𐑦𐑤𐑛 𐑳𐑐 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑮𐑱𐑯.

𐑯𐑹 𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑐𐑮𐑵𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑓 𐑞 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑑𐑼 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑒𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑾𐑕 𐑑𐑳𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑲𐑕 𐑯𐑱𐑗𐑼 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑕𐑐𐑬𐑑. 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑛𐑵 𐑓 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑐𐑽𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑦𐑑, 𐑯 𐑐𐑫𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑱𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑦𐑑. 𐑿 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑜𐑴 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑘𐑹 𐑐𐑦𐑗𐑼 𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑯 𐑓𐑦𐑤 𐑦𐑑, 𐑯 𐑚𐑮𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑑 𐑩𐑢𐑱. 𐑓 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑕𐑤𐑲𐑑 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑨𐑒𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑬𐑑𐑼, 𐑝𐑱𐑐𐑼𐑦 𐑖𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑡𐑧𐑑, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑪𐑓𐑩𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑩𐑯, 𐑘𐑹 𐑕𐑒𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑓𐑰𐑝𐑼𐑦𐑖𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑥𐑸𐑑, 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑨𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑛𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑴 𐑑𐑳𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑑. 𐑯 𐑲 𐑯𐑴 𐑢𐑳𐑯, 𐑣𐑵 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑒𐑤𐑴𐑕𐑼 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑨𐑒𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑬𐑑, 𐑢𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑕𐑲𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑒 𐑪𐑚𐑡𐑧𐑒𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑝𐑿, 𐑹 𐑳𐑞𐑼𐑢𐑲𐑟, 𐑲 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑱, 𐑞 𐑕𐑒𐑦𐑯 𐑐𐑰𐑤𐑛 𐑪𐑓 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑗𐑰𐑒 𐑯 𐑸𐑥. 𐑢𐑺𐑓𐑹, 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑥𐑧𐑯, 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑬𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑛𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑐𐑶𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑕; 𐑞𐑱 𐑑𐑮𐑲 𐑑 𐑦𐑝𐑱𐑛 𐑦𐑑. 𐑩𐑯𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑔𐑦𐑙; 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑣𐑻𐑛 𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑧𐑛, 𐑯 𐑲 𐑛𐑵 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑛𐑬𐑑 𐑦𐑑, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑓 𐑞 𐑡𐑧𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑺𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑐𐑬𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑘𐑹 𐑲𐑟, 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑚𐑤𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑿. 𐑞 𐑢𐑲𐑟𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑜𐑱𐑑𐑼 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑛𐑵 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑟 𐑑 𐑥𐑰, 𐑦𐑟 𐑑 𐑤𐑧𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑛𐑧𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑐𐑬𐑑 𐑩𐑤𐑴𐑯.

𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤, 𐑢𐑰 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑣𐑲𐑐𐑪𐑔𐑦𐑕𐑲𐑟, 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑓 𐑢𐑰 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑵𐑝 𐑯 𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑚𐑤𐑦𐑖. 𐑥𐑲 𐑣𐑲𐑐𐑪𐑔𐑦𐑕𐑦𐑕 𐑦𐑟 𐑞𐑦𐑕: 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑬𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑳𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑑. 𐑯 𐑚𐑦𐑕𐑲𐑛𐑟 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑮𐑰𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑟, 𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑒𐑤𐑵𐑠𐑩𐑯 𐑲 𐑨𐑥 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑧𐑤𐑛, 𐑚𐑲 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑼𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑑𐑳𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑣𐑧𐑮𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑜𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑯 𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤; 𐑲 𐑩𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑯𐑴 𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑯, 𐑖𐑨𐑤𐑴 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙, 𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑟𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑩𐑯 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑿𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑓𐑨𐑒𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑪𐑯 𐑕𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙𐑟, 𐑹 𐑯𐑽 𐑖𐑹𐑟; 𐑷𐑤 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑸. 𐑣𐑰 𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑴𐑔 𐑐𐑪𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑩𐑕 𐑯 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛. 𐑯 𐑲 𐑨𐑥 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑝𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑟 𐑝 𐑷𐑤 𐑐𐑪𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑩𐑕 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙𐑟, 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑨𐑟 ·𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑑𐑴, ·𐑐𐑦𐑮𐑴, 𐑞 ·𐑛𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑤, ·𐑡𐑵𐑐𐑦𐑑𐑼, ·𐑛𐑭𐑯𐑑𐑱, 𐑯 𐑕𐑴 𐑪𐑯, 𐑞𐑺 𐑷𐑤𐑢𐑱𐑟 𐑜𐑴𐑟 𐑳𐑐 𐑩 𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑕𐑧𐑥𐑦-𐑝𐑦𐑟𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑑𐑰𐑥, 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑨𐑒𐑑 𐑝 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑛𐑰𐑐 𐑔𐑷𐑑𐑕. 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑴𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑑𐑮𐑰𐑑𐑦𐑟 𐑪𐑯 ·𐑦𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑦, 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑞 𐑒𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑦𐑪𐑕𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑑 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕 𐑩 𐑥𐑦𐑮𐑼 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑥𐑰; 𐑯 𐑺 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑕𐑷 𐑮𐑦𐑓𐑤𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑞𐑺, 𐑩 𐑒𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑾𐑕 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑪𐑤𐑝𐑛 𐑢𐑻𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑯 𐑳𐑯𐑡𐑩𐑤𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑨𐑑𐑥𐑩𐑕𐑓𐑽 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑥𐑲 𐑣𐑧𐑛. 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑺𐑾𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑥𐑶𐑕𐑗𐑼 𐑝 𐑥𐑲 𐑣𐑺, 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑐𐑤𐑳𐑯𐑡𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑛𐑰𐑐 𐑔𐑷𐑑, 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑕 𐑒𐑳𐑐𐑕 𐑝 𐑣𐑪𐑑 𐑑𐑰 𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑲 𐑔𐑦𐑯 𐑖𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑨𐑑𐑦𐑒, 𐑝 𐑩𐑯 𐑷𐑜𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑯𐑵𐑯; 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑟 𐑩𐑯 𐑩𐑛𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑸𐑜𐑿𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑓 𐑞 𐑩𐑚𐑳𐑝 𐑕𐑳𐑐𐑩𐑟𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯.

𐑯 𐑣𐑬 𐑯𐑴𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑑 𐑮𐑱𐑟𐑩𐑟 𐑬𐑼 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑰𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑥𐑲𐑑𐑦, 𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑦 𐑥𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑼, 𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑕𐑪𐑤𐑩𐑥𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑩 𐑒𐑭𐑥 𐑑𐑮𐑪𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑰; 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑝𐑭𐑕𐑑, 𐑥𐑲𐑤𐑛 𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑴𐑝𐑼𐑣𐑳𐑙 𐑚𐑲 𐑩 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑩𐑐𐑦 𐑝 𐑝𐑱𐑐𐑼, 𐑦𐑯𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑿𐑯𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟, 𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑝𐑱𐑐𐑼—𐑨𐑟 𐑿 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑕𐑰 𐑦𐑑—𐑜𐑤𐑹𐑦𐑓𐑲𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑩 𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑚𐑴, 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑓 ·𐑣𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑑𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑐𐑫𐑑 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑕𐑰𐑤 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑔𐑷𐑑𐑕. 𐑓, 𐑛'𐑘𐑰 𐑕𐑰, 𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑚𐑴𐑟 𐑛𐑵 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑝𐑦𐑟𐑦𐑑 𐑞 𐑒𐑤𐑽 𐑺; 𐑞𐑱 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑮𐑱𐑛𐑦𐑱𐑑 𐑝𐑱𐑐𐑼. 𐑯 𐑕𐑴, 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑔𐑦𐑒 𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑛𐑦𐑥 𐑛𐑬𐑑𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑲 𐑥𐑲𐑯𐑛, 𐑛𐑦𐑝𐑲𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑿𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑯𐑬 𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑖𐑵𐑑, 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑲 𐑓𐑪𐑜 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑣𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑱. 𐑯 𐑓 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑲 𐑔𐑨𐑙𐑒 ·𐑜𐑪𐑛; 𐑓 𐑷𐑤 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑛𐑬𐑑𐑕; 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑛𐑦𐑯𐑲; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑛𐑬𐑑𐑕 𐑹 𐑛𐑦𐑯𐑲𐑩𐑤𐑟, 𐑓𐑿 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞𐑧𐑥, 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑿𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟. 𐑛𐑬𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑷𐑤 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑻𐑔𐑤𐑦, 𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑿𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑣𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑦; 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑚𐑦𐑯𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑥𐑱𐑒𐑕 𐑯𐑲𐑞𐑼 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑰𐑝𐑼 𐑯𐑹 𐑦𐑯𐑓𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑤, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑥𐑱𐑒𐑕 𐑩 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑣𐑵 𐑮𐑦𐑜𐑸𐑛𐑟 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑚𐑴𐑔 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑩𐑤 𐑲.

·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 86. 𐑞 ·𐑑𐑱𐑤.

𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑐𐑴𐑩𐑑𐑕 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑢𐑹𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑱𐑟𐑩𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑪𐑓𐑑 𐑲 𐑝 𐑞 𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑤𐑴𐑐, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑤𐑳𐑝𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑤𐑵𐑥𐑦𐑡 𐑝 𐑞 𐑚𐑻𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑩𐑤𐑲𐑑𐑕; 𐑤𐑧𐑕 𐑕𐑦𐑤𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑾𐑤, 𐑲 𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑩𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑩 𐑑𐑱𐑤.

𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑤𐑸𐑡𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑲𐑟𐑛 ·𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤'𐑟 𐑑𐑱𐑤 𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑜𐑦𐑯 𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑐𐑶𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑙𐑒 𐑢𐑺 𐑦𐑑 𐑑𐑱𐑐𐑼𐑟 𐑑 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑞 𐑜𐑻𐑔 𐑝 𐑩 𐑥𐑨𐑯, 𐑦𐑑 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑮𐑲𐑟𐑩𐑟 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑳𐑐𐑼 𐑕𐑻𐑓𐑦𐑕 𐑩𐑤𐑴𐑯, 𐑩𐑯 𐑺𐑾 𐑝 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑰𐑕𐑑 𐑓𐑦𐑓𐑑𐑦 𐑕𐑒𐑢𐑺 𐑓𐑰𐑑. 𐑞 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑨𐑒𐑑 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦 𐑝 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑮𐑵𐑑 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑑𐑵 𐑚𐑮𐑷𐑛, 𐑓𐑻𐑥, 𐑓𐑤𐑨𐑑 𐑐𐑭𐑥𐑟 𐑹 𐑓𐑤𐑵𐑒𐑕, 𐑜𐑮𐑨𐑡𐑵𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑖𐑴𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑢𐑱 𐑑 𐑤𐑧𐑕 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑗 𐑦𐑯 𐑔𐑦𐑒𐑯𐑩𐑕. 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑪𐑗 𐑹 𐑡𐑳𐑙𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯, 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑓𐑤𐑵𐑒𐑕 𐑕𐑤𐑲𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑴𐑝𐑼𐑤𐑨𐑐, 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑕𐑲𐑛𐑢𐑱𐑟 𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑰𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑰𐑗 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑢𐑦𐑙𐑟, 𐑤𐑰𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑢𐑲𐑛 𐑝𐑱𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑢𐑰𐑯. 𐑦𐑯 𐑯𐑴 𐑤𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑸 𐑞 𐑤𐑲𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑚𐑿𐑑𐑦 𐑥𐑹 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑟𐑦𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑦𐑓𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑧𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑚𐑹𐑛𐑼𐑟 𐑝 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑓𐑤𐑵𐑒𐑕. 𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑳𐑑𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑨𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑫𐑤 𐑜𐑮𐑴𐑯 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑞 𐑑𐑱𐑤 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑼𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑰𐑛 𐑑𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑦 𐑓𐑰𐑑 𐑩𐑒𐑮𐑪𐑕.

𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑲𐑼 𐑥𐑧𐑥𐑚𐑼 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑟 𐑩 𐑛𐑧𐑯𐑕 𐑢𐑧𐑚𐑛 𐑚𐑧𐑛 𐑝 𐑢𐑧𐑤𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑕𐑦𐑯𐑿𐑟; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑒𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑦𐑑, 𐑯 𐑿 𐑓𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑭𐑑𐑩 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑴𐑟 𐑦𐑑:—𐑳𐑐𐑼, 𐑥𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑤, 𐑯 𐑤𐑴𐑼. 𐑞 𐑓𐑲𐑚𐑼𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑳𐑐𐑼 𐑯 𐑤𐑴𐑼 𐑤𐑱𐑼𐑟, 𐑸 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑯 𐑣𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤; 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑥𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑳𐑯, 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑖𐑹𐑑, 𐑯 𐑮𐑳𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑒𐑮𐑪𐑕𐑢𐑲𐑟 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑢𐑰𐑯 𐑞 𐑬𐑑𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑤𐑱𐑼𐑟. 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑿𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑒𐑗𐑼, 𐑨𐑟 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑨𐑟 𐑧𐑯𐑦𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑧𐑤𐑕, 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑸𐑑𐑕 𐑐𐑬𐑼 𐑑 𐑞 𐑑𐑱𐑤. 𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑿𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑴𐑤𐑛 ·𐑮𐑴𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑷𐑤𐑟, 𐑞 𐑥𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑤 𐑤𐑱𐑼 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑓𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑖 𐑩 𐑒𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑾𐑕 𐑐𐑨𐑮𐑩𐑤𐑧𐑤 𐑑 𐑞 𐑔𐑦𐑯 𐑒𐑹𐑕 𐑝 𐑑𐑲𐑤𐑟 𐑷𐑤𐑢𐑱𐑟 𐑷𐑤𐑑𐑼𐑯𐑱𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑴𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑮𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑒𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑰𐑒, 𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑬𐑑𐑩𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑚𐑿𐑑 𐑕𐑴 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑑 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑧𐑙𐑔 𐑝 𐑞 𐑥𐑱𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑼𐑦.

𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑓 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑝𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑤𐑴𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑐𐑬𐑼 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑑𐑱𐑤 𐑢𐑻 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑳𐑓, 𐑞 𐑣𐑴𐑤 𐑚𐑳𐑤𐑒 𐑝 𐑞 𐑤𐑩𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑔𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑦𐑑 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑢𐑹𐑐 𐑯 𐑢𐑵𐑓 𐑝 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑼 𐑓𐑲𐑚𐑼𐑟 𐑯 𐑓𐑦𐑤𐑩𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑐𐑭𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑪𐑯 𐑲𐑞𐑼 𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑞 𐑤𐑶𐑯𐑟 𐑯 𐑮𐑳𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑓𐑤𐑵𐑒𐑕, 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑤𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞𐑧𐑥, 𐑯 𐑤𐑸𐑡𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑚𐑿𐑑 𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑥𐑲𐑑; 𐑕𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑑𐑱𐑤 𐑞 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑓𐑤𐑵𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑥𐑧𐑠𐑼𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑓𐑹𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑣𐑴𐑤 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑟 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑑 𐑩 𐑐𐑶𐑯𐑑. 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑩𐑯𐑲𐑩𐑤𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑩𐑒𐑻 𐑑 𐑥𐑨𐑑𐑼, 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑻 𐑞 𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑛𐑵 𐑦𐑑.

𐑯𐑹 𐑛𐑳𐑟 𐑞𐑦𐑕—𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑩𐑥𐑱𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑧𐑙𐑔, 𐑨𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑑 𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑩𐑤 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑕𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑓𐑤𐑧𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑥𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟; 𐑢𐑺 𐑦𐑯𐑓𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑧𐑕 𐑝 𐑰𐑟 𐑳𐑯𐑡𐑩𐑤𐑱𐑑𐑕 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑩 ·𐑑𐑲𐑑𐑱𐑯𐑦𐑟𐑩𐑥 𐑝 𐑐𐑬𐑼. 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑺𐑦, 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑥𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑛𐑦𐑮𐑲𐑝 𐑞𐑺 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑩𐑐𐑷𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑿𐑑𐑦 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑦𐑑. 𐑮𐑾𐑤 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑧𐑙𐑔 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑺𐑟 𐑚𐑿𐑑𐑦 𐑹 𐑣𐑸𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑦, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑪𐑓𐑩𐑯 𐑚𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑴𐑟 𐑦𐑑; 𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑴𐑟𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑿𐑑𐑦𐑓𐑩𐑤, 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑧𐑙𐑔 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑑 𐑛𐑵 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑥𐑨𐑡𐑦𐑒. 𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑩𐑢𐑱 𐑞 𐑑𐑲𐑛 𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑕𐑰𐑥 𐑚𐑻𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑥𐑸𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑒𐑸𐑝𐑛 ·𐑣𐑻𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑰𐑟, 𐑯 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑗𐑸𐑥 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑚𐑰 𐑜𐑪𐑯. 𐑨𐑟 𐑛𐑦𐑝𐑬𐑑 ·𐑧𐑒𐑼𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑤𐑦𐑓𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑞 𐑤𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑯 𐑖𐑰𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑯𐑱𐑒𐑩𐑛 𐑒𐑹𐑐𐑕 𐑝 ·𐑜𐑻𐑑𐑩, 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑴𐑝𐑼𐑢𐑧𐑤𐑥𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑥𐑨𐑕𐑦𐑝 𐑗𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑥𐑨𐑯, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑨𐑟 𐑩 ·𐑮𐑴𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑳𐑥𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑸𐑗. 𐑢𐑧𐑯 ·𐑨𐑯𐑡𐑩𐑤𐑴 𐑐𐑱𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 ·𐑜𐑪𐑛 𐑞 ·𐑓𐑭𐑞𐑼 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑿𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑓𐑹𐑥, 𐑥𐑸𐑒 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑮𐑴𐑚𐑳𐑕𐑑𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑦𐑟 𐑞𐑺. 𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑑𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑞𐑱 𐑥𐑱 𐑮𐑦𐑝𐑰𐑤 𐑝 𐑞 𐑛𐑦𐑝𐑲𐑯 𐑤𐑳𐑝 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑳𐑯, 𐑞 𐑕𐑪𐑓𐑑, 𐑒𐑻𐑤𐑛, 𐑣𐑻𐑥𐑨𐑓𐑮𐑩𐑛𐑲𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 ·𐑦𐑑𐑨𐑤𐑾𐑯 𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑗𐑼𐑟, 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑲𐑛𐑾 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑩𐑒𐑕𐑧𐑕𐑓𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑥𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦𐑛; 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑗𐑼𐑟, 𐑕𐑴 𐑛𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑑𐑿𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑞𐑱 𐑸 𐑝 𐑷𐑤 𐑚𐑮𐑷𐑯𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑕, 𐑣𐑦𐑯𐑑 𐑯𐑳𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑐𐑬𐑼, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞 𐑥𐑽 𐑯𐑧𐑜𐑩𐑑𐑦𐑝, 𐑓𐑧𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑥𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑻𐑩𐑯𐑕, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑪𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑰𐑛𐑩𐑛, 𐑓𐑹𐑥 𐑞 𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑽 𐑐𐑮𐑨𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑝𐑻𐑗𐑵𐑟 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑑𐑰𐑗𐑦𐑙𐑟.

𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑦𐑟 𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑤𐑨𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑕𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑝 𐑞 𐑹𐑜𐑩𐑯 𐑲 𐑑𐑮𐑰𐑑 𐑝, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑢𐑰𐑤𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑐𐑹𐑑, 𐑹 𐑦𐑯 𐑻𐑯𐑩𐑕𐑑, 𐑹 𐑦𐑯 𐑨𐑙𐑜𐑼, 𐑢𐑪𐑑𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑚𐑰 𐑞 𐑥𐑵𐑛 𐑦𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑦𐑯, 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑓𐑤𐑧𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑸 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑺𐑾𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑥𐑸𐑒𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑰𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑕. 𐑞𐑺𐑦𐑯 𐑯𐑴 𐑓𐑺𐑦'𐑟 𐑸𐑥 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑑.

𐑓𐑲𐑝 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑥𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑸 𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑽 𐑑 𐑦𐑑. 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑿𐑟𐑛 𐑨𐑟 𐑩 𐑓𐑦𐑯 𐑓 𐑐𐑮𐑴𐑜𐑮𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑯; ·𐑕𐑧𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑛, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑿𐑟𐑛 𐑨𐑟 𐑩 𐑥𐑱𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑚𐑨𐑑𐑩𐑤; ·𐑔𐑻𐑛, 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑢𐑰𐑐𐑦𐑙; ·𐑓𐑹𐑔, 𐑦𐑯 𐑤𐑪𐑚𐑑𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙; ·𐑓𐑦𐑓𐑔, 𐑦𐑯 𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑤𐑵𐑒𐑕.

𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑: 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑐𐑩𐑟𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯, 𐑞 ·𐑤𐑩𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑔𐑩𐑯'𐑟 𐑑𐑱𐑤 𐑨𐑒𐑑𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑛𐑦𐑓𐑼𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑥𐑨𐑯𐑼 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑑𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑝 𐑷𐑤 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑕𐑰 𐑒𐑮𐑰𐑗𐑼𐑟. 𐑦𐑑 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑮𐑦𐑜𐑩𐑤𐑟. 𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑹 𐑓𐑦𐑖, 𐑮𐑦𐑜𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑟 𐑩 𐑕𐑲𐑯 𐑝 𐑦𐑯𐑓𐑽𐑦𐑹𐑦𐑑𐑦. 𐑑 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑑𐑱𐑤 𐑦𐑟 𐑞 𐑕𐑴𐑤 𐑥𐑰𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑐𐑳𐑤𐑖𐑩𐑯. 𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑴𐑤-𐑢𐑲𐑟 𐑒𐑶𐑤𐑛 𐑓𐑹𐑢𐑼𐑛𐑟 𐑚𐑦𐑯𐑰𐑔 𐑞 𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦, 𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑮𐑨𐑐𐑦𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑳𐑙 𐑚𐑨𐑒𐑢𐑼𐑛𐑟, 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑜𐑦𐑝𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑿𐑤𐑼 𐑛𐑸𐑑𐑦𐑙, 𐑤𐑰𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑑 𐑞 𐑥𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑼 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑓𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑾𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑢𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑙. 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑲𐑛-𐑓𐑦𐑯𐑟 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑻𐑝 𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑽 𐑚𐑲.

𐑕𐑧𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑛: 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑩 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑦𐑜𐑯𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑓𐑲𐑑𐑕 𐑩𐑯𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑯 𐑡𐑷, 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼𐑞𐑩𐑤𐑧𐑕, 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑓𐑤𐑦𐑒𐑑𐑕 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑥𐑨𐑯, 𐑣𐑰 𐑗𐑰𐑓𐑤𐑦 𐑯 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑥𐑐𐑗𐑵𐑩𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑿𐑟𐑩𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑑𐑱𐑤. 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑨𐑑 𐑩 𐑚𐑴𐑑, 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑢𐑦𐑓𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑻𐑝𐑟 𐑩𐑢𐑱 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑤𐑵𐑒𐑕 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑦𐑑, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑤𐑴 𐑦𐑟 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑯𐑓𐑤𐑦𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑶𐑤. 𐑦𐑓 𐑦𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑳𐑯𐑩𐑚𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑺, 𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑓 𐑦𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑑 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑥𐑸𐑒, 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑴𐑒 𐑦𐑟 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑕𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤. 𐑯𐑴 𐑮𐑦𐑚𐑟 𐑝 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑹 𐑚𐑴𐑑 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑑. 𐑘𐑹 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑨𐑤𐑝𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑤𐑲𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑦𐑤𐑵𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑑; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑓 𐑦𐑑 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑟 𐑕𐑲𐑛𐑢𐑱𐑟 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑞 𐑩𐑐𐑴𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼, 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑐𐑸𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑞 𐑤𐑲𐑑 𐑚𐑶𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤-𐑚𐑴𐑑, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑦𐑤𐑨𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑕𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑝 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑥𐑩𐑑𐑽𐑾𐑤𐑟, 𐑩 𐑒𐑮𐑨𐑒𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑚 𐑹 𐑩 𐑛𐑨𐑖𐑑 𐑐𐑤𐑨𐑙𐑒 𐑹 𐑑𐑵, 𐑩 𐑕𐑹𐑑 𐑝 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑗 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑲𐑛, 𐑦𐑟 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑞 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑽𐑾𐑕 𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑳𐑤𐑑. 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑥𐑻𐑡𐑛 𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑚𐑤𐑴𐑟 𐑸 𐑕𐑴 𐑪𐑓𐑩𐑯 𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑰𐑝𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑼𐑦, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑱 𐑸 𐑩𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑥𐑽 𐑗𐑲𐑤𐑛'𐑟 𐑐𐑤𐑱. 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑕 𐑪𐑓 𐑩 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑒, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑣𐑴𐑤 𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑪𐑐𐑑.

𐑔𐑻𐑛: 𐑲 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑛𐑧𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑦𐑑, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑟 𐑑 𐑥𐑰, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑞 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑕 𐑝 𐑑𐑳𐑗 𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑑𐑱𐑤; 𐑓 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑦𐑟 𐑩 𐑛𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑕𐑦 𐑦𐑯 𐑦𐑑 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑛𐑱𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑓𐑩𐑯𐑑'𐑕 𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑙𐑒. 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑛𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑕𐑦 𐑦𐑟 𐑗𐑰𐑓𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑨𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑕𐑢𐑰𐑐𐑦𐑙, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑱𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑕𐑪𐑓𐑑 𐑕𐑤𐑴𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑥𐑵𐑝𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑕 𐑓𐑤𐑵𐑒𐑕 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑑 𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑻𐑓𐑦𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑰; 𐑯 𐑦𐑓 𐑣𐑰 𐑓𐑰𐑤 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑩 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑼'𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑼, 𐑢𐑴 𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑼, 𐑢𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑼𐑟 𐑯 𐑷𐑤. 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑞𐑺 𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑼𐑦 𐑑𐑳𐑗! 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑑𐑱𐑤 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑐𐑮𐑰𐑣𐑧𐑯𐑕𐑲𐑤 𐑐𐑬𐑼, 𐑲 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑑𐑢𐑱 𐑚𐑦𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒 𐑥𐑰 𐑝 ·𐑛𐑸𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑴𐑛𐑰𐑟' 𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑓𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑴 𐑓𐑮𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑞 𐑓𐑤𐑬𐑼-𐑥𐑸𐑒𐑩𐑑, 𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑤𐑴 𐑕𐑨𐑤𐑿𐑑𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑯𐑴𐑟𐑜𐑱𐑟 𐑑 𐑛𐑨𐑥𐑟𐑩𐑤𐑟, 𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑒𐑼𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑟𐑴𐑯𐑟. 𐑪𐑯 𐑥𐑹 𐑩𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯, 𐑩 𐑐𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑛𐑳𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑐𐑩𐑟𐑧𐑕 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑐𐑮𐑰𐑣𐑧𐑯𐑕𐑲𐑤 𐑝𐑻𐑗𐑵 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑑𐑱𐑤; 𐑓 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑣𐑻𐑛 𐑝 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑩𐑯𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑓𐑩𐑯𐑑, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑢𐑵𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑲𐑑, 𐑒𐑻𐑝𐑛 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑙𐑒 𐑯 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑞 𐑛𐑸𐑑.

𐑓𐑹𐑔: 𐑕𐑑𐑰𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑳𐑯𐑩𐑢𐑺𐑟 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑨𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑛 𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑝 𐑞 𐑥𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑕𐑪𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑼𐑦 𐑕𐑰𐑟, 𐑿 𐑓𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑳𐑯𐑚𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑝𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑒𐑹𐑐𐑿𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑛𐑦𐑜𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑦, 𐑯 𐑒𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑯-𐑤𐑲𐑒, 𐑣𐑰 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑟 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑓 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑻 𐑩 𐑣𐑸𐑔. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑿 𐑕𐑰 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑬𐑼 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑤𐑱. 𐑞 𐑚𐑮𐑷𐑛 𐑐𐑭𐑥𐑟 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑑𐑱𐑤 𐑸 𐑓𐑤𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑣𐑲 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑺; 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑕𐑥𐑲𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑕𐑻𐑓𐑦𐑕, 𐑞 𐑔𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑩𐑕 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑒𐑳𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑓 𐑥𐑲𐑤𐑟. 𐑿 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒 𐑩 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑜𐑳𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑗𐑸𐑡𐑛; 𐑯 𐑦𐑓 𐑿 𐑯𐑴𐑑𐑦𐑕𐑑 𐑞 𐑤𐑲𐑑 𐑮𐑰𐑔 𐑝 𐑝𐑱𐑐𐑼 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑦𐑮𐑩𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑧𐑥𐑦𐑑𐑦, 𐑿 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞 𐑕𐑥𐑴𐑒 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑑𐑳𐑗-𐑣𐑴𐑤.

𐑓𐑦𐑓𐑔: 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑹𐑛𐑦𐑯𐑼𐑦 𐑓𐑤𐑴𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑐𐑪𐑕𐑗𐑼 𐑝 𐑞 𐑤𐑩𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑔𐑩𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑤𐑵𐑒𐑕 𐑤𐑲 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑼𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑴 𐑞 𐑤𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑨𐑒, 𐑞𐑱 𐑸 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑰𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑕𐑲𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑯𐑰𐑔 𐑞 𐑕𐑻𐑓𐑦𐑕; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑣𐑰 𐑦𐑟 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑑 𐑐𐑤𐑳𐑯𐑡 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑛𐑰𐑐𐑕, 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑲𐑼 𐑓𐑤𐑵𐑒𐑕 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑰𐑕𐑑 𐑔𐑻𐑑𐑦 𐑓𐑰𐑑 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦 𐑸 𐑑𐑪𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑺, 𐑯 𐑕𐑴 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑱𐑯 𐑝𐑲𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑥𐑴𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑, 𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑞𐑱 𐑛𐑬𐑯𐑢𐑼𐑛𐑟 𐑖𐑵𐑑 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑝𐑿. 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑧𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑲𐑥 𐑚𐑮𐑰𐑗—𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑢𐑺 𐑧𐑤𐑕 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑚𐑛—𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤'𐑟 𐑓𐑤𐑵𐑒𐑕 𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑼𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑕 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑲𐑑 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑕𐑰𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑥𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑯𐑱𐑗𐑼. 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑚𐑪𐑑𐑩𐑥𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑓𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑟 𐑞 𐑡𐑲𐑜𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑑𐑱𐑤 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑟 𐑕𐑐𐑨𐑟𐑥𐑪𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑯𐑨𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑣𐑲𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑯. 𐑕𐑴 𐑦𐑯 𐑛𐑮𐑰𐑥𐑟, 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑲 𐑕𐑰𐑯 𐑥𐑩𐑡𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑒 ·𐑕𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑔𐑮𐑳𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑹𐑔 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑑𐑹𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑕𐑩𐑤 𐑒𐑤𐑷 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑓𐑤𐑱𐑥 ·𐑚𐑷𐑤𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑝 ·𐑣𐑧𐑤. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑜𐑱𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑕𐑰𐑯𐑟, 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑷𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑥𐑵𐑛 𐑿 𐑸 𐑦𐑯; 𐑦𐑓 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑛𐑭𐑯𐑑𐑱𐑾𐑯, 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑩𐑒𐑻 𐑑 𐑿; 𐑦𐑓 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑝 ·𐑲𐑟𐑱𐑩, 𐑞 𐑸𐑒𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑩𐑤𐑟. 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑-𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑝 𐑥𐑲 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑛𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑕𐑳𐑯𐑮𐑲𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑕𐑒𐑲 𐑯 𐑕𐑰, 𐑲 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑕 𐑕𐑷 𐑩 𐑤𐑸𐑡 𐑣𐑻𐑛 𐑝 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑰𐑕𐑑, 𐑷𐑤 𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑑𐑩𐑢𐑹𐑛𐑟 𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑯, 𐑯 𐑓 𐑩 𐑥𐑴𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑝𐑲𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑼𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑑 𐑓𐑤𐑵𐑒𐑕. 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑑 𐑥𐑰 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑑𐑲𐑥, 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩 𐑜𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑥𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑨𐑛𐑼𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑜𐑪𐑛𐑟 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑚𐑦𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑛, 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯 ·𐑐𐑻𐑖𐑩, 𐑞 𐑣𐑴𐑥 𐑝 𐑞 𐑓𐑲𐑼 𐑢𐑻𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑼𐑟. 𐑨𐑟 ·𐑑𐑪𐑤𐑧𐑥𐑦 ·𐑓𐑲𐑤𐑴𐑐𐑱𐑑𐑼 𐑑𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑓𐑲𐑛 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑨𐑓𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑓𐑩𐑯𐑑, 𐑲 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑑𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑓𐑲𐑛 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑯𐑬𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑞 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑝𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑷𐑤 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙𐑟. 𐑓 𐑩𐑒𐑹𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑑 ·𐑒𐑦𐑙 ·𐑡𐑳𐑚𐑩, 𐑞 𐑥𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑺𐑦 𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑓𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑪𐑓𐑩𐑯 𐑣𐑱𐑤𐑛 𐑞 𐑥𐑹𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞𐑺 𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑙𐑒𐑕 𐑳𐑐𐑤𐑦𐑓𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑕.

𐑞 𐑗𐑭𐑯𐑕 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼, 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑢𐑰𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑯 𐑞 𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑓𐑩𐑯𐑑, 𐑕𐑴 𐑓𐑸 𐑨𐑟 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑨𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑑𐑱𐑤 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑯 𐑞 𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑙𐑒 𐑝 𐑞 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑸 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑻𐑯𐑛, 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑑 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑑𐑵 𐑪𐑐𐑩𐑟𐑦𐑑 𐑹𐑜𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑪𐑯 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑦, 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑤𐑧𐑕 𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑰𐑗𐑼𐑟 𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑞𐑱 𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑝𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑪𐑙. 𐑓 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑥𐑲𐑑𐑾𐑕𐑑 𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑓𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑩 𐑑𐑧𐑮𐑽 𐑑 ·𐑤𐑩𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑔𐑩𐑯, 𐑕𐑴, 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑺𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 ·𐑤𐑩𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑔𐑩𐑯'𐑟 𐑑𐑱𐑤, 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑙𐑒 𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑷𐑒 𐑝 𐑩 𐑤𐑦𐑤𐑦. 𐑞 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑛𐑲𐑼𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑚𐑤𐑴 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑓𐑩𐑯𐑑'𐑕 𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑙𐑒 𐑢𐑻 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑑𐑨𐑐 𐑝 𐑩 𐑓𐑨𐑯, 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑺𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑥𐑧𐑠𐑼𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑒𐑮𐑳𐑖 𐑯 𐑒𐑮𐑨𐑖 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 𐑢𐑱𐑤'𐑟 𐑐𐑪𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑩𐑕 𐑓𐑤𐑵𐑒𐑕, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑦𐑯 𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑰𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑞 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑣𐑻𐑤𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑲𐑼 𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑺 𐑹𐑟 𐑯 𐑒𐑮𐑵𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑺, 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑨𐑟 𐑩𐑯 ·𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑾𐑯 𐑡𐑳𐑜𐑩𐑤𐑼 𐑑𐑪𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑷𐑤𐑟.*

*𐑞𐑴 𐑷𐑤 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑱 𐑝 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑚𐑳𐑤𐑒 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑢𐑰𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑯 𐑞 𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑓𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑪𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑩𐑕, 𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑟𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑐𐑼𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑼 𐑞 𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑓𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑 𐑑 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑩 𐑛𐑪𐑜 𐑛𐑳𐑟 𐑑 𐑞 𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑓𐑩𐑯𐑑; 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼𐑞𐑩𐑤𐑧𐑕, 𐑞𐑺 𐑸 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑐𐑶𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑒𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑾𐑕 𐑕𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑿𐑛; 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑦𐑟 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑬𐑑. 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑧𐑤 𐑯𐑴𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑓𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑪𐑓𐑩𐑯 𐑛𐑮𐑷 𐑳𐑐 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼 𐑹 𐑛𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑙𐑒, 𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑝𐑱𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑑, 𐑡𐑧𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑓𐑹𐑔 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑰𐑥.

𐑞 𐑥𐑹 𐑲 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑼 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑥𐑲𐑑𐑦 𐑑𐑱𐑤, 𐑞 𐑥𐑹 𐑛𐑵 𐑲 𐑛𐑦𐑐𐑤𐑹 𐑥𐑲 𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑑 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑕 𐑦𐑑. 𐑨𐑑 𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑞𐑺 𐑸 𐑡𐑧𐑕𐑗𐑼𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑦𐑑, 𐑢𐑦𐑗, 𐑞𐑴 𐑞𐑱 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑢𐑧𐑤 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑕 𐑞 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑝 𐑥𐑨𐑯, 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑱𐑯 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑤𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤. 𐑦𐑯 𐑩𐑯 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑝 𐑣𐑻𐑛, 𐑕𐑴 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑸𐑒𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤, 𐑩𐑒𐑱𐑠𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑤𐑦, 𐑸 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑡𐑧𐑕𐑗𐑼𐑟, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑣𐑻𐑛 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑟 𐑣𐑵 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑺𐑛 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑩𐑒𐑦𐑯 𐑑 ·𐑓𐑮𐑰-·𐑥𐑱𐑕𐑩𐑯 𐑕𐑲𐑯𐑟 𐑯 𐑕𐑦𐑥𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑟; 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑰𐑛, 𐑚𐑲 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑥𐑧𐑔𐑩𐑛𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑡𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑝𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛. 𐑯𐑹 𐑸 𐑞𐑺 𐑢𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑥𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦, 𐑓𐑫𐑤 𐑝 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑯𐑩𐑕, 𐑯 𐑳𐑯𐑩𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑽𐑾𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑩𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑑. 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑧𐑒𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑣𐑬 𐑲 𐑥𐑱, 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑲 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑜𐑴 𐑕𐑒𐑦𐑯 𐑛𐑰𐑐; 𐑲 𐑯𐑴 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑯𐑪𐑑, 𐑯 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑢𐑦𐑤. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑓 𐑲 𐑯𐑴 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑞 𐑑𐑱𐑤 𐑝 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑣𐑬 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑧𐑛? 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑥𐑹, 𐑣𐑬 𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑣𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑱𐑕, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑓𐑱𐑕 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑯𐑳𐑯? 𐑞𐑬 𐑖𐑨𐑤𐑑 𐑕𐑰 𐑥𐑲 𐑚𐑨𐑒 𐑐𐑸𐑑𐑕, 𐑥𐑲 𐑑𐑱𐑤, 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑟 𐑑 𐑕𐑱, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑥𐑲 𐑓𐑱𐑕 𐑖𐑨𐑤 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑕𐑰𐑯. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑲 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑰𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑥𐑱𐑒 𐑬𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑨𐑒 𐑐𐑸𐑑𐑕; 𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑯𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑱𐑕, 𐑲 𐑕𐑱 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑯𐑴 𐑓𐑱𐑕.

·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 87. 𐑞 ·𐑜𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑛 ·𐑸𐑥𐑭𐑛𐑩.

𐑞 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑯 𐑯𐑼𐑴 𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑿𐑤𐑩 𐑝 ·𐑥𐑩𐑤𐑭𐑒𐑩, 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑬𐑔-𐑰𐑕𐑑𐑢𐑼𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑑𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑹𐑦𐑟 𐑝 ·𐑚𐑻𐑥𐑩, 𐑓𐑹𐑥𐑟 𐑞 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑞𐑼𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑶𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑷𐑤 ·𐑱𐑖𐑩. 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑿𐑩𐑕 𐑤𐑲𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑿𐑤𐑩 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑧𐑗 𐑞 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑝 ·𐑕𐑵𐑥𐑭𐑑𐑮𐑩, ·𐑡𐑭𐑝𐑩, ·𐑚𐑨𐑤𐑦, 𐑯 ·𐑑𐑰𐑥𐑹; 𐑢𐑦𐑗, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑳𐑞𐑼𐑟, 𐑓𐑹𐑥 𐑩 𐑝𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑥𐑴𐑤, 𐑹 𐑮𐑨𐑥𐑐𐑸𐑑, 𐑤𐑧𐑙𐑔𐑢𐑲𐑟 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑙 ·𐑱𐑖𐑩 𐑢𐑦𐑞 ·𐑪𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑤𐑾, 𐑯 𐑛𐑦𐑝𐑲𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑳𐑯𐑚𐑮𐑴𐑒𐑩𐑯 ·𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑾𐑯 𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑔𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑛𐑩𐑛 ·𐑹𐑦𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑸𐑒𐑦𐑐𐑧𐑤𐑩𐑜𐑴𐑟. 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑮𐑨𐑥𐑐𐑸𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑽𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑕𐑧𐑝𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑨𐑤𐑦-𐑐𐑹𐑑𐑕 𐑓 𐑞 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑝𐑰𐑯𐑾𐑯𐑕 𐑝 𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑕 𐑯 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟; 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑩𐑕 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑸 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑑𐑕 𐑝 ·𐑕𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑩 𐑯 ·𐑥𐑩𐑤𐑭𐑒𐑩. 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑑𐑕 𐑝 ·𐑕𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑩, 𐑗𐑰𐑓𐑤𐑦, 𐑝𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑚𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑑 ·𐑗𐑲𐑯𐑩 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑢𐑧𐑕𐑑, 𐑦𐑥𐑻𐑡 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 ·𐑗𐑲𐑯𐑩 𐑕𐑰𐑟.

𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑯𐑼𐑴 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑑𐑕 𐑝 ·𐑕𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑩 𐑛𐑦𐑝𐑲𐑛 ·𐑕𐑵𐑥𐑭𐑑𐑮𐑩 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 ·𐑡𐑭𐑝𐑩; 𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑦𐑛𐑢𐑱 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑝𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑮𐑨𐑥𐑐𐑸𐑑 𐑝 𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛𐑟, 𐑚𐑳𐑑𐑮𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑚𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑯 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑦, 𐑯𐑴𐑯 𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑨𐑟 ·𐑡𐑭𐑝𐑩 ·𐑣𐑧𐑛; 𐑞𐑱 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑩 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑒𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑪𐑯𐑛 𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑩𐑤 𐑜𐑱𐑑𐑢𐑱 𐑴𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑝𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑢𐑷𐑤𐑛 𐑧𐑥𐑐𐑲𐑼: 𐑯 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑜𐑟𐑷𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑧𐑤𐑔 𐑝 𐑕𐑐𐑲𐑕𐑩𐑟, 𐑯 𐑕𐑦𐑤𐑒𐑕, 𐑯 𐑡𐑵𐑩𐑤𐑟, 𐑯 𐑜𐑴𐑤𐑛, 𐑯 𐑲𐑝𐑼𐑦, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑞 𐑔𐑬𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑 ·𐑹𐑦𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑰 𐑸 𐑦𐑯𐑮𐑦𐑗𐑑, 𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑟 𐑩 𐑕𐑦𐑜𐑯𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑝𐑦𐑠𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑯𐑱𐑗𐑼, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑑𐑮𐑧𐑠𐑼𐑟, 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑓𐑹𐑥𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛, 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑰𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑺 𐑞 𐑩𐑐𐑽𐑩𐑯𐑕, 𐑣𐑬𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑓𐑧𐑒𐑗𐑵𐑩𐑤, 𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑜𐑸𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑷𐑤-𐑜𐑮𐑭𐑕𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑯 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛. 𐑞 𐑖𐑹𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑑𐑕 𐑝 ·𐑕𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑩 𐑸 𐑳𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑐𐑤𐑲𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑛𐑪𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑽𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑹𐑑𐑮𐑩𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑜𐑸𐑛 𐑞 𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑥𐑧𐑛𐑦𐑑𐑼𐑱𐑯𐑾𐑯, 𐑞 ·𐑚𐑷𐑤𐑑𐑦𐑒, 𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑐𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑕. 𐑳𐑯𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑞 ·𐑛𐑱𐑯𐑟, 𐑞𐑰𐑟 ·𐑹𐑦𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑛𐑵 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑥𐑭𐑯𐑛 𐑞 𐑪𐑚𐑕𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑾𐑕 𐑣𐑪𐑥𐑦𐑡 𐑝 𐑤𐑴𐑼𐑛 𐑑𐑪𐑐-𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑕𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑕 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑞 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑓 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑗𐑼𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑭𐑕𐑑, 𐑚𐑲 𐑯𐑲𐑑 𐑯 𐑚𐑲 𐑛𐑱, 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑐𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑢𐑰𐑯 𐑞 𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑝 ·𐑕𐑵𐑥𐑭𐑑𐑮𐑩 𐑯 ·𐑡𐑭𐑝𐑩, 𐑓𐑮𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑒𐑪𐑕𐑑𐑤𐑾𐑕𐑑 𐑒𐑸𐑜𐑴𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑰𐑕𐑑. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑞𐑱 𐑓𐑮𐑰𐑤𐑦 𐑢𐑱𐑝 𐑩 𐑕𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑾𐑤 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑞𐑦𐑕, 𐑞𐑱 𐑛𐑵 𐑚𐑲 𐑯𐑴 𐑥𐑰𐑯𐑟 𐑮𐑦𐑯𐑬𐑯𐑕 𐑞𐑺 𐑒𐑤𐑱𐑥 𐑑 𐑥𐑹 𐑕𐑪𐑤𐑦𐑛 𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑚𐑿𐑑.

𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑥𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑞 𐑐𐑲𐑮𐑨𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑐𐑮𐑴𐑩𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑥𐑩𐑤𐑱𐑟, 𐑤𐑻𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑞 𐑤𐑴 𐑖𐑱𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑒𐑴𐑝𐑟 𐑯 𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑑𐑕 𐑝 ·𐑕𐑵𐑥𐑭𐑑𐑮𐑩, 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑕𐑨𐑤𐑦𐑛 𐑬𐑑 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑝𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑑𐑕, 𐑓𐑽𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑦𐑥𐑭𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑚𐑿𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑐𐑶𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑞𐑺 𐑕𐑐𐑽𐑟. 𐑞𐑴 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑰𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑤𐑳𐑛𐑦 𐑗𐑨𐑕𐑑𐑲𐑟𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑞𐑱 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑰𐑝𐑛 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑝 ·𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑩𐑐𐑾𐑯 𐑒𐑮𐑵𐑟𐑼𐑟, 𐑞 𐑷𐑛𐑨𐑕𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑝 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑒𐑹𐑕𐑺𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑝 𐑤𐑱𐑑 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑑; 𐑘𐑧𐑑, 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑛𐑱, 𐑢𐑰 𐑩𐑒𐑱𐑠𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑣𐑽 𐑝 ·𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑤𐑦𐑖 𐑯 ·𐑩𐑥𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑝𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑤𐑟, 𐑢𐑦𐑗, 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼𐑟, 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑹𐑕𐑤𐑩𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑹𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑯 𐑐𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑡𐑛.

𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑓𐑺, 𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑖 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛, 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑬 𐑛𐑮𐑷𐑦𐑙 𐑯𐑲 𐑑 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑑𐑕; ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑐𐑻𐑐𐑩𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑐𐑭𐑕 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 ·𐑡𐑭𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑕𐑰, 𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯𐑕, 𐑒𐑮𐑵𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑯𐑹𐑔𐑢𐑼𐑛𐑟, 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼𐑟 𐑯𐑴𐑯 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑓𐑮𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑣𐑽 𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑕𐑢𐑰𐑐 𐑦𐑯𐑖𐑹 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 ·𐑓𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑐𐑰𐑯 ·𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛𐑟, 𐑯 𐑜𐑱𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑸 𐑒𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑝 ·𐑡𐑩𐑐𐑨𐑯, 𐑦𐑯 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑓 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑰𐑟𐑩𐑯 𐑞𐑺. 𐑚𐑲 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑥𐑰𐑯𐑟, 𐑞 𐑕𐑻𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑯𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑜𐑱𐑑𐑦𐑙 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑕𐑢𐑰𐑐 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑯𐑴𐑯 ·𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑒𐑮𐑵𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑜𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛, 𐑐𐑮𐑰𐑝𐑾𐑕 𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑤𐑲𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑩𐑕𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑒; 𐑢𐑺 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚, 𐑞𐑴 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦𐑢𐑺 𐑧𐑤𐑕 𐑓𐑶𐑤𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑼𐑕𐑿𐑑, 𐑓𐑻𐑥𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑜𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑨𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑑 ·𐑥𐑪𐑚𐑦 ·𐑛𐑦𐑒, 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑰 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑯𐑴𐑯 𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑩𐑯𐑑; 𐑯 𐑨𐑑 𐑩 𐑕𐑰𐑟𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑣𐑰 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑮𐑰𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑰 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑿𐑥𐑛 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑣𐑷𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑑.

𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑣𐑬 𐑯𐑬? 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑟𐑴𐑯𐑛 𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑕𐑑, 𐑛𐑳𐑟 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑑𐑳𐑗 𐑯𐑴 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛? 𐑛𐑳𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑮𐑵 𐑛𐑮𐑦𐑙𐑒 𐑺? 𐑖𐑫𐑼𐑤𐑦, 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑕𐑑𐑪𐑐 𐑓 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼. 𐑯𐑱. 𐑓 𐑩 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑑𐑲𐑥, 𐑯𐑬, 𐑞 𐑕𐑻𐑒𐑩𐑕-𐑮𐑳𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑳𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑮𐑱𐑕𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑲𐑼𐑦 𐑮𐑦𐑙, 𐑯 𐑯𐑰𐑛𐑟 𐑯𐑴 𐑕𐑳𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑑'𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓. 𐑕𐑴 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚. 𐑥𐑸𐑒 𐑞𐑦𐑕, 𐑑𐑵, 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑼. 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑣𐑳𐑤𐑟 𐑸 𐑤𐑴𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑱𐑤𐑾𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑓, 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑕𐑓𐑻𐑛 𐑑 𐑓𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑹𐑝𐑟; 𐑞 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛-𐑢𐑪𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑱𐑤-𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑒𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑴 𐑒𐑸𐑜𐑴 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑣𐑻𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑯 𐑒𐑮𐑵, 𐑞𐑺 𐑢𐑧𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑢𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑕. 𐑖𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑩 𐑣𐑴𐑤 𐑤𐑱𐑒'𐑕 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑚𐑪𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑻 𐑨𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑤 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛. 𐑖𐑰 𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑨𐑤𐑩𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑿𐑑𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑟; 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑷𐑤𐑑𐑩𐑜𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑳𐑯𐑿𐑟𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑐𐑦𐑜-𐑤𐑧𐑛 𐑯 𐑒𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑧𐑡. 𐑖𐑰 𐑒𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑟 𐑘𐑽𐑟' 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑻. 𐑒𐑤𐑽 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑐𐑮𐑲𐑥 ·𐑯𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑑 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼; 𐑢𐑦𐑗, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑘𐑽𐑟 𐑩𐑓𐑤𐑴𐑑, 𐑞 ·𐑯𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑑𐑼, 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑩𐑕𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑒, 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑓𐑻𐑟 𐑑 𐑛𐑮𐑦𐑙𐑒 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑞 𐑚𐑮𐑨𐑒𐑦𐑖 𐑓𐑤𐑵𐑦𐑛, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑘𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑛𐑱 𐑮𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑪𐑓 𐑦𐑯 𐑒𐑭𐑕𐑒𐑕, 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑼𐑵𐑝𐑾𐑯 𐑹 ·𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑾𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑰𐑥𐑟. 𐑣𐑧𐑯𐑕 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟, 𐑞𐑨𐑑, 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑕 𐑥𐑱 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑜𐑪𐑯 𐑑 ·𐑗𐑲𐑯𐑩 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 ·𐑯𐑿 ·𐑘𐑹𐑒, 𐑯 𐑚𐑨𐑒 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯, 𐑑𐑳𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑨𐑑 𐑩 𐑕𐑒𐑹 𐑝 𐑐𐑹𐑑𐑕, 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤-𐑖𐑦𐑐, 𐑦𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑝𐑩𐑤, 𐑥𐑱 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑕𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑯 𐑝 𐑕𐑶𐑤; 𐑣𐑻 𐑒𐑮𐑵 𐑣𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑰𐑯 𐑯𐑴 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑓𐑤𐑴𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑞𐑧𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑝𐑟. 𐑕𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑿 𐑒𐑨𐑮𐑦 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑞 𐑯𐑿𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑩𐑯𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑓𐑤𐑳𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑒𐑳𐑥; 𐑞𐑱 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑼—“𐑢𐑧𐑤, 𐑚𐑶𐑟, 𐑣𐑽'𐑟 𐑞 𐑸𐑒!”

𐑯𐑬, 𐑨𐑟 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 ·𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑗𐑼𐑛 𐑪𐑓 𐑞 𐑢𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑯 𐑒𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑝 ·𐑡𐑭𐑝𐑩, 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑯𐑽 𐑝𐑦𐑕𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑑𐑕 𐑝 ·𐑕𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑩; 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑰𐑛, 𐑨𐑟 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛, 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑, 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑩𐑜𐑯𐑲𐑟𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑼𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑨𐑟 𐑩𐑯 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑩𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑕𐑐𐑪𐑑 𐑓 𐑒𐑮𐑵𐑟𐑦𐑙; 𐑞𐑺𐑓𐑹, 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛 𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑛 𐑥𐑹 𐑯 𐑥𐑹 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 ·𐑡𐑭𐑝𐑩 ·𐑣𐑧𐑛, 𐑞 𐑤𐑫𐑒-𐑬𐑑𐑕 𐑢𐑻 𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑰𐑑𐑩𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑣𐑱𐑤𐑛, 𐑯 𐑨𐑛𐑥𐑪𐑯𐑦𐑖𐑑 𐑑 𐑒𐑰𐑐 𐑢𐑲𐑛 𐑩𐑢𐑱𐑒. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞𐑴 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑯 𐑐𐑭𐑥𐑦 𐑒𐑤𐑦𐑓𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑕𐑵𐑯 𐑤𐑵𐑥𐑛 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑼𐑛 𐑚𐑬, 𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑞 𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑖 𐑕𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑯𐑳𐑓𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑺, 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑩 𐑕𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑩𐑤 𐑡𐑧𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛. 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑯𐑬𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑷𐑤 𐑔𐑷𐑑 𐑝 𐑓𐑷𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑜𐑱𐑥 𐑣𐑽𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑𐑕, 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑢𐑧𐑤 𐑯𐑲 𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑛 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑑𐑕, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑞 𐑒𐑳𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑥𐑼𐑦 𐑗𐑽𐑦𐑙 𐑒𐑮𐑲 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑣𐑻𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑓𐑑, 𐑯 𐑺 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑩 𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑕𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑿𐑤𐑼 𐑥𐑨𐑜𐑯𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑕𐑩𐑤𐑵𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑳𐑕.

𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑣𐑽 𐑚𐑰 𐑦𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑲𐑟𐑛, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑞 𐑳𐑯𐑢𐑽𐑦𐑛 𐑨𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑝 𐑤𐑱𐑑 𐑞𐑱 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑷𐑤 𐑓𐑹 𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟, 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟, 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑛 𐑝 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑺𐑾𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑥𐑷𐑤 𐑛𐑦𐑑𐑨𐑗𐑑 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑟, 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑓𐑹𐑥𐑼 𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟, 𐑸 𐑯𐑬 𐑓𐑮𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑥𐑧𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑦𐑯 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑝 𐑣𐑻𐑛𐑟, 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑦𐑥𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑴 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑩 𐑥𐑳𐑤𐑑𐑦𐑑𐑿𐑛, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑥 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑓 𐑯𐑿𐑥𐑼𐑩𐑕 𐑯𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑕𐑢𐑹𐑯 𐑕𐑪𐑤𐑩𐑥 𐑤𐑰𐑜 𐑯 𐑒𐑳𐑝𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑓 𐑥𐑿𐑗𐑵𐑩𐑤 𐑩𐑕𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑯 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑑𐑧𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯. 𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑨𐑜𐑮𐑦𐑜𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑦𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑕 𐑒𐑨𐑮𐑩𐑝𐑨𐑯𐑟, 𐑥𐑱 𐑚𐑰 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑿𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑞 𐑕𐑻𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑕 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑒𐑮𐑵𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑜𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑟, 𐑿 𐑥𐑱 𐑯𐑬 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑕𐑱𐑤 𐑓 𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑕 𐑯 𐑥𐑳𐑯𐑔𐑕 𐑑𐑩𐑜𐑧𐑞𐑼, 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑩 𐑕𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑐𐑬𐑑; 𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑚𐑰 𐑕𐑳𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑩𐑤𐑵𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑟 𐑔𐑬𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑪𐑯 𐑔𐑬𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑛𐑟.

𐑚𐑮𐑷𐑛 𐑪𐑯 𐑚𐑴𐑔 𐑚𐑬𐑟, 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑝 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑑𐑵 𐑹 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑥𐑲𐑤𐑟, 𐑯 𐑓𐑹𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑕𐑧𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑻𐑒𐑩𐑤, 𐑦𐑥𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑣𐑭𐑓 𐑝 𐑞 𐑤𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑤 𐑣𐑼𐑲𐑟𐑩𐑯, 𐑩 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑿𐑩𐑕 𐑗𐑱𐑯 𐑝 𐑢𐑱𐑤-𐑡𐑧𐑑𐑕 𐑢𐑻 𐑳𐑐-𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑦𐑙 𐑯 𐑕𐑐𐑸𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑯𐑵𐑯-𐑛𐑱 𐑺. 𐑳𐑯𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑐𐑻𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑼 𐑑𐑢𐑦𐑯-𐑡𐑧𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑮𐑲𐑑 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑢𐑦𐑗, 𐑛𐑦𐑝𐑲𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑨𐑑 𐑑𐑪𐑐, 𐑓𐑷𐑤 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑦𐑯 𐑑𐑵 𐑚𐑮𐑭𐑯𐑗𐑩𐑟, 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑞 𐑒𐑤𐑧𐑓𐑑 𐑛𐑮𐑵𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑬𐑟 𐑝 𐑩 𐑢𐑦𐑤𐑴, 𐑞 𐑕𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑩𐑤 𐑓𐑹𐑢𐑼𐑛-𐑕𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑐𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑩 𐑔𐑦𐑒 𐑒𐑻𐑤𐑛 𐑚𐑫𐑖 𐑝 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑑, 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑿𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑲𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑯 𐑓𐑷𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑢𐑱 𐑑 𐑤𐑰𐑢𐑼𐑛.

𐑕𐑰𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛'𐑟 𐑛𐑧𐑒, 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑨𐑟 𐑖𐑰 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑮𐑲𐑟 𐑪𐑯 𐑩 𐑣𐑲 𐑣𐑦𐑤 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑰, 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑣𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑝 𐑝𐑱𐑐𐑼𐑦 𐑕𐑐𐑬𐑑𐑕, 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑡𐑵𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑻𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑳𐑐 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑺, 𐑯 𐑚𐑦𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑛 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑩 𐑚𐑤𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑨𐑑𐑥𐑩𐑕𐑓𐑽 𐑝 𐑚𐑤𐑵𐑦𐑖 𐑣𐑱𐑟, 𐑖𐑴𐑛 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑞 𐑔𐑬𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑗𐑽𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑗𐑦𐑥𐑯𐑦𐑟 𐑝 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑛𐑧𐑯𐑕 𐑥𐑩𐑑𐑮𐑪𐑐𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑕, 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 𐑝 𐑩 𐑚𐑭𐑥𐑦 𐑷𐑑𐑳𐑥𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑥𐑹𐑯𐑦𐑙, 𐑚𐑲 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑣𐑹𐑕𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑪𐑯 𐑩 𐑣𐑲𐑑.

𐑨𐑟 𐑥𐑸𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑸𐑥𐑦𐑟 𐑩𐑐𐑮𐑴𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑯 𐑳𐑯𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑦𐑓𐑲𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑥𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑟, 𐑩𐑒𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑼𐑱𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑥𐑸𐑗, 𐑷𐑤 𐑰𐑜𐑼𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑑 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑐𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑐𐑨𐑕𐑦𐑡 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑮𐑽, 𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑕 𐑥𐑹 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑨𐑮𐑩𐑑𐑦𐑝 𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑯; 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑕𐑴 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑝𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑓𐑤𐑰𐑑 𐑝 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑯𐑬 𐑕𐑰𐑥 𐑣𐑳𐑮𐑦𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑹𐑢𐑼𐑛 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑑𐑕; 𐑜𐑮𐑨𐑡𐑵𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑢𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑝 𐑞𐑺 𐑕𐑧𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑻𐑒𐑩𐑤, 𐑯 𐑕𐑢𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑪𐑯, 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑕𐑪𐑤𐑦𐑛, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑒𐑮𐑧𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑼.

𐑒𐑮𐑬𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑷𐑤 𐑕𐑱𐑤 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑞𐑧𐑥; 𐑞 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑽𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑺 𐑢𐑧𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑟, 𐑯 𐑤𐑬𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑗𐑽𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑟 𐑝 𐑞𐑺 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑕𐑩𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕. 𐑦𐑓 𐑞 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑛, 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑛𐑬𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑞𐑱, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑗𐑱𐑕𐑑 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑞𐑰𐑟 ·𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑑𐑕 𐑝 ·𐑕𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑩, 𐑞 𐑝𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑦𐑐𐑤𐑶 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 ·𐑹𐑦𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑰𐑟 𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑑𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑞 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑗𐑼 𐑝 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑩 𐑓𐑿 𐑝 𐑞𐑺 𐑯𐑳𐑥𐑚𐑼. 𐑯 𐑣𐑵 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑑𐑧𐑤 𐑢𐑧𐑞𐑼, 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑒𐑪𐑙𐑜𐑮𐑦𐑜𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑒𐑨𐑮𐑩𐑝𐑨𐑯, ·𐑥𐑪𐑚𐑦 ·𐑛𐑦𐑒 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑑𐑧𐑥𐑐𐑼𐑺𐑦𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑰 𐑕𐑢𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑙, 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑞 𐑢𐑻𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑑 𐑢𐑲𐑑-𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑓𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑒𐑪𐑮𐑩𐑯𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑕𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑲𐑩𐑥𐑰𐑟! 𐑕𐑴 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑯-𐑕𐑱𐑤 𐑐𐑲𐑤𐑛 𐑪𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑯-𐑕𐑱𐑤, 𐑢𐑰 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑛 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑙, 𐑛𐑮𐑲𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑤𐑩𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑔𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑳𐑕; 𐑢𐑧𐑯, 𐑝 𐑩 𐑕𐑳𐑛𐑩𐑯, 𐑞 𐑝𐑶𐑕 𐑝 ·𐑑𐑨𐑖𐑑𐑱𐑜𐑴 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑣𐑻𐑛, 𐑤𐑬𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑦𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑬𐑼 𐑢𐑱𐑒.

𐑒𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑪𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑧𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑬𐑼 𐑝𐑨𐑯, 𐑢𐑰 𐑚𐑦𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑛 𐑩𐑯𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑦𐑯 𐑬𐑼 𐑮𐑽. 𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑓𐑹𐑥𐑛 𐑝 𐑛𐑦𐑑𐑨𐑗𐑑 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑝𐑱𐑐𐑼𐑟, 𐑮𐑲𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑯 𐑓𐑷𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑬𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟; 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑞𐑱 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑴 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑰𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑯 𐑜𐑴; 𐑓 𐑞𐑱 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑣𐑪𐑝𐑼𐑛, 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑 𐑓𐑲𐑯𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑩𐑐𐑽𐑦𐑙. 𐑤𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑜𐑤𐑭𐑕 𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑕𐑲𐑑, ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑦𐑝𐑪𐑤𐑝𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑦𐑝𐑩𐑑-𐑣𐑴𐑤, 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑦𐑙, “𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑓𐑑 𐑞𐑺, 𐑯 𐑮𐑦𐑜 𐑢𐑦𐑐𐑕 𐑯 𐑚𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑑𐑕 𐑑 𐑢𐑧𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑟;—·𐑥𐑩𐑤𐑱𐑟, 𐑕𐑻, 𐑯 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑳𐑕!”

𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑓 𐑑𐑵 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑤𐑻𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑦𐑣𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑞 𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛𐑟, 𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑓𐑺𐑤𐑦 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑛 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑑𐑕, 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑮𐑭𐑕𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑦 ·𐑱𐑠𐑦𐑨𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑕 𐑢𐑻 𐑯𐑬 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑪𐑑 𐑐𐑼𐑕𐑿𐑑, 𐑑 𐑥𐑱𐑒 𐑳𐑐 𐑓 𐑞𐑺 𐑴𐑝𐑼-𐑒𐑷𐑖𐑩𐑕 𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑱. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑢𐑦𐑓𐑑 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑖 𐑤𐑰𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛, 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑣𐑻𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑪𐑑 𐑗𐑱𐑕; 𐑣𐑬 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑒𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑝 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑑𐑷𐑯𐑦 𐑓𐑦𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑔𐑮𐑪𐑐𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑕 𐑑 𐑩𐑕𐑦𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑻 𐑪𐑯 𐑑 𐑣𐑻 𐑴𐑯 𐑗𐑴𐑟𐑩𐑯 𐑐𐑼𐑕𐑿𐑑,—𐑥𐑽 𐑮𐑲𐑛𐑦𐑙-𐑢𐑦𐑐𐑕 𐑯 𐑮𐑬𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑑 𐑣𐑻, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑱 𐑢𐑻. 𐑨𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑜𐑤𐑭𐑕 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑸𐑥, ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑑-𐑯-𐑓𐑮𐑴 𐑐𐑱𐑕𐑑 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑒; 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑹𐑢𐑼𐑛 𐑑𐑻𐑯 𐑚𐑦𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑥𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑗𐑱𐑕𐑑, 𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑤𐑳𐑛𐑔𐑻𐑕𐑑𐑦 𐑐𐑲𐑮𐑩𐑑𐑕 𐑗𐑱𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑥; 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑓𐑨𐑯𐑕𐑦 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑩𐑚𐑳𐑝 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟. 𐑯 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑣𐑰 𐑜𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑯 𐑢𐑷𐑤𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼𐑦 𐑛𐑦𐑓𐑲𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙, 𐑯 𐑚𐑦𐑔𐑷𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑜𐑱𐑑 𐑤𐑱 𐑞 𐑮𐑵𐑑 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑝𐑧𐑯𐑡𐑩𐑯𐑕, 𐑯 𐑚𐑦𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑛, 𐑣𐑬 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑜𐑱𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑬 𐑚𐑴𐑔 𐑗𐑱𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑯 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑗𐑱𐑕𐑑 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑛𐑧𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑧𐑯𐑛; 𐑯 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑞𐑨𐑑, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑩 𐑣𐑻𐑛 𐑝 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑹𐑕𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑢𐑲𐑤𐑛 𐑐𐑲𐑮𐑩𐑑𐑕 𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑣𐑿𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑱𐑔𐑦𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑛𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑦𐑯𐑓𐑻𐑯𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑗𐑽𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑪𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞𐑺 𐑒𐑻𐑕𐑩𐑟;—𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑰𐑑𐑕 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑐𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑯, ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚'𐑟 𐑚𐑮𐑬 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑤𐑧𐑓𐑑 𐑜𐑷𐑯𐑑 𐑯 𐑮𐑦𐑚𐑛, 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑞 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑒 𐑕𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑚𐑰𐑗 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑕𐑑𐑹𐑥𐑦 𐑑𐑲𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑯𐑷𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑑, 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑱𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑑 𐑛𐑮𐑨𐑜 𐑞 𐑓𐑻𐑥 𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕.

𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑔𐑷𐑑𐑕 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑓𐑿 𐑝 𐑞 𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑒𐑮𐑵; 𐑯 𐑢𐑧𐑯, 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑮𐑪𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑯 𐑛𐑮𐑪𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑐𐑲𐑮𐑩𐑑𐑕 𐑩𐑕𐑑𐑻𐑯, 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑖𐑪𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑝𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑛 𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑯 ·𐑒𐑪𐑒𐑩𐑑𐑵 ·𐑐𐑶𐑯𐑑 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑵𐑥𐑭𐑑𐑮𐑩 𐑕𐑲𐑛, 𐑦𐑥𐑻𐑡𐑦𐑙 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑮𐑷𐑛 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼𐑟 𐑚𐑦𐑘𐑪𐑯𐑛; 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑞 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑽𐑟 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑥𐑹 𐑑 𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑢𐑦𐑓𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐, 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑡𐑶𐑕 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑕𐑴 𐑝𐑦𐑒𐑑𐑹𐑾𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑛 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑥𐑩𐑤𐑱𐑟. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑛𐑮𐑲𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑪𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑒 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟, 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑧𐑙𐑔 𐑞𐑱 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑩𐑚𐑱𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑺 𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑛; 𐑜𐑮𐑨𐑡𐑵𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑯𐑽𐑛 𐑞𐑧𐑥; 𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛 𐑯𐑬 𐑛𐑲𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑢𐑱, 𐑢𐑻𐑛 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑐𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑑 𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑯𐑴 𐑕𐑵𐑯𐑼 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑞 𐑣𐑻𐑛, 𐑚𐑲 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑿𐑥𐑛 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑯𐑴𐑑𐑦𐑓𐑲𐑛 𐑝 𐑞 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑒𐑰𐑤𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑻 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑞𐑧𐑥,—𐑞𐑴 𐑨𐑟 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑩 𐑥𐑲𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑮𐑽,—𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑞𐑱 𐑮𐑨𐑤𐑦𐑛 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯, 𐑯 𐑓𐑹𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑒𐑤𐑴𐑕 𐑮𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑕 𐑯 𐑚𐑩𐑑𐑨𐑤𐑾𐑯𐑟, 𐑕𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑕𐑐𐑬𐑑𐑕 𐑷𐑤 𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑑 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑓𐑤𐑨𐑖𐑦𐑙 𐑤𐑲𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑒𐑑 𐑚𐑱𐑩𐑯𐑧𐑑𐑕, 𐑥𐑵𐑝𐑛 𐑪𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑮𐑦𐑛𐑳𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑝𐑦𐑤𐑪𐑕𐑦𐑑𐑦.

𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑑 𐑑 𐑬𐑼 𐑖𐑻𐑑𐑕 𐑯 𐑛𐑮𐑷𐑼𐑟, 𐑢𐑰 𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑨𐑙 𐑑 𐑞 𐑢𐑲𐑑-𐑨𐑖, 𐑯 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑕𐑧𐑝𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑬𐑼𐑟' 𐑐𐑫𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑻 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑴𐑟𐑛 𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑯𐑬𐑯𐑕 𐑞 𐑗𐑱𐑕, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑩 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑐𐑷𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑜𐑱𐑝 𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑥𐑱𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑑𐑴𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑱 𐑢𐑻 𐑯𐑬 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑓𐑤𐑵𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡 𐑐𐑼𐑐𐑤𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑝 𐑦𐑯𐑻𐑑 𐑦𐑮𐑧𐑟𐑩𐑤𐑵𐑖𐑩𐑯, 𐑢𐑦𐑗, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑼𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑐𐑼𐑕𐑰𐑝 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑞𐑱 𐑕𐑱 𐑣𐑰 𐑦𐑟 𐑜𐑨𐑤𐑦𐑛. 𐑞 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑨𐑒𐑑 𐑥𐑸𐑖𐑩𐑤 𐑒𐑪𐑤𐑩𐑥𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑞𐑱 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑞𐑼𐑑𐑵 𐑮𐑨𐑐𐑦𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑢𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑙, 𐑢𐑻 𐑯𐑬 𐑚𐑮𐑴𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑳𐑐 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑥𐑧𐑠𐑼𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑮𐑬𐑑; 𐑯 𐑤𐑲𐑒 ·𐑒𐑦𐑙 ·𐑐𐑹𐑩𐑕' 𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑓𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑾𐑯 𐑚𐑨𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑦𐑞 ·𐑨𐑤𐑦𐑜𐑟𐑭𐑯𐑛𐑼, 𐑞𐑱 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑜𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑨𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑯𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯. 𐑦𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑛𐑦𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑝𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑮𐑧𐑜𐑿𐑤𐑼 𐑕𐑻𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑟, 𐑯 𐑱𐑥𐑤𐑩𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑢𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑞𐑼 𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑞𐑼, 𐑚𐑲 𐑞𐑺 𐑖𐑹𐑑 𐑔𐑦𐑒 𐑕𐑐𐑬𐑑𐑦𐑙𐑟, 𐑞𐑱 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑛 𐑞𐑺 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑐𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑒. 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑥𐑹 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑝 𐑞𐑺 𐑯𐑳𐑥𐑚𐑼, 𐑣𐑵, 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑰𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑨𐑮𐑩𐑤𐑲𐑟𐑛 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑻, 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑐𐑤𐑩𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑓𐑤𐑴𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼-𐑤𐑪𐑜𐑛 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑥𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑕 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑰. 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑞𐑰𐑟 ·𐑤𐑩𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑔𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑩 𐑓𐑤𐑪𐑒 𐑝 𐑕𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑤 𐑖𐑰𐑐, 𐑐𐑼𐑕𐑿𐑛 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑞 𐑐𐑭𐑕𐑗𐑼 𐑚𐑲 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑓𐑽𐑕 𐑢𐑫𐑤𐑝𐑟, 𐑞𐑱 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑐𐑪𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑧𐑕𐑦𐑝 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑥𐑱. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑩𐑒𐑱𐑠𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑑𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑛𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑨𐑮𐑩𐑒𐑑𐑼𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑝 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑣𐑻𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑒𐑮𐑰𐑗𐑼𐑟. 𐑞𐑴 𐑚𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑑𐑩𐑜𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑦𐑯 𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑔𐑬𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑛𐑟, 𐑞 𐑤𐑲𐑩𐑯-𐑥𐑱𐑯𐑛 𐑚𐑳𐑓𐑩𐑤𐑴𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑢𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑓𐑤𐑧𐑛 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑩 𐑕𐑪𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑼𐑦 𐑣𐑹𐑕𐑥𐑩𐑯. 𐑢𐑦𐑑𐑯𐑩𐑕, 𐑑𐑵, 𐑷𐑤 𐑣𐑿𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙𐑟, 𐑣𐑬 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑣𐑻𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑑𐑩𐑜𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑖𐑰𐑐𐑓𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑝 𐑩 𐑔𐑾𐑑𐑼'𐑟 𐑐𐑦𐑑, 𐑞𐑱 𐑢𐑦𐑤, 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑤𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑩𐑤𐑸𐑥 𐑝 𐑓𐑲𐑼, 𐑮𐑳𐑖 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑑𐑼-𐑕𐑒𐑧𐑤𐑑𐑼 𐑓 𐑞 𐑬𐑑𐑤𐑧𐑑𐑕, 𐑒𐑮𐑬𐑛𐑦𐑙, 𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙, 𐑡𐑨𐑥𐑦𐑙, 𐑯 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑹𐑕𐑤𐑩𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑨𐑖𐑦𐑙 𐑰𐑗 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑑 𐑛𐑧𐑔. 𐑚𐑧𐑕𐑑, 𐑞𐑺𐑓𐑹, 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑩𐑥𐑱𐑟𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑤𐑦 𐑜𐑨𐑤𐑦𐑛 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑳𐑕, 𐑓 𐑞𐑺 𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑴 𐑓𐑪𐑤𐑦 𐑝 𐑞 𐑚𐑰𐑕𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑻𐑔 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑓𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑬𐑑𐑛𐑳𐑯 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑥𐑨𐑛𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑥𐑧𐑯.

𐑞𐑴 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟, 𐑨𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑕𐑧𐑛, 𐑢𐑻 𐑦𐑯 𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑥𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯, 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑩𐑚𐑟𐑻𐑝𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑩 𐑣𐑴𐑤 𐑞 𐑣𐑻𐑛 𐑯𐑲𐑞𐑼 𐑩𐑛𐑝𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑯𐑹 𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑮𐑰𐑑𐑩𐑛, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑝𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑱𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕. 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑳𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑥𐑼𐑦 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑒𐑱𐑕𐑩𐑟, 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕 𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑕 𐑕𐑧𐑐𐑼𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛, 𐑰𐑗 𐑥𐑱𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑓 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑤𐑴𐑯 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑬𐑑𐑕𐑒𐑻𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑖𐑴𐑤. 𐑦𐑯 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑕' 𐑑𐑲𐑥, ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜'𐑟 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑓𐑤𐑳𐑙; 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑓𐑦𐑖 𐑛𐑸𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑤𐑲𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑱 𐑦𐑯 𐑬𐑼 𐑓𐑱𐑕𐑩𐑟, 𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑮𐑳𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑢𐑱 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑳𐑕 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑤𐑲𐑑, 𐑕𐑑𐑽𐑛 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑓 𐑞 𐑣𐑸𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑣𐑻𐑛. 𐑞𐑴 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩 𐑥𐑵𐑝𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑐𐑸𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑒 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑕𐑻𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟, 𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑯𐑴 𐑢𐑲𐑟 𐑳𐑯𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛; 𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑰𐑛 𐑦𐑟 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑷𐑤𐑢𐑱𐑟 𐑥𐑹 𐑹 𐑤𐑧𐑕 𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑕𐑦𐑐𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛; 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑛𐑳𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑥𐑹 𐑐𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑝𐑦𐑕𐑦𐑕𐑦𐑑𐑿𐑛𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑼𐑦. 𐑓 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑕𐑢𐑦𐑓𐑑 𐑥𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑼 𐑛𐑮𐑨𐑜𐑟 𐑿 𐑛𐑰𐑐𐑼 𐑯 𐑛𐑰𐑐𐑼 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑓𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑖𐑴𐑤, 𐑿 𐑚𐑦𐑛 𐑩𐑛𐑿 𐑑 𐑕𐑻𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑 𐑤𐑲𐑓 𐑯 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑜𐑟𐑦𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑽𐑾𐑕 𐑔𐑮𐑪𐑚.

𐑨𐑟, 𐑚𐑤𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑯 𐑛𐑧𐑓, 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑐𐑤𐑳𐑯𐑡𐑛 𐑓𐑹𐑢𐑼𐑛, 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑓 𐑚𐑲 𐑖𐑽 𐑐𐑬𐑼 𐑝 𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑛 𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑝 𐑞 𐑲𐑼𐑯 𐑤𐑰𐑗 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑓𐑭𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥; 𐑨𐑟 𐑢𐑰 𐑞𐑳𐑕 𐑑𐑹 𐑩 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑜𐑨𐑖 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑰, 𐑪𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑕𐑲𐑛𐑟 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑢𐑰 𐑓𐑤𐑵, 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑱𐑟𐑛 𐑒𐑮𐑰𐑗𐑼𐑟 𐑑 𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑴 𐑮𐑳𐑖𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑳𐑕; 𐑬𐑼 𐑚𐑦𐑕𐑧𐑑 𐑚𐑴𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑥𐑪𐑚𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑲𐑕-𐑲𐑤𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑑𐑧𐑥𐑐𐑦𐑕𐑑, 𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑽 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑞𐑺 𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑦𐑒𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑗𐑨𐑯𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑑𐑕, 𐑯𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑥𐑴𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑥𐑱 𐑚𐑰 𐑤𐑪𐑒𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑯 𐑒𐑮𐑳𐑖𐑑.

𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑩 𐑚𐑦𐑑 𐑛𐑷𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛, ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜 𐑕𐑑𐑽𐑛 𐑳𐑕 𐑥𐑨𐑯𐑓𐑩𐑤𐑦; 𐑯𐑬 𐑖𐑽𐑦𐑙 𐑪𐑓 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑥𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑼 𐑛𐑦𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑩𐑒𐑮𐑪𐑕 𐑬𐑼 𐑮𐑵𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑩𐑛𐑝𐑭𐑯𐑕; 𐑯𐑬 𐑧𐑡𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑢𐑱 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞𐑨𐑑, 𐑣𐑵𐑟 𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑕𐑩𐑤 𐑓𐑤𐑵𐑒𐑕 𐑢𐑻 𐑕𐑩𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑴𐑝𐑼𐑣𐑧𐑛, 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑑𐑲𐑥, ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒 𐑕𐑑𐑫𐑛 𐑳𐑐 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑬𐑟, 𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛, 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑬𐑼 𐑢𐑱 𐑢𐑪𐑑𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑮𐑰𐑗 𐑚𐑲 𐑖𐑹𐑑 𐑛𐑸𐑑𐑕, 𐑓 𐑞𐑺 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑴 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑑 𐑥𐑱𐑒 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑟. 𐑯𐑹 𐑢𐑻 𐑞 𐑹𐑟𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑒𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑲𐑛𐑩𐑤, 𐑞𐑴 𐑞𐑺 𐑢𐑴𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑛𐑿𐑑𐑦 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑬 𐑷𐑤𐑑𐑩𐑜𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞. 𐑞𐑱 𐑗𐑰𐑓𐑤𐑦 𐑩𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑑 𐑞 𐑖𐑬𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑐𐑸𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑚𐑦𐑟𐑯𐑩𐑕. “𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑱, ·𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑛𐑹!” 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 𐑢𐑳𐑯, 𐑑 𐑩 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑛𐑮𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑛𐑼𐑦 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑝 𐑩 𐑕𐑳𐑛𐑩𐑯 𐑮𐑴𐑟 𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑦 𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑻𐑓𐑦𐑕, 𐑯 𐑓 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑔𐑮𐑧𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑑 𐑕𐑢𐑪𐑥𐑐 𐑳𐑕. “𐑣𐑸𐑛 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑘𐑹 𐑑𐑱𐑤, 𐑞𐑺!” 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 𐑩 𐑕𐑧𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑑 𐑩𐑯𐑳𐑞𐑼, 𐑢𐑦𐑗, 𐑒𐑤𐑴𐑕 𐑑 𐑬𐑼 𐑜𐑳𐑯𐑩𐑤, 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑒𐑭𐑥𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑵𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑴𐑯 𐑓𐑨𐑯-𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑧𐑥𐑦𐑑𐑦.

𐑷𐑤 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕 𐑒𐑨𐑮𐑦 𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑒𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑾𐑕 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑝𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟, 𐑼𐑦𐑡𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 ·𐑯𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑑 ·𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑾𐑯𐑟, 𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑛 𐑛𐑮𐑳𐑜𐑟. 𐑑𐑵 𐑔𐑦𐑒 𐑕𐑒𐑢𐑺𐑟 𐑝 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑝 𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑲𐑟 𐑸 𐑕𐑑𐑬𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑤𐑧𐑯𐑗𐑑 𐑑𐑩𐑜𐑧𐑞𐑼, 𐑕𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑱 𐑒𐑮𐑪𐑕 𐑰𐑗 𐑳𐑞𐑼'𐑟 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑯 𐑨𐑑 𐑮𐑲𐑑 𐑨𐑙𐑜𐑩𐑤𐑟; 𐑩 𐑤𐑲𐑯 𐑝 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑼𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑤𐑧𐑙𐑔 𐑦𐑟 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑩𐑑𐑨𐑗𐑑 𐑑 𐑞 𐑥𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑚𐑤𐑪𐑒, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑝 𐑞 𐑤𐑲𐑯 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑤𐑵𐑐𐑑, 𐑦𐑑 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑥𐑴𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑓𐑭𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑑 𐑩 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯. 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑗𐑰𐑓𐑤𐑦 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑜𐑨𐑤𐑦𐑛 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑛𐑮𐑳𐑜 𐑦𐑟 𐑿𐑟𐑛. 𐑓 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑥𐑹 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑸 𐑒𐑤𐑴𐑕 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑿 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑿 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑐𐑪𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑗𐑱𐑕 𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑑𐑲𐑥. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑸 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑛𐑱 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑛; 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑿 𐑥𐑱, 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑿 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑒𐑦𐑤 𐑷𐑤 𐑿 𐑒𐑨𐑯. 𐑯 𐑦𐑓 𐑿 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑒𐑦𐑤 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑷𐑤 𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑕, 𐑿 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑧𐑥, 𐑕𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑱 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑚𐑰 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼𐑢𐑼𐑛𐑟 𐑒𐑦𐑤𐑛 𐑨𐑑 𐑘𐑹 𐑤𐑧𐑠𐑼. 𐑣𐑧𐑯𐑕 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑞 𐑛𐑮𐑳𐑜, 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑟𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯. 𐑬𐑼 𐑚𐑴𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑓𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑖𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑝 𐑞𐑧𐑥. 𐑞 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑯 𐑕𐑧𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑢𐑻 𐑕𐑩𐑒𐑕𐑧𐑕𐑓𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑸𐑑𐑩𐑛, 𐑯 𐑢𐑰 𐑕𐑷 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑜𐑼𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑳𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑪𐑓, 𐑓𐑧𐑑𐑼𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑹𐑥𐑩𐑕 𐑕𐑲𐑛𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑑𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑛𐑮𐑳𐑜. 𐑞𐑱 𐑢𐑻 𐑒𐑮𐑨𐑥𐑐𐑑 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑥𐑨𐑤𐑦𐑓𐑨𐑒𐑑𐑼𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑗𐑱𐑯 𐑯 𐑚𐑷𐑤. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑓𐑤𐑦𐑙𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑔𐑻𐑛, 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑨𐑒𐑑 𐑝 𐑑𐑪𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑴𐑝𐑼𐑚𐑹𐑛 𐑞 𐑒𐑤𐑳𐑥𐑟𐑦 𐑢𐑫𐑛𐑩𐑯 𐑚𐑤𐑪𐑒, 𐑦𐑑 𐑒𐑷𐑑 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑰𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑, 𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑑𐑹 𐑦𐑑 𐑬𐑑 𐑯 𐑒𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑛 𐑦𐑑 𐑩𐑢𐑱, 𐑛𐑮𐑪𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑹𐑟𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑'𐑕 𐑚𐑪𐑑𐑩𐑥 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑕𐑰𐑑 𐑕𐑤𐑦𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑣𐑦𐑥. 𐑪𐑯 𐑚𐑴𐑔 𐑕𐑲𐑛𐑟 𐑞 𐑕𐑰 𐑒𐑱𐑥 𐑦𐑯 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑢𐑵𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑐𐑤𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑕, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑰 𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑓𐑑 𐑑𐑵 𐑹 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑛𐑮𐑷𐑼𐑟 𐑯 𐑖𐑻𐑑𐑕 𐑦𐑯, 𐑯 𐑕𐑴 𐑕𐑑𐑪𐑐𐑑 𐑞 𐑤𐑰𐑒𐑕 𐑓 𐑞 𐑑𐑲𐑥.

𐑦𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑯𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑 𐑑 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑪𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑑 𐑛𐑸𐑑 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑛𐑮𐑳𐑜𐑛-𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑟, 𐑢𐑻 𐑦𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑢𐑰 𐑩𐑛𐑝𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑣𐑻𐑛, 𐑬𐑼 𐑢𐑱𐑤'𐑟 𐑢𐑱 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑖𐑑; 𐑥𐑹𐑴𐑝𐑼, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑢𐑰 𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑓𐑻𐑞𐑼 𐑯 𐑓𐑻𐑞𐑼 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑕𐑼𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑓𐑼𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑝 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯, 𐑞 𐑛𐑲𐑼𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑹𐑛𐑼𐑟 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑢𐑱𐑯𐑦𐑙. 𐑕𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑞 𐑡𐑻𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯 𐑛𐑮𐑵 𐑬𐑑, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑑𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑕𐑲𐑛𐑢𐑱𐑟 𐑝𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑖𐑑; 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑑𐑱𐑐𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑹𐑕 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑸𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑴𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑥, 𐑢𐑰 𐑜𐑤𐑲𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑢𐑰𐑯 𐑑𐑵 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑼𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑸𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑖𐑴𐑤, 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑓 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑥𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑑𐑪𐑮𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑢𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑕𐑤𐑦𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑩 𐑕𐑼𐑰𐑯 𐑝𐑨𐑤𐑦 𐑤𐑱𐑒. 𐑣𐑽 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑹𐑥𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑮𐑹𐑦𐑙 𐑜𐑤𐑧𐑯𐑟 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑢𐑰𐑯 𐑞 𐑬𐑑𐑼𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟, 𐑢𐑻 𐑣𐑻𐑛 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑓𐑧𐑤𐑑. 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑨𐑯𐑕 𐑞 𐑕𐑰 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑥𐑵𐑞 𐑕𐑨𐑑𐑦𐑯-𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑕𐑻𐑓𐑦𐑕, 𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑛 𐑩 𐑕𐑤𐑰𐑒, 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑛𐑿𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑥𐑶𐑕𐑗𐑼 𐑔𐑮𐑴𐑯 𐑪𐑓 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑹 𐑒𐑢𐑲𐑩𐑑 𐑥𐑵𐑛𐑟. 𐑘𐑧𐑕, 𐑢𐑰 𐑢𐑻 𐑯𐑬 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑗𐑭𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑒𐑭𐑥 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑞𐑱 𐑕𐑱 𐑤𐑻𐑒𐑕 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑣𐑸𐑑 𐑝 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯. 𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑢𐑰 𐑚𐑦𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑛 𐑞 𐑑𐑿𐑥𐑳𐑤𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑬𐑑𐑼 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑒 𐑕𐑻𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑟, 𐑯 𐑕𐑷 𐑕𐑩𐑒𐑕𐑧𐑕𐑦𐑝 𐑐𐑪𐑛𐑟 𐑝 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟, 𐑱𐑑 𐑹 𐑑𐑧𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑰𐑗, 𐑕𐑢𐑦𐑓𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑜𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑯 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛, 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑥𐑳𐑤𐑑𐑦𐑐𐑤𐑲𐑛 𐑕𐑐𐑨𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑣𐑹𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑮𐑦𐑙; 𐑯 𐑕𐑴 𐑒𐑤𐑴𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑖𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑼 𐑑 𐑖𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑼, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑩 ·𐑑𐑲𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑒 𐑕𐑻𐑒𐑩𐑕-𐑮𐑲𐑛𐑼 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑰𐑟𐑦𐑤𐑦 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑴𐑝𐑼-𐑸𐑗𐑑 𐑞 𐑥𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑟, 𐑯 𐑕𐑴 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑜𐑪𐑯 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑪𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑚𐑨𐑒𐑕. 𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑝 𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑬𐑛 𐑝 𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑴𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟, 𐑥𐑹 𐑦𐑥𐑰𐑛𐑾𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑼𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑦𐑥𐑚𐑱𐑛 𐑨𐑒𐑕𐑦𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑣𐑻𐑛, 𐑯𐑴 𐑐𐑪𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑗𐑭𐑯𐑕 𐑝 𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑱𐑐 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑨𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑩𐑓𐑹𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑳𐑕. 𐑢𐑰 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑗 𐑓 𐑩 𐑚𐑮𐑰𐑗 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑤𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑧𐑥𐑛 𐑳𐑕 𐑦𐑯; 𐑞 𐑢𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑩𐑛𐑥𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑳𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑹𐑛𐑼 𐑑 𐑖𐑳𐑑 𐑳𐑕 𐑳𐑐. 𐑒𐑰𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑼 𐑝 𐑞 𐑤𐑱𐑒, 𐑢𐑰 𐑢𐑻 𐑩𐑒𐑱𐑠𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑝𐑦𐑟𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑕𐑥𐑷𐑤 𐑑𐑱𐑥 𐑒𐑬𐑟 𐑯 𐑒𐑭𐑝𐑟; 𐑞 𐑢𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑯 𐑯 𐑗𐑦𐑤𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑮𐑬𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑣𐑴𐑕𐑑.

𐑯𐑬, 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑤𐑵𐑕𐑦𐑝 𐑝 𐑞 𐑩𐑒𐑱𐑠𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑲𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑢𐑰𐑯 𐑞 𐑮𐑦𐑝𐑪𐑤𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑬𐑑𐑼 𐑕𐑻𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑟, 𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑤𐑵𐑕𐑦𐑝 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑱𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑢𐑰𐑯 𐑞 𐑝𐑺𐑾𐑕 𐑐𐑪𐑛𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑕𐑻𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑟, 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑲𐑼 𐑺𐑾 𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑡𐑳𐑙𐑒𐑗𐑼, 𐑦𐑥𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑣𐑴𐑤 𐑥𐑳𐑤𐑑𐑦𐑑𐑿𐑛, 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑱𐑯𐑛 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑰𐑕𐑑 𐑑𐑵 𐑹 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑕𐑒𐑢𐑺 𐑥𐑲𐑤𐑟. 𐑨𐑑 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑮𐑱𐑑—𐑞𐑴 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑰𐑛 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩 𐑑𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑧𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑝—𐑕𐑐𐑬𐑑𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑳𐑝𐑼𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑬𐑼 𐑤𐑴 𐑚𐑴𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑦𐑙 𐑳𐑐 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑮𐑦𐑥 𐑝 𐑞 𐑣𐑼𐑲𐑟𐑩𐑯. 𐑲 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑕𐑻𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑕, 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑪𐑟, 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑓 𐑞 𐑒𐑬𐑟 𐑯 𐑒𐑭𐑝𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑐𐑻𐑐𐑩𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑤𐑪𐑒𐑑 𐑳𐑐 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑦𐑯𐑼𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑓𐑴𐑤𐑛; 𐑯 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑓 𐑞 𐑢𐑲𐑛 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑣𐑻𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑞𐑼𐑑𐑵 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑝𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑤𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑲𐑕 𐑒𐑷𐑟 𐑝 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑕𐑑𐑪𐑐𐑦𐑙; 𐑹, 𐑐𐑪𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑦, 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑴 𐑘𐑳𐑙, 𐑳𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑓𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛, 𐑯 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑢𐑱 𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑽𐑾𐑯𐑕𐑑; 𐑣𐑬𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑦𐑑 𐑥𐑱 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑯, 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑕𐑥𐑷𐑤𐑼 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟—𐑯𐑬 𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑝𐑦𐑟𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑬𐑼 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑭𐑥𐑛 𐑚𐑴𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑥𐑸𐑡𐑦𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑤𐑱𐑒—𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑩 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑕 𐑓𐑽𐑤𐑩𐑕𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑯 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑓𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑕, 𐑹 𐑧𐑤𐑕 𐑩 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑚𐑦𐑗𐑸𐑥𐑛 𐑐𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑒 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑪𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑑 𐑥𐑸𐑝𐑩𐑤 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑣𐑬𐑕𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑛𐑪𐑜𐑟 𐑞𐑱 𐑒𐑱𐑥 𐑕𐑯𐑳𐑓𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑳𐑕, 𐑮𐑲𐑑 𐑳𐑐 𐑑 𐑬𐑼 𐑜𐑳𐑯𐑩𐑤𐑟, 𐑯 𐑑𐑳𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑧𐑥; 𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑦𐑑 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑤 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑕𐑳𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑩𐑥𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑞𐑧𐑥. ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜 𐑐𐑨𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑞𐑺 𐑓𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑛𐑟; ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒 𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑨𐑗𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑚𐑨𐑒𐑕 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑕; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑓𐑽𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑞 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑢𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟, 𐑓 𐑞 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑮𐑦𐑓𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑛𐑸𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑑.

𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑓𐑸 𐑚𐑦𐑯𐑰𐑔 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑕 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑻𐑓𐑦𐑕, 𐑩𐑯𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑼 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛 𐑥𐑧𐑑 𐑬𐑼 𐑲𐑟 𐑨𐑟 𐑢𐑰 𐑜𐑱𐑟𐑛 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑞 𐑕𐑲𐑛. 𐑓, 𐑕𐑩𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼𐑦 𐑝𐑷𐑤𐑑𐑕, 𐑓𐑤𐑴𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑞 𐑓𐑹𐑥𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑯𐑻𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑳𐑞𐑼𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟, 𐑯 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑞𐑺 𐑦𐑯𐑹𐑥𐑩𐑕 𐑜𐑻𐑔 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑖𐑹𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑥𐑳𐑞𐑼𐑟. 𐑞 𐑤𐑱𐑒, 𐑨𐑟 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛, 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑑 𐑩 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑼𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑛𐑧𐑐𐑔 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑰𐑛𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑕𐑐𐑨𐑮𐑩𐑯𐑑; 𐑯 𐑨𐑟 𐑣𐑿𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑓𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑕𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑒𐑭𐑥𐑤𐑦 𐑯 𐑓𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑩𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑜𐑱𐑟 𐑩𐑢𐑱 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑚𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑑, 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑓 𐑤𐑰𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑑𐑵 𐑛𐑦𐑓𐑼𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑤𐑲𐑝𐑟 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑑𐑲𐑥; 𐑯 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑛𐑮𐑷𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑹𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑯𐑳𐑮𐑦𐑖𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑, 𐑚𐑰 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑕𐑐𐑦𐑮𐑦𐑗𐑵𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑓𐑰𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑳𐑯𐑻𐑔𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑧𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑕;—𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑕𐑴 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑞 𐑘𐑳𐑙 𐑝 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑕𐑰𐑥 𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑳𐑐 𐑑𐑩𐑢𐑹𐑛𐑟 𐑳𐑕, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑳𐑕, 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑓 𐑢𐑰 𐑢𐑻 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑩 𐑚𐑦𐑑 𐑝 ·𐑜𐑳𐑤𐑓𐑢𐑰𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑯𐑿-𐑚𐑹𐑯 𐑕𐑲𐑑. 𐑓𐑤𐑴𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑪𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑕𐑲𐑛𐑟, 𐑞 𐑥𐑳𐑞𐑼𐑟 𐑷𐑤𐑕𐑴 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑒𐑢𐑲𐑩𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑲𐑦𐑙 𐑳𐑕. 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑯𐑓𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑒𐑢𐑽 𐑑𐑴𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑣𐑸𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑩 𐑛𐑱 𐑴𐑤𐑛, 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑥𐑧𐑠𐑼𐑛 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑓𐑹𐑑𐑰𐑯 𐑓𐑰𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑤𐑧𐑙𐑔, 𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑕 𐑓𐑰𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑜𐑻𐑔. 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑓𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑦; 𐑞𐑴 𐑨𐑟 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑕𐑒𐑺𐑕 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑳𐑝𐑼𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑻𐑒𐑕𐑩𐑥 𐑐𐑩𐑟𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑕𐑴 𐑤𐑱𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑪𐑒𐑿𐑐𐑲𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑥𐑩𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑮𐑧𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤; 𐑢𐑺, 𐑑𐑱𐑤 𐑑 𐑣𐑧𐑛, 𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑦 𐑓 𐑞 𐑓𐑲𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑙, 𐑞 𐑳𐑯𐑚𐑹𐑯 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑤𐑲𐑟 𐑚𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 ·𐑑𐑸𐑑𐑼'𐑟 𐑚𐑴. 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑑 𐑕𐑲𐑛-𐑓𐑦𐑯𐑟, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑐𐑭𐑥𐑟 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑤𐑵𐑒𐑕, 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑖𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑱𐑯𐑛 𐑞 𐑐𐑤𐑨𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑒𐑮𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑩𐑐𐑽𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑝 𐑩 𐑚𐑱𐑚𐑦'𐑟 𐑽𐑟 𐑯𐑿𐑤𐑦 𐑼𐑲𐑝𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑓𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑯 𐑐𐑸𐑑𐑕.

“𐑤𐑲𐑯! 𐑤𐑲𐑯!” 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜, 𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑞 𐑜𐑳𐑯𐑩𐑤; “𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑓𐑭𐑕𐑑! 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑓𐑭𐑕𐑑!—𐑣𐑵 𐑤𐑲𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥! 𐑣𐑵 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑒?—𐑑𐑵 𐑢𐑱𐑤; 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑚𐑦𐑜, 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤!”

“𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑘𐑰, 𐑥𐑨𐑯?” 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒.

“𐑤𐑫𐑒-𐑰 𐑣𐑽,” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜, 𐑐𐑶𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑛𐑬𐑯.

𐑨𐑟 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑑𐑳𐑚 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑮𐑰𐑤𐑛 𐑬𐑑 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑛𐑟 𐑝 𐑓𐑨𐑞𐑩𐑥𐑟 𐑝 𐑮𐑴𐑐; 𐑨𐑟, 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑛𐑰𐑐 𐑕𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙, 𐑣𐑰 𐑓𐑤𐑴𐑑𐑕 𐑳𐑐 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯, 𐑯 𐑖𐑴𐑟 𐑞 𐑕𐑤𐑨𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑒𐑻𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑤𐑲𐑯 𐑚𐑶𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑲𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑯 𐑕𐑐𐑲𐑮𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑑𐑩𐑢𐑹𐑛𐑟 𐑞 𐑺; 𐑕𐑴 𐑯𐑬, ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒 𐑕𐑷 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑒𐑶𐑤𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑳𐑥𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑒𐑹𐑛 𐑝 ·𐑥𐑩𐑛𐑭𐑥 ·𐑤𐑩𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑔𐑩𐑯, 𐑚𐑲 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑞 𐑘𐑳𐑙 𐑒𐑳𐑚 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑑𐑧𐑞𐑼𐑛 𐑑 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑛𐑨𐑥. 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑛𐑩𐑥 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑮𐑨𐑐𐑦𐑛 𐑝𐑦𐑕𐑦𐑕𐑦𐑑𐑿𐑛𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑗𐑱𐑕, 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑯𐑨𐑗𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑤𐑲𐑯, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑥𐑩𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑤𐑵𐑕, 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑨𐑙𐑜𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑣𐑧𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯, 𐑕𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑒𐑳𐑚 𐑦𐑟 𐑞𐑺𐑚𐑲 𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑐𐑑. 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑒𐑮𐑩𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑰𐑟 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑛𐑲𐑝𐑳𐑤𐑡𐑛 𐑑 𐑳𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑦𐑯𐑗𐑭𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑐𐑪𐑯𐑛. 𐑢𐑰 𐑕𐑷 𐑘𐑳𐑙 ·𐑤𐑩𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑔𐑩𐑯 𐑩𐑥𐑫𐑼𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑛𐑰𐑐.*

*𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑨𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑷𐑤 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑖𐑰𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑤𐑩𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑔𐑩𐑯, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑳𐑯𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑓𐑦𐑖, 𐑚𐑮𐑰𐑛𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑓𐑼𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑨𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑕𐑰𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑟; 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑩 𐑡𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑥𐑱 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑚𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑰 𐑕𐑧𐑑 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑨𐑑 𐑯𐑲𐑯 𐑥𐑳𐑯𐑔𐑕, 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑛𐑿𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑨𐑑 𐑩 𐑑𐑲𐑥; 𐑞𐑴 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑓𐑿 𐑯𐑴𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑜𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑻𐑔 𐑑 𐑩𐑯 ·𐑰𐑕𐑷 𐑯 ·𐑡𐑱𐑒𐑩𐑚:—𐑩 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑡𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑝𐑲𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑓 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑲 𐑑𐑵 𐑑𐑰𐑑𐑕, 𐑒𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑾𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑦𐑗𐑵𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛, 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑪𐑯 𐑰𐑗 𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑝 𐑞 𐑱𐑯𐑩𐑕; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞 𐑚𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑕 𐑞𐑧𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑝𐑟 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑳𐑐𐑢𐑼𐑛𐑟 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞𐑨𐑑. 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑚𐑲 𐑗𐑭𐑯𐑕 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑕 𐑐𐑸𐑑𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑯𐑻𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑸 𐑒𐑳𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑑𐑼'𐑟 𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑕, 𐑞 𐑥𐑳𐑞𐑼'𐑟 𐑐𐑹𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑦𐑤𐑒 𐑯 𐑚𐑤𐑳𐑛 𐑮𐑲𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑳𐑤𐑼 𐑞 𐑕𐑰 𐑓 𐑮𐑪𐑛𐑟. 𐑞 𐑥𐑦𐑤𐑒 𐑦𐑟 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑕𐑢𐑰𐑑 𐑯 𐑮𐑦𐑗; 𐑦𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑑𐑱𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑥𐑨𐑯; 𐑦𐑑 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑛𐑵 𐑢𐑧𐑤 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑷𐑚𐑼𐑦𐑟. 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑴𐑝𐑼𐑓𐑤𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑥𐑿𐑗𐑵𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑰𐑥, 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑕𐑩𐑤𐑵𐑑 𐑥𐑹 𐑣𐑴𐑥𐑲𐑯𐑩𐑥.

𐑯 𐑞𐑳𐑕, 𐑞𐑴 𐑕𐑼𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑕𐑻𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑕𐑻𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑯𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑯 𐑩𐑓𐑮𐑲𐑑𐑕, 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑵𐑑𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑒𐑮𐑰𐑗𐑼𐑟 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑼 𐑓𐑮𐑰𐑤𐑦 𐑯 𐑓𐑽𐑤𐑩𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑳𐑤𐑡 𐑦𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑐𐑰𐑕𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑻𐑯𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕; 𐑘𐑱, 𐑕𐑼𐑰𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑛𐑨𐑤𐑾𐑯𐑕 𐑯 𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑲𐑑. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑕𐑴, 𐑩𐑥𐑦𐑛 𐑞 𐑑𐑹𐑯𐑱𐑛𐑴𐑛 ·𐑩𐑑𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑝 𐑥𐑲 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙, 𐑛𐑵 𐑲 𐑥𐑲𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑓 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑹𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑿𐑑 𐑒𐑭𐑥; 𐑯 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑐𐑪𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑩𐑕 𐑐𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑩𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑳𐑯𐑢𐑱𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑴 𐑮𐑦𐑝𐑪𐑤𐑝 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑥𐑰, 𐑛𐑰𐑐 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑯 𐑛𐑰𐑐 𐑦𐑯𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑞𐑺 𐑲 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑚𐑱𐑞 𐑥𐑰 𐑦𐑯 𐑦𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑥𐑲𐑤𐑛𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑡𐑶.

𐑥𐑰𐑯𐑢𐑲𐑤, 𐑨𐑟 𐑢𐑰 𐑞𐑳𐑕 𐑤𐑱 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑑, 𐑞 𐑩𐑒𐑱𐑠𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑳𐑛𐑩𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑞 𐑨𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑝 𐑞 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕, 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑦𐑯𐑜𐑱𐑡𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑛𐑮𐑳𐑜𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑮𐑳𐑯𐑑𐑽 𐑝 𐑞 𐑣𐑴𐑕𐑑; 𐑹 𐑐𐑪𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑦𐑙 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑹 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑻𐑒𐑩𐑤, 𐑢𐑺 𐑩𐑚𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑝 𐑮𐑵𐑥 𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑝𐑰𐑯𐑾𐑯𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑮𐑰𐑑𐑕 𐑢𐑻 𐑩𐑓𐑹𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑞𐑧𐑥. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑲𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑮𐑱𐑡𐑛 𐑛𐑮𐑳𐑜𐑛 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑯𐑬 𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑚𐑤𐑲𐑯𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑸𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑴 𐑩𐑒𐑮𐑪𐑕 𐑞 𐑕𐑻𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑟, 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑳𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑥𐑧𐑑 𐑬𐑼 𐑲𐑟. 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑞 𐑒𐑳𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑥 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑓𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑑 𐑩 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑥𐑹 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑬𐑼𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑯 𐑩𐑤𐑻𐑑, 𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑒 𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑥𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑻, 𐑚𐑲 𐑕𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑹 𐑥𐑱𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑡𐑲𐑜𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑑𐑱𐑤-𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑯. 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑛𐑳𐑯 𐑚𐑲 𐑛𐑸𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑖𐑹𐑑-𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑒𐑳𐑑𐑦𐑙-𐑕𐑐𐑱𐑛, 𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑦𐑟 𐑩𐑑𐑨𐑗𐑑 𐑩 𐑮𐑴𐑐 𐑓 𐑣𐑷𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑑 𐑚𐑨𐑒 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯. 𐑩 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑢𐑵𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 (𐑨𐑟 𐑢𐑰 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼𐑢𐑼𐑛𐑟 𐑤𐑻𐑯𐑛) 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑐𐑸𐑑, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑦𐑓𐑧𐑒𐑗𐑵𐑩𐑤𐑦, 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛, 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑮𐑴𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑩𐑢𐑱 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑, 𐑒𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑣𐑭𐑓 𐑝 𐑞 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯 𐑤𐑲𐑯; 𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑹𐑛𐑦𐑯𐑼𐑦 𐑨𐑜𐑩𐑯𐑦 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑵𐑯𐑛, 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑬 𐑛𐑨𐑖𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑞 𐑮𐑦𐑝𐑪𐑤𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑻𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑞 𐑤𐑴𐑯 𐑥𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑛𐑧𐑕𐑐𐑼𐑭𐑛𐑴 ·𐑸𐑯𐑩𐑤𐑛, 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑚𐑨𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑝 ·𐑕𐑨𐑮𐑩𐑑𐑴𐑜𐑩, 𐑒𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑦𐑙 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑥𐑱 𐑢𐑺𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑑.

𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑨𐑜𐑩𐑯𐑲𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑨𐑟 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞 𐑢𐑵𐑯𐑛 𐑝 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑯 𐑩𐑯 𐑩𐑐𐑷𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑯𐑳𐑓, 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑢𐑱; 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑞 𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑽 𐑣𐑪𐑮𐑼 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑐𐑲𐑼 𐑞 𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑣𐑻𐑛, 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑩 𐑒𐑷𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑨𐑑 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑝𐑰𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑩𐑚𐑕𐑒𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑳𐑕. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑧𐑙𐑔 𐑢𐑰 𐑐𐑼𐑕𐑰𐑝𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑳𐑯𐑦𐑥𐑨𐑡𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑨𐑒𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑼𐑦, 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑨𐑙𐑜𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯-𐑤𐑲𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑑𐑴𐑛; 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑷𐑤𐑕𐑴 𐑮𐑳𐑯 𐑩𐑢𐑱 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑒𐑳𐑑𐑦𐑙-𐑕𐑐𐑱𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥; 𐑯 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑞 𐑓𐑮𐑰 𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑝 𐑞 𐑮𐑴𐑐 𐑩𐑑𐑨𐑗𐑑 𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑧𐑐𐑩𐑯, 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑐𐑻𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑷𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑒𐑶𐑤𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯-𐑤𐑲𐑯 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑑𐑱𐑤, 𐑞 𐑒𐑳𐑑𐑦𐑙-𐑕𐑐𐑱𐑛 𐑦𐑑𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑢𐑻𐑒𐑑 𐑤𐑵𐑕 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑤𐑧𐑖. 𐑕𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑑𐑹𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑑 𐑥𐑨𐑛𐑯𐑩𐑕, 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑬 𐑗𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑞 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼, 𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑓𐑤𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑤𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑑𐑱𐑤, 𐑯 𐑑𐑪𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑒𐑰𐑯 𐑕𐑐𐑱𐑛 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑢𐑵𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑯 𐑥𐑻𐑛𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑴𐑯 𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑮𐑱𐑛𐑟.

𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑑𐑼𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑒 𐑪𐑚𐑡𐑧𐑒𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑣𐑴𐑤 𐑣𐑻𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞𐑺 𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑼𐑦 𐑓𐑮𐑲𐑑. 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑, 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑓𐑹𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑥𐑸𐑡𐑦𐑯 𐑝 𐑬𐑼 𐑤𐑱𐑒 𐑚𐑦𐑜𐑨𐑯 𐑑 𐑒𐑮𐑬𐑛 𐑩 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤, 𐑯 𐑑𐑳𐑥𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑰𐑗 𐑳𐑞𐑼, 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑓 𐑤𐑦𐑓𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑣𐑭𐑓 𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑴𐑟 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑩𐑓𐑸; 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑞 𐑤𐑱𐑒 𐑦𐑑𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑚𐑦𐑜𐑨𐑯 𐑓𐑱𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑑 𐑣𐑰𐑝 𐑯 𐑕𐑢𐑧𐑤; 𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑚𐑥𐑼𐑰𐑯 𐑚𐑮𐑲𐑛𐑩𐑤-𐑗𐑱𐑥𐑚𐑼𐑟 𐑯 𐑯𐑻𐑕𐑼𐑦𐑟 𐑝𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑖𐑑; 𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑹 𐑯 𐑥𐑹 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑹𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑥𐑹 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑻𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑚𐑦𐑜𐑨𐑯 𐑑 𐑕𐑢𐑦𐑥 𐑦𐑯 𐑔𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑒𐑤𐑳𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑟. 𐑘𐑧𐑕, 𐑞 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑒𐑭𐑥 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑛𐑦𐑐𐑸𐑑𐑦𐑙. 𐑩 𐑤𐑴 𐑩𐑛𐑝𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑳𐑥 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑵𐑯 𐑣𐑻𐑛; 𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑑 𐑞 𐑑𐑿𐑥𐑳𐑤𐑗𐑵𐑩𐑕 𐑥𐑨𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑝 𐑚𐑤𐑪𐑒-𐑲𐑕 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑝𐑼 ·𐑣𐑳𐑛𐑕𐑩𐑯 𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑒𐑕 𐑳𐑐 𐑦𐑯 ·𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑙, 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑲𐑼 𐑣𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑝 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑒𐑱𐑥 𐑑𐑳𐑥𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑦𐑯𐑼 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑼, 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑓 𐑑 𐑐𐑲𐑤 𐑞𐑧𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑝𐑟 𐑳𐑐 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑥𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑯. 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒 𐑯 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜 𐑗𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑛 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕𐑩𐑟; ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒 𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑻𐑯.

“𐑹𐑟! 𐑹𐑟!” 𐑣𐑰 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑢𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑼𐑛, 𐑕𐑰𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑥—“𐑜𐑮𐑲𐑐 𐑘𐑹 𐑹𐑟, 𐑯 𐑒𐑤𐑳𐑗 𐑘𐑹 𐑕𐑴𐑤𐑟, 𐑯𐑬! 𐑥𐑲 ·𐑜𐑪𐑛, 𐑥𐑧𐑯, 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑚𐑲! 𐑖𐑳𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑪𐑓, 𐑿 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜—𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑞𐑺!—𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑒 𐑣𐑦𐑥!—𐑣𐑦𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥! 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑳𐑐—𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑳𐑐, 𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑱 𐑕𐑴! 𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑙, 𐑥𐑧𐑯—𐑐𐑫𐑤, 𐑥𐑧𐑯; 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑥𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑞𐑺 𐑚𐑨𐑒𐑕—𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑱𐑐 𐑞𐑧𐑥!—𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑱𐑐 𐑩𐑢𐑱!”

𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑬 𐑷𐑤 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑡𐑨𐑥𐑛 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑢𐑰𐑯 𐑑𐑵 𐑝𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑒 𐑚𐑳𐑤𐑒𐑕, 𐑤𐑰𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑯𐑼𐑴 ·𐑛𐑸𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑧𐑤𐑟 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑢𐑰𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑤𐑧𐑙𐑔𐑕. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑛𐑧𐑕𐑐𐑼𐑩𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑢𐑰 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑖𐑪𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑩 𐑑𐑧𐑥𐑐𐑼𐑼𐑦 𐑴𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑙; 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑜𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑱 𐑮𐑨𐑐𐑦𐑛𐑤𐑦, 𐑯 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑻𐑯𐑩𐑕𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑢𐑪𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑓 𐑩𐑯𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑬𐑑𐑤𐑧𐑑. 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑕𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑤𐑼 𐑣𐑺-𐑚𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑔 𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑱𐑐𐑕, 𐑢𐑰 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑢𐑦𐑓𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑜𐑤𐑲𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑡𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑬𐑑𐑼 𐑕𐑻𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑟, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑯𐑬 𐑒𐑮𐑪𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑥 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟, 𐑷𐑤 𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑥𐑱𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑓 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑼. 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑤𐑳𐑒𐑦 𐑕𐑨𐑤𐑝𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑗𐑰𐑐𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑻𐑗𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑤𐑪𐑕 𐑝 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜'𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑑, 𐑣𐑵, 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑬𐑟 𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑒 𐑞 𐑓𐑿𐑡𐑩𐑑𐑦𐑝 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟, 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑑 𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑒𐑤𐑰𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑺-𐑧𐑛𐑦 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑛𐑩𐑯 𐑑𐑪𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑩 𐑐𐑺 𐑝 𐑚𐑮𐑷𐑛 𐑓𐑤𐑵𐑒𐑕 𐑒𐑤𐑴𐑕 𐑚𐑲.

𐑮𐑲𐑩𐑑𐑩𐑕 𐑯 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑹𐑛𐑼𐑛 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑿𐑯𐑦𐑝𐑻𐑕𐑩𐑤 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑯𐑬 𐑢𐑪𐑟, 𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑵𐑯 𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑪𐑤𐑝𐑛 𐑦𐑑𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑩 𐑕𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑥𐑨𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑥𐑵𐑝𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑; 𐑓 𐑣𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑒𐑤𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑑 𐑑𐑩𐑜𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑛𐑧𐑯𐑕 𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦, 𐑞𐑱 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑮𐑦𐑯𐑿𐑛 𐑞𐑺 𐑪𐑯𐑢𐑼𐑛 𐑓𐑤𐑲𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑷𐑜𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑓𐑤𐑰𐑑𐑯𐑩𐑕. 𐑓𐑻𐑞𐑼 𐑐𐑼𐑕𐑿𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑿𐑕𐑤𐑩𐑕; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑤𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑼𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑢𐑱𐑒 𐑑 𐑐𐑦𐑒 𐑳𐑐 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑛𐑮𐑳𐑜𐑛 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑛𐑮𐑪𐑐𐑑 𐑩𐑕𐑑𐑻𐑯, 𐑯 𐑤𐑲𐑒𐑢𐑲𐑟 𐑑 𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑘𐑫𐑼 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑗 ·𐑓𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑒 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑒𐑦𐑤𐑛 𐑯 𐑢𐑱𐑓𐑑. 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑓 𐑦𐑟 𐑩 𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑐𐑴𐑤, 𐑑𐑵 𐑹 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑝 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑸 𐑒𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑚𐑴𐑑; 𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑗, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑩𐑛𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑜𐑱𐑥 𐑦𐑟 𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛, 𐑸 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑳𐑐𐑮𐑲𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑓𐑤𐑴𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦 𐑝 𐑩 𐑛𐑧𐑛 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑚𐑴𐑔 𐑑 𐑥𐑸𐑒 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑰, 𐑯 𐑷𐑤𐑕𐑴 𐑨𐑟 𐑑𐑴𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑐𐑮𐑲𐑼 𐑐𐑩𐑟𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑯, 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑛𐑮𐑷 𐑯𐑽.

𐑞 𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑳𐑤𐑑 𐑝 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑤𐑴𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑦𐑤𐑩𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑩𐑑𐑦𐑝 𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑕 𐑕𐑱𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑼𐑦,—𐑞 𐑥𐑹 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑞 𐑤𐑧𐑕 𐑓𐑦𐑖. 𐑝 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑛𐑮𐑳𐑜𐑛 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑗𐑼𐑛. 𐑞 𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑝𐑛 𐑑 𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑱𐑐 𐑓 𐑞 𐑑𐑲𐑥, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑩𐑯, 𐑨𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑣𐑽𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑚𐑰 𐑕𐑰𐑯, 𐑚𐑲 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑒𐑮𐑭𐑓𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛.

·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 88. 𐑕𐑒𐑵𐑤𐑟 𐑯 ·𐑕𐑒𐑵𐑤𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑟.

𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑰𐑝𐑾𐑕 𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 𐑜𐑱𐑝 𐑩𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑕 𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦 𐑹 𐑣𐑻𐑛 𐑝 ·𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟, 𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑷𐑤𐑕𐑴 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑜𐑦𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑚𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑒𐑷𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑿𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑝𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑨𐑜𐑮𐑦𐑜𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟.

𐑯𐑬, 𐑞𐑴 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦𐑟 𐑸 𐑨𐑑 𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑛, 𐑘𐑧𐑑, 𐑨𐑟 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑕𐑰𐑯, 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑛𐑱, 𐑕𐑥𐑷𐑤 𐑛𐑦𐑑𐑨𐑗𐑑 𐑚𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑸 𐑩𐑒𐑱𐑠𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑩𐑚𐑟𐑻𐑝𐑛, 𐑦𐑥𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑑𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑦 𐑑 𐑓𐑦𐑓𐑑𐑦 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑡𐑵𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑰𐑗. 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑚𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑸 𐑯𐑴𐑯 𐑨𐑟 𐑕𐑒𐑵𐑤𐑟. 𐑞𐑱 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑸 𐑝 𐑑𐑵 𐑕𐑹𐑑𐑕; 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑴𐑟𐑛 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑲𐑼𐑤𐑦 𐑝 𐑓𐑰𐑥𐑱𐑤𐑟, 𐑯 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑯𐑳𐑯 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑘𐑳𐑙 𐑝𐑦𐑜𐑼𐑩𐑕 𐑥𐑱𐑤𐑟, 𐑹 𐑚𐑫𐑤𐑟, 𐑨𐑟 𐑞𐑱 𐑸 𐑓𐑩𐑥𐑦𐑤𐑽𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑧𐑟𐑦𐑜𐑯𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛.

𐑦𐑯 𐑒𐑨𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑽 𐑩𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑒𐑵𐑤 𐑝 𐑓𐑰𐑥𐑱𐑤𐑟, 𐑿 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑺𐑾𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑰 𐑩 𐑥𐑱𐑤 𐑝 𐑓𐑫𐑤 𐑜𐑮𐑴𐑯 𐑥𐑨𐑜𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑿𐑛, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑴𐑤𐑛; 𐑣𐑵, 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑩𐑤𐑸𐑥, 𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑜𐑨𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑦 𐑚𐑲 𐑓𐑷𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑮𐑽 𐑯 𐑒𐑳𐑝𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑓𐑤𐑲𐑑 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑤𐑱𐑛𐑦𐑟. 𐑦𐑯 𐑑𐑮𐑵𐑔, 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑟 𐑩 𐑤𐑳𐑜𐑠𐑫𐑼𐑾𐑕 ·𐑪𐑑𐑩𐑥𐑩𐑯, 𐑕𐑢𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑞 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼𐑦 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛, 𐑕𐑼𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑩𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑕𐑪𐑤𐑦𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑽𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑣𐑸𐑰𐑥. 𐑞 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑢𐑰𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 ·𐑪𐑑𐑩𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑪𐑙𐑒𐑿𐑚𐑲𐑯𐑟 𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑒𐑦𐑙; 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑪𐑟, 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑣𐑰 𐑦𐑟 𐑷𐑤𐑢𐑱𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑤𐑸𐑡𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑤𐑩𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑔𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑒 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑐𐑹𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟, 𐑞 𐑤𐑱𐑛𐑦𐑟, 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑨𐑑 𐑓𐑫𐑤 𐑜𐑮𐑴𐑔, 𐑸 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑥𐑹 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯-𐑔𐑻𐑛 𐑝 𐑞 𐑚𐑳𐑤𐑒 𐑝 𐑩𐑯 𐑨𐑝𐑼𐑦𐑡-𐑕𐑲𐑟𐑛 𐑥𐑱𐑤. 𐑞𐑱 𐑸 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑨𐑮𐑩𐑑𐑦𐑝𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑑, 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑰𐑛; 𐑲 𐑛𐑺 𐑕𐑱, 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑑 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑰𐑛 𐑣𐑭𐑓 𐑩 𐑛𐑳𐑟𐑩𐑯 𐑘𐑸𐑛𐑟 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑕𐑑. 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼𐑞𐑩𐑤𐑧𐑕, 𐑦𐑑 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑛𐑦𐑯𐑲𐑛, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑣𐑴𐑤 𐑞𐑱 𐑸 𐑣𐑼𐑧𐑛𐑦𐑑𐑺𐑦𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑑 𐑧𐑯 𐑚𐑪𐑯 𐑐𐑶𐑯𐑑.

𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑒𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑾𐑕 𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑗 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑣𐑸𐑰𐑥 𐑯 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑤𐑹𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑮𐑨𐑥𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙𐑟. 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑓𐑨𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑟, 𐑞𐑱 𐑸 𐑓 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑥𐑵𐑝 𐑦𐑯 𐑤𐑧𐑠𐑼𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑻𐑗 𐑝 𐑝𐑼𐑲𐑩𐑑𐑦. 𐑿 𐑥𐑰𐑑 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑤𐑲𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑓 𐑞 𐑓𐑫𐑤 𐑓𐑤𐑬𐑼 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑧𐑒𐑢𐑩𐑑𐑹𐑾𐑤 𐑓𐑰𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑰𐑟𐑩𐑯, 𐑣𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑡𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑮𐑩𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑛, 𐑐𐑼𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑕, 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑼 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑯𐑹𐑞𐑼𐑯 𐑕𐑰𐑟, 𐑯 𐑕𐑴 𐑗𐑰𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑼 𐑝 𐑷𐑤 𐑳𐑯𐑐𐑤𐑧𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑢𐑽𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑯 𐑢𐑹𐑥𐑔. 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑞𐑱 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑤𐑬𐑯𐑡𐑛 𐑳𐑐 𐑯 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑭𐑛 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑦𐑒𐑢𐑱𐑑𐑼 𐑩𐑢𐑲𐑤, 𐑞𐑱 𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑑 𐑓 𐑞 ·𐑹𐑦𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑕𐑦𐑐𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑒𐑵𐑤 𐑕𐑰𐑟𐑩𐑯 𐑞𐑺, 𐑯 𐑕𐑴 𐑦𐑝𐑱𐑛 𐑞 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑧𐑕𐑦𐑝 𐑑𐑧𐑥𐑐𐑼𐑩𐑗𐑼 𐑝 𐑞 𐑘𐑽.

𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑕𐑼𐑰𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑩𐑛𐑝𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑪𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑡𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑟, 𐑦𐑓 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡 𐑕𐑩𐑕𐑐𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑕 𐑕𐑲𐑑𐑕 𐑸 𐑕𐑰𐑯, 𐑥𐑲 𐑤𐑹𐑛 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑒𐑰𐑐𐑕 𐑩 𐑢𐑺𐑦 𐑲 𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑩𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑨𐑥𐑤𐑦. 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑳𐑯𐑢𐑪𐑮𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑻𐑑 𐑘𐑳𐑙 ·𐑤𐑩𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑔𐑩𐑯 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑱, 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑿𐑥 𐑑 𐑛𐑮𐑷 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑓𐑦𐑛𐑧𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑤𐑴𐑕 𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑤𐑱𐑛𐑦𐑟, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑛𐑦𐑡𐑩𐑕 𐑓𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑦 𐑞 ·𐑚𐑨𐑖𐑷 𐑩𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑯 𐑗𐑱𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑩𐑢𐑱! 𐑣𐑲 𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟, 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑰𐑛, 𐑦𐑓 𐑳𐑯𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑐𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑘𐑳𐑙 𐑮𐑱𐑒𐑕 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑸 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑐𐑼𐑥𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑱𐑛 𐑞 𐑕𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑝 𐑛𐑩𐑥𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑚𐑤𐑦𐑕; 𐑞𐑴 𐑛𐑵 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑚𐑨𐑖𐑷 𐑢𐑦𐑤, 𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑒𐑰𐑐 𐑞 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑯𐑴𐑑𐑹𐑾𐑕 ·𐑤𐑴𐑔𐑸𐑦𐑴 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑧𐑛; 𐑓, 𐑩𐑤𐑨𐑕! 𐑷𐑤 𐑓𐑦𐑖 𐑚𐑧𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑯. 𐑨𐑟 𐑩𐑖𐑹, 𐑞 𐑤𐑱𐑛𐑦𐑟 𐑪𐑓𐑩𐑯 𐑒𐑷𐑟 𐑞 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑑𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑛𐑿𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑞𐑺 𐑮𐑲𐑝𐑩𐑤 𐑩𐑛𐑥𐑲𐑼𐑼𐑟; 𐑡𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑴 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟, 𐑣𐑵 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑑 𐑛𐑧𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑨𐑑𐑩𐑤, 𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑓 𐑤𐑳𐑝. 𐑞𐑱 𐑓𐑧𐑯𐑕 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞𐑺 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑤𐑴𐑼 𐑡𐑷𐑟, 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑤𐑪𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑑𐑩𐑜𐑧𐑞𐑼, 𐑯 𐑕𐑴 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑓 𐑞 𐑕𐑵𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑥𐑩𐑕𐑦 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑧𐑤𐑒𐑕 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑹𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑢𐑰𐑝 𐑞𐑺 𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑼𐑟. 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑩 𐑓𐑿 𐑸 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑗𐑼𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑛𐑰𐑐 𐑕𐑒𐑸𐑟 𐑝 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑟,—𐑓𐑳𐑮𐑴𐑛 𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑟, 𐑚𐑮𐑴𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑑𐑰𐑔, 𐑕𐑒𐑪𐑤𐑩𐑐𐑑 𐑓𐑦𐑯𐑟; 𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟, 𐑮𐑧𐑯𐑗𐑑 𐑯 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑤𐑴𐑒𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑥𐑬𐑞𐑟.

𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑕𐑩𐑐𐑴𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑱𐑛𐑼 𐑝 𐑛𐑩𐑥𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑚𐑤𐑦𐑕 𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑩𐑢𐑱 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑮𐑳𐑖 𐑝 𐑞 𐑣𐑸𐑰𐑥'𐑟 𐑤𐑹𐑛, 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑛𐑲𐑝𐑻𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑗 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑹𐑛. 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑣𐑰 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑯𐑿𐑱𐑑𐑕 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑝𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑳𐑤𐑒 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯 𐑯 𐑮𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑞𐑺 𐑩𐑢𐑲𐑤, 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑲𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑝𐑦𐑕𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑑 𐑘𐑳𐑙 ·𐑤𐑴𐑔𐑸𐑦𐑴, 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑐𐑲𐑩𐑕 ·𐑕𐑪𐑤𐑩𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑛𐑦𐑝𐑬𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑢𐑻𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑔𐑬𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑒𐑪𐑙𐑒𐑿𐑚𐑲𐑯𐑟. 𐑜𐑮𐑭𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑲𐑑, 𐑞 𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑼𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑛𐑩𐑥 𐑜𐑦𐑝 𐑗𐑱𐑕 𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑞𐑰𐑟 ·𐑜𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑛 ·𐑑𐑻𐑒𐑕; 𐑓 𐑞𐑰𐑟 ·𐑜𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑛 ·𐑑𐑻𐑒𐑕 𐑸 𐑑𐑵 𐑤𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑖 𐑝 𐑞𐑺 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑧𐑙𐑔, 𐑯 𐑣𐑧𐑯𐑕 𐑞𐑺 𐑳𐑙𐑒𐑗𐑵𐑩𐑕𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑥𐑷𐑤. 𐑨𐑟 𐑓 𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑯𐑟 𐑯 𐑞 𐑛𐑷𐑑𐑼𐑟 𐑞𐑱 𐑚𐑦𐑜𐑧𐑑, 𐑢𐑲, 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑕𐑳𐑯𐑟 𐑯 𐑛𐑷𐑑𐑼𐑟 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑒𐑺 𐑝 𐑞𐑧𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑝𐑟; 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑰𐑕𐑑, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑞 𐑥𐑩𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑐. 𐑓 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑪𐑥𐑯𐑦𐑝𐑼𐑩𐑕 𐑮𐑴𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑤𐑳𐑝𐑼𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑯𐑱𐑥𐑛, 𐑥𐑲 ·𐑤𐑹𐑛 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑯𐑴 𐑑𐑱𐑕𐑑 𐑓 𐑞 𐑯𐑻𐑕𐑼𐑦, 𐑣𐑬𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑓 𐑞 𐑚𐑬𐑼; 𐑯 𐑕𐑴, 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑼, 𐑣𐑰 𐑤𐑰𐑝𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑩𐑯𐑪𐑯𐑦𐑥𐑩𐑕 𐑚𐑱𐑚𐑦𐑟 𐑷𐑤 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑞 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛; 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑚𐑱𐑚𐑦 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑜𐑟𐑪𐑑𐑦𐑒. 𐑦𐑯 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑑𐑲𐑥, 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼𐑞𐑩𐑤𐑧𐑕, 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑸𐑛𐑼 𐑝 𐑿𐑔 𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑲𐑯𐑟; 𐑨𐑟 𐑘𐑽𐑟 𐑯 𐑛𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑕 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑮𐑰𐑕; 𐑨𐑟 𐑮𐑦𐑓𐑤𐑧𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑤𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑣𐑻 𐑕𐑪𐑤𐑩𐑥 𐑐𐑷𐑟𐑩𐑟; 𐑦𐑯 𐑖𐑹𐑑, 𐑨𐑟 𐑩 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑤𐑨𐑕𐑦𐑑𐑿𐑛 𐑴𐑝𐑼𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑕 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 ·𐑑𐑻𐑒; 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑩 𐑤𐑳𐑝 𐑝 𐑰𐑟 𐑯 𐑝𐑻𐑗𐑵 𐑕𐑩𐑐𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑞 𐑤𐑳𐑝 𐑓 𐑥𐑱𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑟; 𐑬𐑼 ·𐑪𐑑𐑩𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑟 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑, 𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑, 𐑨𐑛𐑥𐑪𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑼𐑦 𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑡 𐑝 𐑤𐑲𐑓, 𐑓𐑹𐑕𐑢𐑺𐑟, 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑚𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑞 𐑣𐑸𐑰𐑥, 𐑯 𐑜𐑮𐑴𐑯 𐑑 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑜𐑟𐑧𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑼𐑦, 𐑕𐑳𐑤𐑒𐑦 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑕𐑴𐑤, 𐑜𐑴𐑟 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑩𐑤𐑴𐑯 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑞 𐑥𐑼𐑦𐑛𐑾𐑯𐑟 𐑯 𐑐𐑨𐑮𐑩𐑤𐑧𐑤𐑟 𐑕𐑱𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑮𐑱𐑼𐑟, 𐑯 𐑢𐑹𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑰𐑗 𐑘𐑳𐑙 ·𐑤𐑩𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑔𐑩𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑨𐑥𐑼𐑩𐑕 𐑻𐑼𐑟.

𐑯𐑬, 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑣𐑸𐑰𐑥 𐑝 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑼𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑩 𐑕𐑒𐑵𐑤, 𐑕𐑴 𐑦𐑟 𐑞 𐑤𐑹𐑛 𐑯 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑼 𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑒𐑵𐑤 𐑑𐑧𐑒𐑯𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑦 𐑯𐑴𐑯 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑕𐑒𐑵𐑤𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑼. 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑞𐑺𐑓𐑹 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑑 𐑒𐑨𐑮𐑩𐑒𐑑𐑼, 𐑣𐑬𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑨𐑛𐑥𐑼𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑩𐑑𐑦𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑜𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑕𐑒𐑵𐑤 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓, 𐑣𐑰 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑜𐑴 𐑩𐑚𐑮𐑷𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑳𐑤𐑒𐑱𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑤𐑻𐑯𐑛 𐑞𐑺, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞 𐑓𐑪𐑤𐑦 𐑝 𐑦𐑑. 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑑𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑤, 𐑕𐑒𐑵𐑤𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑼, 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑯𐑨𐑗𐑼𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑰𐑥 𐑛𐑦𐑮𐑲𐑝𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑯𐑱𐑥 𐑚𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑴𐑛 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑣𐑸𐑰𐑥 𐑦𐑑𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑕𐑼𐑥𐑲𐑟𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑣𐑵 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑞𐑳𐑕 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑕𐑹𐑑 𐑝 ·𐑪𐑑𐑩𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑮𐑧𐑛 𐑞 𐑥𐑧𐑥𐑢𐑸𐑟 𐑝 ·𐑝𐑰𐑛𐑴𐑒, 𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑓𐑹𐑥𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑹𐑑 𐑝 𐑩 𐑒𐑳𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑦-𐑕𐑒𐑵𐑤𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑼 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑓𐑱𐑥𐑩𐑕 ·𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑯𐑗𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑘𐑳𐑙𐑜𐑼 𐑛𐑱𐑟, 𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞 𐑯𐑱𐑗𐑼 𐑝 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑪𐑒𐑳𐑤𐑑 𐑤𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑳𐑤𐑒𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑿𐑐𐑩𐑤𐑟.

𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑵𐑛𐑩𐑛𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑯 𐑲𐑕𐑩𐑤𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑞 𐑕𐑒𐑵𐑤𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑼 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑕 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑩𐑛𐑝𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑘𐑽𐑟, 𐑦𐑟 𐑑𐑮𐑵 𐑝 𐑷𐑤 𐑱𐑡𐑛 ·𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟. 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑿𐑯𐑦𐑝𐑻𐑕𐑩𐑤𐑦, 𐑩 𐑤𐑴𐑯 𐑢𐑱𐑤—𐑨𐑟 𐑩 𐑕𐑪𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑼𐑦 ·𐑤𐑩𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑔𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑛—𐑐𐑮𐑵𐑝𐑟 𐑩𐑯 𐑱𐑯𐑗𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯. 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑝𐑧𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑥𐑪𐑕-𐑚𐑽𐑛𐑩𐑛 ·𐑛𐑨𐑯𐑾𐑤 ·𐑚𐑵𐑯, 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑯𐑴 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑯𐑽 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑚𐑳𐑑 ·𐑯𐑱𐑗𐑼 𐑣𐑻𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓; 𐑯 𐑣𐑻 𐑣𐑰 𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑕 𐑑 𐑢𐑲𐑓 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑦𐑤𐑛𐑼𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼𐑟, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑝 𐑢𐑲𐑝𐑟 𐑖𐑰 𐑦𐑟, 𐑞𐑴 𐑖𐑰 𐑒𐑰𐑐𐑕 𐑕𐑴 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑥𐑵𐑛𐑦 𐑕𐑰𐑒𐑮𐑩𐑑𐑕.

𐑞 𐑕𐑒𐑵𐑤𐑟 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑴𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑯𐑳𐑯 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑘𐑳𐑙 𐑯 𐑝𐑦𐑜𐑼𐑩𐑕 𐑥𐑱𐑤𐑟, 𐑐𐑮𐑰𐑝𐑾𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑛, 𐑪𐑓𐑼 𐑩 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑪𐑙 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑑 𐑞 𐑣𐑸𐑰𐑥 𐑕𐑒𐑵𐑤𐑟. 𐑓 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑓𐑰𐑥𐑱𐑤 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑸 𐑒𐑨𐑮𐑩𐑒𐑑𐑼𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑦 𐑑𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑛, 𐑞 𐑘𐑳𐑙 𐑥𐑱𐑤𐑟, 𐑹 𐑓𐑹𐑑𐑦-𐑚𐑨𐑮𐑩𐑤-𐑚𐑫𐑤𐑟, 𐑨𐑟 𐑞𐑱 𐑒𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑧𐑥, 𐑸 𐑚𐑲 𐑓𐑸 𐑞 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑐𐑳𐑜𐑯𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑷𐑤 ·𐑤𐑩𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑔𐑩𐑯𐑟, 𐑯 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑝𐑻𐑚𐑾𐑤𐑦 𐑞 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑛𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑼𐑩𐑕 𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑼; 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑧𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑕 𐑜𐑮𐑱-𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑩𐑛, 𐑜𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟, 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑥𐑧𐑑, 𐑯 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑓𐑲𐑑 𐑿 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑜𐑮𐑦𐑥 𐑓𐑰𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑦𐑜𐑟𐑨𐑕𐑐𐑼𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑩 𐑐𐑰𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑜𐑬𐑑.

𐑞 ·𐑓𐑹𐑑𐑦-𐑚𐑨𐑮𐑩𐑤-𐑚𐑫𐑤 𐑕𐑒𐑵𐑤𐑟 𐑸 𐑤𐑸𐑡𐑼 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑞 𐑣𐑸𐑰𐑥 𐑕𐑒𐑵𐑤𐑟. 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑥𐑪𐑚 𐑝 𐑘𐑳𐑙 𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑰𐑡𐑩𐑯𐑟, 𐑞𐑱 𐑸 𐑓𐑫𐑤 𐑝 𐑓𐑲𐑑, 𐑓𐑳𐑯, 𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑛𐑯𐑩𐑕, 𐑑𐑳𐑥𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑞 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛 𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩 𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑤𐑩𐑕, 𐑮𐑪𐑤𐑦𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑮𐑱𐑑, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑯𐑴 𐑐𐑮𐑵𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑮𐑲𐑑𐑼 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑖𐑫𐑼 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑥𐑹 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑩 𐑮𐑲𐑩𐑑𐑩𐑕 𐑤𐑨𐑛 𐑨𐑑 ·𐑘𐑱𐑤 𐑹 ·𐑣𐑸𐑝𐑼𐑛. 𐑞𐑱 𐑕𐑵𐑯 𐑮𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑖 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑑𐑻𐑚𐑿𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑞𐑴, 𐑯 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑔𐑮𐑰-𐑓𐑹𐑔𐑕 𐑜𐑮𐑴𐑯, 𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑒 𐑳𐑐, 𐑯 𐑕𐑧𐑐𐑼𐑩𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑜𐑴 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑝 𐑕𐑧𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑟, 𐑣𐑸𐑰𐑥𐑟.

𐑩𐑯𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑐𐑶𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑛𐑦𐑓𐑼𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑢𐑰𐑯 𐑞 𐑥𐑱𐑤 𐑯 𐑓𐑰𐑥𐑱𐑤 𐑕𐑒𐑵𐑤𐑟 𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑥𐑹 𐑒𐑨𐑮𐑩𐑒𐑑𐑼𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑩𐑟. 𐑕𐑱 𐑿 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑒 𐑩 ·𐑓𐑹𐑑𐑦-𐑚𐑨𐑮𐑩𐑤-𐑚𐑫𐑤—𐑐𐑫𐑼 𐑛𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑤! 𐑷𐑤 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑮𐑱𐑛𐑟 𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑥𐑧𐑥𐑚𐑼 𐑝 𐑞 𐑣𐑸𐑰𐑥 𐑕𐑒𐑵𐑤, 𐑯 𐑣𐑻 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑨𐑯𐑘𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑕𐑢𐑦𐑥 𐑼𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑣𐑻 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑑𐑴𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑻𐑯, 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑤𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑴 𐑯𐑽 𐑣𐑻 𐑯 𐑕𐑴 𐑤𐑪𐑙, 𐑨𐑟 𐑞𐑧𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑝𐑟 𐑑 𐑓𐑷𐑤 𐑩 𐑐𐑮𐑱.

·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 89. 𐑓𐑭𐑕𐑑-·𐑓𐑦𐑖 𐑯 ·𐑤𐑵𐑕-·𐑓𐑦𐑖.

𐑞 𐑩𐑤𐑵𐑠𐑩𐑯 𐑑 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑓 𐑯 𐑢𐑱𐑓-𐑐𐑴𐑤𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯, 𐑯𐑦𐑕𐑧𐑕𐑦𐑑𐑱𐑑𐑕 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑩𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑤𐑷𐑟 𐑯 𐑮𐑧𐑜𐑿𐑤𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑼𐑦, 𐑝 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑓 𐑥𐑱 𐑚𐑰 𐑛𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑕𐑦𐑥𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑯 𐑚𐑨𐑡.

𐑦𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑕𐑧𐑝𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑕 𐑸 𐑒𐑮𐑵𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑦, 𐑩 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑥𐑱 𐑚𐑰 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑒 𐑚𐑲 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑤, 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑱𐑐, 𐑯 𐑚𐑰 𐑓𐑲𐑯𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑦𐑤𐑛 𐑯 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑗𐑼𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑩𐑯𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑝𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑤; 𐑯 𐑣𐑽𐑦𐑯 𐑸 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑮𐑲𐑟𐑛 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑥𐑲𐑯𐑼 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑡𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑟, 𐑷𐑤 𐑐𐑸𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑜𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑓𐑰𐑗𐑼. 𐑓 𐑦𐑜𐑟𐑭𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑤,—𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑩 𐑢𐑽𐑦 𐑯 𐑐𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑗𐑱𐑕 𐑯 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑗𐑼 𐑝 𐑩 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑞 𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦 𐑥𐑱 𐑜𐑧𐑑 𐑤𐑵𐑕 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑚𐑲 𐑮𐑰𐑟𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑩 𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑹𐑥; 𐑯 𐑛𐑮𐑦𐑓𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑸 𐑩𐑢𐑱 𐑑 𐑤𐑰𐑢𐑼𐑛, 𐑚𐑰 𐑮𐑰𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑚𐑲 𐑩 𐑕𐑧𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑼, 𐑣𐑵, 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑒𐑭𐑥, 𐑕𐑯𐑳𐑜𐑤𐑦 𐑑𐑴𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑙𐑕𐑲𐑛, 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑒 𐑝 𐑤𐑲𐑓 𐑹 𐑤𐑲𐑯. 𐑞𐑳𐑕 𐑞 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑝𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑕 𐑯 𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑿𐑑𐑕 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑪𐑓𐑩𐑯 𐑼𐑲𐑟 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑢𐑰𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑼𐑥𐑧𐑯, 𐑢𐑻 𐑞𐑺 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑹 𐑳𐑯𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑯, 𐑿𐑯𐑦𐑝𐑻𐑕𐑩𐑤, 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑿𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑤𐑷 𐑩𐑐𐑤𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑒𐑱𐑕𐑩𐑟.

𐑐𐑼𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑕 𐑞 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑓𐑹𐑥𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑒𐑴𐑛 𐑷𐑔𐑼𐑲𐑟𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑤𐑧𐑡𐑦𐑕𐑤𐑩𐑑𐑦𐑝 𐑦𐑯𐑨𐑒𐑑𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑, 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑝 ·𐑣𐑪𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛. 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑮𐑰𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑑𐑕-·𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑯 ⸰𐑱𐑛 1695. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞𐑴 𐑯𐑴 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑯𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑤𐑷, 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑩𐑥𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑼𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑴𐑯 𐑤𐑧𐑡𐑦𐑕𐑤𐑱𐑑𐑼𐑟 𐑯 𐑤𐑷𐑘𐑼𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑥𐑨𐑑𐑼. 𐑞𐑱 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑝𐑲𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑩 𐑕𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑥 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑓 𐑑𐑻𐑕 𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑣𐑧𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑝𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑕𐑼𐑐𐑭𐑕𐑩𐑟 ·𐑡𐑳𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑾𐑯'𐑟 ·𐑐𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑕 𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑲-𐑤𐑷𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑗𐑲𐑯𐑰𐑟 ·𐑕𐑩𐑕𐑲𐑩𐑑𐑦 𐑓 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑩𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 ·𐑥𐑧𐑛𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑳𐑞𐑼 ·𐑐𐑰𐑐𐑩𐑤'𐑟 ·𐑚𐑦𐑟𐑯𐑩𐑕. 𐑘𐑧𐑕; 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑤𐑷𐑟 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑦𐑯𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑪𐑯 𐑩 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑯 ·𐑨𐑯'𐑟 𐑓𐑸𐑞𐑦𐑙, 𐑹 𐑞 𐑚𐑸𐑚 𐑝 𐑩 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯, 𐑯 𐑢𐑹𐑯 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑞 𐑯𐑧𐑒, 𐑕𐑴 𐑕𐑥𐑷𐑤 𐑸 𐑞𐑱.

𐑲. 𐑩 ·𐑓𐑭𐑕𐑑-·𐑓𐑦𐑖 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑪𐑙𐑟 𐑑 𐑞 𐑐𐑸𐑑𐑦 𐑓𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑑 𐑦𐑑.

II. 𐑩 ·𐑤𐑵𐑕-·𐑓𐑦𐑖 𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑺 𐑜𐑱𐑥 𐑓 𐑧𐑯𐑦𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦 𐑣𐑵 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑕𐑵𐑯𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑒𐑨𐑗 𐑦𐑑.

𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑟 𐑞 𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑗𐑦𐑓 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑴𐑛 𐑦𐑟 𐑞 𐑨𐑛𐑥𐑼𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑚𐑮𐑰𐑝𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑝 𐑦𐑑, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑯𐑦𐑕𐑧𐑕𐑦𐑑𐑱𐑑𐑕 𐑩 𐑝𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑝𐑪𐑤𐑿𐑥 𐑝 𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑺𐑦𐑟 𐑑 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑑.

𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑: 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑩 ·𐑓𐑭𐑕𐑑-·𐑓𐑦𐑖? 𐑩𐑤𐑲𐑝 𐑹 𐑛𐑧𐑛 𐑩 𐑓𐑦𐑖 𐑦𐑟 𐑑𐑧𐑒𐑯𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑦 𐑓𐑭𐑕𐑑, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩𐑯 𐑪𐑒𐑿𐑐𐑲𐑛 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑹 𐑚𐑴𐑑, 𐑚𐑲 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑥𐑰𐑛𐑾𐑥 𐑨𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑴𐑤𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑪𐑒𐑿𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑹 𐑪𐑒𐑿𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕,—𐑩 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑, 𐑩𐑯 𐑹, 𐑩 𐑯𐑲𐑯-𐑦𐑯𐑗 𐑒𐑱𐑚𐑩𐑤, 𐑩 𐑑𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑜𐑮𐑨𐑓 𐑢𐑲𐑼, 𐑹 𐑩 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑝 𐑒𐑪𐑚𐑢𐑧𐑚, 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥. 𐑤𐑲𐑒𐑢𐑲𐑟 𐑩 𐑓𐑦𐑖 𐑦𐑟 𐑑𐑧𐑒𐑯𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑦 𐑓𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑦𐑑 𐑚𐑺𐑟 𐑩 𐑢𐑱𐑓, 𐑹 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑩𐑜𐑯𐑲𐑟𐑛 𐑕𐑦𐑥𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑐𐑩𐑟𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑯; 𐑕𐑴 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑐𐑸𐑑𐑦 𐑢𐑱𐑓𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑑 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑯𐑕 𐑞𐑺 𐑩𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑨𐑑 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑑 𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑦𐑑 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑙𐑕𐑲𐑛, 𐑨𐑟 𐑢𐑧𐑤 𐑨𐑟 𐑞𐑺 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑕𐑴 𐑑 𐑛𐑵.

𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑸 𐑕𐑲𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑒 𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑺𐑦𐑟; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞 𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑺𐑦𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑝𐑟 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑸𐑛 𐑢𐑻𐑛𐑟 𐑯 𐑣𐑸𐑛𐑼 𐑯𐑪𐑒𐑕—𐑞 ·𐑒𐑴𐑒-𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯-·𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑓𐑦𐑕𐑑. 𐑑𐑮𐑵, 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑞 𐑥𐑹 𐑳𐑐𐑮𐑲𐑑 𐑯 𐑪𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑩𐑤𐑬𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑸 𐑷𐑤𐑢𐑱𐑟 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑓 𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑽 𐑒𐑱𐑕𐑩𐑟, 𐑢𐑺 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑚𐑰 𐑩𐑯 𐑬𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑡𐑩𐑕 𐑥𐑪𐑮𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑯𐑡𐑳𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑕 𐑓 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑐𐑸𐑑𐑦 𐑑 𐑒𐑤𐑱𐑥 𐑐𐑩𐑟𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑩 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑐𐑮𐑰𐑝𐑾𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑗𐑱𐑕𐑑 𐑹 𐑒𐑦𐑤𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑩𐑯𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑐𐑸𐑑𐑦. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑳𐑞𐑼𐑟 𐑸 𐑚𐑲 𐑯𐑴 𐑥𐑰𐑯𐑟 𐑕𐑴 𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑵𐑐𐑿𐑤𐑩𐑕.

𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑓𐑦𐑓𐑑𐑦 𐑘𐑽𐑟 𐑩𐑜𐑴 𐑞𐑺 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩 𐑒𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑾𐑕 𐑒𐑱𐑕 𐑝 𐑢𐑱𐑤-𐑑𐑮𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑜𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑯 ·𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛, 𐑢𐑺𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑓𐑕 𐑕𐑧𐑑 𐑓𐑹𐑔 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑩 𐑣𐑸𐑛 𐑗𐑱𐑕 𐑝 𐑩 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑯𐑹𐑞𐑼𐑯 𐑕𐑰𐑟; 𐑯 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑰𐑛 𐑞𐑱 (𐑞 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑓𐑕) 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑕𐑩𐑒𐑕𐑰𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑓𐑦𐑖; 𐑞𐑱 𐑢𐑻 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑, 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑐𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑤 𐑝 𐑞𐑺 𐑤𐑲𐑝𐑟, 𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑲𐑡𐑛 𐑑 𐑓𐑼𐑕𐑱𐑒 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑞𐑺 𐑤𐑲𐑯𐑟, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑚𐑴𐑑 𐑦𐑑𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓. 𐑳𐑤𐑑𐑦𐑥𐑩𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑞 𐑛𐑦𐑓𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕 (𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑵 𐑝 𐑩𐑯𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑖𐑦𐑐) 𐑒𐑱𐑥 𐑳𐑐 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑒, 𐑒𐑦𐑤𐑛, 𐑕𐑰𐑟𐑛, 𐑯 𐑓𐑲𐑯𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑩𐑐𐑮𐑴𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑞 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑲𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑓𐑕. 𐑯 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑛𐑦𐑓𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑢𐑻 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞, 𐑞𐑺 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑯𐑨𐑐𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑼𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑓𐑕' 𐑑𐑰𐑔, 𐑯 𐑩𐑖𐑫𐑼𐑛 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑢𐑱 𐑝 𐑛𐑪𐑒𐑕𐑪𐑤𐑩𐑡𐑦 𐑑 𐑞 𐑛𐑰𐑛 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑛𐑳𐑯, 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑯𐑬 𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑱𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑤𐑲𐑯, 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑟, 𐑯 𐑚𐑴𐑑, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑱𐑯𐑛 𐑩𐑑𐑨𐑗𐑑 𐑑 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑰𐑠𐑼. 𐑢𐑺𐑓𐑹 𐑞 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑓𐑕 𐑯𐑬 𐑕𐑵𐑛 𐑓 𐑞 𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑳𐑝𐑼𐑦 𐑝 𐑞 𐑝𐑨𐑤𐑿 𐑝 𐑞𐑺 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑤𐑲𐑯, 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑟, 𐑯 𐑚𐑴𐑑.

·𐑥𐑼 ·𐑻𐑕𐑒𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑤 𐑓 𐑞 𐑛𐑦𐑓𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕; ·𐑤𐑹𐑛 ·𐑧𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑚𐑼𐑩 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞 𐑡𐑳𐑡. 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑒𐑹𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑛𐑦𐑓𐑧𐑯𐑕, 𐑞 𐑢𐑦𐑑𐑦 ·𐑻𐑕𐑒𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑪𐑯 𐑑 𐑦𐑤𐑳𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑩𐑟𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯, 𐑚𐑲 𐑩𐑤𐑵𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑩 𐑮𐑰𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑥. 𐑒𐑪𐑯. 𐑒𐑱𐑕, 𐑢𐑺𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑥𐑩𐑯, 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑦𐑯 𐑝𐑱𐑯 𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑚𐑮𐑲𐑛𐑩𐑤 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑲𐑓'𐑕 𐑝𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑕𐑯𐑩𐑕, 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑩𐑚𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑣𐑻 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑰𐑟 𐑝 𐑤𐑲𐑓; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑒𐑹𐑕 𐑝 𐑘𐑽𐑟, 𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑐, 𐑣𐑰 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑑𐑿𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑩𐑯 𐑨𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑳𐑝𐑼 𐑐𐑩𐑟𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑣𐑻. ·𐑻𐑕𐑒𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑕𐑲𐑛; 𐑯 𐑣𐑰 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑕𐑩𐑐𐑹𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑕𐑱𐑦𐑙, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑴 𐑞 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑼𐑦𐑡𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑛 𐑞 𐑤𐑱𐑛𐑦, 𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑕 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑣𐑻 𐑓𐑭𐑕𐑑, 𐑯 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑲 𐑮𐑰𐑟𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑧𐑕 𐑝 𐑣𐑻 𐑐𐑤𐑳𐑯𐑡𐑦𐑙 𐑝𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑕𐑯𐑩𐑕, 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑩𐑚𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑣𐑻; 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑩𐑚𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑯 𐑣𐑻 𐑣𐑰 𐑛𐑦𐑛, 𐑕𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑖𐑰 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑱𐑥 𐑩 𐑤𐑵𐑕-𐑓𐑦𐑖; 𐑯 𐑞𐑺𐑓𐑹 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑩 𐑕𐑳𐑚𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑢𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑮𐑰-𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑛 𐑣𐑻, 𐑞 𐑤𐑱𐑛𐑦 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑱𐑥 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑚𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑢𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑥𐑩𐑯'𐑟 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑐𐑼𐑑𐑦, 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑢𐑪𐑑𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑻.

𐑯𐑬 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑒𐑱𐑕 ·𐑻𐑕𐑒𐑦𐑯 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑦𐑜𐑟𐑭𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑯 𐑞 𐑤𐑱𐑛𐑦 𐑢𐑻 𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑦𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑒𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑤𐑩𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑩𐑑𐑦𐑝 𐑝 𐑰𐑗 𐑳𐑞𐑼.

𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑐𐑤𐑰𐑛𐑦𐑙𐑟, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑼 𐑐𐑤𐑰𐑛𐑦𐑙𐑟, 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑛𐑵𐑤𐑦 𐑣𐑻𐑛, 𐑞 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑤𐑻𐑯𐑛 𐑡𐑳𐑡 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑧𐑑 𐑑𐑻𐑥𐑟 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑲𐑛𐑩𐑛, 𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑑,—𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑓 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑, 𐑣𐑰 𐑩𐑢𐑹𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑑 𐑑 𐑞 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑓𐑕, 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑪𐑟 𐑞𐑱 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑥𐑽𐑤𐑦 𐑩𐑚𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑑 𐑑 𐑕𐑱𐑝 𐑞𐑺 𐑤𐑲𐑝𐑟; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑮𐑦𐑜𐑸𐑛 𐑑 𐑞 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑩𐑝𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑟, 𐑯 𐑤𐑲𐑯, 𐑞𐑱 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑪𐑙𐑛 𐑑 𐑞 𐑛𐑦𐑓𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕; 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑪𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩 ·𐑤𐑵𐑕-·𐑓𐑦𐑖 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑝 𐑞 𐑓𐑲𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑗𐑼; 𐑯 𐑞 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑟 𐑯 𐑤𐑲𐑯 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑪𐑟 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑦𐑖 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑪𐑓 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞𐑧𐑥, 𐑦𐑑 (𐑞 𐑓𐑦𐑖) 𐑩𐑒𐑢𐑲𐑼𐑛 𐑩 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑐𐑼𐑑𐑦 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑸𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑟; 𐑯 𐑣𐑧𐑯𐑕 𐑧𐑯𐑦𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦 𐑣𐑵 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼𐑢𐑼𐑛𐑟 𐑑𐑫𐑒 𐑞 𐑓𐑦𐑖 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑩 𐑮𐑲𐑑 𐑑 𐑞𐑧𐑥. 𐑯𐑬 𐑞 𐑛𐑦𐑓𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼𐑢𐑼𐑛𐑟 𐑑𐑫𐑒 𐑞 𐑓𐑦𐑖; 𐑻𐑜𐑴, 𐑞 𐑩𐑓𐑹𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑸𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑞𐑺𐑟.

𐑩 𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑦𐑠𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑤𐑻𐑯𐑛 ·𐑡𐑳𐑡, 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑐𐑪𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑩𐑚𐑡𐑧𐑒𐑑 𐑑 𐑦𐑑. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑐𐑤𐑬𐑛 𐑳𐑐 𐑑 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑲𐑥𐑼𐑦 𐑮𐑪𐑒 𐑝 𐑞 𐑥𐑨𐑑𐑼, 𐑞 𐑑𐑵 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑐𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑤𐑱𐑛 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑑𐑢𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑤𐑷𐑟 𐑐𐑮𐑰𐑝𐑾𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑢𐑴𐑑𐑩𐑛, 𐑯 𐑩𐑐𐑤𐑲𐑛 𐑯 𐑦𐑤𐑵𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑲 ·𐑤𐑹𐑛 ·𐑧𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑚𐑼𐑩 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑩𐑚𐑳𐑝 𐑕𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑒𐑱𐑕; 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑑𐑵 𐑤𐑷𐑟 𐑑𐑳𐑗𐑦𐑙 ·𐑓𐑭𐑕𐑑-·𐑓𐑦𐑖 𐑯 ·𐑤𐑵𐑕-·𐑓𐑦𐑖, 𐑲 𐑕𐑱, 𐑢𐑦𐑤, 𐑪𐑯 𐑮𐑦𐑓𐑤𐑧𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯, 𐑚𐑰 𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑞 𐑓𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑝 𐑷𐑤 𐑣𐑿𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑡𐑫𐑼𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑵𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑕; 𐑓 𐑯𐑪𐑑𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑦𐑒𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑕𐑼𐑦 𐑝 𐑕𐑒𐑳𐑤𐑐𐑗𐑼, 𐑞 ·𐑑𐑧𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑤𐑷, 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑞 ·𐑑𐑧𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑓𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑲𐑯𐑟, 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑑𐑵 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑐𐑕 𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑪𐑯.

𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑩 𐑕𐑱𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑢𐑳𐑯'𐑟 𐑥𐑬𐑔, ·𐑐𐑩𐑟𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑭𐑓 𐑝 𐑞 𐑤𐑷: 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑟, 𐑮𐑦𐑜𐑸𐑛𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑣𐑬 𐑞 𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑒𐑱𐑥 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑐𐑩𐑟𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑯? 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑪𐑓𐑩𐑯 𐑐𐑩𐑟𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑟 𐑞 𐑣𐑴𐑤 𐑝 𐑞 𐑤𐑷. 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑸 𐑞 𐑕𐑦𐑯𐑿𐑟 𐑯 𐑕𐑴𐑤𐑟 𐑝 ·𐑮𐑳𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑕𐑻𐑓𐑕 𐑯 ·𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑳𐑚𐑤𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑕𐑤𐑱𐑝𐑟 𐑚𐑳𐑑 ·𐑓𐑭𐑕𐑑-·𐑓𐑦𐑖, 𐑢𐑺𐑪𐑝 𐑐𐑩𐑟𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑟 𐑞 𐑣𐑴𐑤 𐑝 𐑞 𐑤𐑷? 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑑 𐑞 𐑮𐑩𐑐𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑕 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑤𐑹𐑛 𐑦𐑟 𐑞 𐑢𐑦𐑛𐑴'𐑟 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑩 ·𐑓𐑭𐑕𐑑-·𐑓𐑦𐑖? 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑘𐑪𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑑𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑝𐑦𐑤𐑩𐑯'𐑟 𐑥𐑸𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑥𐑨𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑛𐑹-𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑑 𐑓 𐑩 𐑢𐑱𐑓; 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑩 ·𐑓𐑭𐑕𐑑-·𐑓𐑦𐑖? 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑞 𐑮𐑵𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑗 ·𐑥𐑹𐑛𐑩𐑒𐑲, 𐑞 𐑚𐑮𐑴𐑒𐑼, 𐑜𐑧𐑑𐑕 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑐𐑫𐑼 ·𐑢𐑴𐑚𐑦𐑜𐑪𐑯, 𐑞 𐑚𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑮𐑳𐑐𐑑, 𐑪𐑯 𐑩 𐑤𐑴𐑯 𐑑 𐑒𐑰𐑐 ·𐑢𐑴𐑚𐑦𐑜𐑪𐑯'𐑟 𐑓𐑨𐑥𐑤𐑦 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑝𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯; 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑮𐑵𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑩 ·𐑓𐑭𐑕𐑑-·𐑓𐑦𐑖? 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑞 ·𐑸𐑗𐑚𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑐 𐑝 ·𐑕𐑱𐑝𐑕𐑴𐑤'𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑝 £100,000 𐑕𐑰𐑟𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑕𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑑 𐑚𐑮𐑧𐑛 𐑯 𐑗𐑰𐑟 𐑝 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑛𐑟 𐑝 𐑔𐑬𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑝 𐑚𐑮𐑴𐑒𐑩𐑯-𐑚𐑨𐑒𐑑 𐑤𐑱𐑚𐑼𐑼𐑟 (𐑷𐑤 𐑖𐑫𐑼 𐑝 𐑣𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑝 ·𐑕𐑱𐑝𐑕𐑴𐑤'𐑟 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑐) 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑜𐑤𐑪𐑚𐑿𐑤𐑼 £100,000 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑩 ·𐑓𐑭𐑕𐑑-·𐑓𐑦𐑖? 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑸 𐑞 ·𐑛𐑿𐑒 𐑝 ·𐑛𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼'𐑟 𐑣𐑼𐑧𐑛𐑦𐑑𐑼𐑦 𐑑𐑬𐑯𐑟 𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑥𐑤𐑩𐑑𐑕 𐑚𐑳𐑑 ·𐑓𐑭𐑕𐑑-·𐑓𐑦𐑖? 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑛𐑬𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑽, ·𐑡𐑪𐑯 ·𐑚𐑫𐑤, 𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑫𐑼 ·𐑲𐑼𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑩 ·𐑓𐑭𐑕𐑑-·𐑓𐑦𐑖? 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑨𐑐𐑩𐑕𐑑𐑪𐑤𐑦𐑒 𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑼, ·𐑚𐑮𐑳𐑞𐑼 ·𐑡𐑪𐑯𐑩𐑔𐑩𐑯, 𐑦𐑟 ·𐑑𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑩𐑕 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑩 ·𐑓𐑭𐑕𐑑-·𐑓𐑦𐑖? 𐑯 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑰𐑟, 𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 ·𐑐𐑩𐑟𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑞 𐑣𐑴𐑤 𐑝 𐑞 𐑤𐑷?

𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑓 𐑞 𐑛𐑪𐑒𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑯 𐑝 ·𐑓𐑭𐑕𐑑-·𐑓𐑦𐑖 𐑚𐑰 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑩𐑐𐑤𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤, 𐑞 𐑒𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑛 𐑛𐑪𐑒𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑯 𐑝 ·𐑤𐑵𐑕-·𐑓𐑦𐑖 𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑥𐑹 𐑢𐑲𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑴. 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑯𐑨𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑯 𐑿𐑯𐑦𐑝𐑻𐑕𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑩𐑐𐑤𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤.

𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 ·𐑩𐑥𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑩 𐑦𐑯 1492 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑩 ·𐑤𐑵𐑕-·𐑓𐑦𐑖, 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑗 ·𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑳𐑥𐑚𐑩𐑕 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑒 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑐𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑖 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑢𐑱 𐑝 𐑢𐑱𐑓𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑑 𐑓 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑮𐑶𐑩𐑤 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑼 𐑯 𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑩𐑕? 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 ·𐑐𐑴𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑑𐑕𐑸? 𐑢𐑪𐑑 ·𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑕 𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑑𐑻𐑒? 𐑢𐑪𐑑 ·𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑾 𐑑 ·𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛? 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑤 ·𐑥𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑴 𐑚𐑰 𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑿𐑯𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑛 ·𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑑𐑕? 𐑷𐑤 ·𐑤𐑵𐑕-·𐑓𐑦𐑖.

𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑸 𐑞 ·𐑮𐑲𐑑𐑕 𐑝 ·𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑤𐑦𐑚𐑼𐑑𐑦𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛 𐑚𐑳𐑑 ·𐑤𐑵𐑕-·𐑓𐑦𐑖? 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑥𐑧𐑯'𐑟 𐑥𐑲𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑯 𐑩𐑐𐑦𐑯𐑘𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑚𐑳𐑑 ·𐑤𐑵𐑕-·𐑓𐑦𐑖? 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑐𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑮𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑡𐑩𐑕 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑰𐑓 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑩 ·𐑤𐑵𐑕-·𐑓𐑦𐑖? 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑑 𐑞 𐑪𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑕 𐑕𐑥𐑳𐑜𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑝𐑻𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑕 𐑸 𐑞 𐑔𐑷𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑼𐑟 𐑚𐑳𐑑 ·𐑤𐑵𐑕-·𐑓𐑦𐑖? 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑜𐑤𐑴𐑚 𐑦𐑑𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑩 ·𐑤𐑵𐑕-·𐑓𐑦𐑖? 𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑸 𐑿, 𐑮𐑰𐑛𐑼, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑩 ·𐑤𐑵𐑕-·𐑓𐑦𐑖 𐑯 𐑩 ·𐑓𐑭𐑕𐑑-·𐑓𐑦𐑖, 𐑑𐑵?

·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 90. 𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑟 𐑹 ·𐑑𐑱𐑤𐑟.

“𐑛𐑦 𐑚𐑱𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑩 ·𐑝𐑽𐑴 𐑕𐑩𐑓𐑲𐑕𐑦𐑑, 𐑕𐑰 𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑕 𐑣𐑨𐑚𐑰𐑑 𐑒𐑱𐑐𐑳𐑑, 𐑧𐑑 ·𐑮𐑦𐑡𐑲𐑯𐑩 𐑒𐑷𐑛𐑩𐑥.” 𐑚𐑮𐑨𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑯, l. 3, c 3.

·𐑤𐑨𐑑𐑦𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑚𐑫𐑒𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑤𐑷𐑟 𐑝 ·𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑, 𐑥𐑰𐑯𐑟, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑝 𐑷𐑤 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑗𐑼𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑧𐑯𐑦𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑒𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛, 𐑞 ·𐑒𐑦𐑙, 𐑨𐑟 ·𐑪𐑯𐑼𐑼𐑦 ·𐑜𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑛 ·𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑽, 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑞 𐑣𐑧𐑛, 𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑯 𐑚𐑰 𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑓𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑑𐑱𐑤. 𐑩 𐑛𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑠𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑗, 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑣𐑭𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑯 𐑨𐑐𐑩𐑤; 𐑞𐑺 𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑴 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑥𐑰𐑛𐑾𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑱𐑯𐑛𐑼. 𐑯𐑬 𐑨𐑟 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑤𐑷, 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑩 𐑥𐑪𐑛𐑦𐑓𐑲𐑛 𐑓𐑹𐑥, 𐑦𐑟 𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑛𐑱 𐑦𐑯 𐑓𐑹𐑕 𐑦𐑯 ·𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛; 𐑯 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑪𐑓𐑼𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑝𐑺𐑾𐑕 𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑕 𐑩 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡 𐑩𐑯𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑑𐑳𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑤𐑷 𐑝 ·𐑓𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑯 ·𐑤𐑵𐑕-·𐑓𐑦𐑖, 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑽 𐑑𐑮𐑰𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑝 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑕𐑧𐑐𐑼𐑩𐑑 𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼, 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑒𐑻𐑑𐑾𐑕 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑐𐑩𐑤 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑥𐑐𐑑𐑕 𐑞 ·𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑤𐑦𐑖 𐑮𐑱𐑤𐑢𐑱𐑟 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑕 𐑝 𐑩 𐑕𐑧𐑐𐑼𐑩𐑑 𐑒𐑸, 𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑻𐑝𐑛 𐑓 𐑞 𐑩𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑛𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑮𐑶𐑩𐑤𐑑𐑦. 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕, 𐑦𐑯 𐑒𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑾𐑕 𐑐𐑮𐑵𐑓 𐑝 𐑞 𐑓𐑨𐑒𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑩𐑚𐑳𐑝-𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑤𐑷 𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑓𐑹𐑕, 𐑲 𐑐𐑮𐑴𐑕𐑰𐑛 𐑑 𐑤𐑱 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑿 𐑩 𐑕𐑻𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑕 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑑𐑵 𐑘𐑽𐑟.

𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑪𐑯𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑥𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑯𐑼𐑟 𐑝 ·𐑛𐑴𐑝𐑼, 𐑹 ·𐑕𐑨𐑯𐑢𐑦𐑡, 𐑹 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑗𐑰𐑯𐑒𐑢𐑧 ·𐑐𐑹𐑑𐑕, 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑩 𐑣𐑸𐑛 𐑗𐑱𐑕 𐑕𐑩𐑒𐑕𐑰𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑒𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑯 𐑚𐑰𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑓𐑲𐑯 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑞𐑱 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑼𐑦𐑡𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 𐑩𐑓𐑸 𐑪𐑓 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑖𐑹. 𐑯𐑬 𐑞 ·𐑗𐑰𐑯𐑒𐑢𐑧 ·𐑐𐑹𐑑𐑕 𐑸 𐑐𐑸𐑖𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑹 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑣𐑬 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑞 𐑡𐑫𐑼𐑦𐑕𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑩 𐑕𐑹𐑑 𐑝 𐑐𐑩𐑤𐑰𐑕𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑹 𐑚𐑰𐑛𐑩𐑤, 𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑛 𐑩 ·𐑤𐑹𐑛 ·𐑢𐑹𐑛𐑩𐑯. 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑪𐑓𐑦𐑕 𐑛𐑦𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑬𐑯, 𐑲 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑰𐑝, 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑮𐑶𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑥𐑪𐑤𐑿𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑗𐑰𐑯𐑒𐑢𐑧 ·𐑐𐑹𐑑 𐑑𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑹𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑚𐑲 𐑩𐑕𐑲𐑯𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟. 𐑚𐑲 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑮𐑲𐑑𐑼𐑟 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑪𐑓𐑦𐑕 𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑛 𐑩 𐑕𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑒𐑘𐑫𐑼. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑴. 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑪𐑟 𐑞 ·𐑤𐑹𐑛 ·𐑢𐑹𐑛𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑦𐑟𐑦𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑶𐑛 𐑨𐑑 𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑓𐑪𐑚𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑻𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑟𐑦𐑑𐑕; 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑸 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑗𐑰𐑓𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑲 𐑝𐑻𐑗𐑵 𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑓𐑪𐑚𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑞𐑧𐑥.

𐑯𐑬 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑐𐑫𐑼 𐑕𐑳𐑯-𐑚𐑻𐑯𐑑 𐑥𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑯𐑼𐑟, 𐑚𐑺-𐑓𐑫𐑑𐑩𐑛, 𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞𐑺 𐑑𐑮𐑴𐑟𐑼𐑟 𐑮𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑣𐑲 𐑳𐑐 𐑪𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑰𐑤𐑦 𐑤𐑧𐑜𐑟, 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑢𐑽𐑦𐑤𐑦 𐑣𐑷𐑤𐑛 𐑞𐑺 𐑓𐑨𐑑 𐑓𐑦𐑖 𐑣𐑲 𐑯 𐑛𐑮𐑲, 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑧𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑝𐑟 𐑩 𐑜𐑫𐑛 £150 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑕 𐑶𐑤 𐑯 𐑚𐑴𐑯; 𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑓𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑕𐑦 𐑕𐑦𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑮𐑺 𐑑𐑰 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞𐑺 𐑢𐑲𐑝𐑟, 𐑯 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑱𐑤 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞𐑺 𐑒𐑮𐑴𐑯𐑦𐑟, 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑧𐑙𐑔 𐑝 𐑞𐑺 𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑝 𐑖𐑺𐑟; 𐑳𐑐 𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑐𐑕 𐑩 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑤𐑻𐑯𐑛 𐑯 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 ·𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑗𐑩𐑯 𐑯 𐑗𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑥𐑩𐑯, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑒𐑪𐑐𐑦 𐑝 ·𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑴𐑯 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑸𐑥; 𐑯 𐑤𐑱𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑑 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤'𐑟 𐑣𐑧𐑛, 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑧𐑟—“𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑪𐑓! 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑓𐑦𐑖, 𐑥𐑲 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑟, 𐑦𐑟 𐑩 ·𐑓𐑭𐑕𐑑-·𐑓𐑦𐑖. 𐑲 𐑕𐑰𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 ·𐑤𐑹𐑛 ·𐑢𐑹𐑛𐑩𐑯'𐑟.” 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑞 𐑐𐑫𐑼 𐑥𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑯𐑼𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑯𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯—𐑕𐑴 𐑑𐑮𐑵𐑤𐑦 ·𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑤𐑦𐑖—𐑯𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑑 𐑕𐑱, 𐑓𐑷𐑤 𐑑 𐑝𐑦𐑜𐑼𐑩𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑨𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑺 𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑟 𐑷𐑤 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛; 𐑥𐑰𐑯𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑮𐑵𐑓𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑜𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑼. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑯𐑴𐑢𐑲𐑟 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑞 𐑥𐑨𐑑𐑼, 𐑹 𐑨𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑕𐑪𐑓𐑩𐑯 𐑞 𐑣𐑸𐑛 𐑣𐑸𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑤𐑻𐑯𐑛 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑒𐑪𐑐𐑦 𐑝 ·𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑴𐑯. 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑧𐑙𐑔 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑞𐑧𐑥, 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑨𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑓 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑲𐑛𐑾𐑟, 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑚𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑑 𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑒,

“𐑐𐑤𐑰𐑟, 𐑕𐑻, 𐑣𐑵 𐑦𐑟 𐑞 ·𐑤𐑹𐑛 ·𐑢𐑹𐑛𐑩𐑯?”

“𐑞 ·𐑛𐑿𐑒.”

“𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞 𐑛𐑿𐑒 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑯𐑳𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑛𐑵 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑓𐑦𐑖?”

“𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑟.”

“𐑢𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑨𐑑 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑚𐑩𐑤, 𐑯 𐑐𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑤, 𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑕, 𐑯 𐑦𐑟 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑑 𐑜𐑴 𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑛𐑿𐑒'𐑕 𐑚𐑧𐑯𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑑; 𐑢𐑰 𐑜𐑧𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑯𐑳𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑨𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑓 𐑬𐑼 𐑐𐑱𐑯𐑟 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑬𐑼 𐑚𐑤𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑟?”

“𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑟.”

“𐑦𐑟 𐑞 ·𐑛𐑿𐑒 𐑕𐑴 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑐𐑫𐑼 𐑨𐑟 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑓𐑹𐑕𐑑 𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑛𐑧𐑕𐑐𐑼𐑩𐑑 𐑥𐑴𐑛 𐑝 𐑜𐑧𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑤𐑲𐑝𐑤𐑦𐑣𐑫𐑛?”

“𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑟.”

“𐑲 𐑔𐑷𐑑 𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑤𐑰𐑝 𐑥𐑲 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑚𐑧𐑛-𐑮𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑯 𐑥𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑚𐑲 𐑐𐑸𐑑 𐑝 𐑥𐑲 𐑖𐑺 𐑝 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑱𐑤.”

“𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑟.”

“𐑢𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑛𐑿𐑒 𐑚𐑰 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑒𐑢𐑹𐑑𐑼 𐑹 𐑩 𐑣𐑭𐑓?”

“𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑟.”

𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑢𐑻𐑛, 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑰𐑟𐑛 𐑯 𐑕𐑴𐑤𐑛, 𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 ·𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑕 𐑞 ·𐑛𐑿𐑒 𐑝 ·𐑢𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑙𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑰𐑝𐑛 𐑞 𐑥𐑳𐑯𐑦. 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑝𐑿𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑐𐑼𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑼 𐑤𐑲𐑑𐑕, 𐑞 𐑒𐑱𐑕 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑩 𐑚𐑺 𐑐𐑪𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑕𐑥𐑷𐑤 𐑛𐑦𐑜𐑮𐑰 𐑚𐑰 𐑛𐑰𐑥𐑛, 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑞 𐑕𐑻𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟, 𐑩 𐑮𐑭𐑞𐑼 𐑣𐑸𐑛 𐑢𐑳𐑯, 𐑩𐑯 𐑪𐑯𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑒𐑤𐑻𐑡𐑦𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑑𐑬𐑯 𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑓𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑩𐑛𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑩 𐑯𐑴𐑑 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 ·𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑕, 𐑚𐑧𐑜𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑑 𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑞 𐑒𐑱𐑕 𐑝 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑳𐑯𐑓𐑹𐑗𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑑 𐑥𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑯𐑼𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑓𐑫𐑤 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑼𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯. 𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑥𐑲 ·𐑤𐑹𐑛 ·𐑛𐑿𐑒 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑚𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑤𐑲𐑛 (𐑚𐑴𐑔 𐑤𐑧𐑑𐑼𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑐𐑳𐑚𐑤𐑦𐑖𐑑) 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑷𐑤𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑦 𐑛𐑳𐑯 𐑕𐑴, 𐑯 𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑰𐑝𐑛 𐑞 𐑥𐑳𐑯𐑦, 𐑯 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑚𐑰 𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑲𐑡𐑛 𐑑 𐑞 𐑮𐑧𐑝𐑼𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑓 𐑓 𐑞 𐑓𐑿𐑗𐑼 𐑣𐑰 (𐑞 𐑮𐑧𐑝𐑼𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑥𐑩𐑯) 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑲𐑯 𐑥𐑧𐑛𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑐𐑰𐑐𐑩𐑤'𐑟 𐑚𐑦𐑟𐑯𐑩𐑕. 𐑦𐑟 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑥𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑥𐑨𐑯, 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑒𐑹𐑯𐑼𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑒𐑦𐑙𐑛𐑩𐑥𐑟, 𐑪𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑒𐑴𐑻𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑭𐑥𐑟 𐑝 𐑚𐑧𐑜𐑼𐑟?

𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑰 𐑕𐑰𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑒𐑱𐑕 𐑞 𐑩𐑤𐑧𐑡𐑛 𐑮𐑲𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑛𐑿𐑒 𐑑 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩 𐑛𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑜𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑪𐑝𐑮𐑩𐑯. 𐑢𐑰 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑯𐑰𐑛𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑢𐑲𐑼 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑪𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑐𐑩𐑤 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑪𐑝𐑮𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑟 𐑼𐑦𐑡𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑮𐑲𐑑. 𐑞 𐑤𐑷 𐑦𐑑𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑷𐑤𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑦 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑕𐑧𐑑 𐑓𐑹𐑔. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 ·𐑐𐑤𐑬𐑛𐑩𐑯 𐑜𐑦𐑝𐑟 𐑳𐑕 𐑞 𐑮𐑰𐑟𐑩𐑯 𐑓 𐑦𐑑. 𐑕𐑧𐑟 ·𐑐𐑤𐑬𐑛𐑩𐑯, 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑕𐑴 𐑒𐑷𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑪𐑙𐑟 𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑯 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑯, “𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑪𐑟 𐑝 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑕𐑵𐑐𐑽𐑽 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑩𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑕.” 𐑯 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑕𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑱𐑑𐑼𐑟 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑛 𐑩 𐑒𐑴𐑡𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑸𐑜𐑿𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑥𐑨𐑑𐑼𐑟.

𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑲 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑞 ·𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑞 𐑣𐑧𐑛, 𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑯 𐑞 𐑑𐑱𐑤? 𐑩 𐑮𐑰𐑟𐑩𐑯 𐑓 𐑞𐑨𐑑, 𐑘𐑰 𐑤𐑷𐑘𐑼𐑟!

𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑑𐑮𐑰𐑑𐑦𐑟 𐑪𐑯 “𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑯-·𐑜𐑴𐑤𐑛,” 𐑹 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑯-𐑐𐑦𐑯𐑥𐑳𐑯𐑦, 𐑩𐑯 𐑴𐑤𐑛 ·𐑒𐑦𐑙'𐑟 ·𐑚𐑧𐑯𐑗 𐑷𐑔𐑼, 𐑢𐑳𐑯 ·𐑢𐑦𐑤𐑾𐑥 ·𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑯, 𐑞𐑳𐑕 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑹𐑕𐑩𐑔: “𐑘𐑰 𐑑𐑱𐑤 𐑦𐑟 𐑘𐑰 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑯'𐑟, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑘𐑰 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑯'𐑟 𐑢𐑹𐑛𐑮𐑴𐑚 𐑥𐑱 𐑚𐑰 𐑕𐑩𐑐𐑤𐑲𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑘𐑰 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑚𐑴𐑯.” 𐑯𐑬 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑨𐑑 𐑩 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑒 𐑤𐑦𐑥𐑚𐑼 𐑚𐑴𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑯𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑹 ·𐑮𐑲𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑤𐑸𐑡𐑤𐑦 𐑿𐑟𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑤𐑱𐑛𐑦𐑟' 𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑩𐑟. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑚𐑴𐑯 𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑑𐑱𐑤; 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑣𐑧𐑛, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑦𐑟 𐑩 𐑕𐑨𐑛 𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑓 𐑩 𐑕𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑕 𐑤𐑷𐑘𐑼 𐑤𐑲𐑒 ·𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑯. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑞 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑯 𐑩 𐑥𐑻𐑥𐑱𐑛, 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑑𐑱𐑤? 𐑩𐑯 𐑨𐑤𐑦𐑜𐑹𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑥𐑰𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑱 𐑤𐑻𐑒 𐑣𐑽.

𐑞𐑺 𐑸 𐑑𐑵 𐑮𐑶𐑩𐑤 𐑓𐑦𐑖 𐑕𐑴 𐑕𐑑𐑲𐑤𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 ·𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑤𐑦𐑖 𐑤𐑷 𐑮𐑲𐑑𐑼𐑟—𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑻𐑡𐑩𐑯; 𐑚𐑴𐑔 𐑮𐑶𐑩𐑤 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑐𐑼𐑑𐑦 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑤𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑑𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟, 𐑯 𐑯𐑪𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑩𐑐𐑤𐑲𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑔 𐑚𐑮𐑭𐑯𐑗 𐑝 𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑬𐑯'𐑟 𐑹𐑛𐑦𐑯𐑼𐑦 𐑮𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑯𐑿. 𐑲 𐑯𐑴 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑷𐑔𐑼 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑝 𐑞 𐑥𐑨𐑑𐑼; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑦𐑯𐑓𐑼𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑟 𐑑 𐑥𐑰 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑻𐑡𐑩𐑯 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑛𐑦𐑝𐑲𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑢𐑱 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑞 ·𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑰𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑣𐑲𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑧𐑯𐑕 𐑯 𐑦𐑤𐑨𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑽 𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑓𐑦𐑖, 𐑢𐑦𐑗, 𐑕𐑦𐑥𐑚𐑪𐑤𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑦𐑜𐑸𐑛𐑩𐑛, 𐑥𐑱 𐑐𐑪𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑰 𐑣𐑿𐑥𐑼𐑩𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑜𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑿𐑥𐑛 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑡𐑰𐑯𐑦𐑨𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑦. 𐑯 𐑞𐑳𐑕 𐑞𐑺 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑟 𐑩 𐑮𐑰𐑟𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑟, 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑤𐑷.

·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 91. 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛 ·𐑥𐑰𐑑𐑕 𐑞 ·𐑮𐑴𐑟-·𐑚𐑳𐑛.

“𐑦𐑯 𐑝𐑱𐑯 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑑 𐑮𐑱𐑒 𐑓 ·𐑨𐑥𐑚𐑼𐑜𐑮𐑦𐑰𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑐𐑷𐑯𐑗 𐑝 𐑞𐑦𐑕 ·𐑤𐑩𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑔𐑩𐑯, 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑳𐑓𐑼𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑓𐑰𐑑𐑼 𐑛𐑦𐑯𐑲𐑦𐑙 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑢𐑲𐑼𐑦.” 𐑕𐑻 T. 𐑚𐑮𐑬𐑯, V.E.

·𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩 𐑢𐑰𐑒 𐑹 𐑑𐑵 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑞 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑰𐑯 𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛, 𐑯 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑢𐑰 𐑢𐑻 𐑕𐑤𐑴𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑩 𐑕𐑤𐑰𐑐𐑦, 𐑝𐑱𐑐𐑼𐑦, 𐑥𐑦𐑛-𐑛𐑱 𐑕𐑰, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑯𐑴𐑟𐑩𐑟 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛'𐑟 𐑛𐑧𐑒 𐑐𐑮𐑵𐑝𐑛 𐑥𐑹 𐑝𐑦𐑡𐑦𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑳𐑝𐑼𐑼𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑞 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑐𐑺𐑟 𐑝 𐑲𐑟 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑓𐑑. 𐑩 𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑽 𐑯 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑐𐑤𐑧𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑕𐑥𐑧𐑤 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑥𐑧𐑤𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑰.

“𐑲 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑚𐑧𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑯𐑬,” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚, “𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑢𐑺 𐑣𐑽𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑𐑕 𐑸 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑝 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑛𐑮𐑳𐑜𐑛 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑢𐑰 𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑞 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑛𐑱. 𐑲 𐑔𐑷𐑑 𐑞𐑱 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑒𐑰𐑤 𐑳𐑐 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑤𐑪𐑙.”

𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦, 𐑞 𐑝𐑱𐑐𐑼𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑩𐑛𐑝𐑭𐑯𐑕 𐑕𐑤𐑦𐑛 𐑩𐑕𐑲𐑛; 𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑤𐑱 𐑩 𐑖𐑦𐑐, 𐑣𐑵𐑟 𐑓𐑻𐑤𐑛 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑴𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑕𐑹𐑑 𐑝 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑙𐑕𐑲𐑛. 𐑨𐑟 𐑢𐑰 𐑜𐑤𐑲𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑯𐑽𐑼, 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑼 𐑖𐑴𐑛 ·𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑯𐑗 𐑒𐑳𐑤𐑼𐑟 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑰𐑒; 𐑯 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑧𐑛𐑦𐑦𐑙 𐑒𐑤𐑬𐑛 𐑝 𐑝𐑳𐑤𐑗𐑼 𐑕𐑰-𐑓𐑬𐑤 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑻𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑛, 𐑯 𐑣𐑪𐑝𐑼𐑛, 𐑯 𐑕𐑢𐑵𐑐𐑑 𐑼𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑙𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑞 𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑼𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑒𐑷𐑤 𐑩 𐑚𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑟, 𐑩 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑛𐑲𐑛 𐑳𐑯𐑥𐑩𐑤𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑰, 𐑯 𐑕𐑴 𐑓𐑤𐑴𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑩𐑯 𐑳𐑯𐑩𐑐𐑮𐑴𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑒𐑹𐑐𐑕. 𐑦𐑑 𐑥𐑱 𐑢𐑧𐑤 𐑚𐑰 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑰𐑝𐑛, 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑩𐑯 𐑳𐑯𐑕𐑱𐑝𐑼𐑦 𐑴𐑛𐑼 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩 𐑥𐑨𐑕 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑣𐑱𐑤; 𐑢𐑻𐑕 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑩𐑯 ·𐑩𐑕𐑽𐑾𐑯 𐑕𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑜, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑞 𐑤𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑸 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑐𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑑 𐑚𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑞 𐑛𐑦𐑐𐑸𐑑𐑩𐑛. 𐑕𐑴 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑪𐑤𐑼𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑰𐑛 𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑜𐑸𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑕𐑳𐑥, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑯𐑴 𐑒𐑿𐑐𐑦𐑛𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑐𐑼𐑕𐑢𐑱𐑛 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑑 𐑥𐑫𐑼 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑙𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑝 𐑦𐑑. 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑸 𐑞𐑺 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑣𐑵 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑛𐑵 𐑦𐑑; 𐑯𐑪𐑑𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑓𐑨𐑒𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑶𐑤 𐑩𐑚𐑑𐑱𐑯𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑕𐑳𐑚𐑡𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑕 𐑦𐑟 𐑝 𐑩 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑦𐑯𐑓𐑽𐑽 𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑦, 𐑯 𐑚𐑲 𐑯𐑴 𐑥𐑰𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑯𐑱𐑗𐑼 𐑝 𐑨𐑑𐑼-𐑝-𐑮𐑴𐑟.

𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑯𐑽𐑼 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑲𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑮𐑰𐑟, 𐑢𐑰 𐑕𐑷 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑯𐑗𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑩 𐑕𐑧𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑙𐑕𐑲𐑛; 𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑕𐑧𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑥𐑹 𐑝 𐑩 𐑯𐑴𐑟𐑜𐑱 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑. 𐑦𐑯 𐑑𐑮𐑵𐑔, 𐑦𐑑 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑛 𐑬𐑑 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑚𐑤𐑩𐑥𐑨𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑥 𐑑 𐑛𐑮𐑲 𐑳𐑐 𐑯 𐑛𐑲 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑕𐑹𐑑 𐑝 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑛𐑦𐑡𐑩𐑕 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑐𐑕𐑾, 𐑹 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑡𐑧𐑕𐑗𐑩𐑯; 𐑤𐑰𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑺 𐑛𐑦𐑓𐑳𐑙𐑒𐑑 𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦𐑟 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑲𐑼𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑮𐑳𐑐𐑑 𐑝 𐑧𐑯𐑦𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑶𐑤. 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼𐑞𐑩𐑤𐑧𐑕, 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑐𐑼 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕 𐑢𐑰 𐑖𐑨𐑤 𐑕𐑰 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑯𐑴 𐑯𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑼𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑑𐑻𐑯 𐑳𐑐 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑴𐑟 𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑨𐑟 𐑞𐑦𐑕, 𐑣𐑬𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑣𐑰 𐑥𐑱 𐑖𐑳𐑯 𐑚𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑤.

𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑯𐑬 𐑕𐑢𐑧𐑐𐑑 𐑕𐑴 𐑯𐑲 𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑼, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚 𐑝𐑬𐑛 𐑣𐑰 𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑩𐑜𐑯𐑲𐑟𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑳𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑐𐑱𐑛-𐑐𐑴𐑤 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑨𐑙𐑜𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑤𐑲𐑯𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑻 𐑯𐑪𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑞 𐑑𐑱𐑤 𐑝 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟.

“𐑞𐑺'𐑟 𐑩 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑓𐑧𐑤𐑴, 𐑯𐑬,” 𐑣𐑰 𐑚𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑤𐑭𐑓𐑑, 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐'𐑕 𐑚𐑬𐑟, “𐑞𐑺'𐑟 𐑩 𐑡𐑨𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑓 𐑘𐑰! 𐑲 𐑢𐑧𐑤 𐑯𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑰𐑟 ·𐑒𐑮𐑨𐑐𐑴𐑟 𐑝 ·𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑯𐑗𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑸 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑐𐑫𐑼 𐑛𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑼𐑦; 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑤𐑴𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑺 𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕 𐑓 𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑒𐑼𐑟, 𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑓 ·𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑕𐑐𐑬𐑑𐑕; 𐑘𐑧𐑕, 𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞𐑺 𐑐𐑹𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞𐑺 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑓𐑫𐑤 𐑝 𐑚𐑪𐑒𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑝 𐑑𐑨𐑤𐑴 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑤𐑟, 𐑯 𐑒𐑱𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑝 𐑕𐑯𐑳𐑓𐑼𐑟, 𐑓𐑹𐑕𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑶𐑤 𐑞𐑱 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑜𐑧𐑑 𐑢𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑦𐑯𐑳𐑓 𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑐 𐑞 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯'𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑒 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵; 𐑲, 𐑢𐑰 𐑷𐑤 𐑯𐑴 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑟; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑤𐑫𐑒 𐑘𐑰, 𐑣𐑽'𐑟 𐑩 ·𐑒𐑮𐑨𐑐𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑬𐑼 𐑤𐑰𐑝𐑦𐑙𐑟, 𐑞 𐑛𐑮𐑳𐑜𐑛 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑞𐑺, 𐑲 𐑥𐑰𐑯; 𐑲, 𐑯 𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑑𐑵 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑱𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑛𐑮𐑲 𐑚𐑴𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑕 𐑓𐑦𐑖 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑞𐑺. 𐑐𐑫𐑼 𐑛𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑤! 𐑲 𐑕𐑱, 𐑐𐑭𐑕 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑩 𐑣𐑨𐑑, 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑢𐑳𐑯, 𐑯 𐑤𐑧𐑑'𐑕 𐑥𐑱𐑒 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑩 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑩 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑶𐑤 𐑓 𐑛𐑽 𐑗𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑦'𐑟 𐑕𐑱𐑒. 𐑓 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑶𐑤 𐑣𐑰'𐑤 𐑜𐑧𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑛𐑮𐑳𐑜𐑛 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑞𐑺, 𐑢𐑫𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑓𐑦𐑑 𐑑 𐑚𐑻𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑡𐑱𐑤; 𐑯𐑴, 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑛𐑧𐑥𐑛 𐑕𐑧𐑤. 𐑯 𐑨𐑟 𐑓 𐑞 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑢𐑲, 𐑲'𐑤 𐑩𐑜𐑮𐑰 𐑑 𐑜𐑧𐑑 𐑥𐑹 𐑶𐑤 𐑚𐑲 𐑗𐑪𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑳𐑐 𐑯 𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑦𐑙 𐑬𐑑 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑬𐑼𐑟, 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑣𐑰'𐑤 𐑜𐑧𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑚𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑚𐑴𐑯𐑟; 𐑞𐑴, 𐑯𐑬 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑲 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒 𐑝 𐑦𐑑, 𐑦𐑑 𐑥𐑱 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑱𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑻𐑔 𐑩 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑛𐑰𐑤 𐑥𐑹 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑶𐑤; 𐑘𐑧𐑕, 𐑨𐑥𐑚𐑼𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑕. 𐑲 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑯𐑬 𐑦𐑓 𐑬𐑼 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑔𐑷𐑑 𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑. 𐑦𐑑'𐑕 𐑢𐑻𐑔 𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑦𐑙. 𐑘𐑧𐑕, 𐑲'𐑥 𐑓 𐑦𐑑;” 𐑯 𐑕𐑴 𐑕𐑱𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑓 𐑞 𐑒𐑢𐑹𐑑𐑼-𐑛𐑧𐑒.

𐑚𐑲 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑞 𐑓𐑱𐑯𐑑 𐑺 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑩 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑰𐑑 𐑒𐑭𐑥; 𐑕𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑹 𐑯𐑴, 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑬 𐑓𐑺𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑐𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑥𐑧𐑤, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑯𐑴 𐑣𐑴𐑐 𐑝 𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑱𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑧𐑐𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑚𐑮𐑰𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑳𐑐 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯. 𐑦𐑖𐑿𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑒𐑨𐑚𐑦𐑯, ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚 𐑯𐑬 𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑴𐑑'𐑕 𐑒𐑮𐑵, 𐑯 𐑐𐑫𐑤𐑛 𐑪𐑓 𐑓 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑼. 𐑛𐑮𐑷𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑒𐑮𐑪𐑕 𐑣𐑻 𐑚𐑬, 𐑣𐑰 𐑐𐑼𐑕𐑰𐑝𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑩𐑒𐑹𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑓𐑨𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑓𐑩𐑤 ·𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑯𐑗 𐑑𐑱𐑕𐑑, 𐑞 𐑳𐑐𐑼 𐑐𐑸𐑑 𐑝 𐑣𐑻 𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑥-𐑐𐑰𐑕 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑒𐑸𐑝𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑤𐑲𐑒𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑩 𐑣𐑿𐑡 𐑛𐑮𐑵𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑑𐑷𐑒, 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑐𐑱𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑯, 𐑯 𐑓 𐑔𐑹𐑯𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑒𐑪𐑐𐑼 𐑕𐑐𐑲𐑒𐑕 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑡𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑦𐑑 𐑣𐑽 𐑯 𐑞𐑺; 𐑞 𐑣𐑴𐑤 𐑑𐑻𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑱𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑕𐑦𐑥𐑧𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑓𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑳𐑤𐑚 𐑝 𐑩 𐑚𐑮𐑲𐑑 𐑮𐑧𐑛 𐑒𐑳𐑤𐑼. 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑻 𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑚𐑹𐑛𐑟, 𐑦𐑯 𐑤𐑸𐑡 𐑜𐑦𐑤𐑑 𐑤𐑧𐑑𐑼𐑟, 𐑣𐑰 𐑮𐑧𐑛 “𐑚𐑬𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑛𐑦 ·𐑮𐑴𐑟,”—𐑮𐑴𐑟-𐑚𐑳𐑑𐑩𐑯, 𐑹 ·𐑮𐑴𐑟-𐑚𐑳𐑛; 𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞 𐑮𐑴𐑥𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑯𐑱𐑥 𐑝 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑨𐑮𐑩𐑥𐑨𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑖𐑦𐑐.

𐑞𐑴 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑞 ·𐑚𐑬𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑐𐑸𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑖𐑩𐑯, 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑞 𐑢𐑻𐑛 𐑮𐑴𐑟, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑳𐑤𐑚𐑩𐑕 𐑓𐑦𐑜𐑼-𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑐𐑫𐑑 𐑑𐑩𐑜𐑧𐑞𐑼, 𐑕𐑩𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑯𐑛 𐑞 𐑣𐑴𐑤 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥.

“𐑩 𐑢𐑫𐑛𐑩𐑯 𐑮𐑴𐑟-𐑚𐑳𐑛, 𐑱?” 𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑴𐑟, “𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑛𐑵 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑢𐑧𐑤; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑣𐑬 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑷𐑤 𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑥𐑧𐑤𐑟!”

𐑯𐑬 𐑦𐑯 𐑹𐑛𐑼 𐑑 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑛𐑦𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑑 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑿𐑯𐑦𐑒𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑐𐑰𐑐𐑩𐑤 𐑪𐑯 𐑛𐑧𐑒, 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑑 𐑐𐑫𐑤 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑞 𐑚𐑬𐑟 𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑼𐑛 𐑕𐑲𐑛, 𐑯 𐑞𐑳𐑕 𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑒𐑤𐑴𐑕 𐑑 𐑞 𐑚𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑱𐑤; 𐑯 𐑕𐑴 𐑑𐑷𐑒 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑦𐑑.

𐑼𐑲𐑝𐑛 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑕𐑐𐑪𐑑, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑴𐑟, 𐑣𐑰 𐑚𐑷𐑤𐑛—“𐑚𐑬𐑑𐑩𐑯-𐑛𐑦-·𐑮𐑴𐑟, 𐑩𐑣𐑶! 𐑸 𐑞𐑺 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑝 𐑿 ·𐑚𐑬𐑑𐑩𐑯-𐑛𐑦-·𐑮𐑴𐑟𐑩𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑒 ·𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑤𐑦𐑖?”

“𐑘𐑧𐑕,” 𐑮𐑰𐑡𐑶𐑯𐑛 𐑩 ·𐑜𐑻𐑯𐑟𐑦-𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑚𐑫𐑤𐑢𐑼𐑒𐑕, 𐑣𐑵 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑛 𐑬𐑑 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑞 𐑗𐑰𐑓-𐑥𐑱𐑑.

“𐑢𐑧𐑤, 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑥𐑲 ·𐑚𐑬𐑑𐑩𐑯-𐑛𐑦-·𐑮𐑴𐑟-𐑚𐑳𐑛, 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑿 𐑕𐑰𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑢𐑲𐑑 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤?”

“𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑤?”

“𐑞 ·𐑢𐑲𐑑 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤—𐑩 ·𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤—·𐑥𐑪𐑚𐑦 ·𐑛𐑦𐑒, 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑘𐑰 𐑕𐑰𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥?

“𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑣𐑻𐑛 𐑝 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩 𐑢𐑱𐑤. 𐑒𐑨𐑖𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑑 ·𐑚𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑖! 𐑢𐑲𐑑 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤—𐑯𐑴.”

“𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑜𐑫𐑛, 𐑞𐑧𐑯; 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑯𐑬, 𐑯 𐑲'𐑤 𐑒𐑷𐑤 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑑.”

𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑮𐑨𐑐𐑦𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑫𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑨𐑒 𐑑𐑩𐑢𐑹𐑛𐑟 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛, 𐑯 𐑕𐑰𐑦𐑙 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑤𐑰𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑞 𐑒𐑢𐑹𐑑𐑼-𐑛𐑧𐑒 𐑮𐑱𐑤 𐑩𐑢𐑱𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑹𐑑, 𐑣𐑰 𐑥𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑑𐑵 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑩 𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑑 𐑯 𐑖𐑬𐑑𐑩𐑛—“𐑯𐑴, ·𐑕𐑻! 𐑯𐑴!” 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑗 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑲𐑼𐑛, 𐑯 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚 𐑮𐑩𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑛 𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑯𐑗𐑥𐑩𐑯.

𐑣𐑰 𐑯𐑬 𐑐𐑼𐑕𐑰𐑝𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑜𐑻𐑯𐑟𐑦-𐑥𐑨𐑯, 𐑣𐑵 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑡𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑜𐑪𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑗𐑱𐑯𐑟, 𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑿𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑒𐑳𐑑𐑦𐑙-𐑕𐑐𐑱𐑛, 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑕𐑤𐑳𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑴𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑕𐑹𐑑 𐑝 𐑚𐑨𐑜.

“𐑢𐑪𐑑'𐑕 𐑞 𐑥𐑨𐑑𐑼 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑘𐑹 𐑯𐑴𐑟, 𐑞𐑺?” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚. “𐑚𐑮𐑴𐑒 𐑦𐑑?”

“𐑲 𐑢𐑦𐑖 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑚𐑮𐑴𐑒𐑩𐑯, 𐑹 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑲 𐑛𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑯𐑴𐑟 𐑨𐑑 𐑷𐑤!” 𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑼𐑛 𐑞 ·𐑜𐑻𐑯𐑟𐑦-𐑥𐑨𐑯, 𐑣𐑵 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑥 𐑑 𐑮𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑖 𐑞 𐑡𐑪𐑚 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑨𐑑 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑥𐑳𐑗. “𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑸 𐑿 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑘𐑹𐑟 𐑓?”

“𐑴, 𐑯𐑳𐑔𐑦𐑙! 𐑦𐑑'𐑕 𐑩 𐑢𐑨𐑒𐑕 𐑯𐑴𐑟; 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑓 𐑑 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑦𐑑 𐑪𐑯. 𐑓𐑲𐑯 𐑛𐑱, 𐑱𐑯𐑑 𐑦𐑑? 𐑺 𐑮𐑭𐑞𐑼 𐑜𐑸𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑦, 𐑲 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑕𐑱; 𐑔𐑮𐑴 𐑳𐑕 𐑩 𐑚𐑳𐑯𐑗 𐑝 𐑐𐑴𐑟𐑦𐑟, 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑘𐑰, ·𐑚𐑬𐑑𐑩𐑯-𐑛𐑦-·𐑮𐑴𐑟?”

“𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑤'𐑟 𐑯𐑱𐑥 𐑛𐑵 𐑿 𐑢𐑪𐑯𐑑 𐑣𐑽?” 𐑮𐑹𐑛 𐑞 ·𐑜𐑻𐑯𐑟𐑦𐑥𐑩𐑯, 𐑓𐑤𐑲𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑩 𐑕𐑳𐑛𐑩𐑯 𐑐𐑭𐑖𐑩𐑯.

“𐑴! 𐑒𐑰𐑐 𐑒𐑵𐑤—𐑒𐑵𐑤? 𐑘𐑧𐑕, 𐑞𐑨𐑑'𐑕 𐑞 𐑢𐑻𐑛! 𐑢𐑲 𐑛𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑿 𐑐𐑨𐑒 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑲𐑕 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑿'𐑼 𐑢𐑻𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑨𐑑 '𐑩𐑥? 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑡𐑴𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑕𐑲𐑛, 𐑞𐑴; 𐑛𐑵 𐑿 𐑯𐑴, ·𐑮𐑴𐑟-𐑚𐑳𐑛, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑑'𐑕 𐑷𐑤 𐑯𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑕 𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑜𐑧𐑑 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑶𐑤 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟? 𐑨𐑟 𐑓 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑛𐑮𐑲𐑛 𐑳𐑐 𐑢𐑳𐑯, 𐑞𐑺, 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑩 𐑜𐑦𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑴𐑤 𐑒𐑸𐑒𐑩𐑕.”

“𐑲 𐑯𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑧𐑤 𐑦𐑯𐑳𐑓; 𐑚𐑳𐑑, 𐑛'𐑘𐑰 𐑕𐑰, 𐑞 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑽 𐑢𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑰𐑝 𐑦𐑑; 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑝𐑶𐑦𐑡; 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩 ·𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑴𐑯 𐑥𐑨𐑯𐑿𐑓𐑨𐑒𐑗𐑼𐑼 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑩𐑚𐑹𐑛, 𐑯 𐑥𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑐 𐑣𐑰'𐑤 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑰𐑝 𐑿, 𐑦𐑓 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑥𐑰; 𐑯 𐑕𐑴 𐑲'𐑤 𐑜𐑧𐑑 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑛𐑻𐑑𐑦 𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑱𐑐.”

“𐑧𐑯𐑦𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑲𐑡 𐑘𐑰, 𐑥𐑲 𐑕𐑢𐑰𐑑 𐑯 𐑐𐑤𐑧𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑓𐑧𐑤𐑴,” 𐑮𐑰𐑡𐑶𐑯𐑛 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚, 𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑵𐑯 𐑥𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑑 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑒. 𐑞𐑺 𐑩 𐑒𐑢𐑽 𐑕𐑰𐑯 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑑𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓. 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑼𐑟, 𐑦𐑯 𐑑𐑨𐑕𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑕 𐑝 𐑮𐑧𐑛 𐑢𐑫𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛, 𐑢𐑻 𐑜𐑧𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑣𐑧𐑝𐑦 𐑑𐑨𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑓 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞𐑱 𐑢𐑻𐑒𐑑 𐑮𐑭𐑞𐑼 𐑕𐑤𐑴 𐑯 𐑑𐑷𐑒𐑑 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑓𐑭𐑕𐑑, 𐑯 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑧𐑯𐑦𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑩 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑣𐑿𐑥𐑼. 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑺 𐑯𐑴𐑟𐑩𐑟 𐑳𐑐𐑢𐑼𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑡𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞𐑺 𐑓𐑱𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑕𐑴 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑡𐑦𐑚-𐑚𐑵𐑥𐑟. 𐑯𐑬 𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑐𐑺𐑟 𐑝 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑛𐑮𐑪𐑐 𐑞𐑺 𐑢𐑻𐑒, 𐑯 𐑮𐑳𐑯 𐑳𐑐 𐑑 𐑞 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑-𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑑 𐑜𐑧𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑖 𐑺. 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑱 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑒𐑨𐑗 𐑞 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑜, 𐑛𐑦𐑐𐑑 𐑴𐑒𐑩𐑥 𐑦𐑯 𐑒𐑴𐑤-𐑑𐑸, 𐑯 𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑛 𐑦𐑑 𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑯𐑪𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑩𐑤𐑟. 𐑳𐑞𐑼𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑮𐑴𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑥𐑟 𐑝 𐑞𐑺 𐑐𐑲𐑐𐑕 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑖𐑹𐑑 𐑪𐑓 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑤, 𐑢𐑻 𐑝𐑦𐑜𐑼𐑩𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑳𐑓𐑦𐑙 𐑑𐑩𐑚𐑨𐑒𐑴-𐑕𐑥𐑴𐑒, 𐑕𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑓𐑦𐑤𐑛 𐑞𐑺 𐑪𐑤𐑓𐑨𐑒𐑑𐑼𐑦𐑟.

𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑒 𐑚𐑲 𐑩 𐑖𐑬𐑼 𐑝 𐑬𐑑𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑟 𐑯 𐑩𐑯𐑨𐑔𐑩𐑥𐑩𐑟 𐑐𐑮𐑴𐑕𐑰𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯'𐑟 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛-𐑣𐑬𐑕 𐑩𐑚𐑭𐑓𐑑; 𐑯 𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑕𐑷 𐑩 𐑓𐑲𐑼𐑦 𐑓𐑱𐑕 𐑔𐑮𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑚𐑦𐑣𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑞 𐑛𐑹, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑛 𐑩𐑡𐑸 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑦𐑯. 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞 𐑑𐑹𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑕𐑻𐑡𐑩𐑯, 𐑣𐑵, 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑦𐑯 𐑝𐑱𐑯 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑴𐑕𐑰𐑛𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑛𐑱, 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯'𐑟 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛-𐑣𐑬𐑕 (𐑒𐑨𐑚𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑛 𐑦𐑑) 𐑑 𐑩𐑝𐑶𐑛 𐑞 𐑐𐑧𐑕𐑑; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤, 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑐 𐑘𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑬𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑰𐑑𐑦𐑟 𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑜𐑯𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑨𐑑 𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟.

𐑥𐑸𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑦𐑕, ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚 𐑸𐑜𐑿𐑛 𐑢𐑧𐑤 𐑓 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑒𐑰𐑥, 𐑯 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑜𐑻𐑯𐑟𐑦-𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑩 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑗𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑛𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑼 𐑥𐑱𐑑 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑛𐑦𐑑𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 𐑨𐑟 𐑩 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑰𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑜𐑯𐑼𐑱𐑥𐑩𐑕, 𐑣𐑵 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑮𐑷𐑑 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑷𐑤 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑕𐑴 𐑳𐑯𐑕𐑱𐑝𐑼𐑦 𐑯 𐑳𐑯𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑓𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑩 𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤. 𐑕𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑒𐑺𐑓𐑩𐑤𐑦, ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚 𐑓𐑻𐑞𐑼 𐑐𐑼𐑕𐑰𐑝𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑜𐑻𐑯𐑟𐑦-𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑤𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑩𐑕𐑐𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑨𐑥𐑚𐑼𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑕. 𐑣𐑰 𐑞𐑺𐑓𐑹 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑰𐑕 𐑪𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑧𐑛, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑳𐑞𐑼𐑢𐑲𐑟 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑒𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑨𐑙𐑒 𐑯 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑓𐑦𐑛𐑧𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑕𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑑𐑵 𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑒𐑪𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑩 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑐𐑤𐑨𐑯 𐑓 𐑚𐑴𐑔 𐑕𐑻𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑝𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑯 𐑕𐑨𐑑𐑼𐑲𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑞 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯, 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑨𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑛𐑮𐑰𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑺 𐑕𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑦. 𐑩𐑒𐑹𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑐𐑤𐑨𐑯 𐑝 𐑞𐑺𐑟, 𐑞 ·𐑜𐑻𐑯𐑟𐑦-𐑥𐑨𐑯, 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑒𐑳𐑝𐑼 𐑝 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑻𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑑𐑼'𐑟 𐑪𐑓𐑦𐑕, 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑑 𐑑𐑧𐑤 𐑞 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑐𐑤𐑰𐑟𐑛, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚; 𐑯 𐑨𐑟 𐑓 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚, 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑑 𐑳𐑑𐑼 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑯𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑕 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑳𐑐𐑼𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑛𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑝𐑿.

𐑚𐑲 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑞𐑺 𐑛𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑛 𐑝𐑦𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑥 𐑩𐑐𐑽𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑨𐑚𐑦𐑯. 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩 𐑕𐑥𐑷𐑤 𐑯 𐑛𐑸𐑒, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑮𐑭𐑞𐑼 𐑛𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑑 𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑓 𐑩 𐑕𐑰-𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑤𐑸𐑡 𐑢𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑼𐑟 𐑯 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑𐑭𐑖, 𐑣𐑬𐑧𐑝𐑼; 𐑯 𐑢𐑹 𐑩 𐑮𐑧𐑛 𐑒𐑪𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑝𐑧𐑤𐑝𐑩𐑑 𐑝𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑢𐑪𐑗-𐑕𐑰𐑤𐑟 𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑲𐑛. 𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑥𐑩𐑯, ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑬 𐑐𐑩𐑤𐑲𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑩𐑛𐑿𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 ·𐑜𐑻𐑯𐑟𐑦-𐑥𐑨𐑯, 𐑣𐑵 𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑕 𐑪𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑫𐑑 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑨𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑 𐑝 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑻𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑢𐑰𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑥.

“𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑖𐑨𐑤 𐑲 𐑕𐑱 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑?” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑣𐑰.

“𐑢𐑲,” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚, 𐑲𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑝𐑧𐑤𐑝𐑩𐑑 𐑝𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑪𐑗 𐑯 𐑕𐑰𐑤𐑟, “𐑿 𐑥𐑱 𐑨𐑟 𐑢𐑧𐑤 𐑚𐑦𐑜𐑦𐑯 𐑚𐑲 𐑑𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑕 𐑩 𐑕𐑹𐑑 𐑝 𐑚𐑱𐑚𐑦𐑦𐑖 𐑑 𐑥𐑰, 𐑞𐑴 𐑲 𐑛𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑩 𐑡𐑳𐑡.”

“𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑧𐑟, ·𐑥𐑩𐑕𐑘𐑻,” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑞 ·𐑜𐑻𐑯𐑟𐑦-𐑥𐑨𐑯, 𐑦𐑯 ·𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑯𐑗, 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯, “𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑘𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑛𐑱 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑕𐑐𐑴𐑒 𐑩 𐑝𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑤, 𐑣𐑵𐑟 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 𐑯 𐑗𐑰𐑓-𐑥𐑱𐑑, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑕 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑼𐑟, 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑷𐑤 𐑛𐑲𐑛 𐑝 𐑩 𐑓𐑰𐑝𐑼 𐑒𐑷𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑩 𐑚𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑞𐑱 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑮𐑷𐑑 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑙𐑕𐑲𐑛.”

𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑞 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑑𐑩𐑛, 𐑯 𐑰𐑜𐑼𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑦𐑟𐑲𐑼𐑛 𐑑 𐑯𐑴 𐑥𐑹.

“𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑯𐑬?” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑞 ·𐑜𐑻𐑯𐑟𐑦-𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑑 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚.

“𐑢𐑲, 𐑕𐑦𐑯𐑕 𐑣𐑰 𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑕 𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑴 𐑰𐑟𐑦, 𐑑𐑧𐑤 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑯𐑬 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑲𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑒𐑺𐑓𐑩𐑤𐑦, 𐑲'𐑥 𐑒𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑰'𐑟 𐑯𐑴 𐑥𐑹 𐑓𐑦𐑑 𐑑 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑭𐑯𐑛 𐑩 𐑢𐑱𐑤-𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑩 ·𐑕𐑑 ·𐑡𐑨𐑜𐑴 𐑥𐑳𐑙𐑒𐑦. 𐑦𐑯 𐑓𐑨𐑒𐑑, 𐑑𐑧𐑤 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑥𐑰 𐑣𐑰'𐑟 𐑩 𐑚𐑩𐑚𐑵𐑯.”

“𐑣𐑰 𐑝𐑬𐑟 𐑯 𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑺𐑟, ·𐑥𐑩𐑕𐑘𐑻, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑞 𐑛𐑮𐑲𐑛 𐑢𐑳𐑯, 𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑸 𐑥𐑹 𐑛𐑧𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑳𐑯; 𐑦𐑯 𐑓𐑲𐑯, ·𐑥𐑩𐑕𐑘𐑻, 𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑳𐑯𐑡𐑼𐑟 𐑳𐑕, 𐑨𐑟 𐑢𐑰 𐑝𐑨𐑤𐑿 𐑬𐑼 𐑤𐑲𐑝𐑟, 𐑑 𐑒𐑳𐑑 𐑤𐑵𐑕 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑓𐑦𐑖.”

𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑞 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 𐑮𐑨𐑯 𐑓𐑹𐑢𐑼𐑛, 𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑤𐑬𐑛 𐑝𐑶𐑕 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑭𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑮𐑵 𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑟𐑦𐑕𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑣𐑶𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑒𐑳𐑑𐑦𐑙-𐑑𐑨𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑟, 𐑯 𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑕 𐑒𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑤𐑵𐑕 𐑞 𐑒𐑱𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑯 𐑗𐑱𐑯𐑟 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑓𐑲𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑑 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐.

“𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑯𐑬?” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑞 ·𐑜𐑻𐑯𐑟𐑦-𐑥𐑨𐑯, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑮𐑩𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑛 𐑑 𐑞𐑧𐑥.

“𐑢𐑲, 𐑤𐑧𐑑 𐑥𐑰 𐑕𐑰; 𐑘𐑧𐑕, 𐑿 𐑥𐑱 𐑨𐑟 𐑢𐑧𐑤 𐑑𐑧𐑤 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑯𐑬 𐑞𐑨𐑑—𐑞𐑨𐑑—𐑦𐑯 𐑓𐑨𐑒𐑑, 𐑑𐑧𐑤 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑲'𐑝 𐑛𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑯 (𐑩𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓) 𐑐𐑼𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑕 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦 𐑧𐑤𐑕.”

“𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑧𐑟, ·𐑥𐑩𐑕𐑘𐑻, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑰'𐑟 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑦 𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑝 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑕𐑻𐑝𐑦𐑕 𐑑 𐑳𐑕.”

𐑣𐑽𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑦𐑕, 𐑞 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 𐑝𐑬𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑱 𐑢𐑻 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑐𐑸𐑑𐑦𐑟 (𐑥𐑰𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑯 𐑥𐑱𐑑) 𐑯 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑒𐑤𐑵𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑲𐑑𐑦𐑙 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑨𐑚𐑦𐑯 𐑑 𐑛𐑮𐑦𐑙𐑒 𐑩 𐑚𐑪𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑝 ·𐑚𐑹𐑛𐑴.

“𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑿 𐑑 𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑩 𐑜𐑤𐑭𐑕 𐑝 𐑢𐑲𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑥,” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑻𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑑𐑼.

“𐑔𐑨𐑙𐑒 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑣𐑸𐑑𐑦𐑤𐑦; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑑𐑧𐑤 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑦𐑑'𐑕 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑥𐑲 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑐𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑑 𐑛𐑮𐑦𐑙𐑒 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑲'𐑝 𐑛𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑤𐑛. 𐑦𐑯 𐑓𐑨𐑒𐑑, 𐑑𐑧𐑤 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑲 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑜𐑴.”

“𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑧𐑟, ·𐑥𐑩𐑕𐑘𐑻, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑐𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑢𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑩𐑛𐑥𐑦𐑑 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑛𐑮𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑦𐑙; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑓 ·𐑥𐑩𐑕𐑘𐑻 𐑢𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑑 𐑤𐑦𐑝 𐑩𐑯𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑛𐑱 𐑑 𐑛𐑮𐑦𐑙𐑒, 𐑞𐑧𐑯 ·𐑥𐑩𐑕𐑘𐑻 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑛𐑮𐑪𐑐 𐑷𐑤 𐑓𐑹 𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕, 𐑯 𐑐𐑫𐑤 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑩𐑢𐑱 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟, 𐑓 𐑦𐑑'𐑕 𐑕𐑴 𐑒𐑭𐑥 𐑞𐑱 𐑢𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑛𐑮𐑦𐑓𐑑.”

𐑚𐑲 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑑𐑲𐑥 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑞 𐑕𐑲𐑛, 𐑯 𐑜𐑧𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑴𐑑, 𐑣𐑱𐑤𐑛 𐑞 ·𐑜𐑻𐑯𐑟𐑦-𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑦𐑓𐑧𐑒𐑑,—𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑑𐑴-𐑤𐑲𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑴𐑑, 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑛𐑵 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑑 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑐 𐑞𐑧𐑥, 𐑚𐑲 𐑐𐑫𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑬𐑑 𐑞 𐑤𐑲𐑑𐑼 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑝 𐑞 𐑑𐑵 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐'𐑕 𐑕𐑲𐑛. 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑞 ·𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑯𐑗𐑥𐑩𐑯'𐑟 𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕, 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑢𐑻 𐑦𐑯𐑜𐑱𐑡𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑑𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑢𐑱, ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚 𐑚𐑦𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑑𐑴𐑛 𐑩𐑢𐑱 𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑞 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑢𐑱, 𐑪𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑤𐑨𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑬𐑑 𐑩 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑳𐑯𐑿𐑠𐑵𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑑𐑴-𐑤𐑲𐑯.

𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑩 𐑚𐑮𐑰𐑟 𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑨𐑙 𐑳𐑐; ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚 𐑓𐑱𐑯𐑛 𐑑 𐑒𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑪𐑓 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤; 𐑣𐑶𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕, 𐑞 ·𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑯𐑗𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑕𐑵𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑮𐑰𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕, 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛 𐑕𐑤𐑦𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑢𐑰𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑯 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚'𐑟 𐑢𐑱𐑤. 𐑢𐑺𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚 𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑫𐑤𐑛 𐑑 𐑞 𐑓𐑤𐑴𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦, 𐑯 𐑣𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛 𐑑 𐑜𐑦𐑝 𐑯𐑴𐑑𐑦𐑕 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟, 𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑕 𐑐𐑮𐑴𐑕𐑰𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑑 𐑮𐑰𐑐 𐑞 𐑓𐑮𐑵𐑑 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑳𐑯𐑮𐑲𐑗𐑩𐑕 𐑒𐑳𐑯𐑦𐑙. 𐑕𐑰𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑖𐑸𐑐 𐑚𐑴𐑑-𐑕𐑐𐑱𐑛, 𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑩𐑯 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑒𐑩𐑝𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦, 𐑩 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑚𐑦𐑣𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑞 𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑓𐑦𐑯. 𐑿 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑔𐑷𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑛𐑦𐑜𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑼 𐑞𐑺 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑰; 𐑯 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑧𐑙𐑔 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑐𐑱𐑛 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑒 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑞 𐑜𐑷𐑯𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑚𐑟, 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑳𐑐 𐑴𐑤𐑛 ·𐑮𐑴𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑑𐑲𐑤𐑟 𐑯 𐑐𐑪𐑑𐑼𐑦 𐑚𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑓𐑨𐑑 ·𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑤𐑦𐑖 𐑤𐑴𐑥. 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑴𐑑'𐑕 𐑒𐑮𐑵 𐑢𐑻 𐑷𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑲 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑲𐑑𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑, 𐑰𐑜𐑼𐑤𐑦 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑺 𐑗𐑰𐑓, 𐑯 𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑨𐑟 𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑕 𐑨𐑟 𐑜𐑴𐑤𐑛-𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑟.

𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑯𐑳𐑥𐑚𐑼𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑓𐑬𐑤𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑛𐑲𐑝𐑦𐑙, 𐑯 𐑛𐑳𐑒𐑦𐑙, 𐑯 𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑰𐑥𐑦𐑙, 𐑯 𐑘𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑙, 𐑯 𐑓𐑲𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑼𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑞𐑧𐑥. 𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑚𐑦𐑜𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑤𐑫𐑒 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑩𐑐𐑶𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛, 𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑣𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑯𐑴𐑟𐑜𐑱 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑮𐑰𐑕𐑑, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑬𐑑 𐑞 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑣𐑸𐑑 𐑝 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑜, 𐑞𐑺 𐑕𐑑𐑴𐑤 𐑩 𐑓𐑱𐑯𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑰𐑥 𐑝 𐑐𐑻𐑓𐑿𐑥, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑓𐑤𐑴𐑛 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑞 𐑑𐑲𐑛 𐑝 𐑚𐑨𐑛 𐑕𐑥𐑧𐑤𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑚𐑕𐑹𐑚𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑦𐑑, 𐑨𐑟 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑮𐑦𐑝𐑼 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑓𐑤𐑴 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩𐑯𐑳𐑞𐑼, 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑚𐑤𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑦𐑑 𐑓 𐑩 𐑑𐑲𐑥.

“𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑦𐑑, 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑦𐑑,” 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑲𐑑, 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑚𐑑𐑼𐑱𐑯𐑾𐑯 𐑮𐑰𐑡𐑩𐑯𐑟, “𐑩 𐑐𐑻𐑕! 𐑩 𐑐𐑻𐑕!”

𐑛𐑮𐑪𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑐𐑱𐑛, 𐑣𐑰 𐑔𐑮𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑴𐑔 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑦𐑯, 𐑯 𐑛𐑮𐑵 𐑬𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑓𐑫𐑤𐑟 𐑝 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑑 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑮𐑲𐑐 ·𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑟𐑼 𐑕𐑴𐑐, 𐑹 𐑮𐑦𐑗 𐑥𐑪𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑗𐑰𐑟; 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑳𐑙𐑒𐑗𐑵𐑩𐑕 𐑯 𐑕𐑱𐑝𐑼𐑦 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑷𐑤. 𐑿 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑰𐑟𐑦𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑘𐑹 𐑔𐑳𐑥; 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑝 𐑩 𐑣𐑿 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑢𐑰𐑯 𐑘𐑧𐑤𐑴 𐑯 𐑨𐑖 𐑒𐑳𐑤𐑼. 𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕, 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑟, 𐑦𐑟 𐑨𐑥𐑚𐑼𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑕, 𐑢𐑻𐑔 𐑩 𐑜𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑜𐑦𐑯𐑦 𐑩𐑯 𐑬𐑯𐑕 𐑑 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑛𐑮𐑳𐑜𐑦𐑕𐑑. 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑕 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑓𐑫𐑤𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑩𐑚𐑑𐑱𐑯𐑛; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑥𐑹 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑳𐑯𐑩𐑝𐑶𐑛𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑤𐑪𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑰, 𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑥𐑹, 𐑐𐑼𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑕, 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑛 𐑢𐑻 𐑦𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑓 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑑 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚'𐑟 𐑤𐑬𐑛 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑭𐑯𐑛 𐑑 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚 𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑟𐑦𐑕𐑑, 𐑯 𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑪𐑯 𐑚𐑹𐑛, 𐑧𐑤𐑕 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑚𐑦𐑛 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑚𐑲.

·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 92. 𐑨𐑥𐑚𐑼𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑕.

𐑯𐑬 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑨𐑥𐑚𐑼𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑕 𐑦𐑟 𐑩 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑒𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑾𐑕 𐑕𐑳𐑚𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕, 𐑯 𐑕𐑴 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑹𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑩𐑯 𐑸𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑻𐑕, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑯 1791 𐑩 𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑯 ·𐑯𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑑-𐑚𐑹𐑯 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 ·𐑒𐑪𐑓𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑦𐑜𐑟𐑨𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑛 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑚𐑸 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑤𐑦𐑖 ·𐑣𐑬𐑕 𐑝 ·𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑪𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑚𐑡𐑧𐑒𐑑. 𐑓 𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑑𐑲𐑥, 𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑰𐑛 𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑩 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑨𐑮𐑩𐑑𐑦𐑝𐑤𐑦 𐑤𐑱𐑑 𐑛𐑱, 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑲𐑕 𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑡𐑦𐑯 𐑝 𐑨𐑥𐑚𐑼𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑕 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑱𐑯𐑛, 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑨𐑥𐑚𐑼 𐑦𐑑𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓, 𐑩 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑚𐑤𐑩𐑥 𐑑 𐑞 𐑤𐑻𐑯𐑛. 𐑞𐑴 𐑞 𐑢𐑻𐑛 𐑨𐑥𐑚𐑼𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑕 𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑯𐑗 𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑐𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑓 𐑜𐑮𐑱 𐑨𐑥𐑚𐑼, 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑞 𐑑𐑵 𐑕𐑳𐑚𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑸 𐑒𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑑. 𐑓 𐑨𐑥𐑚𐑼, 𐑞𐑴 𐑨𐑑 𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑰-𐑒𐑴𐑕𐑑, 𐑦𐑟 𐑷𐑤𐑕𐑴 𐑛𐑳𐑜 𐑳𐑐 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑓𐑸 𐑦𐑯𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑕𐑶𐑤𐑟, 𐑢𐑺𐑨𐑟 𐑨𐑥𐑚𐑼𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑕 𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑧𐑐𐑑 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑰. 𐑚𐑦𐑕𐑲𐑛𐑟, 𐑨𐑥𐑚𐑼 𐑦𐑟 𐑩 𐑣𐑸𐑛, 𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑕𐑐𐑨𐑮𐑩𐑯𐑑, 𐑚𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤, 𐑴𐑛𐑼𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑕𐑳𐑚𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕, 𐑿𐑟𐑛 𐑓 𐑥𐑬𐑔-𐑐𐑰𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑑 𐑐𐑲𐑐𐑕, 𐑓 𐑚𐑰𐑛𐑟 𐑯 𐑹𐑯𐑩𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑨𐑥𐑚𐑼𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑕 𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑪𐑓𐑑, 𐑢𐑨𐑒𐑕𐑦, 𐑯 𐑕𐑴 𐑣𐑲𐑤𐑦 𐑓𐑮𐑱𐑜𐑮𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑯 𐑕𐑐𐑲𐑕𐑦, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑤𐑸𐑡𐑤𐑦 𐑿𐑟𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑐𐑻𐑓𐑿𐑥𐑼𐑦, 𐑦𐑯 𐑐𐑱𐑕𐑑𐑲𐑤𐑟, 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑕 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑤𐑟, 𐑣𐑺-𐑐𐑬𐑛𐑼𐑟, 𐑯 𐑐𐑪𐑥𐑭𐑑𐑩𐑥. 𐑞 ·𐑑𐑻𐑒𐑕 𐑿𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑒𐑫𐑒𐑦𐑙, 𐑯 𐑷𐑤𐑕𐑴 𐑒𐑨𐑮𐑦 𐑦𐑑 𐑑 ·𐑥𐑧𐑒𐑩, 𐑓 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑐𐑻𐑐𐑩𐑕 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑕 𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑛 𐑑 ·𐑕𐑑 ·𐑐𐑰𐑑𐑼'𐑟 𐑦𐑯 ·𐑮𐑴𐑥. 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑢𐑲𐑯 𐑥𐑻𐑗𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑛𐑮𐑪𐑐 𐑩 𐑓𐑿 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑒𐑤𐑨𐑮𐑩𐑑, 𐑑 𐑓𐑤𐑱𐑝𐑼 𐑦𐑑.

𐑣𐑵 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒, 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑓𐑲𐑯 𐑤𐑱𐑛𐑦𐑟 𐑯 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑮𐑦𐑜𐑱𐑤 𐑞𐑧𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑝𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩𐑯 𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑜𐑤𐑹𐑾𐑕 𐑚𐑬𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑝 𐑩 𐑕𐑦𐑒 𐑢𐑱𐑤! 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑕𐑴 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟. 𐑚𐑲 𐑕𐑳𐑥, 𐑨𐑥𐑚𐑼𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑕 𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑩𐑐𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑞 𐑒𐑷𐑟, 𐑯 𐑚𐑲 𐑳𐑞𐑼𐑟 𐑞 𐑦𐑓𐑧𐑒𐑑, 𐑝 𐑞 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑐𐑕𐑾 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤. 𐑣𐑬 𐑑 𐑒𐑘𐑫𐑼 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑐𐑕𐑾 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑻 𐑣𐑸𐑛 𐑑 𐑕𐑱, 𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑧𐑕 𐑚𐑲 𐑩𐑛𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑹 𐑓𐑹 𐑚𐑴𐑑 𐑤𐑴𐑛𐑟 𐑝 ·𐑚𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑔'𐑕 𐑐𐑦𐑤𐑟, 𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑮𐑳𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑣𐑸𐑥'𐑟 𐑢𐑱, 𐑨𐑟 𐑤𐑱𐑚𐑼𐑼𐑟 𐑛𐑵 𐑦𐑯 𐑚𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑮𐑪𐑒𐑕.

𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑓𐑼𐑜𐑪𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑑 𐑕𐑱 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑢𐑻 𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑨𐑥𐑚𐑼𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑕, 𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑣𐑸𐑛, 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛, 𐑚𐑴𐑯𐑦 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑑𐑕, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑨𐑑 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚 𐑔𐑷𐑑 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑼𐑟' 𐑑𐑮𐑴𐑟𐑼𐑟 𐑚𐑳𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑟; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼𐑢𐑼𐑛𐑟 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑛 𐑬𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑱 𐑢𐑻 𐑯𐑳𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑹 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑐𐑰𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑝 𐑕𐑥𐑷𐑤 𐑕𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑛 𐑚𐑴𐑯𐑟 𐑦𐑥𐑚𐑭𐑥𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑨𐑯𐑼.

𐑯𐑬 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑼𐑳𐑐𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑱𐑜𐑮𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑨𐑥𐑚𐑼𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑕 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑚𐑰 𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑣𐑸𐑑 𐑝 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑱; 𐑦𐑟 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑯𐑳𐑔𐑦𐑙? 𐑚𐑦𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒 𐑞𐑰 𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑱𐑦𐑙 𐑝 ·𐑕𐑑 ·𐑐𐑷𐑤 𐑦𐑯 ·𐑒𐑼𐑦𐑯𐑔𐑾𐑯𐑟, 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑒𐑼𐑳𐑐𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑼𐑳𐑐𐑖𐑩𐑯; 𐑣𐑬 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑰 𐑸 𐑕𐑴𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑪𐑯𐑼, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑮𐑱𐑟𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑜𐑤𐑹𐑦. 𐑯 𐑤𐑲𐑒𐑢𐑲𐑟 𐑒𐑷𐑤 𐑑 𐑥𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑱𐑦𐑙 𐑝 ·𐑐𐑨𐑮𐑩𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑕𐑩𐑕 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑱𐑒𐑩𐑔 𐑞 𐑚𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑒. 𐑷𐑤𐑕𐑴 𐑓𐑼𐑜𐑧𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡 𐑓𐑨𐑒𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑝 𐑷𐑤 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑝 𐑦𐑤-𐑕𐑱𐑝𐑼, ·𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑴𐑯-𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼, 𐑦𐑯 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑮𐑵𐑛𐑦𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑥𐑨𐑯𐑿𐑓𐑨𐑒𐑗𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑡𐑩𐑟, 𐑦𐑟 𐑞 𐑢𐑻𐑕𐑑.

𐑲 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑑 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑒𐑤𐑵𐑛 𐑞 𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑩𐑚𐑳𐑝 𐑩𐑐𐑰𐑤, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑪𐑑, 𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑥𐑲 𐑨𐑙𐑟𐑲𐑩𐑑𐑦 𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑧𐑤 𐑩 𐑗𐑸𐑡 𐑪𐑓𐑩𐑯 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑥𐑧𐑯, 𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑗, 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑥𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑷𐑤𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑦 𐑚𐑲𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑥𐑲𐑯𐑛𐑟, 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑼𐑛 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑖𐑦𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑯𐑗𐑥𐑩𐑯'𐑟 𐑑𐑵 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟. 𐑧𐑤𐑕𐑢𐑺 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑝𐑪𐑤𐑿𐑥 𐑞 𐑕𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑩𐑕 𐑩𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑵𐑝𐑛, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑝𐑴𐑒𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑟 𐑔𐑮𐑵𐑬𐑑 𐑩 𐑕𐑤𐑨𐑑𐑼𐑯𐑤𐑦, 𐑳𐑯𐑑𐑲𐑛𐑦 𐑚𐑦𐑟𐑯𐑩𐑕. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑦𐑟 𐑩𐑯𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑚𐑳𐑑. 𐑞𐑱 𐑣𐑦𐑯𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑷𐑤𐑢𐑱𐑟 𐑕𐑥𐑧𐑤 𐑚𐑨𐑛. 𐑯𐑬 𐑣𐑬 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑴𐑛𐑾𐑕 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑜𐑥𐑩 𐑼𐑦𐑡𐑦𐑯𐑱𐑑?

𐑲 𐑩𐑐𐑲𐑯, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑑 𐑞 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑼𐑲𐑝𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑯𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑕 𐑦𐑯 ·𐑤𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑯, 𐑥𐑹 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑑𐑵 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑗𐑼𐑦𐑟 𐑩𐑜𐑴. 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑪𐑟 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑯 𐑛𐑵 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑯𐑬, 𐑑𐑮𐑲 𐑬𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑶𐑤 𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑰 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑳𐑞𐑼𐑯 𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑕 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑷𐑤𐑢𐑱𐑟 𐑛𐑳𐑯; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑒𐑳𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑳𐑐 𐑞 𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑖 𐑚𐑤𐑳𐑚𐑼 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑥𐑷𐑤 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑕, 𐑔𐑮𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑞 𐑚𐑳𐑙 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑟 𐑝 𐑤𐑸𐑡 𐑒𐑭𐑕𐑒𐑕, 𐑯 𐑒𐑨𐑮𐑦 𐑦𐑑 𐑣𐑴𐑥 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑨𐑯𐑼; 𐑞 𐑖𐑹𐑑𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑰𐑟𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑴𐑟 ·𐑲𐑕𐑦 ·𐑕𐑰𐑟, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑛𐑩𐑯 𐑯 𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑹𐑥𐑟 𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑞𐑱 𐑸 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑴𐑟𐑛, 𐑓𐑼𐑚𐑦𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑒𐑹𐑕. 𐑞 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑢𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑦𐑟, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛, 𐑯 𐑳𐑯𐑤𐑴𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑕𐑧𐑥𐑩𐑑𐑼𐑦𐑟, 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑯𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑛𐑪𐑒, 𐑩 𐑕𐑱𐑝𐑼 𐑦𐑟 𐑜𐑦𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑓𐑹𐑔 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑤𐑼 𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑼𐑲𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑒𐑩𐑝𐑱𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑯 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑕𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑝-𐑘𐑸𐑛, 𐑓 𐑞 𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑩 ·𐑤𐑲𐑦𐑙-𐑦𐑯 ·𐑣𐑪𐑕𐑐𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤.

𐑲 𐑐𐑸𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑼𐑥𐑲𐑟 𐑷𐑤𐑕𐑴, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑛 𐑗𐑸𐑡 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑼𐑟 𐑥𐑱 𐑚𐑰 𐑤𐑲𐑒𐑢𐑲𐑟 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑿𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑑 𐑞 𐑦𐑜𐑟𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑒𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑝 ·𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑯𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛, 𐑦𐑯 𐑓𐑹𐑥𐑼 𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟, 𐑝 𐑩 ·𐑛𐑳𐑗 𐑝𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑡 𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑛 ·𐑖𐑥𐑺𐑩𐑯𐑚𐑻𐑜 𐑹 ·𐑕𐑥𐑽𐑩𐑯𐑚𐑼𐑜, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑤𐑨𐑑𐑼 𐑯𐑱𐑥 𐑦𐑟 𐑞 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑿𐑟𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑤𐑻𐑯𐑛 ·𐑓𐑪𐑜𐑴 ·𐑝𐑪𐑯 ·𐑕𐑤𐑨𐑒, 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑢𐑻𐑒 𐑪𐑯 ·𐑕𐑥𐑧𐑤𐑟, 𐑩 𐑑𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑-𐑚𐑫𐑒 𐑪𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑚𐑡𐑧𐑒𐑑. 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑯𐑱𐑥 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑹𐑑𐑕 (𐑕𐑥𐑽, 𐑓𐑨𐑑; 𐑚𐑻𐑜, 𐑑 𐑐𐑫𐑑 𐑳𐑐), 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑝𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑡 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑹𐑛𐑼 𐑑 𐑩𐑓𐑹𐑛 𐑩 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕 𐑓 𐑞 𐑚𐑤𐑳𐑚𐑼 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑛𐑳𐑗 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑓𐑤𐑰𐑑 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑛 𐑬𐑑, 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑣𐑴𐑥 𐑑 ·𐑣𐑪𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑓 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑐𐑻𐑐𐑩𐑕. 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩 𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑧𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑓𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑕𐑩𐑟, 𐑓𐑨𐑑-𐑒𐑧𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑟, 𐑯 𐑶𐑤 𐑖𐑧𐑛𐑟; 𐑯 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑻𐑒𐑕 𐑢𐑻 𐑦𐑯 𐑓𐑫𐑤 𐑪𐑐𐑼𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑜𐑱𐑝 𐑓𐑹𐑔 𐑯𐑴 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑐𐑤𐑧𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑕𐑱𐑝𐑼. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑓𐑼𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 ·𐑕𐑬𐑔 ·𐑕𐑰 ·𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑼; 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑝𐑶𐑦𐑡 𐑝 𐑓𐑹 𐑘𐑽𐑟 𐑐𐑼𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑕, 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑰𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑓𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑻 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑶𐑤, 𐑛𐑳𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑, 𐑐𐑼𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑕, 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑿𐑥 𐑓𐑦𐑓𐑑𐑦 𐑛𐑱𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑦𐑟𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑚𐑶𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑬𐑑; 𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑭𐑕𐑒𐑑, 𐑞 𐑶𐑤 𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑽𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑩𐑕. 𐑞 𐑑𐑮𐑵𐑔 𐑦𐑟, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑹 𐑛𐑧𐑛, 𐑦𐑓 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑛𐑰𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑑𐑮𐑰𐑑𐑩𐑛, 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑨𐑟 𐑩 𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑖𐑰𐑟 𐑸 𐑚𐑲 𐑯𐑴 𐑥𐑰𐑯𐑟 𐑒𐑮𐑰𐑗𐑼𐑟 𐑝 𐑦𐑤 𐑴𐑛𐑼; 𐑯𐑹 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑚𐑰 𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑩𐑜𐑯𐑲𐑟𐑛, 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑐𐑰𐑐𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑞 𐑥𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑤 𐑱𐑡𐑩𐑟 𐑩𐑓𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑑𐑧𐑒𐑑 𐑩 ·𐑡𐑵 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑦, 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑯𐑴𐑟. 𐑯𐑹 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑰𐑛 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑐𐑪𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑰 𐑳𐑞𐑼𐑢𐑲𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑱𐑜𐑮𐑩𐑯𐑑, 𐑢𐑧𐑯, 𐑨𐑟 𐑩 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑔𐑦𐑙, 𐑣𐑰 𐑦𐑯𐑡𐑶𐑟 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑣𐑲 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑔; 𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑚𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑝 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑼𐑕𐑲𐑟; 𐑷𐑤𐑢𐑱𐑟 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑛𐑹𐑟; 𐑞𐑴, 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑑𐑮𐑵, 𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑛𐑩𐑥 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑴𐑐𐑩𐑯 𐑺. 𐑲 𐑕𐑱, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑥𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑩 ·𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤'𐑟 𐑓𐑤𐑵𐑒𐑕 𐑩𐑚𐑳𐑝 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑩 𐑐𐑻𐑓𐑿𐑥, 𐑨𐑟 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑩 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑒-𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑤𐑱𐑛𐑦 𐑮𐑳𐑕𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑣𐑻 𐑛𐑮𐑧𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑢𐑹𐑥 𐑐𐑸𐑤𐑼. 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑖𐑨𐑤 𐑲 𐑤𐑲𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑑 𐑓 𐑓𐑮𐑱𐑜𐑮𐑩𐑯𐑕, 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑨𐑜𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑿𐑛? 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑓𐑱𐑥𐑩𐑕 𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑓𐑩𐑯𐑑, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑡𐑵𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑑𐑳𐑕𐑒𐑕, 𐑯 𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑩𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑥𐑻, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑤𐑧𐑛 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑩𐑯 ·𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑾𐑯 𐑑𐑬𐑯 𐑑 𐑛𐑵 𐑪𐑯𐑼 𐑑 ·𐑨𐑤𐑦𐑜𐑟𐑭𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑞 ·𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑?

·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 93. 𐑞 ·𐑒𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑢𐑱.

𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑓𐑿 𐑛𐑱𐑟 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑞 ·𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑯𐑗𐑥𐑩𐑯, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑩 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑦𐑜𐑯𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑦𐑝𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑧𐑤 𐑞 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑜𐑯𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛'𐑟 𐑒𐑮𐑵; 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑝𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑤𐑨𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤; 𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑝𐑲𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑥𐑨𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑥𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑯 𐑐𐑮𐑰𐑛𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑒𐑮𐑭𐑓𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑤𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑯 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑩𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑦𐑙 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑓𐑩𐑕𐑦 𐑝 𐑢𐑪𐑑𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑖𐑨𐑑𐑼𐑛 𐑕𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑩𐑤 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑵𐑝 𐑣𐑻 𐑴𐑯.

𐑯𐑬, 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑖𐑦𐑐, 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑜𐑴𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕. 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑓𐑿 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑸 𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑻𐑝𐑛 𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑛 𐑖𐑦𐑐-𐑒𐑰𐑐𐑼𐑟, 𐑣𐑵𐑟 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑝𐑦𐑯𐑕 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑑 𐑢𐑻𐑒 𐑞 𐑝𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕 𐑸 𐑐𐑼𐑕𐑿𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤. 𐑨𐑟 𐑩 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑔𐑦𐑙, 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑖𐑦𐑐-𐑒𐑰𐑐𐑼𐑟 𐑸 𐑨𐑟 𐑣𐑸𐑛𐑦 𐑓𐑧𐑤𐑴𐑟 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑮𐑲𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕' 𐑒𐑮𐑵𐑟. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑓 𐑞𐑺 𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑩𐑯 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑩𐑯 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑿𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑤𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑼, 𐑒𐑤𐑳𐑥𐑟𐑦, 𐑹 𐑑𐑦𐑥𐑼𐑩𐑕 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑩 𐑖𐑦𐑐-𐑒𐑰𐑐𐑼. 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑴 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑯𐑰𐑜𐑮𐑴 ·𐑐𐑦𐑐𐑦𐑯 𐑚𐑲 𐑯𐑦𐑒-𐑯𐑱𐑥, ·𐑐𐑦𐑐 𐑚𐑲 𐑩𐑚𐑮𐑰𐑝𐑦𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯. 𐑐𐑫𐑼 ·𐑐𐑦𐑐! 𐑘𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑣𐑻𐑛 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹; 𐑘𐑰 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑧𐑥𐑚𐑼 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑑𐑨𐑥𐑚𐑼𐑰𐑯 𐑪𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑥𐑨𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑥𐑦𐑛𐑯𐑲𐑑, 𐑕𐑴 𐑜𐑤𐑵𐑥𐑦-𐑡𐑪𐑤𐑦.

𐑦𐑯 𐑬𐑑𐑼 𐑨𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑, ·𐑐𐑦𐑐 𐑯 ·𐑛𐑴-·𐑚𐑶 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑩 𐑥𐑨𐑗, 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑒 𐑐𐑴𐑯𐑦 𐑯 𐑩 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯, 𐑝 𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑩𐑤 𐑛𐑦𐑝𐑧𐑤𐑩𐑐𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕, 𐑞𐑴 𐑝 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑤𐑼 𐑒𐑳𐑤𐑼, 𐑛𐑮𐑦𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑒 𐑕𐑐𐑨𐑯. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑤𐑩𐑕 ·𐑛𐑴-·𐑚𐑶 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑚𐑲 𐑯𐑱𐑗𐑼 𐑛𐑳𐑤 𐑯 𐑑𐑹𐑐𐑦𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑕, ·𐑐𐑦𐑐, 𐑞𐑴 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑼-𐑣𐑸𐑑𐑩𐑛, 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑨𐑑 𐑚𐑪𐑑𐑩𐑥 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑚𐑮𐑲𐑑, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑐𐑤𐑧𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑑, 𐑡𐑰𐑯𐑾𐑤, 𐑡𐑪𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑮𐑲𐑑𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑽 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑚; 𐑩 𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑚, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑦𐑯𐑡𐑶 𐑷𐑤 𐑣𐑪𐑤𐑦𐑛𐑱𐑟 𐑯 𐑓𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑓𐑲𐑯𐑼, 𐑓𐑮𐑰𐑼 𐑮𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑖 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑮𐑱𐑕. 𐑓 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑒𐑕, 𐑞 𐑘𐑽'𐑟 𐑒𐑨𐑤𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑖𐑴 𐑯𐑷𐑑 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑛 𐑯 𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑦-𐑓𐑲𐑝 ·𐑓𐑹𐑔 𐑝 ·𐑡𐑵𐑤𐑦𐑟 𐑯 ·𐑯𐑿 ·𐑘𐑽'𐑟 ·𐑛𐑱𐑟. 𐑯𐑹 𐑕𐑥𐑲𐑤 𐑕𐑴, 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑲 𐑮𐑲𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑒 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑚𐑮𐑦𐑤𐑾𐑯𐑑, 𐑓 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑒𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑚𐑮𐑦𐑤𐑾𐑯𐑕𐑦; 𐑚𐑦𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑘𐑪𐑯 𐑤𐑳𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑩𐑕 𐑧𐑚𐑩𐑯𐑦, 𐑐𐑨𐑯𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑒𐑦𐑙'𐑟 𐑒𐑨𐑚𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑑𐑕. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 ·𐑐𐑦𐑐 𐑤𐑳𐑝𐑛 𐑤𐑲𐑓, 𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑤𐑲𐑓'𐑕 𐑐𐑰𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑟; 𐑕𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑐𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑒-𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑦𐑟𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑣𐑬 𐑳𐑯𐑩𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑐𐑑, 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑨𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑤𐑻𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑮𐑲𐑑𐑯𐑩𐑕; 𐑞𐑴, 𐑨𐑟 𐑺 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑚𐑰 𐑕𐑰𐑯, 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞𐑳𐑕 𐑑𐑧𐑥𐑐𐑼𐑺𐑦𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑛𐑿𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑛𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑛 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑤𐑫𐑼𐑦𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑤𐑵𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡 𐑢𐑲𐑤𐑛 𐑓𐑲𐑼𐑟, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑓𐑦𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑖𐑴𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑪𐑓 𐑑 𐑑𐑧𐑯 𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑞 𐑯𐑨𐑗𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑤𐑳𐑕𐑑𐑼 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑱𐑑𐑦𐑝 ·𐑑𐑪𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛 ·𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑦 𐑦𐑯 ·𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑧𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑑, 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑕 𐑦𐑯𐑤𐑲𐑝𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑩 𐑓𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑤𐑼'𐑟 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑤𐑦𐑒 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑯; 𐑯 𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑦𐑤𐑴𐑛𐑾𐑕 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯-𐑑𐑲𐑛, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑜𐑱 𐑣𐑭-𐑣𐑭! 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑛 𐑞 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑣𐑼𐑲𐑟𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑸-𐑚𐑧𐑤𐑛 𐑑𐑨𐑥𐑚𐑼𐑰𐑯. 𐑕𐑴, 𐑞𐑴 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑒𐑤𐑽 𐑺 𐑝 𐑛𐑱, 𐑕𐑩𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑩 𐑚𐑤𐑵-𐑝𐑱𐑯𐑛 𐑯𐑧𐑒, 𐑞 𐑐𐑘𐑫𐑼-𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼𐑛 𐑛𐑲𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑛𐑮𐑪𐑐 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑔𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑜𐑤𐑴; 𐑘𐑧𐑑, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑞 𐑒𐑳𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑡𐑵𐑩𐑤𐑼 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑖𐑴 𐑿 𐑞 𐑛𐑲𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑦𐑝 𐑤𐑳𐑕𐑑𐑼, 𐑣𐑰 𐑤𐑱𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑩 𐑜𐑤𐑵𐑥𐑦 𐑜𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛, 𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑤𐑲𐑑𐑕 𐑦𐑑 𐑳𐑐, 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑯, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑳𐑯𐑯𐑨𐑗𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑜𐑨𐑕𐑩𐑟. 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑬𐑑 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑓𐑲𐑼𐑦 𐑦𐑓𐑳𐑤𐑡𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟, 𐑦𐑯𐑓𐑻𐑯𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑵𐑐𐑻𐑚; 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑞 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑤-𐑚𐑤𐑱𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑛𐑲𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑛, 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑕 𐑞 𐑛𐑦𐑝𐑲𐑯𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑦𐑥𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑒𐑲𐑟, 𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑕 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑒𐑮𐑬𐑯-𐑡𐑵𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑑𐑴𐑤𐑩𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 ·𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑝 ·𐑣𐑧𐑤. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑤𐑧𐑑 𐑳𐑕 𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑹𐑦.

𐑦𐑑 𐑒𐑱𐑥 𐑑 𐑐𐑭𐑕, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑨𐑥𐑚𐑼𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑕 𐑩𐑓𐑺 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚'𐑟 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼-𐑹𐑟𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑗𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑴 𐑑 𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑱𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛, 𐑨𐑟 𐑓 𐑩 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑒𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑥𐑱𐑥𐑛; 𐑯, 𐑑𐑧𐑥𐑐𐑼𐑺𐑦𐑤𐑦, ·𐑐𐑦𐑐 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑐𐑫𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕.

𐑞 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑑𐑲𐑥 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚 𐑤𐑴𐑼𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑥, ·𐑐𐑦𐑐 𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑯𐑻𐑝𐑩𐑕𐑯𐑩𐑕; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑦𐑤𐑦, 𐑓 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑑𐑲𐑥, 𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑱𐑐𐑑 𐑒𐑤𐑴𐑕 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑨𐑒𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤; 𐑯 𐑞𐑺𐑓𐑹 𐑒𐑱𐑥 𐑪𐑓 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑷𐑤𐑑𐑩𐑜𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑦; 𐑞𐑴 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚 𐑩𐑚𐑟𐑻𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑑𐑫𐑒 𐑒𐑺, 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼𐑢𐑼𐑛𐑟, 𐑑 𐑦𐑜𐑟𐑹𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑑 𐑗𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑖 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑼𐑱𐑡𐑩𐑕𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑑 𐑞 𐑳𐑑𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑, 𐑓 𐑣𐑰 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑪𐑓𐑩𐑯 𐑓𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑑 𐑯𐑰𐑛𐑓𐑩𐑤.

𐑯𐑬 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑧𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑤𐑴𐑼𐑦𐑙, 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑 𐑐𐑨𐑛𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤; 𐑯 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑓𐑦𐑖 𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑰𐑝𐑛 𐑞 𐑛𐑸𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑲𐑼𐑯, 𐑦𐑑 𐑜𐑱𐑝 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑒𐑳𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑥𐑼𐑦 𐑮𐑨𐑐, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑛, 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕, 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑮𐑲𐑑 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑐𐑫𐑼 ·𐑐𐑦𐑐'𐑕 𐑕𐑰𐑑. 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑪𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑦 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑯𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑥𐑴𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑒𐑷𐑟𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑑 𐑤𐑰𐑐, 𐑐𐑨𐑛𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛, 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑; 𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩 𐑢𐑱, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑐𐑸𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑤𐑨𐑒 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑤𐑲𐑯 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑗𐑧𐑕𐑑, 𐑣𐑰 𐑚𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑑 𐑴𐑝𐑼𐑚𐑹𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑕𐑴 𐑨𐑟 𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑨𐑙𐑜𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑦𐑑, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑐𐑤𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼. 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑪𐑯 𐑩 𐑓𐑽𐑕 𐑮𐑳𐑯, 𐑞 𐑤𐑲𐑯 𐑕𐑢𐑦𐑓𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑛; 𐑯 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑴! 𐑐𐑫𐑼 ·𐑐𐑦𐑐 𐑒𐑱𐑥 𐑷𐑤 𐑓𐑴𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑳𐑐 𐑑 𐑞 𐑗𐑪𐑒𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑, 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑹𐑕𐑤𐑩𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑮𐑨𐑜𐑛 𐑞𐑺 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑤𐑲𐑯, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑕𐑧𐑝𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑟 𐑼𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑗𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑯 𐑯𐑧𐑒.

·𐑑𐑨𐑖𐑑𐑱𐑜𐑴 𐑕𐑑𐑫𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑬𐑟. 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑓𐑫𐑤 𐑝 𐑞 𐑓𐑲𐑼 𐑝 𐑞 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑑. 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 ·𐑐𐑦𐑐 𐑓 𐑩 𐑐𐑪𐑤𐑑𐑮𐑵𐑯. 𐑕𐑯𐑨𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑-𐑯𐑲𐑓 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑖𐑰𐑔, 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑩𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑖𐑸𐑐 𐑧𐑡 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑞 𐑤𐑲𐑯, 𐑯 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑑𐑩𐑢𐑹𐑛𐑟 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚, 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑒𐑤𐑱𐑥𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑪𐑜𐑩𐑑𐑦𐑝𐑤𐑦, “𐑒𐑳𐑑?” 𐑥𐑰𐑯𐑑𐑲𐑥 ·𐑐𐑦𐑐'𐑕 𐑚𐑤𐑵, 𐑗𐑴𐑒𐑑 𐑓𐑱𐑕 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑑, 𐑛𐑵, 𐑓 ·𐑜𐑪𐑛'𐑟 𐑕𐑱𐑒! 𐑷𐑤 𐑐𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑓𐑤𐑨𐑖. 𐑦𐑯 𐑤𐑧𐑕 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑣𐑭𐑓 𐑩 𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑑, 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑲𐑼 𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑛.

“𐑛𐑨𐑥 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑒𐑳𐑑!” 𐑮𐑹𐑛 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚; 𐑯 𐑕𐑴 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑤𐑪𐑕𐑑 𐑯 ·𐑐𐑦𐑐 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑱𐑝𐑛.

𐑕𐑴 𐑕𐑵𐑯 𐑨𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑳𐑝𐑼𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓, 𐑞 𐑐𐑫𐑼 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑯𐑰𐑜𐑮𐑴 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑘𐑧𐑤𐑟 𐑯 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑮𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑵. 𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑼𐑥𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑦𐑮𐑧𐑜𐑿𐑤𐑼 𐑒𐑻𐑕𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑑 𐑦𐑝𐑨𐑐𐑼𐑱𐑑, ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑯, 𐑚𐑦𐑟𐑯𐑩𐑕-𐑤𐑲𐑒, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑣𐑭𐑓 𐑣𐑿𐑥𐑼𐑩𐑕 𐑥𐑨𐑯𐑼, 𐑒𐑻𐑕𐑑 ·𐑐𐑦𐑐 𐑩𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑤𐑦; 𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑛𐑳𐑯, 𐑳𐑯𐑩𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑜𐑱𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑕𐑩𐑥 𐑩𐑛𐑝𐑲𐑕. 𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑚𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑢𐑪𐑟, ·𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑡𐑳𐑥𐑐 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑩 𐑚𐑴𐑑, ·𐑐𐑦𐑐, 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑧𐑐𐑑—𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑧𐑓𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑑, 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑕𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑩𐑛𐑝𐑲𐑕 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑦𐑟. 𐑯𐑬, 𐑦𐑯 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑤, ·𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑑 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑, 𐑦𐑟 𐑘𐑹 𐑑𐑮𐑵 𐑥𐑪𐑑𐑴 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑒𐑱𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑧𐑯 ·𐑤𐑰𐑐 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑, 𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑚𐑧𐑑𐑼. 𐑥𐑹𐑴𐑝𐑼, 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑓 𐑐𐑼𐑕𐑰𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑓 𐑣𐑰 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑜𐑦𐑝 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑲𐑤𐑵𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑖𐑦𐑧𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑕 𐑩𐑛𐑝𐑲𐑕 𐑑 ·𐑐𐑦𐑐, 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑚𐑰 𐑤𐑰𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑑𐑵 𐑢𐑲𐑛 𐑩 𐑥𐑸𐑡𐑦𐑯 𐑑 𐑡𐑳𐑥𐑐 𐑦𐑯 𐑓 𐑞 𐑓𐑿𐑗𐑼; ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚 𐑕𐑳𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑮𐑪𐑐𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑩𐑛𐑝𐑲𐑕, 𐑯 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑒𐑤𐑵𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑐𐑼𐑧𐑥𐑐𐑑𐑼𐑦 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑭𐑯𐑛, “𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑑 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑, ·𐑐𐑦𐑐, 𐑹 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 ·𐑤𐑹𐑛, 𐑲 𐑢𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑐𐑦𐑒 𐑿 𐑳𐑐 𐑦𐑓 𐑿 𐑡𐑳𐑥𐑐; 𐑥𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑. 𐑢𐑰 𐑒𐑭𐑯𐑑 𐑩𐑓𐑹𐑛 𐑑 𐑤𐑵𐑟 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑤𐑲𐑒𐑕 𐑝 𐑿; 𐑩 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑕𐑧𐑤 𐑓 𐑔𐑻𐑑𐑦 𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑿 𐑢𐑫𐑛, ·𐑐𐑦𐑐, 𐑦𐑯 ·𐑨𐑤𐑩𐑚𐑨𐑥𐑩. 𐑚𐑺 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑲𐑯𐑛, 𐑯 𐑛𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑡𐑳𐑥𐑐 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑥𐑹.” 𐑣𐑽𐑚𐑲 𐑐𐑼𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑕 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑣𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑴 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑤𐑳𐑝𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑧𐑤𐑴, 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑦𐑟 𐑩 𐑥𐑳𐑯𐑦-𐑥𐑱𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑥𐑩𐑤, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑑𐑵 𐑪𐑓𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑓𐑽𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑦𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑕.

𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑰 𐑸 𐑷𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑜𐑪𐑛𐑟; 𐑯 ·𐑐𐑦𐑐 𐑡𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑑 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯. 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑕𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑤𐑼 𐑕𐑻𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑑 𐑞 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑐𐑼𐑓𐑹𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑕; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑣𐑰 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑚𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑬𐑑 𐑞 𐑤𐑲𐑯; 𐑯 𐑣𐑧𐑯𐑕, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑑 𐑮𐑳𐑯, ·𐑐𐑦𐑐 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑤𐑧𐑓𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑣𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑰, 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑣𐑳𐑮𐑦𐑛 𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑼'𐑟 𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑙𐑒. 𐑩𐑤𐑨𐑕! 𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑑𐑵 𐑑𐑮𐑵 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑻𐑛. 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩 𐑚𐑿𐑑𐑦𐑓𐑩𐑤, 𐑚𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑾𐑕, 𐑚𐑤𐑵 𐑛𐑱; 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑨𐑙𐑜𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑕𐑰 𐑒𐑭𐑥 𐑯 𐑒𐑵𐑤, 𐑯 𐑓𐑤𐑨𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑧𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑢𐑱, 𐑷𐑤 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛, 𐑑 𐑞 𐑣𐑼𐑲𐑟𐑩𐑯, 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑜𐑴𐑤𐑛-𐑚𐑰𐑑𐑼'𐑟 𐑕𐑒𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑥𐑼𐑛 𐑬𐑑 𐑑 𐑞 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑰𐑥𐑩𐑕𐑑. 𐑚𐑪𐑚𐑦𐑙 𐑳𐑐 𐑯 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑰, ·𐑐𐑦𐑐'𐑕 𐑦𐑚𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑖𐑴𐑛 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑝 𐑒𐑤𐑴𐑝𐑟. 𐑯𐑴 𐑚𐑴𐑑-𐑯𐑲𐑓 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑤𐑦𐑓𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑣𐑰 𐑓𐑧𐑤 𐑕𐑴 𐑮𐑨𐑐𐑦𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑩𐑕𐑑𐑻𐑯. 𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚'𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑼𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑚𐑨𐑒 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑛 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥; 𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑙𐑛. 𐑦𐑯 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑕, 𐑩 𐑣𐑴𐑤 𐑥𐑲𐑤 𐑝 𐑖𐑹𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑢𐑰𐑯 ·𐑐𐑦𐑐 𐑯 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚. 𐑬𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑼 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑰, 𐑐𐑫𐑼 ·𐑐𐑦𐑐 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑐, 𐑒𐑻𐑤𐑦𐑙, 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑒 𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑯, 𐑩𐑯𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑤𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑢𐑱, 𐑞𐑴 𐑞 𐑤𐑪𐑓𐑑𐑾𐑕𐑑 𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑮𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑕𐑑.

𐑯𐑬, 𐑦𐑯 𐑒𐑭𐑥 𐑢𐑧𐑞𐑼, 𐑑 𐑕𐑢𐑦𐑥 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑴𐑐𐑩𐑯 𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑟 𐑨𐑟 𐑰𐑟𐑦 𐑑 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑨𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑢𐑦𐑥𐑼 𐑨𐑟 𐑑 𐑮𐑲𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑙-𐑒𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑡 𐑩𐑖𐑹. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞 𐑷𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑤𐑴𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑥𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑪𐑤𐑼𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤. 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑕 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑥𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩 𐑣𐑸𐑑𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑦𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑑𐑦, 𐑥𐑲 ·𐑜𐑪𐑛! 𐑣𐑵 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑑𐑧𐑤 𐑦𐑑? 𐑥𐑸𐑒, 𐑣𐑬 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑼𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑛𐑧𐑛 𐑒𐑭𐑥 𐑚𐑱𐑞 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑴𐑐𐑩𐑯 𐑕𐑰—𐑥𐑸𐑒 𐑣𐑬 𐑒𐑤𐑴𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑞𐑱 𐑣𐑳𐑜 𐑞𐑺 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑯 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑣𐑻 𐑕𐑲𐑛𐑟.

𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑛 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚 𐑮𐑾𐑤𐑦 𐑩𐑚𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑞 𐑐𐑫𐑼 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑯𐑰𐑜𐑮𐑴 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑱𐑑? 𐑯𐑴; 𐑣𐑰 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑥𐑰𐑯 𐑑, 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑰𐑕𐑑. 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑪𐑟 𐑞𐑺 𐑢𐑻 𐑑𐑵 𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑱𐑒, 𐑯 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑩𐑐𐑴𐑟𐑛, 𐑯𐑴 𐑛𐑬𐑑, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑱 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑝 𐑒𐑹𐑕 𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑳𐑐 𐑑 ·𐑐𐑦𐑐 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑦, 𐑯 𐑐𐑦𐑒 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑳𐑐; 𐑞𐑴, 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑰𐑛, 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑼𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑑𐑩𐑢𐑹𐑛𐑟 𐑹𐑟𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑡𐑧𐑐𐑼𐑛𐑲𐑟𐑛 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑞𐑺 𐑴𐑯 𐑑𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑛𐑦𐑑𐑦, 𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑷𐑤𐑢𐑱𐑟 𐑥𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑓𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑕𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑤𐑼 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟; 𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑳𐑯𐑓𐑮𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑩𐑒𐑻; 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑺𐑾𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑼𐑦, 𐑩 𐑒𐑬𐑼𐑛, 𐑕𐑴 𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑛, 𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑸𐑒𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑮𐑵𐑔𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑛𐑦𐑑𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑽 𐑑 𐑥𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑺𐑦 𐑯𐑱𐑝𐑦𐑟 𐑯 𐑸𐑥𐑦𐑟.

𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑴 𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑛, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕, 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑦𐑙 ·𐑐𐑦𐑐, 𐑕𐑳𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑐𐑲𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑒𐑤𐑴𐑕 𐑑 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑪𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑕𐑲𐑛, 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑛, 𐑯 𐑜𐑱𐑝 𐑗𐑱𐑕; 𐑯 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚'𐑟 𐑚𐑴𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑬 𐑕𐑴 𐑓𐑸 𐑩𐑢𐑱, 𐑯 𐑣𐑰 𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑮𐑵 𐑕𐑴 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑦𐑖, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 ·𐑐𐑦𐑐'𐑕 𐑮𐑦𐑙𐑛 𐑣𐑼𐑲𐑟𐑩𐑯 𐑚𐑦𐑜𐑨𐑯 𐑑 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑼𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑥𐑦𐑟𐑼𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑦. 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑥𐑽𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑗𐑭𐑯𐑕 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑦𐑑𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑒𐑿𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑬𐑼 𐑞 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑯𐑰𐑜𐑮𐑴 𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑒 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑛𐑾𐑑; 𐑕𐑳𐑗, 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑰𐑕𐑑, 𐑞𐑱 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟. 𐑞 𐑕𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑡𐑽𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑧𐑐𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑲𐑯𐑲𐑑 𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦 𐑳𐑐, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑛𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑓𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑑 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑴𐑤. 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑛𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑲𐑼𐑤𐑦, 𐑞𐑴. 𐑮𐑭𐑞𐑼 𐑒𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑛 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑩𐑤𐑲𐑝 𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑕 𐑛𐑧𐑐𐑔𐑕, 𐑢𐑺 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡 𐑖𐑱𐑐𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑳𐑯𐑢𐑹𐑐𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑲𐑥𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛 𐑜𐑤𐑲𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑑 𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑴 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑨𐑕𐑦𐑝 𐑲𐑟; 𐑯 𐑞 𐑥𐑲𐑟𐑼-𐑥𐑻𐑥𐑩𐑯, ·𐑢𐑦𐑟𐑛𐑩𐑥, 𐑮𐑦𐑝𐑰𐑤𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑹𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑣𐑰𐑐𐑕; 𐑯 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑞 𐑡𐑶𐑩𐑕, 𐑣𐑸𐑑𐑤𐑩𐑕, 𐑧𐑝𐑼-𐑡𐑵𐑝𐑩𐑯𐑲𐑤 𐑦𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑟, ·𐑐𐑦𐑐 𐑕𐑷 𐑞 𐑥𐑳𐑤𐑑𐑦𐑑𐑿𐑛𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑕, ·𐑜𐑪𐑛-𐑪𐑥𐑯𐑦𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑑, 𐑒𐑪𐑮𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑕, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑓𐑻𐑥𐑩𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼𐑟 𐑣𐑰𐑝𐑛 𐑞 𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑕𐑩𐑤 𐑹𐑚𐑟. 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑷 ·𐑜𐑪𐑛'𐑟 𐑓𐑫𐑑 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑑𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑞 𐑤𐑵𐑥, 𐑯 𐑕𐑐𐑴𐑒 𐑦𐑑; 𐑯 𐑞𐑺𐑓𐑹 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑥𐑱𐑑𐑕 𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑥𐑨𐑛. 𐑕𐑴 𐑥𐑨𐑯'𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑯'𐑟 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑕; 𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑷𐑤 𐑥𐑹𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑮𐑰𐑟𐑩𐑯, 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑟 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑦𐑤𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑾𐑤 𐑔𐑷𐑑, 𐑢𐑦𐑗, 𐑑 𐑮𐑰𐑟𐑩𐑯, 𐑦𐑟 𐑩𐑚𐑕𐑻𐑛 𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑒; 𐑯 𐑢𐑰𐑤 𐑹 𐑢𐑴, 𐑓𐑰𐑤𐑟 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑳𐑯𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑥𐑲𐑟𐑛, 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑓𐑼𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑟 ·𐑜𐑪𐑛.

𐑓 𐑞 𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑑, 𐑚𐑤𐑱𐑥 𐑯𐑪𐑑 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚 𐑑𐑵 𐑣𐑸𐑛𐑤𐑦. 𐑞 𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑼𐑦; 𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑞 𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑑𐑦𐑝, 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑚𐑰 𐑕𐑰𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩𐑚𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑧𐑤 𐑥𐑲𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓.

·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 94. 𐑩 ·𐑕𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛.

𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑝 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚'𐑟, 𐑕𐑴 𐑛𐑽𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑻𐑗𐑩𐑕𐑑, 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑛𐑵𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑮𐑷𐑑 𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛'𐑟 𐑕𐑲𐑛, 𐑢𐑺 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑒𐑳𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑯 𐑣𐑶𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑪𐑐𐑼𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑐𐑮𐑰𐑝𐑾𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑰𐑑𐑱𐑤𐑛, 𐑢𐑻 𐑮𐑧𐑜𐑿𐑤𐑼𐑤𐑦 𐑜𐑪𐑯 𐑔𐑮𐑵, 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑑 𐑞 𐑚𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑣𐑲𐑛𐑩𐑤𐑚𐑼𐑩 ·𐑑𐑳𐑯, 𐑹 ·𐑒𐑱𐑕.

𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑢𐑻 𐑪𐑒𐑿𐑐𐑲𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑤𐑨𐑑𐑼 𐑛𐑿𐑑𐑦, 𐑳𐑞𐑼𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑶𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑛𐑮𐑨𐑜𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑢𐑱 𐑞 𐑤𐑸𐑡𐑼 𐑑𐑳𐑚𐑟, 𐑕𐑴 𐑕𐑵𐑯 𐑨𐑟 𐑓𐑦𐑤𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥; 𐑯 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑐𐑼 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑼𐑲𐑝𐑛, 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑒𐑺𐑓𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑐𐑿𐑤𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑺 𐑜𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑞 𐑑𐑮𐑲-𐑢𐑻𐑒𐑕, 𐑝 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑩𐑯𐑪𐑯.

𐑦𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑒𐑵𐑤𐑛 𐑯 𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑲𐑟𐑛 𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩 𐑛𐑦𐑜𐑮𐑰, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑧𐑯, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑕𐑧𐑝𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑳𐑞𐑼𐑟, 𐑲 𐑕𐑨𐑑 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑩 𐑤𐑸𐑡 ·𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑰𐑯'𐑟 𐑚𐑭𐑔 𐑝 𐑦𐑑, 𐑲 𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑒𐑮𐑰𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑤𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑕, 𐑣𐑽 𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑮𐑴𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑤𐑦𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑛 𐑐𐑸𐑑. 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑬𐑼 𐑚𐑦𐑟𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑑 𐑕𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑟 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑤𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑕 𐑚𐑨𐑒 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑓𐑤𐑵𐑦𐑛. 𐑩 𐑕𐑢𐑰𐑑 𐑯 𐑳𐑙𐑒𐑗𐑵𐑩𐑕 𐑛𐑿𐑑𐑦! 𐑯𐑴 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩 𐑓𐑱𐑝𐑼𐑦𐑑 𐑒𐑪𐑟𐑥𐑧𐑑𐑦𐑒. 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩 𐑒𐑤𐑽𐑼! 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩 𐑕𐑢𐑰𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑼! 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩 𐑕𐑪𐑓𐑩𐑯𐑼! 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩 𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑕 𐑥𐑴𐑤𐑦𐑓𐑲𐑼! 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑣𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑦𐑑 𐑓 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑩 𐑓𐑿 𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑕, 𐑥𐑲 𐑓𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑼𐑟 𐑓𐑧𐑤𐑑 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑰𐑤𐑟, 𐑯 𐑚𐑦𐑜𐑨𐑯, 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑻, 𐑑 𐑕𐑻𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑲𐑯 𐑯 𐑕𐑐𐑲𐑮𐑩𐑤𐑲𐑟.

𐑨𐑟 𐑲 𐑕𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑲 𐑰𐑟, 𐑒𐑮𐑪𐑕-𐑤𐑧𐑜𐑩𐑛 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑒; 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑞 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑼 𐑦𐑜𐑟𐑻𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑤𐑩𐑕; 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑩 𐑚𐑤𐑵 𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑕𐑒𐑲; 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑕𐑱𐑤, 𐑯 𐑜𐑤𐑲𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑴 𐑕𐑼𐑰𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑙; 𐑨𐑟 𐑲 𐑚𐑱𐑞𐑛 𐑥𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑕𐑪𐑓𐑑, 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑜𐑤𐑪𐑚𐑿𐑤𐑟 𐑝 𐑦𐑯𐑓𐑦𐑤𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑑𐑦𐑖𐑿𐑟, 𐑢𐑴𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑬𐑼; 𐑨𐑟 𐑞𐑱 𐑮𐑦𐑗𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑮𐑴𐑒 𐑑 𐑥𐑲 𐑓𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑼𐑟, 𐑯 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑗𐑸𐑡𐑛 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑺 𐑪𐑐𐑿𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑕, 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑓𐑫𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑲𐑐 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑐𐑕 𐑞𐑺 𐑢𐑲𐑯; 𐑨𐑟 𐑲 𐑕𐑯𐑳𐑓𐑑 𐑳𐑐 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑳𐑯𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑨𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑼𐑴𐑥𐑩,—𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑼𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑯 𐑑𐑮𐑵𐑤𐑦, 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑞 𐑕𐑥𐑧𐑤 𐑝 𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑙 𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑤𐑩𐑑𐑕; 𐑲 𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑺 𐑑 𐑿, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑓 𐑞 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑲 𐑤𐑦𐑝𐑛 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑒𐑦 𐑥𐑧𐑛𐑴; 𐑲 𐑓𐑼𐑜𐑪𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑬𐑼 𐑣𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑴𐑔; 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥, 𐑲 𐑢𐑪𐑖𐑑 𐑥𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑯 𐑥𐑲 𐑣𐑸𐑑 𐑝 𐑦𐑑; 𐑲 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑜𐑨𐑯 𐑑 𐑒𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑦𐑑 𐑞 𐑴𐑤𐑛 ·𐑐𐑨𐑮𐑩𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑕𐑩𐑯 𐑕𐑵𐑐𐑼𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 𐑦𐑟 𐑝 𐑮𐑺 𐑝𐑻𐑗𐑵 𐑦𐑯 𐑩𐑤𐑱𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑣𐑰𐑑 𐑝 𐑨𐑙𐑜𐑼; 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑚𐑱𐑞𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑚𐑭𐑔, 𐑲 𐑓𐑧𐑤𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑝𐑲𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑓𐑮𐑰 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑷𐑤 𐑦𐑤-𐑢𐑦𐑤, 𐑹 𐑐𐑧𐑑𐑿𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑕, 𐑹 𐑥𐑨𐑤𐑦𐑕, 𐑝 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑕𐑹𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑑𐑕𐑴𐑧𐑝𐑼.

𐑕𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑟! 𐑕𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑟! 𐑕𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑟! 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑥𐑹𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑤𐑪𐑙; 𐑲 𐑕𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑟𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑲 𐑥𐑲𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑥𐑧𐑤𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑦𐑑; 𐑲 𐑕𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑟𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑩 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡 𐑕𐑹𐑑 𐑝 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑒𐑱𐑥 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑥𐑰; 𐑯 𐑲 𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑥𐑲𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑳𐑯𐑢𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑲 𐑒𐑴-𐑤𐑱𐑚𐑼𐑼𐑟' 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑦𐑑, 𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑺 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑓 𐑞 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑜𐑤𐑪𐑚𐑿𐑤𐑟. 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩𐑯 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙, 𐑩𐑓𐑧𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑑, 𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑤𐑦, 𐑤𐑳𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑰𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑨𐑝𐑩𐑒𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑚𐑦𐑜𐑧𐑑; 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑲 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑿𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑺 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟, 𐑯 𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑳𐑐 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞𐑺 𐑲𐑟 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑦; 𐑨𐑟 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑨𐑟 𐑑 𐑕𐑱,—𐑴! 𐑥𐑲 𐑛𐑽 𐑓𐑧𐑤𐑴 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙𐑟, 𐑢𐑲 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑢𐑰 𐑤𐑪𐑙𐑜𐑼 𐑗𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑖 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑕𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑤 𐑩𐑕𐑻𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑟, 𐑹 𐑯𐑴 𐑞 𐑕𐑤𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑤-𐑣𐑿𐑥𐑼 𐑹 𐑧𐑯𐑝𐑦! 𐑒𐑳𐑥; 𐑤𐑧𐑑 𐑳𐑕 𐑕𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑷𐑤 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛; 𐑯𐑱, 𐑤𐑧𐑑 𐑳𐑕 𐑷𐑤 𐑕𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑟 𐑬𐑼𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑝𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑰𐑗 𐑳𐑞𐑼; 𐑤𐑧𐑑 𐑳𐑕 𐑕𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑟 𐑬𐑼𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑝𐑟 𐑿𐑯𐑦𐑝𐑻𐑕𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑥𐑦𐑤𐑒 𐑯 𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 𐑝 𐑒𐑲𐑯𐑛𐑯𐑩𐑕.

𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑲 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑒𐑰𐑐 𐑕𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 𐑓 𐑧𐑝𐑼! 𐑓 𐑯𐑬, 𐑕𐑦𐑯𐑕 𐑚𐑲 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑐𐑮𐑴𐑤𐑪𐑙𐑛, 𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑰𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑽𐑾𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟, 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑐𐑼𐑕𐑰𐑝𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑒𐑱𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑝𐑧𐑯𐑗𐑵𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑤𐑴𐑼, 𐑹 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑰𐑕𐑑 𐑖𐑦𐑓𐑑, 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑰𐑑 𐑝 𐑩𐑑𐑱𐑯𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑓𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑕𐑦𐑑𐑦; 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑑 𐑧𐑯𐑦𐑢𐑺 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑧𐑒𐑑 𐑹 𐑞 𐑓𐑨𐑯𐑕𐑦; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑲𐑓, 𐑞 𐑣𐑸𐑑, 𐑞 𐑚𐑧𐑛, 𐑞 𐑑𐑱𐑚𐑩𐑤, 𐑞 𐑕𐑨𐑛𐑩𐑤, 𐑞 𐑓𐑲𐑼𐑕𐑲𐑛, 𐑞 𐑒𐑳𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑦; 𐑯𐑬 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑐𐑼𐑕𐑰𐑝𐑛 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑦𐑕, 𐑲 𐑨𐑥 𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑦 𐑑 𐑕𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑟 𐑒𐑱𐑕 𐑦𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑩𐑤𐑦. 𐑦𐑯 𐑔𐑷𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑝𐑦𐑠𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑯𐑲𐑑, 𐑲 𐑕𐑷 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑮𐑴𐑟 𐑝 𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑐𐑨𐑮𐑩𐑛𐑲𐑕, 𐑰𐑗 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑡𐑸 𐑝 𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥𐑩𐑕𐑧𐑑𐑦.

𐑯𐑬, 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑹𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥, 𐑦𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑣𐑵𐑝𐑟 𐑑 𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑒 𐑝 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑩𐑒𐑦𐑯 𐑑 𐑦𐑑, 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑦𐑟𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑺𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑓 𐑞 𐑑𐑮𐑲-𐑢𐑻𐑒𐑕.

𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑟 𐑢𐑲𐑑-𐑣𐑹𐑕, 𐑕𐑴 𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑛, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑦𐑟 𐑩𐑚𐑑𐑱𐑯𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑑𐑱𐑐𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑐𐑸𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑓𐑦𐑖, 𐑯 𐑷𐑤𐑕𐑴 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑔𐑦𐑒𐑼 𐑐𐑹𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑤𐑵𐑒𐑕. 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑑𐑳𐑓 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑡𐑰𐑤𐑛 𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑟—𐑩 𐑢𐑪𐑛 𐑝 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑩𐑤—𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑱𐑯𐑟 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑶𐑤. 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑧𐑝𐑼𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑞 𐑢𐑲𐑑-𐑣𐑹𐑕 𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑒𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑐𐑹𐑑𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑪𐑚𐑤𐑪𐑙𐑟 𐑺 𐑜𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑞 𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑼. 𐑞𐑱 𐑤𐑫𐑒 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑚𐑤𐑪𐑒𐑕 𐑝 ·𐑚𐑸𐑒𐑖𐑼 𐑥𐑸𐑚𐑩𐑤.

𐑐𐑤𐑳𐑥-𐑐𐑫𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑟 𐑞 𐑑𐑻𐑥 𐑚𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑴𐑛 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑨𐑜𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑦 𐑐𐑸𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤'𐑟 𐑓𐑤𐑧𐑖, 𐑣𐑽 𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑨𐑛𐑣𐑽𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑞 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑩𐑑 𐑝 𐑚𐑤𐑳𐑚𐑼, 𐑯 𐑪𐑓𐑩𐑯 𐑐𐑸𐑑𐑦𐑕𐑦𐑐𐑱𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑩 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑼𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑛𐑦𐑜𐑮𐑰 𐑦𐑯 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑳𐑙𐑒𐑗𐑵𐑩𐑕𐑯𐑩𐑕. 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑩 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑖𐑦𐑙, 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑝𐑦𐑝𐑾𐑤, 𐑚𐑿𐑑𐑦𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑪𐑚𐑡𐑧𐑒𐑑 𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛. 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑯𐑱𐑥 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑹𐑑𐑕, 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑝 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑰𐑛𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑦𐑗, 𐑥𐑪𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑑, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑚𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑰𐑒𐑑 𐑕𐑯𐑴𐑦 𐑯 𐑜𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑩𐑯 𐑜𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛, 𐑛𐑪𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑪𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑛𐑰𐑐𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑟𐑩𐑯 𐑯 𐑐𐑻𐑐𐑩𐑤. 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑤𐑳𐑥𐑟 𐑝 𐑮𐑵𐑚𐑦𐑟, 𐑦𐑯 𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑗𐑼𐑟 𐑝 𐑕𐑦𐑑𐑮𐑩𐑯. 𐑕𐑐𐑲𐑑 𐑝 𐑮𐑰𐑟𐑩𐑯, 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑸𐑛 𐑑 𐑒𐑰𐑐 𐑘𐑹𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑰𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑑. 𐑲 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑓𐑧𐑕, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑕 𐑲 𐑕𐑑𐑴𐑤 𐑚𐑦𐑣𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑞 𐑓𐑹𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑑 𐑑𐑮𐑲 𐑦𐑑. 𐑦𐑑 𐑑𐑱𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑨𐑟 𐑲 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑰𐑝 𐑩 𐑮𐑶𐑩𐑤 𐑒𐑳𐑑𐑤𐑩𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑔𐑲 𐑝 ·𐑤𐑵𐑦 𐑤𐑩 ·𐑜𐑮𐑴𐑟 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑑𐑱𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛, 𐑕𐑩𐑐𐑴𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑒𐑦𐑤𐑛 𐑞 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑛𐑱 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑞 𐑝𐑧𐑯𐑦𐑟𐑩𐑯 𐑕𐑰𐑟𐑩𐑯, 𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑐𐑼𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑼 𐑝𐑧𐑯𐑦𐑟𐑩𐑯 𐑕𐑰𐑟𐑩𐑯 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑥𐑐𐑼𐑼𐑦 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩𐑯 𐑳𐑯𐑿𐑠𐑵𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑓𐑲𐑯 𐑝𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑡 𐑝 𐑞 𐑝𐑦𐑯𐑘𐑼𐑛𐑟 𐑝 ·𐑖𐑨𐑥𐑐𐑱𐑯.

𐑞𐑺 𐑦𐑟 𐑩𐑯𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑕𐑳𐑚𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕, 𐑯 𐑩 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑕𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑿𐑤𐑼 𐑢𐑳𐑯, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑟 𐑳𐑐 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑒𐑹𐑕 𐑝 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑚𐑦𐑟𐑯𐑩𐑕, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑲 𐑓𐑰𐑤 𐑦𐑑 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑐𐑳𐑟𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑨𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑢𐑩𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑚. 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑛 𐑕𐑤𐑪𐑚𐑜𐑴𐑤𐑾𐑯; 𐑩𐑯 𐑨𐑐𐑩𐑤𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑼𐑦𐑡𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑥𐑧𐑯, 𐑯 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑕𐑴 𐑦𐑟 𐑞 𐑯𐑱𐑗𐑼 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑚𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕. 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑧𐑓𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑵𐑟𐑦, 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑙𐑦 𐑩𐑓𐑺, 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑑𐑳𐑚𐑟 𐑝 𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥, 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑩 𐑐𐑮𐑴𐑤𐑪𐑙𐑛 𐑕𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑟𐑦𐑙, 𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑚𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑢𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑙. 𐑲 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑦𐑑 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑞 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑔𐑦𐑯, 𐑮𐑳𐑐𐑗𐑼𐑛 𐑥𐑧𐑥𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑒𐑱𐑕, 𐑒𐑴𐑩𐑤𐑧𐑕𐑦𐑙.

𐑜𐑻𐑦, 𐑕𐑴 𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑛, 𐑦𐑟 𐑩 𐑑𐑻𐑥 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑐𐑼𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑪𐑙𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑮𐑲𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑥𐑧𐑯, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑿𐑟𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑼𐑥𐑧𐑯. 𐑦𐑑 𐑛𐑧𐑟𐑦𐑜𐑯𐑱𐑑𐑕 𐑞 𐑛𐑸𐑒, 𐑜𐑤𐑵𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑕𐑳𐑚𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑱𐑐𐑑 𐑪𐑓 𐑞 𐑚𐑨𐑒 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑯𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑹 𐑮𐑲𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑯 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑝 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑒𐑳𐑝𐑼𐑟 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑒𐑕 𐑝 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑓𐑽𐑽 𐑕𐑴𐑤𐑟 𐑣𐑵 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑜𐑯𐑴𐑚𐑩𐑤 ·𐑤𐑩𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑔𐑩𐑯.

𐑯𐑦𐑐𐑼𐑟. 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑻𐑛 𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑡𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑑 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤'𐑟 𐑝𐑴𐑒𐑨𐑚𐑿𐑤𐑼𐑦. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑩𐑐𐑤𐑲𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑥𐑧𐑯, 𐑦𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑟 𐑕𐑴. 𐑩 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑥𐑩𐑯'𐑟 𐑯𐑦𐑐𐑼 𐑦𐑟 𐑩 𐑖𐑹𐑑 𐑓𐑻𐑥 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑐 𐑝 𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑓 𐑒𐑳𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑑𐑱𐑐𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑐𐑸𐑑 𐑝 ·𐑤𐑩𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑔𐑩𐑯'𐑟 𐑑𐑱𐑤: 𐑦𐑑 𐑨𐑝𐑼𐑦𐑡𐑩𐑟 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑗 𐑦𐑯 𐑔𐑦𐑒𐑯𐑩𐑕, 𐑯 𐑓 𐑞 𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑑, 𐑦𐑟 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑲𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑲𐑼𐑯 𐑐𐑸𐑑 𐑝 𐑩 𐑣𐑴. 𐑧𐑡𐑢𐑲𐑟 𐑥𐑵𐑝𐑛 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑞 𐑶𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑧𐑒, 𐑦𐑑 𐑪𐑐𐑼𐑱𐑑𐑕 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑤𐑧𐑞𐑼𐑯 𐑕𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑤𐑡𐑰; 𐑯 𐑚𐑲 𐑯𐑱𐑥𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑖𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕, 𐑨𐑟 𐑝 𐑥𐑨𐑡𐑦𐑒, 𐑩𐑤𐑫𐑼𐑟 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑦𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑟.

𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑑 𐑤𐑻𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑛𐑲𐑑 𐑥𐑨𐑑𐑼𐑟, 𐑘𐑹 𐑚𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑢𐑱 𐑦𐑟 𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑕 𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑚𐑤𐑳𐑚𐑼-𐑮𐑵𐑥, 𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑩 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑑𐑷𐑒 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑦𐑯𐑥𐑱𐑑𐑕. 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑐𐑮𐑰𐑝𐑾𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑧𐑐𐑑𐑩𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑓 𐑞 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑩𐑑-𐑐𐑰𐑕𐑩𐑟, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑑 𐑯 𐑣𐑶𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤. 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑐𐑼 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑼𐑲𐑝𐑟 𐑓 𐑒𐑳𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑳𐑐 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑕, 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑩𐑐𐑸𐑑𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑩 𐑕𐑰𐑯 𐑝 𐑑𐑧𐑮𐑼 𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑑𐑲𐑮𐑴𐑟, 𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑲 𐑯𐑲𐑑. 𐑪𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑕𐑲𐑛, 𐑤𐑦𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑩 𐑛𐑳𐑤 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑯, 𐑩 𐑕𐑐𐑱𐑕 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑤𐑧𐑓𐑑 𐑒𐑤𐑽 𐑓 𐑞 𐑢𐑻𐑒𐑥𐑧𐑯. 𐑞𐑱 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑜𐑴 𐑦𐑯 𐑐𐑺𐑟,—𐑩 𐑐𐑲𐑒-𐑯-𐑜𐑨𐑓𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑯 𐑩 𐑕𐑐𐑱𐑛-𐑥𐑨𐑯. 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙-𐑐𐑲𐑒 𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑤𐑼 𐑑 𐑩 𐑓𐑮𐑦𐑜𐑩𐑑'𐑕 𐑚𐑹𐑛𐑦𐑙-𐑢𐑧𐑐𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑯𐑱𐑥. 𐑞 𐑜𐑨𐑓 𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑚𐑴𐑑-𐑣𐑫𐑒. 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑜𐑨𐑓, 𐑞 𐑜𐑨𐑓𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑣𐑫𐑒𐑕 𐑪𐑯 𐑑 𐑩 𐑖𐑰𐑑 𐑝 𐑚𐑤𐑳𐑚𐑼, 𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑝𐑟 𐑑 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑦𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑕𐑤𐑦𐑐𐑦𐑙, 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑐𐑦𐑗𐑩𐑟 𐑯 𐑤𐑻𐑗𐑩𐑟 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑. 𐑥𐑰𐑯𐑢𐑲𐑤, 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑱𐑛-𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑖𐑰𐑑 𐑦𐑑𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓, 𐑐𐑻𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑼𐑤𐑦 𐑗𐑪𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑐𐑹𐑑𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑣𐑹𐑕-𐑐𐑰𐑕𐑩𐑟. 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑕𐑐𐑱𐑛 𐑦𐑟 𐑖𐑸𐑐 𐑨𐑟 𐑣𐑴𐑯 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑥𐑱𐑒 𐑦𐑑; 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑱𐑛𐑥𐑩𐑯'𐑟 𐑓𐑰𐑑 𐑸 𐑖𐑵𐑤𐑩𐑕; 𐑞 𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑪𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑦𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑤𐑲𐑛 𐑩𐑢𐑱 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑕𐑤𐑧𐑡. 𐑦𐑓 𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑳𐑑𐑕 𐑪𐑓 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑴𐑯 𐑑𐑴𐑟, 𐑹 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑩𐑕𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕', 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑿 𐑚𐑰 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑩𐑕𐑑𐑪𐑯𐑦𐑖𐑑? 𐑑𐑴𐑟 𐑸 𐑕𐑒𐑺𐑕 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑝𐑧𐑑𐑼𐑩𐑯 𐑚𐑤𐑳𐑚𐑼-𐑮𐑵𐑥 𐑥𐑧𐑯.

·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 95. 𐑞 ·𐑒𐑨𐑕𐑩𐑒.

𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑿 𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑐𐑑 𐑪𐑯 𐑚𐑹𐑛 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛 𐑨𐑑 𐑩 𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑡𐑳𐑙𐑒𐑗𐑼 𐑝 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑐𐑴𐑕𐑑-𐑥𐑹𐑑𐑧𐑥𐑲𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤; 𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑿 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑓𐑹𐑢𐑼𐑛 𐑯𐑲 𐑞 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑤𐑩𐑕, 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑖𐑫𐑼 𐑨𐑥 𐑲 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑿 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑕𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑯𐑴 𐑕𐑥𐑷𐑤 𐑒𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑦𐑪𐑕𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑩 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡, 𐑧𐑯𐑦𐑜𐑥𐑨𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑪𐑚𐑡𐑧𐑒𐑑, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑿 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑕𐑰𐑯 𐑞𐑺, 𐑤𐑲𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑤𐑧𐑙𐑔𐑢𐑲𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑤𐑰 𐑕𐑒𐑳𐑐𐑼𐑟. 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑞 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑕 𐑕𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤'𐑟 𐑣𐑿𐑡 𐑣𐑧𐑛; 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑛𐑦𐑡𐑦 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑳𐑯𐑣𐑦𐑯𐑡𐑛 𐑤𐑴𐑼 𐑡𐑷; 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑞 𐑥𐑦𐑮𐑩𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑦𐑥𐑧𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑑𐑱𐑤; 𐑯𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑕𐑴 𐑕𐑼𐑐𐑮𐑲𐑟 𐑿, 𐑨𐑟 𐑣𐑭𐑓 𐑩 𐑜𐑤𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑕 𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑳𐑯𐑩𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑒𐑴𐑯,—𐑤𐑪𐑙𐑜𐑼 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑩 ·𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑳𐑒𐑾𐑯 𐑦𐑟 𐑑𐑷𐑤, 𐑯𐑲 𐑩 𐑓𐑫𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑛𐑲𐑨𐑥𐑦𐑑𐑼 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑚𐑱𐑕, 𐑯 𐑡𐑧𐑑-𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑒 𐑨𐑟 ·𐑘𐑴𐑡𐑴, 𐑞 𐑧𐑚𐑩𐑯𐑦 𐑲𐑛𐑩𐑤 𐑝 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜. 𐑯 𐑩𐑯 𐑲𐑛𐑩𐑤, 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑰𐑛, 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟; 𐑹, 𐑮𐑭𐑞𐑼, 𐑦𐑯 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟, 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑤𐑲𐑒𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑢𐑪𐑟. 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩𐑯 𐑲𐑛𐑩𐑤 𐑨𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑰𐑒𐑮𐑩𐑑 𐑜𐑮𐑴𐑝𐑟 𐑝 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑯 ·𐑥𐑸𐑒𐑩 𐑦𐑯 ·𐑡𐑵𐑛𐑾; 𐑯 𐑓 𐑢𐑻𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑦𐑗, ·𐑒𐑦𐑙 ·𐑱𐑕𐑩, 𐑣𐑻 𐑕𐑳𐑯, 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑛𐑦𐑐𐑴𐑟 𐑣𐑻, 𐑯 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑶𐑛 𐑞 𐑲𐑛𐑩𐑤, 𐑯 𐑚𐑻𐑯𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑓 𐑩𐑯 𐑩𐑚𐑪𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑚𐑮𐑫𐑒 ·𐑒𐑧𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑯, 𐑨𐑟 𐑛𐑸𐑒𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑧𐑑 𐑓𐑹𐑔 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 15𐑔 𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 𐑝 𐑞 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 ·𐑚𐑫𐑒 𐑝 ·𐑒𐑦𐑙𐑟.

𐑤𐑫𐑒 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑼, 𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑛 𐑞 𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑼, 𐑣𐑵 𐑯𐑬 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑟 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑙, 𐑯 𐑩𐑕𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑑𐑵 𐑨𐑤𐑲𐑟, 𐑣𐑧𐑝𐑦𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑨𐑒𐑕 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑕, 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑥𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑯𐑼𐑟 𐑒𐑷𐑤 𐑦𐑑, 𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑚𐑬𐑛 𐑖𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑼𐑟, 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑜𐑼𐑟 𐑪𐑓 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑦𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑓 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑻 𐑩 𐑜𐑮𐑧𐑯𐑩𐑛𐑽 𐑒𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑛𐑧𐑛 𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑮𐑱𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑓𐑰𐑤𐑛. 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑑 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑴𐑒𐑕𐑩𐑤 𐑛𐑧𐑒, 𐑣𐑰 𐑯𐑬 𐑐𐑮𐑴𐑕𐑰𐑛𐑟 𐑕𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑦 𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑵𐑝 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑛𐑸𐑒 𐑐𐑧𐑤𐑑, 𐑨𐑟 𐑩𐑯 ·𐑨𐑓𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑑𐑼 𐑞 𐑐𐑧𐑤𐑑 𐑝 𐑩 𐑚𐑴𐑩. 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑛𐑳𐑯 𐑣𐑰 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑟 𐑞 𐑐𐑧𐑤𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑬𐑑, 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑐𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑵𐑯 𐑤𐑧𐑜; 𐑜𐑦𐑝𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑩 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑧𐑗𐑦𐑙, 𐑕𐑴 𐑨𐑟 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑑 𐑛𐑳𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑛𐑲𐑨𐑥𐑦𐑑𐑼; 𐑯 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑙𐑟 𐑦𐑑, 𐑢𐑧𐑤 𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑛, 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑮𐑦𐑜𐑦𐑙, 𐑑 𐑛𐑮𐑲. 𐑺 𐑤𐑪𐑙, 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑛𐑬𐑯; 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑵𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑓𐑰𐑑 𐑝 𐑦𐑑, 𐑑𐑩𐑢𐑹𐑛𐑟 𐑞 𐑐𐑶𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑧𐑥𐑦𐑑𐑦, 𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑒𐑳𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑑𐑵 𐑕𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑓 𐑸𐑥-𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑟 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑧𐑯𐑛, 𐑣𐑰 𐑤𐑧𐑙𐑔𐑢𐑲𐑟 𐑕𐑤𐑦𐑐𐑕 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑦𐑑. 𐑞 𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑼 𐑯𐑬 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑿 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑫𐑤 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑪𐑯𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑦𐑙. 𐑦𐑥𐑩𐑥𐑹𐑾𐑤 𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑹𐑛𐑼, 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑗𐑼 𐑩𐑤𐑴𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑨𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑢𐑩𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑑𐑧𐑒𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑶𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑽 𐑓𐑳𐑙𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑪𐑓𐑦𐑕.

𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑪𐑓𐑦𐑕 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑣𐑹𐑕-𐑐𐑰𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑝 𐑚𐑤𐑳𐑚𐑼 𐑓 𐑞 𐑐𐑪𐑑𐑕; 𐑩𐑯 𐑪𐑐𐑼𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑛𐑳𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑨𐑑 𐑩 𐑒𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑾𐑕 𐑢𐑫𐑛𐑩𐑯 𐑣𐑹𐑕, 𐑐𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑢𐑲𐑟 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑞 𐑚𐑫𐑤𐑢𐑼𐑒𐑕, 𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑒𐑩𐑐𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑕 𐑑𐑳𐑚 𐑚𐑦𐑯𐑰𐑔 𐑦𐑑, 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑞 𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑐𐑰𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑛𐑮𐑪𐑐, 𐑓𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑖𐑰𐑑𐑕 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑩 𐑮𐑨𐑐𐑑 𐑪𐑮𐑩𐑑𐑼'𐑟 𐑛𐑧𐑕𐑒. 𐑼𐑱𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑛𐑰𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑒; 𐑪𐑒𐑿𐑐𐑲𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑩𐑕 𐑐𐑫𐑤𐑐𐑦𐑑; 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑪𐑯 𐑚𐑲𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑤𐑰𐑝𐑟; 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑩 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑑 𐑓 𐑩𐑯 𐑸𐑗𐑚𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑒, 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑩 𐑤𐑨𐑛 𐑓 𐑩 ·𐑐𐑴𐑐 𐑢𐑻 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑼!*

*𐑚𐑲𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑤𐑰𐑝𐑟! 𐑚𐑲𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑤𐑰𐑝𐑟! 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑦𐑟 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑺𐑾𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑒𐑮𐑲 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑥𐑱𐑑𐑕 𐑑 𐑞 𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑼. 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑡𐑶𐑯𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑒𐑺𐑓𐑩𐑤, 𐑯 𐑒𐑳𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑻𐑒 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑨𐑟 𐑔𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑤𐑲𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑨𐑟 𐑐𐑪𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤, 𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑟𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑨𐑟 𐑚𐑲 𐑕𐑴 𐑛𐑵𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑚𐑦𐑟𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑚𐑶𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑬𐑑 𐑞 𐑶𐑤 𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑩𐑒𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑼𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛, 𐑯 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑼𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑮𐑰𐑕𐑑, 𐑚𐑦𐑕𐑲𐑛𐑟 𐑐𐑼𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑕 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑮𐑵𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑦.

·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 96. 𐑞 ·𐑑𐑮𐑲-·𐑢𐑻𐑒𐑕.

𐑚𐑦𐑕𐑲𐑛𐑟 𐑣𐑻 𐑣𐑶𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕, 𐑩𐑯 ·𐑩𐑥𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑼 𐑦𐑟 𐑬𐑑𐑢𐑼𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑢𐑦𐑖𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑣𐑻 𐑑𐑮𐑲-𐑢𐑻𐑒𐑕. 𐑖𐑰 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑞 𐑒𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑾𐑕 𐑩𐑯𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑝 𐑞 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑪𐑤𐑦𐑛 𐑥𐑱𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑼𐑦 𐑡𐑶𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑴𐑒 𐑯 𐑣𐑧𐑥𐑐 𐑦𐑯 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑑𐑿𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑰𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑖𐑦𐑐. 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑓 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑴𐑐𐑩𐑯 𐑓𐑰𐑤𐑛 𐑩 𐑚𐑮𐑦𐑒-𐑒𐑦𐑤𐑯 𐑢𐑻 𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑕𐑐𐑹𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑑 𐑣𐑻 𐑐𐑤𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑕.

𐑞 𐑑𐑮𐑲-𐑢𐑻𐑒𐑕 𐑸 𐑐𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑢𐑰𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑹𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑯 𐑥𐑱𐑯𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑, 𐑞 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑮𐑵𐑥𐑦 𐑐𐑸𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑒. 𐑞 𐑑𐑦𐑥𐑚𐑼𐑟 𐑚𐑦𐑯𐑰𐑔 𐑸 𐑝 𐑩 𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑽 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑧𐑙𐑔, 𐑓𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑑 𐑕𐑩𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑑 𐑝 𐑩𐑯 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑪𐑤𐑦𐑛 𐑥𐑨𐑕 𐑝 𐑚𐑮𐑦𐑒 𐑯 𐑥𐑹𐑑𐑼, 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑑𐑧𐑯 𐑓𐑰𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑱𐑑 𐑕𐑒𐑢𐑺, 𐑯 𐑓𐑲𐑝 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑲𐑑. 𐑞 𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑛𐑳𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑒, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞 𐑥𐑱𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑼𐑦 𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑻𐑥𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑛 𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑻𐑓𐑦𐑕 𐑚𐑲 𐑐𐑪𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑩𐑕 𐑯𐑰𐑟 𐑝 𐑲𐑼𐑯 𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑑 𐑪𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑕𐑲𐑛𐑟, 𐑯 𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑵𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑑 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑑 𐑞 𐑑𐑦𐑥𐑚𐑼𐑟. 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑤𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑕 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑱𐑕𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑢𐑫𐑛, 𐑯 𐑨𐑑 𐑑𐑪𐑐 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑰𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑳𐑝𐑼𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑩 𐑤𐑸𐑡, 𐑕𐑤𐑴𐑐𐑦𐑙, 𐑚𐑨𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑗𐑢𐑱. 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑵𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑣𐑨𐑗 𐑢𐑰 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑴𐑟 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑑𐑮𐑲-𐑐𐑪𐑑𐑕, 𐑑𐑵 𐑦𐑯 𐑯𐑳𐑥𐑚𐑼, 𐑯 𐑰𐑗 𐑝 𐑕𐑧𐑝𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑚𐑨𐑮𐑩𐑤𐑟' 𐑒𐑩𐑐𐑨𐑕𐑦𐑑𐑦. 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑿𐑕, 𐑞𐑱 𐑸 𐑒𐑧𐑐𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑸𐑒𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑤𐑰𐑯. 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑞𐑱 𐑸 𐑐𐑪𐑤𐑦𐑖𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑕𐑴𐑐𐑕𐑑𐑴𐑯 𐑯 𐑕𐑨𐑯𐑛, 𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑞𐑱 𐑖𐑲𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑦𐑯 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑕𐑦𐑤𐑝𐑼 𐑐𐑳𐑯𐑗-𐑚𐑴𐑤𐑟. 𐑛𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑯𐑲𐑑-𐑢𐑪𐑗𐑩𐑟 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑕𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑼𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑒𐑮𐑷𐑤 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑯 𐑒𐑶𐑤 𐑞𐑧𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑝𐑟 𐑩𐑢𐑱 𐑞𐑺 𐑓 𐑩 𐑯𐑨𐑐. 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑶𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑐𐑪𐑤𐑦𐑖𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑧𐑥—𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑰𐑗 𐑐𐑪𐑑, 𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑕𐑲𐑛—𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑓𐑦𐑛𐑧𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑤 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑿𐑯𐑦𐑒𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑸 𐑒𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑛 𐑪𐑯, 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑞 𐑲𐑼𐑯 𐑤𐑦𐑐𐑕. 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑩 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕 𐑷𐑤𐑕𐑴 𐑓 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑥𐑨𐑔𐑩𐑥𐑨𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑥𐑧𐑛𐑦𐑑𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯. 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑤𐑧𐑓𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑑𐑮𐑲-𐑐𐑪𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑕𐑴𐑐𐑕𐑑𐑴𐑯 𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑡𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑻𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑥𐑰, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑲 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑒 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑸𐑒𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑓𐑨𐑒𐑑, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑡𐑦𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑑𐑮𐑦 𐑷𐑤 𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦𐑟 𐑜𐑤𐑲𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑞 𐑕𐑲𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑶𐑛, 𐑥𐑲 𐑕𐑴𐑐𐑕𐑑𐑴𐑯 𐑓 𐑦𐑜𐑟𐑭𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑤, 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑐𐑶𐑯𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑲𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑑𐑲𐑥.

𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑵𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑓𐑲𐑼-𐑚𐑹𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑓𐑮𐑳𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑑𐑮𐑲-𐑢𐑻𐑒𐑕, 𐑞 𐑚𐑺 𐑥𐑱𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑼𐑦 𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑴𐑟𐑛, 𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑑𐑵 𐑲𐑼𐑯 𐑥𐑬𐑞𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑓𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑕𐑩𐑟, 𐑛𐑦𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑯𐑰𐑔 𐑞 𐑐𐑪𐑑𐑕. 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑥𐑬𐑞𐑟 𐑸 𐑓𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑧𐑝𐑦 𐑛𐑹𐑟 𐑝 𐑲𐑼𐑯. 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑕 𐑣𐑰𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑓𐑲𐑼 𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑝𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑿𐑯𐑦𐑒𐑱𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑑𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑑 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑒, 𐑚𐑲 𐑥𐑰𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑩 𐑖𐑨𐑤𐑴 𐑮𐑧𐑟𐑼𐑝𐑢𐑸 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑲𐑼 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑤𐑴𐑟𐑛 𐑕𐑻𐑓𐑦𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑻𐑒𐑕. 𐑚𐑲 𐑩 𐑑𐑳𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑮𐑽, 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑮𐑧𐑟𐑼𐑝𐑢𐑸 𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑧𐑐𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑤𐑧𐑯𐑦𐑖𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼 𐑨𐑟 𐑓𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑝𐑨𐑐𐑼𐑱𐑑𐑕. 𐑞𐑺 𐑸 𐑯𐑴 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑗𐑦𐑥𐑯𐑦𐑟; 𐑞𐑱 𐑴𐑐𐑩𐑯 𐑛𐑦𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑮𐑽 𐑢𐑷𐑤. 𐑯 𐑣𐑽 𐑤𐑧𐑑 𐑳𐑕 𐑜𐑴 𐑚𐑨𐑒 𐑓 𐑩 𐑥𐑴𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑.

𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑯𐑲𐑯 𐑴'𐑒𐑤𐑪𐑒 𐑨𐑑 𐑯𐑲𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛'𐑟 𐑑𐑮𐑲-𐑢𐑻𐑒𐑕 𐑢𐑻 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑪𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑝𐑶𐑦𐑡. 𐑦𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑪𐑙𐑛 𐑑 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚 𐑑 𐑴𐑝𐑼𐑕𐑰 𐑞 𐑚𐑦𐑟𐑯𐑩𐑕.

“𐑷𐑤 𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑦 𐑞𐑺? 𐑪𐑓 𐑣𐑨𐑗, 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑑 𐑣𐑻. 𐑿 𐑒𐑫𐑒, 𐑓𐑲𐑼 𐑞 𐑢𐑻𐑒𐑕.” 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩𐑯 𐑰𐑟𐑦 𐑔𐑦𐑙, 𐑓 𐑞 𐑒𐑸𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑼 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑔𐑮𐑳𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑖𐑱𐑝𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑓𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑕 𐑔𐑮𐑵𐑬𐑑 𐑞 𐑐𐑨𐑕𐑦𐑡. 𐑣𐑽 𐑚𐑰 𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑝𐑶𐑦𐑡 𐑞 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑓𐑲𐑼 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑑𐑮𐑲-𐑢𐑻𐑒𐑕 𐑣𐑨𐑕 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑓𐑧𐑛 𐑓 𐑩 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑢𐑫𐑛. 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑯𐑴 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑦𐑟 𐑿𐑟𐑛, 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑧𐑐𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑩 𐑥𐑰𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑒 𐑦𐑜𐑯𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑐𐑩𐑤 𐑓𐑿𐑩𐑤. 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑢𐑻𐑛, 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑛 𐑬𐑑, 𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑐, 𐑖𐑮𐑦𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑚𐑤𐑳𐑚𐑼, 𐑯𐑬 𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑛 𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑨𐑐𐑕 𐑹 𐑓𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑼𐑟, 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑱𐑯𐑟 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑼𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑳𐑙𐑒𐑗𐑵𐑩𐑕 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑐𐑼𐑑𐑦𐑟. 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑓𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑼𐑟 𐑓𐑰𐑛 𐑞 𐑓𐑤𐑱𐑥𐑟. 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑐𐑤𐑧𐑔𐑹𐑦𐑒 𐑚𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑸𐑑𐑼, 𐑹 𐑩 𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓-𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑿𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑔𐑮𐑴𐑐, 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑕 𐑦𐑜𐑯𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑛, 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑕𐑩𐑐𐑤𐑲𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑴𐑯 𐑓𐑿𐑩𐑤 𐑯 𐑚𐑻𐑯𐑟 𐑚𐑲 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑴𐑯 𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦. 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑿𐑥𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑴𐑯 𐑕𐑥𐑴𐑒! 𐑓 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑥𐑴𐑒 𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑣𐑱𐑤, 𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑣𐑱𐑤 𐑦𐑑 𐑿 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑, 𐑯 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑞𐑨𐑑, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑿 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑤𐑦𐑝 𐑦𐑯 𐑦𐑑 𐑓 𐑞 𐑑𐑲𐑥. 𐑦𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑩𐑯 𐑳𐑯𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤, 𐑢𐑲𐑤𐑛, ·𐑣𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑵 𐑴𐑛𐑼 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑦𐑑, 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑨𐑟 𐑥𐑱 𐑤𐑻𐑒 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑝𐑦𐑕𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑝 𐑓𐑿𐑯𐑽𐑾𐑤 𐑐𐑲𐑼𐑟. 𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑥𐑧𐑤𐑟 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑞 𐑤𐑧𐑓𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑞 𐑛𐑱 𐑝 𐑡𐑳𐑡𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑; 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑩𐑯 𐑸𐑜𐑿𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑓 𐑞 𐑐𐑦𐑑.

𐑚𐑲 𐑥𐑦𐑛𐑯𐑲𐑑 𐑞 𐑢𐑻𐑒𐑕 𐑢𐑻 𐑦𐑯 𐑓𐑫𐑤 𐑪𐑐𐑼𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯. 𐑢𐑰 𐑢𐑻 𐑒𐑤𐑽 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑒𐑸𐑒𐑩𐑕; 𐑕𐑱𐑤 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑥𐑱𐑛; 𐑞 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑙; 𐑞 𐑢𐑲𐑤𐑛 𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑛𐑸𐑒𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑕. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑛𐑸𐑒𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑤𐑦𐑒𐑑 𐑳𐑐 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑓𐑽𐑕 𐑓𐑤𐑱𐑥𐑟, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑓𐑹𐑒𐑑 𐑓𐑹𐑔 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑕𐑫𐑑𐑦 𐑓𐑤𐑵𐑟, 𐑯 𐑦𐑤𐑵𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑤𐑪𐑓𐑑𐑦 𐑮𐑴𐑐 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑮𐑦𐑜𐑦𐑙, 𐑨𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑓𐑱𐑥𐑛 ·𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑒 𐑓𐑲𐑼. 𐑞 𐑚𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑛𐑮𐑴𐑝 𐑪𐑯, 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑓 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑹𐑕𐑤𐑩𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑝𐑧𐑯𐑡𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑛𐑰𐑛. 𐑕𐑴 𐑞 𐑐𐑦𐑗 𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑤𐑓𐑼-𐑓𐑮𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑮𐑦𐑜𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑤𐑛 ·𐑣𐑲𐑛𐑮𐑲𐑴𐑑, ·𐑒𐑱𐑯𐑼𐑦𐑕, 𐑦𐑖𐑿𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞𐑺 𐑥𐑦𐑛𐑯𐑲𐑑 𐑣𐑸𐑚𐑼𐑟, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑚𐑮𐑷𐑛 𐑖𐑰𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑓𐑤𐑱𐑥 𐑓 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑟, 𐑚𐑹 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑑𐑻𐑒𐑦𐑖 𐑓𐑮𐑦𐑜𐑩𐑑𐑕, 𐑯 𐑓𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑦𐑯 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑓𐑤𐑩𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟.

𐑞 𐑣𐑨𐑗, 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑵𐑝𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑑𐑪𐑐 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑻𐑒𐑕, 𐑯𐑬 𐑩𐑓𐑹𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑩 𐑢𐑲𐑛 𐑣𐑸𐑔 𐑦𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑳𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑞𐑧𐑥. 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑪𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑻 𐑞 ·𐑑𐑸𐑑𐑼𐑾𐑯 𐑖𐑱𐑐𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑐𐑱𐑜𐑩𐑯 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑽𐑟, 𐑷𐑤𐑢𐑱𐑟 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤-𐑖𐑦𐑐'𐑕 𐑕𐑑𐑴𐑒𐑼𐑟. 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑿𐑡 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑙𐑛 𐑐𐑴𐑤𐑟 𐑞𐑱 𐑐𐑦𐑗𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑨𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑝 𐑚𐑤𐑳𐑚𐑼 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑕𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑐𐑪𐑑𐑕, 𐑹 𐑕𐑑𐑻𐑛 𐑳𐑐 𐑞 𐑓𐑲𐑼𐑟 𐑚𐑦𐑯𐑰𐑔, 𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑞 𐑕𐑯𐑱𐑒𐑦 𐑓𐑤𐑱𐑥𐑟 𐑛𐑸𐑑𐑩𐑛, 𐑒𐑻𐑤𐑦𐑙, 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑛𐑹𐑟 𐑑 𐑒𐑨𐑗 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑓𐑰𐑑. 𐑞 𐑕𐑥𐑴𐑒 𐑮𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑩𐑢𐑱 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑤𐑩𐑯 𐑣𐑰𐑐𐑕. 𐑑 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑐𐑦𐑗 𐑝 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑞𐑺 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩 𐑐𐑦𐑗 𐑝 𐑞 𐑚𐑶𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑶𐑤, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑷𐑤 𐑰𐑜𐑼𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑑 𐑤𐑰𐑐 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞𐑺 𐑓𐑱𐑕𐑩𐑟. 𐑪𐑐𐑩𐑟𐑦𐑑 𐑞 𐑥𐑬𐑔 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑻𐑒𐑕, 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑻𐑞𐑼 𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑲𐑛 𐑢𐑫𐑛𐑩𐑯 𐑣𐑸𐑔, 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑤𐑩𐑕. 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑕𐑻𐑝𐑛 𐑓 𐑩 𐑕𐑰-𐑕𐑴𐑓𐑩. 𐑣𐑽 𐑤𐑬𐑯𐑡𐑛 𐑞 𐑢𐑪𐑗, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑳𐑞𐑼𐑢𐑲𐑟 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑶𐑛, 𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑮𐑧𐑛 𐑣𐑰𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑓𐑲𐑼, 𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑞𐑺 𐑲𐑟 𐑓𐑧𐑤𐑑 𐑕𐑒𐑹𐑗𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑟. 𐑞𐑺 𐑑𐑷𐑯𐑦 𐑓𐑰𐑗𐑼𐑟, 𐑯𐑬 𐑷𐑤 𐑚𐑦𐑜𐑮𐑲𐑥𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑕𐑥𐑴𐑒 𐑯 𐑕𐑢𐑧𐑑, 𐑞𐑺 𐑥𐑨𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑽𐑛𐑟, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑸𐑚𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑒 𐑚𐑮𐑦𐑤𐑾𐑯𐑕𐑦 𐑝 𐑞𐑺 𐑑𐑰𐑔, 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑦𐑝𐑰𐑤𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑒𐑩𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑕 𐑦𐑥𐑚𐑤𐑱𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑻𐑒𐑕. 𐑨𐑟 𐑞𐑱 𐑯𐑼𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑑 𐑰𐑗 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑞𐑺 𐑳𐑯𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑦 𐑩𐑛𐑝𐑧𐑯𐑗𐑼𐑟, 𐑞𐑺 𐑑𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑝 𐑑𐑧𐑮𐑼 𐑑𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑻𐑛𐑟 𐑝 𐑥𐑻𐑔; 𐑨𐑟 𐑞𐑺 𐑳𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑤𐑲𐑟𐑛 𐑤𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑓𐑹𐑒𐑑 𐑳𐑐𐑢𐑼𐑛𐑟 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑞𐑧𐑥, 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑞 𐑓𐑤𐑱𐑥𐑟 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑓𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑕; 𐑨𐑟 𐑑 𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑴, 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑓𐑮𐑳𐑯𐑑, 𐑞 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑽𐑟 𐑢𐑲𐑤𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑡𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞𐑺 𐑣𐑿𐑡 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑙𐑛 𐑓𐑹𐑒𐑕 𐑯 𐑛𐑦𐑐𐑼𐑟; 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛 𐑣𐑬𐑤𐑛 𐑪𐑯, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑰 𐑤𐑰𐑐𐑑, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑜𐑮𐑴𐑯𐑛 𐑯 𐑛𐑲𐑝𐑛, 𐑯 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑛𐑓𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑖𐑪𐑑 𐑣𐑻 𐑮𐑧𐑛 𐑣𐑧𐑤 𐑓𐑻𐑞𐑼 𐑯 𐑓𐑻𐑞𐑼 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑒𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑰 𐑯 𐑞 𐑯𐑲𐑑, 𐑯 𐑕𐑒𐑹𐑯𐑓𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑗𐑨𐑥𐑐𐑑 𐑞 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑚𐑴𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑻 𐑥𐑬𐑔, 𐑯 𐑝𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑐𐑨𐑑 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑣𐑻 𐑪𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑕𐑲𐑛𐑟; 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑞 𐑮𐑳𐑖𐑦𐑙 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛, 𐑓𐑮𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑕𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑡𐑩𐑟, 𐑯 𐑤𐑱𐑛𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑓𐑲𐑼, 𐑯 𐑚𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑒𐑹𐑐𐑕, 𐑯 𐑐𐑤𐑳𐑯𐑡𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑒𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑛𐑸𐑒𐑯𐑩𐑕, 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑞 𐑥𐑩𐑑𐑽𐑾𐑤 𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑐𐑸𐑑 𐑝 𐑣𐑻 𐑥𐑪𐑯𐑩𐑥𐑱𐑯𐑦𐑨𐑒 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑭𐑯𐑛𐑼'𐑟 𐑕𐑴𐑤.

𐑕𐑴 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑦𐑑 𐑑 𐑥𐑰, 𐑨𐑟 𐑲 𐑕𐑑𐑫𐑛 𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑻 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑥, 𐑯 𐑓 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑬𐑼𐑟 𐑕𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑜𐑲𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑞 𐑢𐑱 𐑝 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑓𐑲𐑼-𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑰. 𐑮𐑨𐑐𐑑, 𐑓 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑝𐑩𐑤, 𐑦𐑯 𐑛𐑸𐑒𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑥𐑲𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓, 𐑲 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞 𐑚𐑧𐑑𐑼 𐑕𐑷 𐑞 𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑯𐑩𐑕, 𐑞 𐑥𐑨𐑛𐑯𐑩𐑕, 𐑞 𐑜𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑤𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑳𐑞𐑼𐑟. 𐑞 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑿𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑲𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑓𐑰𐑯𐑛 𐑖𐑱𐑐𐑕 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑥𐑰, 𐑒𐑱𐑐𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑭𐑓 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑥𐑴𐑒 𐑯 𐑣𐑭𐑓 𐑦𐑯 𐑓𐑲𐑼, 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑜𐑨𐑑 𐑒𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑛 𐑝𐑦𐑠𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑲 𐑕𐑴𐑤, 𐑕𐑴 𐑕𐑵𐑯 𐑨𐑟 𐑲 𐑚𐑦𐑜𐑨𐑯 𐑑 𐑘𐑰𐑤𐑛 𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑳𐑯𐑩𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑛𐑮𐑬𐑟𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑥𐑰 𐑨𐑑 𐑩 𐑥𐑦𐑛𐑯𐑲𐑑 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑥.

𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑯𐑲𐑑, 𐑦𐑯 𐑐𐑼𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑼, 𐑩 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡 (𐑯 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑕𐑦𐑯𐑕 𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑤𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤) 𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑒𐑻𐑛 𐑑 𐑥𐑰. 𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑩 𐑚𐑮𐑰𐑓 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑤𐑰𐑐, 𐑲 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑣𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑪𐑙. 𐑞 𐑡𐑷-𐑚𐑴𐑯 𐑑𐑦𐑤𐑼 𐑕𐑥𐑴𐑑 𐑥𐑲 𐑕𐑲𐑛, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑤𐑰𐑯𐑛 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑑; 𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑲 𐑽𐑟 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞 𐑤𐑴 𐑣𐑳𐑥 𐑝 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑟, 𐑡𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑜𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑖𐑱𐑒 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛; 𐑲 𐑔𐑷𐑑 𐑥𐑲 𐑲𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑴𐑐𐑩𐑯; 𐑲 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑣𐑭𐑓 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑐𐑫𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑲 𐑓𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑼𐑟 𐑑 𐑞 𐑤𐑦𐑛𐑟 𐑯 𐑥𐑦𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑧𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑓𐑻𐑞𐑼 𐑩𐑐𐑸𐑑. 𐑚𐑳𐑑, 𐑕𐑐𐑲𐑑 𐑝 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑦𐑕, 𐑲 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑕𐑰 𐑯𐑴 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑕 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑥𐑰 𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑽 𐑚𐑲; 𐑞𐑴 𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑩 𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑦𐑯𐑕 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑒𐑸𐑛, 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑛𐑦 𐑚𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑤𐑨𐑥𐑐 𐑦𐑤𐑵𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑱𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑑. 𐑯𐑳𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑥𐑰 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑩 𐑡𐑧𐑑 𐑜𐑤𐑵𐑥, 𐑯𐑬 𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑜𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑲 𐑓𐑤𐑨𐑖𐑩𐑟 𐑝 𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑯𐑩𐑕. 𐑳𐑐𐑼𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑯, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑑𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑕𐑢𐑦𐑓𐑑, 𐑮𐑳𐑖𐑦𐑙 𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑲 𐑕𐑑𐑫𐑛 𐑪𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑴 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑚𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑑 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑣𐑱𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑩𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑨𐑟 𐑮𐑳𐑖𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑷𐑤 𐑣𐑱𐑝𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑩𐑕𐑑𐑻𐑯. 𐑩 𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑒, 𐑚𐑦𐑢𐑦𐑤𐑛𐑼𐑛 𐑓𐑰𐑤𐑦𐑙, 𐑨𐑟 𐑝 𐑛𐑧𐑔, 𐑒𐑱𐑥 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑥𐑰. 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑝𐑳𐑤𐑕𐑦𐑝𐑤𐑦 𐑥𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑜𐑮𐑭𐑕𐑐𐑑 𐑞 𐑑𐑦𐑤𐑼, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑱𐑟𐑦 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑰𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑑𐑦𐑤𐑼 𐑢𐑪𐑟, 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑣𐑬, 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑦𐑯𐑗𐑭𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑱, 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑛. 𐑥𐑲 ·𐑜𐑪𐑛! 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑞 𐑥𐑨𐑑𐑼 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑥𐑰? 𐑔𐑷𐑑 𐑲. 𐑤𐑴! 𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑲 𐑚𐑮𐑰𐑓 𐑕𐑤𐑰𐑐 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑛 𐑥𐑲𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑, 𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑓𐑮𐑳𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐'𐑕 𐑕𐑑𐑻𐑯, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑥𐑲 𐑚𐑨𐑒 𐑑 𐑣𐑻 𐑐𐑮𐑬 𐑯 𐑞 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑕. 𐑦𐑯 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑲 𐑓𐑱𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑨𐑒, 𐑡𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑝𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑞 𐑝𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑤 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑓𐑤𐑲𐑦𐑙 𐑳𐑐 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛, 𐑯 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑚𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑕𐑲𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑻. 𐑣𐑬 𐑜𐑤𐑨𐑛 𐑯 𐑣𐑬 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑞 𐑮𐑦𐑤𐑰𐑓 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑳𐑯𐑯𐑨𐑗𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑣𐑩𐑤𐑵𐑕𐑦𐑯𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑯𐑲𐑑, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑡𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦 𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑮𐑷𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑤𐑰!

𐑤𐑫𐑒 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑑𐑵 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑱𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑓𐑲𐑼, 𐑴 𐑥𐑨𐑯! 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑛𐑮𐑰𐑥 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑥! 𐑑𐑻𐑯 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑞𐑲 𐑚𐑨𐑒 𐑑 𐑞 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑕; 𐑩𐑒𐑕𐑧𐑐𐑑 𐑞 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑑𐑦𐑤𐑼; 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑰𐑝 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑞 𐑸𐑑𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑤 𐑓𐑲𐑼, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑥𐑱𐑒𐑕 𐑷𐑤 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑤𐑫𐑒 𐑜𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑤𐑦. 𐑑-𐑥𐑪𐑮𐑴, 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑯𐑨𐑗𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑳𐑯, 𐑞 𐑕𐑒𐑲𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑚𐑰 𐑚𐑮𐑲𐑑; 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑣𐑵 𐑜𐑤𐑺𐑛 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑛𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑹𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑤𐑱𐑥𐑟, 𐑞 𐑥𐑹𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑖𐑴 𐑦𐑯 𐑓𐑸 𐑳𐑞𐑼, 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑰𐑕𐑑 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑼, 𐑮𐑦𐑤𐑰𐑓; 𐑞 𐑜𐑤𐑹𐑾𐑕, 𐑜𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑩𐑯, 𐑜𐑤𐑨𐑛 𐑕𐑳𐑯, 𐑞 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑑𐑮𐑵 𐑤𐑨𐑥𐑐—𐑷𐑤 𐑳𐑞𐑼𐑟 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑤𐑲𐑼𐑟!

𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼𐑞𐑩𐑤𐑧𐑕 𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑯 𐑣𐑲𐑛𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 ·𐑝𐑼𐑡𐑦𐑯𐑾'𐑟 ·𐑛𐑦𐑟𐑥𐑩𐑤 ·𐑕𐑢𐑪𐑥𐑐, 𐑯𐑹 ·𐑮𐑴𐑥'𐑟 𐑩𐑒𐑻𐑕𐑩𐑛 ·𐑒𐑨𐑥𐑐𐑭𐑯𐑘𐑩, 𐑯𐑹 𐑢𐑲𐑛 ·𐑕𐑩𐑣𐑸𐑩, 𐑯𐑹 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑥𐑦𐑤𐑾𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑥𐑲𐑤𐑟 𐑝 𐑛𐑧𐑟𐑼𐑑𐑕 𐑯 𐑝 𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑓𐑕 𐑚𐑦𐑯𐑰𐑔 𐑞 𐑥𐑵𐑯. 𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑯 𐑣𐑲𐑛𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑞 𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑦𐑟 𐑞 𐑛𐑸𐑒 𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑝 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑻𐑔, 𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑦𐑟 𐑑𐑵 𐑔𐑻𐑛𐑟 𐑝 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑻𐑔. 𐑕𐑴, 𐑞𐑺𐑓𐑹, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑹𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑣𐑵 𐑣𐑨𐑔 𐑥𐑹 𐑝 𐑡𐑶 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑕𐑪𐑮𐑴 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑹𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑑𐑮𐑵—𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑑𐑮𐑵, 𐑹 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑝𐑧𐑤𐑩𐑐𐑑. 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑚𐑫𐑒𐑕 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥. 𐑞 𐑑𐑮𐑵𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑝 𐑷𐑤 𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞 ·𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑝 ·𐑕𐑪𐑮𐑴𐑟, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑑𐑮𐑵𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑝 𐑷𐑤 𐑚𐑫𐑒𐑕 𐑦𐑟 ·𐑕𐑪𐑤𐑩𐑥𐑩𐑯'𐑟, 𐑯 ·𐑧𐑒𐑤𐑰𐑟𐑦𐑨𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑟 𐑞 𐑓𐑲𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑥𐑼𐑛 𐑕𐑑𐑰𐑤 𐑝 𐑢𐑴. “𐑷𐑤 𐑦𐑟 𐑝𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑦.” 𐑷𐑤. 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑦𐑤𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑔 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑜𐑪𐑑 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑝 ·𐑳𐑯𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑗𐑩𐑯 ·𐑕𐑪𐑤𐑩𐑥𐑩𐑯'𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑟𐑛𐑩𐑥 𐑘𐑧𐑑. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑵 𐑛𐑪𐑡𐑩𐑟 𐑣𐑪𐑕𐑐𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑯 𐑡𐑱𐑤𐑟, 𐑯 𐑢𐑷𐑒𐑕 𐑓𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑒𐑮𐑪𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑝𐑘𐑸𐑛𐑟, 𐑯 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑮𐑭𐑞𐑼 𐑑𐑷𐑒 𐑝 𐑪𐑐𐑼𐑩𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑣𐑧𐑤; 𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑟 ·𐑒𐑵𐑐𐑼, ·𐑘𐑳𐑙, ·𐑐𐑨𐑕𐑒𐑭𐑤, ·𐑮𐑵𐑕𐑴, 𐑐𐑫𐑼 𐑛𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑷𐑤 𐑝 𐑕𐑦𐑒 𐑥𐑧𐑯; 𐑯 𐑔𐑮𐑵𐑬𐑑 𐑩 𐑒𐑺-𐑓𐑮𐑰 𐑤𐑲𐑓𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑕𐑢𐑺𐑟 𐑚𐑲 ·𐑮𐑭𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑱 𐑨𐑟 𐑐𐑭𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑲𐑟, 𐑯 𐑞𐑺𐑓𐑹 𐑡𐑪𐑤𐑦;—𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑑 𐑕𐑦𐑑 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑪𐑯 𐑑𐑵𐑥-𐑕𐑑𐑴𐑯𐑟, 𐑯 𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑒 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑯 𐑛𐑨𐑥𐑐 𐑥𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑳𐑯𐑓𐑨𐑞𐑩𐑥𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑕 ·𐑕𐑪𐑤𐑩𐑥𐑩𐑯.

𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 ·𐑕𐑪𐑤𐑩𐑥𐑩𐑯, 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑧𐑟, “𐑞 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑩𐑔 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑱 𐑝 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑖𐑨𐑤 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑱𐑯” (𐑲𐑰, 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑤𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑙) “𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑒𐑪𐑙𐑜𐑮𐑦𐑜𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑛.” 𐑜𐑦𐑝 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑞𐑲𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑳𐑐, 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑑 𐑓𐑲𐑼, 𐑤𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑻𐑑 𐑞𐑰, 𐑛𐑧𐑛𐑩𐑯 𐑞𐑰; 𐑨𐑟 𐑓 𐑞 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑦𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑥𐑰. 𐑞𐑺 𐑦𐑟 𐑩 𐑢𐑦𐑟𐑛𐑩𐑥 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑴; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑦𐑟 𐑩 𐑢𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑨𐑛𐑯𐑩𐑕. 𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑦𐑟 𐑩 ·𐑒𐑨𐑑𐑕𐑒𐑦𐑤 𐑰𐑜𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑕𐑴𐑤𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑩𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑛𐑲𐑝 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑒𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑜𐑹𐑡𐑩𐑟, 𐑯 𐑕𐑹 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯 𐑯 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑦𐑟𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑯𐑦 𐑕𐑐𐑱𐑕𐑩𐑟. 𐑯 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑓 𐑣𐑰 𐑓 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑓𐑤𐑲𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑜𐑹𐑡, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑜𐑹𐑡 𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑥𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑟; 𐑕𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑤𐑴𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑢𐑵𐑐 𐑞 𐑥𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑰𐑜𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑣𐑲𐑼 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑚𐑻𐑛𐑟 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑯, 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑞𐑴 𐑞𐑱 𐑕𐑹.

·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 97. 𐑞 ·𐑤𐑨𐑥𐑐.

𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑿 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛'𐑟 𐑑𐑮𐑲-𐑢𐑻𐑒𐑕 𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛'𐑟 𐑓𐑴𐑒𐑕𐑩𐑤, 𐑢𐑺 𐑞 𐑪𐑓 𐑛𐑿𐑑𐑦 𐑢𐑪𐑗 𐑢𐑻 𐑕𐑤𐑰𐑐𐑦𐑙, 𐑓 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑕𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑩𐑤 𐑥𐑴𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑿 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑔𐑷𐑑 𐑿 𐑢𐑻 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑦𐑤𐑵𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑖𐑮𐑲𐑯 𐑝 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑩𐑯𐑲𐑟𐑛 𐑒𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑯 𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑤𐑼𐑟. 𐑞𐑺 𐑞𐑱 𐑤𐑱 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑨𐑙𐑜𐑿𐑤𐑼 𐑴𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑝𐑷𐑤𐑑𐑕, 𐑰𐑗 𐑥𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑯𐑼 𐑩 𐑗𐑦𐑟𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑥𐑿𐑑𐑯𐑩𐑕; 𐑩 𐑕𐑒𐑹 𐑝 𐑤𐑨𐑥𐑐𐑕 𐑓𐑤𐑨𐑖𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑫𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑲𐑟.

𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑻𐑗𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑥𐑧𐑯, 𐑶𐑤 𐑓 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑼 𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑹 𐑕𐑒𐑺𐑕 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑞 𐑥𐑦𐑤𐑒 𐑝 𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑯𐑟. 𐑑 𐑛𐑮𐑧𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑛𐑸𐑒, 𐑯 𐑰𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑛𐑸𐑒, 𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑥𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑛𐑸𐑒𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑨𐑤𐑩𐑑, 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑿𐑠𐑵𐑩𐑤 𐑤𐑪𐑑. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑥𐑩𐑯, 𐑨𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑰𐑒𐑕 𐑞 𐑓𐑵𐑛 𐑝 𐑤𐑲𐑑, 𐑕𐑴 𐑣𐑰 𐑤𐑦𐑝𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑤𐑲𐑑. 𐑣𐑰 𐑥𐑱𐑒𐑕 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑻𐑔 𐑩𐑯 ·𐑩𐑤𐑨𐑛𐑦𐑯'𐑟 𐑤𐑨𐑥𐑐, 𐑯 𐑤𐑱𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑦𐑑; 𐑕𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑐𐑦𐑗𐑾𐑕𐑑 𐑯𐑲𐑑 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐'𐑕 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑒 𐑣𐑳𐑤 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑣𐑬𐑟𐑩𐑟 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑤𐑵𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯.

𐑕𐑰 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑲𐑼 𐑓𐑮𐑰𐑛𐑩𐑥 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑕 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑓𐑫𐑤 𐑝 𐑤𐑨𐑥𐑐𐑕—𐑪𐑓𐑩𐑯 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑚𐑪𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑯 𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑤𐑟, 𐑞𐑴—𐑑 𐑞 𐑒𐑪𐑐𐑼 𐑒𐑵𐑤𐑼 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑑𐑮𐑲-𐑢𐑻𐑒𐑕, 𐑯 𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑤𐑧𐑯𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑟 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑞𐑺, 𐑨𐑟 𐑥𐑳𐑜𐑟 𐑝 𐑱𐑤 𐑨𐑑 𐑩 𐑝𐑨𐑑. 𐑣𐑰 𐑚𐑻𐑯𐑟, 𐑑𐑵, 𐑞 𐑐𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑝 𐑶𐑤, 𐑦𐑯 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑳𐑯𐑥𐑨𐑯𐑿𐑓𐑨𐑒𐑗𐑼𐑛, 𐑯, 𐑞𐑺𐑓𐑹, 𐑳𐑯𐑝𐑦𐑖𐑦𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑑; 𐑩 𐑓𐑤𐑵𐑦𐑛 𐑳𐑯𐑯𐑴𐑯 𐑑 𐑕𐑴𐑤𐑼, 𐑤𐑵𐑯𐑼, 𐑹 𐑨𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑩𐑤 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑝𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑩𐑖𐑹. 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑢𐑰𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑻𐑤𐑦 𐑜𐑮𐑭𐑕 𐑚𐑳𐑑𐑼 𐑦𐑯 𐑱𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑤. 𐑣𐑰 𐑜𐑴𐑟 𐑯 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑓 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑶𐑤, 𐑕𐑴 𐑨𐑟 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑖𐑫𐑼 𐑝 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑖𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑯 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑿𐑦𐑯𐑯𐑩𐑕, 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑼 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑺𐑦 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑳𐑐 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑴𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑐𐑼 𐑝 𐑜𐑱𐑥.

·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 98. 𐑕𐑑𐑴𐑦𐑙 ·𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑯 ·𐑒𐑤𐑽𐑦𐑙 𐑳𐑐.

𐑷𐑤𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑦 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑮𐑦𐑤𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑣𐑬 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑤𐑩𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑔𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑟 𐑩𐑓𐑸 𐑪𐑓 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑-𐑣𐑧𐑛; 𐑣𐑬 𐑣𐑰 𐑦𐑟 𐑗𐑱𐑕𐑑 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑞 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼𐑦 𐑥𐑫𐑼𐑟, 𐑯 𐑕𐑤𐑷𐑑𐑼𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑝𐑨𐑤𐑦𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑛𐑰𐑐; 𐑣𐑬 𐑣𐑰 𐑦𐑟 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑑𐑴𐑛 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑙𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑯 𐑚𐑦𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑩𐑛; 𐑯 𐑣𐑬 (𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑐𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑞 𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑟𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑑 𐑞 𐑜𐑸𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑞 𐑚𐑦𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑒𐑦𐑤𐑛) 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑐𐑨𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑬𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑟 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑐𐑼𐑑𐑦 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑼; 𐑣𐑬, 𐑦𐑯 𐑛𐑿 𐑑𐑲𐑥, 𐑣𐑰 𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑛𐑧𐑥𐑛 𐑑 𐑞 𐑐𐑪𐑑𐑕, 𐑯, 𐑤𐑲𐑒 ·𐑖𐑨𐑛𐑮𐑨𐑒, ·𐑥𐑰𐑖𐑨𐑒, 𐑯 ·𐑩𐑚𐑧𐑛𐑯𐑦𐑜𐑴, 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥𐑩𐑕𐑧𐑑𐑦, 𐑶𐑤, 𐑯 𐑚𐑴𐑯 𐑐𐑭𐑕 𐑳𐑯𐑕𐑒𐑱𐑞𐑛 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑞 𐑓𐑲𐑼;—𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑯𐑬 𐑦𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑱𐑯𐑟 𐑑 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑒𐑤𐑵𐑛 𐑞 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 𐑝 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑐𐑸𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑚𐑲 𐑮𐑦𐑣𐑻𐑕𐑦𐑙—𐑕𐑦𐑙𐑦𐑙, 𐑦𐑓 𐑲 𐑥𐑱—𐑞 𐑮𐑴𐑥𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑐𐑮𐑴𐑕𐑰𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑪𐑓 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑶𐑤 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑒𐑭𐑕𐑒𐑕 𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛, 𐑢𐑺 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑕 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯 𐑤𐑩𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑔𐑩𐑯 𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑟 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑱𐑑𐑦𐑝 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑓𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑟, 𐑕𐑤𐑲𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑚𐑦𐑯𐑰𐑔 𐑞 𐑕𐑻𐑓𐑦𐑕 𐑨𐑟 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹; 𐑚𐑳𐑑, 𐑩𐑤𐑨𐑕! 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑥𐑹 𐑑 𐑮𐑲𐑟 𐑯 𐑚𐑤𐑴.

𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑢𐑹𐑥, 𐑞 𐑶𐑤, 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑣𐑪𐑑 𐑐𐑳𐑯𐑗, 𐑦𐑟 𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑰𐑝𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑕-𐑚𐑨𐑮𐑩𐑤 𐑒𐑭𐑕𐑒𐑕; 𐑯 𐑢𐑲𐑤, 𐑐𐑼𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑕, 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑦𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑯 𐑮𐑴𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑱 𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑥𐑦𐑛𐑯𐑲𐑑 𐑕𐑰, 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑹𐑥𐑩𐑕 𐑒𐑭𐑕𐑒𐑕 𐑸 𐑕𐑤𐑵𐑛 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑯 𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑴𐑝𐑼, 𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑓 𐑧𐑯𐑛, 𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑐𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑤𐑩𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑒𐑵𐑑 𐑩𐑒𐑮𐑪𐑕 𐑞 𐑕𐑤𐑦𐑐𐑼𐑦 𐑛𐑧𐑒, 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑕𐑴 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑕𐑤𐑲𐑛𐑟, 𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑥𐑨𐑯-𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑒𐑹𐑕; 𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑞 𐑣𐑵𐑐𐑕, 𐑮𐑨𐑐, 𐑮𐑨𐑐, 𐑜𐑴 𐑨𐑟 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑣𐑨𐑥𐑼𐑟 𐑨𐑟 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑐𐑤𐑱 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑥, 𐑓 𐑯𐑬, 𐑧𐑒𐑕 𐑪𐑓𐑦𐑕𐑦𐑴, 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑼 𐑦𐑟 𐑩 𐑒𐑵𐑐𐑼.

𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑧𐑙𐑔, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑞 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑐𐑲𐑯𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑭𐑕𐑒𐑑, 𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑵𐑤, 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑗𐑢𐑱𐑟 𐑸 𐑳𐑯𐑕𐑰𐑤𐑛, 𐑞 𐑚𐑬𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑸 𐑔𐑮𐑴𐑯 𐑴𐑐𐑩𐑯, 𐑯 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑜𐑴 𐑞 𐑒𐑭𐑕𐑒𐑕 𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑓𐑲𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑰. 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑛𐑳𐑯, 𐑞 𐑣𐑨𐑗𐑩𐑟 𐑸 𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕𐑑, 𐑯 𐑣𐑻𐑥𐑧𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑤𐑴𐑟𐑛, 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑒𐑤𐑪𐑟𐑩𐑑 𐑢𐑷𐑤𐑛 𐑳𐑐.

𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑼𐑦, 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑼𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑕 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑸𐑒𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑚𐑦𐑟𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙. 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑛𐑱 𐑞 𐑐𐑤𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑕 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑰𐑥 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑚𐑤𐑳𐑛 𐑯 𐑶𐑤; 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑒𐑮𐑩𐑛 𐑒𐑢𐑹𐑑𐑼-𐑛𐑧𐑒 𐑦𐑯𐑹𐑥𐑩𐑕 𐑥𐑨𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤'𐑟 𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑸 𐑐𐑮𐑴𐑓𐑱𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑲𐑤𐑛; 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑮𐑳𐑕𐑑𐑦 𐑒𐑭𐑕𐑒𐑕 𐑤𐑲 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑, 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑚𐑮𐑵𐑼𐑦 𐑘𐑸𐑛; 𐑞 𐑕𐑥𐑴𐑒 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑑𐑮𐑲-𐑢𐑻𐑒𐑕 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑚𐑦𐑕𐑫𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑚𐑫𐑤𐑢𐑼𐑒𐑕; 𐑞 𐑥𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑯𐑼𐑟 𐑜𐑴 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑕𐑩𐑓𐑿𐑟𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑳𐑙𐑒𐑗𐑵𐑩𐑕𐑯𐑩𐑕; 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑲𐑼 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑟 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑤𐑩𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑔𐑩𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓; 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑪𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑞 𐑛𐑦𐑯 𐑦𐑟 𐑛𐑧𐑓𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑙.

𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑩 𐑛𐑱 𐑹 𐑑𐑵 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼, 𐑿 𐑤𐑫𐑒 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑿, 𐑯 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑒 𐑘𐑹 𐑽𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓-𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑖𐑦𐑐; 𐑯 𐑢𐑻 𐑦𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑓 𐑞 𐑑𐑧𐑤-𐑑𐑱𐑤 𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕 𐑯 𐑑𐑮𐑲-𐑢𐑻𐑒𐑕, 𐑿 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑷𐑤 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑕𐑢𐑺 𐑿 𐑑𐑮𐑪𐑛 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑕𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑥𐑻𐑗𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑝𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑤, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑵𐑐𐑿𐑤𐑩𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑯𐑰𐑑 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑭𐑯𐑛𐑼. 𐑞 𐑳𐑯𐑥𐑨𐑯𐑿𐑓𐑨𐑒𐑗𐑼𐑛 𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 𐑶𐑤 𐑐𐑩𐑟𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑩 𐑕𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑿𐑤𐑼𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑤𐑧𐑯𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑝𐑻𐑗𐑵. 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑦𐑟 𐑞 𐑮𐑰𐑟𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑲 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑒𐑕 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑤𐑫𐑒 𐑕𐑴 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑡𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑞𐑱 𐑒𐑷𐑤 𐑩𐑯 𐑩𐑓𐑺 𐑝 𐑶𐑤. 𐑚𐑦𐑕𐑲𐑛𐑟, 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑨𐑖𐑩𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑚𐑻𐑯𐑛 𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑨𐑐𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑩 𐑐𐑴𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑤𐑲 𐑦𐑟 𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑦 𐑥𐑱𐑛; 𐑯 𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑨𐑛𐑣𐑰𐑕𐑦𐑝𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑚𐑨𐑒 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑱𐑯𐑟 𐑒𐑤𐑦𐑙𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑲𐑛, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑲 𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑦 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑻𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑱𐑑𐑕 𐑦𐑑. 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑜𐑴 𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑡𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑞 𐑚𐑫𐑤𐑢𐑼𐑒𐑕, 𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑚𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼 𐑯 𐑮𐑨𐑜𐑟 𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑹 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑓𐑫𐑤 𐑑𐑲𐑛𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑕. 𐑞 𐑕𐑫𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑮𐑳𐑖𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑤𐑴𐑼 𐑮𐑦𐑜𐑦𐑙. 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑯𐑿𐑥𐑼𐑩𐑕 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑦𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑿𐑕 𐑸 𐑤𐑲𐑒𐑢𐑲𐑟 𐑓𐑱𐑔𐑓𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑤𐑧𐑯𐑟𐑛 𐑯 𐑐𐑫𐑑 𐑩𐑢𐑱. 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑗 𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑳𐑚𐑛 𐑯 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕𐑑 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑑𐑮𐑲-𐑢𐑻𐑒𐑕, 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑰𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑣𐑲𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑐𐑪𐑑𐑕; 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑒𐑭𐑕𐑒 𐑦𐑟 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑕𐑲𐑑; 𐑷𐑤 𐑑𐑨𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑸 𐑒𐑶𐑤𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑳𐑯𐑕𐑰𐑯 𐑯𐑫𐑒𐑕; 𐑯 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑚𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑯 𐑕𐑦𐑥𐑩𐑤𐑑𐑱𐑯𐑾𐑕 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑳𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑦 𐑝 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑲𐑼 𐑖𐑦𐑐'𐑕 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑦, 𐑞 𐑣𐑴𐑤 𐑝 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑖𐑦𐑧𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑕 𐑛𐑿𐑑𐑦 𐑦𐑟 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑒𐑤𐑵𐑛𐑩𐑛, 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑵 𐑞𐑧𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑝𐑟 𐑐𐑮𐑴𐑕𐑰𐑛 𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑴𐑯 𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑵𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟; 𐑖𐑦𐑓𐑑 𐑞𐑧𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑝𐑟 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑑𐑪𐑐 𐑑 𐑑𐑴; 𐑯 𐑓𐑲𐑯𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑖𐑿 𐑑 𐑞 𐑦𐑥𐑨𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑩𐑑 𐑛𐑧𐑒, 𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑖 𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑩𐑜𐑤𐑴, 𐑨𐑟 𐑚𐑮𐑲𐑛𐑜𐑮𐑵𐑥𐑟 𐑯𐑿-𐑤𐑰𐑐𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑬𐑑 𐑞 𐑛𐑱𐑯𐑑𐑾𐑕𐑑 ·𐑣𐑪𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛.

𐑯𐑬, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑦𐑤𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑐, 𐑞𐑱 𐑐𐑱𐑕 𐑞 𐑐𐑤𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑑𐑵𐑟 𐑯 𐑔𐑮𐑰𐑟, 𐑯 𐑣𐑿𐑥𐑼𐑩𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑹𐑕 𐑝 𐑐𐑸𐑤𐑼𐑟, 𐑕𐑴𐑓𐑩𐑟, 𐑒𐑸𐑐𐑩𐑑𐑕, 𐑯 𐑓𐑲𐑯 𐑒𐑱𐑥𐑚𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑕; 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑐𐑴𐑟 𐑑 𐑥𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑒; 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒 𐑝 𐑣𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑨𐑙𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑞 𐑑𐑪𐑐; 𐑪𐑚𐑡𐑧𐑒𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑑 𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑑𐑰 𐑚𐑲 𐑥𐑵𐑯𐑤𐑲𐑑 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑐𐑦𐑨𐑑𐑕𐑩 𐑝 𐑞 𐑓𐑴𐑒𐑕𐑩𐑤. 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑯𐑑 𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑒𐑑 𐑥𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑯𐑼𐑟 𐑝 𐑶𐑤, 𐑯 𐑚𐑴𐑯, 𐑯 𐑚𐑤𐑳𐑚𐑼, 𐑢𐑻 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑖𐑹𐑑 𐑝 𐑷𐑛𐑨𐑕𐑦𐑑𐑦. 𐑞𐑱 𐑯𐑴 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑞 𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑿 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑩𐑤𐑵𐑛 𐑑. 𐑩𐑢𐑱, 𐑯 𐑚𐑮𐑦𐑙 𐑳𐑕 𐑯𐑨𐑐𐑒𐑦𐑯𐑟!

𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑥𐑸𐑒: 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑓𐑑 𐑞𐑺, 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑟, 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑪𐑯 𐑕𐑐𐑲𐑦𐑙 𐑬𐑑 𐑥𐑹 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟, 𐑢𐑦𐑗, 𐑦𐑓 𐑒𐑷𐑑, 𐑦𐑯𐑓𐑨𐑤𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯 𐑕𐑶𐑤 𐑞 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑴𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑓𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑗𐑼, 𐑯 𐑛𐑮𐑪𐑐 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑰𐑕𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑕𐑥𐑷𐑤 𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑕-𐑕𐑐𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑢𐑺. 𐑘𐑧𐑕; 𐑯 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑦𐑟 𐑞 𐑑𐑲𐑥, 𐑢𐑧𐑯, 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑞 𐑕𐑦𐑝𐑽𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑳𐑯𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑳𐑐𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑤𐑱𐑚𐑼𐑟, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑯𐑴 𐑯𐑴 𐑯𐑲𐑑; 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑿𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑓 𐑯𐑲𐑯𐑑𐑦-𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑕 𐑬𐑼𐑟; 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑, 𐑢𐑺 𐑞𐑱 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑕𐑢𐑧𐑤𐑛 𐑞𐑺 𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑕 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑷𐑤 𐑛𐑱 𐑮𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑤𐑲𐑯,—𐑞𐑱 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑐 𐑑 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑒 𐑑 𐑒𐑨𐑮𐑦 𐑝𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑗𐑱𐑯𐑟, 𐑯 𐑣𐑰𐑝 𐑞 𐑣𐑧𐑝𐑦 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑤𐑩𐑕, 𐑯 𐑒𐑳𐑑 𐑯 𐑕𐑤𐑨𐑖, 𐑘𐑱, 𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑕𐑢𐑧𐑑𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑕𐑥𐑴𐑒𐑑 𐑯 𐑚𐑻𐑯𐑛 𐑩𐑯𐑿 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑚𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑓𐑲𐑼𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑧𐑒𐑢𐑩𐑑𐑹𐑾𐑤 𐑕𐑳𐑯 𐑯 𐑞 𐑧𐑒𐑢𐑩𐑑𐑹𐑾𐑤 𐑑𐑮𐑲-𐑢𐑻𐑒𐑕; 𐑢𐑧𐑯, 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑣𐑰𐑤 𐑝 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑦𐑕, 𐑞𐑱 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑓𐑲𐑯𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑻𐑛 𐑞𐑧𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑝𐑟 𐑑 𐑒𐑤𐑧𐑯𐑟 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐, 𐑯 𐑥𐑱𐑒 𐑩 𐑕𐑐𐑪𐑑𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑛𐑺𐑦 𐑮𐑵𐑥 𐑝 𐑦𐑑; 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑦𐑟 𐑞 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑞 𐑐𐑫𐑼 𐑓𐑧𐑤𐑴𐑟, 𐑡𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑳𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑯𐑧𐑒𐑕 𐑝 𐑞𐑺 𐑒𐑤𐑰𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑒𐑕, 𐑸 𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑲 𐑝 “𐑞𐑺 𐑖𐑰 𐑚𐑤𐑴𐑟!” 𐑯 𐑩𐑢𐑱 𐑞𐑱 𐑓𐑤𐑲 𐑑 𐑓𐑲𐑑 𐑩𐑯𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑯 𐑜𐑴 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑞 𐑣𐑴𐑤 𐑢𐑽𐑦 𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯. 𐑴! 𐑥𐑲 𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑟, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑨𐑯-𐑒𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑙! 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑦𐑟 𐑤𐑲𐑓. 𐑓 𐑣𐑸𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑢𐑰 𐑥𐑹𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑚𐑲 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑑𐑶𐑤𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛'𐑟 𐑝𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑳𐑤𐑒 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑕𐑥𐑷𐑤 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑝𐑨𐑤𐑿𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥; 𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑢𐑽𐑦 𐑐𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑕, 𐑒𐑤𐑧𐑯𐑟𐑛 𐑬𐑼𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑝𐑟 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑛𐑦𐑓𐑲𐑤𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕, 𐑯 𐑤𐑻𐑯𐑛 𐑑 𐑤𐑦𐑝 𐑣𐑽 𐑦𐑯 𐑒𐑤𐑰𐑯 𐑑𐑨𐑚𐑼𐑯𐑨𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑴𐑤; 𐑣𐑸𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑟 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑛𐑳𐑯, 𐑢𐑧𐑯—𐑞𐑺 𐑖𐑰 𐑚𐑤𐑴𐑟!—𐑞 𐑜𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑐𐑬𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑳𐑐, 𐑯 𐑩𐑢𐑱 𐑢𐑰 𐑕𐑱𐑤 𐑑 𐑓𐑲𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛, 𐑯 𐑜𐑴 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑘𐑳𐑙 𐑤𐑲𐑓'𐑕 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑮𐑵𐑑𐑰𐑯 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯.

𐑴! 𐑞 𐑥𐑧𐑑𐑩𐑥𐑕𐑲𐑒𐑴𐑕𐑦𐑕! 𐑴! ·𐑐𐑲𐑔𐑨𐑜𐑼𐑩𐑕, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑚𐑮𐑲𐑑 ·𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑕, 𐑑𐑵 𐑔𐑬𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑘𐑽𐑟 𐑩𐑜𐑴, 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑛𐑲, 𐑕𐑴 𐑜𐑫𐑛, 𐑕𐑴 𐑢𐑲𐑟, 𐑕𐑴 𐑥𐑲𐑤𐑛; 𐑲 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞𐑰 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑼𐑵𐑝𐑾𐑯 𐑒𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑝𐑶𐑦𐑡—𐑯, 𐑓𐑵𐑤𐑦𐑖 𐑨𐑟 𐑲 𐑨𐑥, 𐑑𐑷𐑑 𐑞𐑰, 𐑩 𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑯 𐑕𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑤 𐑚𐑶, 𐑣𐑬 𐑑 𐑕𐑐𐑤𐑲𐑕 𐑩 𐑮𐑴𐑐!

·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 99. 𐑞 ·𐑛𐑳𐑚𐑤𐑵𐑯.

𐑺 𐑯𐑬 𐑦𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑮𐑦𐑤𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑣𐑬 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑢𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑑 𐑐𐑱𐑕 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑢𐑹𐑑𐑼-𐑛𐑧𐑒, 𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑮𐑧𐑜𐑿𐑤𐑼 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑟 𐑨𐑑 𐑲𐑞𐑼 𐑤𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑑, 𐑞 𐑚𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑯 𐑥𐑱𐑯𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑥𐑳𐑤𐑑𐑦𐑐𐑤𐑦𐑕𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑝 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑢𐑲𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑯𐑼𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑨𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑣𐑬 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑢𐑷𐑒𐑕, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑐𐑤𐑳𐑯𐑡𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑵𐑛, 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑢𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑑 𐑐𐑷𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑑𐑻𐑯 𐑨𐑑 𐑰𐑗 𐑕𐑐𐑪𐑑, 𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑞𐑺 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑤𐑦 𐑲𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑐𐑼𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑼 𐑪𐑚𐑡𐑧𐑒𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑣𐑦𐑥. 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑷𐑤𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑞 𐑚𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑒𐑩𐑤, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑜𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑕 𐑓𐑭𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑐𐑶𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑯𐑰𐑛𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑕, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑜𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑕 𐑖𐑪𐑑 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑡𐑨𐑝𐑤𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑐𐑶𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑻𐑐𐑩𐑕; 𐑯 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑿𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑷𐑒 𐑣𐑰 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯 𐑐𐑷𐑟𐑛 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑞 𐑥𐑱𐑯𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑, 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑮𐑦𐑝𐑩𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑜𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑕 𐑓𐑭𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑮𐑦𐑝𐑩𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑜𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑒𐑶𐑯 𐑞𐑺, 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑢𐑹 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑨𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑 𐑝 𐑯𐑱𐑤𐑛 𐑓𐑻𐑥𐑯𐑩𐑕, 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑨𐑖𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑲𐑤𐑛 𐑤𐑪𐑙𐑦𐑙, 𐑦𐑓 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑣𐑴𐑐𐑓𐑩𐑤𐑯𐑩𐑕.

𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑥𐑹𐑯𐑦𐑙, 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑐𐑭𐑕 𐑞 𐑛𐑳𐑚𐑤𐑵𐑯, 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑯𐑿𐑤𐑦 𐑩𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡 𐑓𐑦𐑜𐑼𐑟 𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑥𐑐𐑑 𐑪𐑯 𐑦𐑑, 𐑨𐑟 𐑞𐑴 𐑯𐑬 𐑓 𐑞 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑚𐑦𐑜𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑻𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑑 𐑓 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑥𐑪𐑯𐑩𐑥𐑱𐑯𐑦𐑨𐑒 𐑢𐑱 𐑢𐑪𐑑𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑕𐑦𐑜𐑯𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑤𐑻𐑒 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑥. 𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑕𐑦𐑜𐑯𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑤𐑻𐑒𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑟, 𐑧𐑤𐑕 𐑷𐑤 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑸 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑻𐑔, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛 𐑦𐑑𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑩𐑯 𐑧𐑥𐑐𐑑𐑦 𐑕𐑲𐑓𐑼, 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑧𐑐𐑑 𐑑 𐑕𐑧𐑤 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑒𐑸𐑑𐑤𐑴𐑛, 𐑨𐑟 𐑞𐑱 𐑛𐑵 𐑣𐑦𐑤𐑟 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 ·𐑚𐑪𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯, 𐑑 𐑓𐑦𐑤 𐑳𐑐 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑥𐑼𐑨𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑥𐑦𐑤𐑒𐑦 𐑢𐑱.

𐑯𐑬 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑛𐑳𐑚𐑤𐑵𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑝 𐑐𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑩𐑕𐑑, 𐑝𐑻𐑡𐑦𐑯 𐑜𐑴𐑤𐑛, 𐑮𐑱𐑒𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑢𐑺 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑣𐑸𐑑 𐑝 𐑜𐑹𐑡𐑩𐑕 𐑣𐑦𐑤𐑟, 𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑕, 𐑰𐑕𐑑 𐑯 𐑢𐑧𐑕𐑑, 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑜𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑩𐑯 𐑕𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟, 𐑞 𐑣𐑧𐑛-𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼𐑟 𐑝 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑩 ·𐑐𐑨𐑒𐑑𐑴𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑓𐑤𐑴𐑟. 𐑯 𐑞𐑴 𐑯𐑬 𐑯𐑱𐑤𐑛 𐑩𐑥𐑦𐑛𐑕𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑮𐑳𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑲𐑼𐑯 𐑚𐑴𐑤𐑑𐑕 𐑯 𐑞 𐑝𐑻𐑛𐑦𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑕 𐑝 𐑒𐑪𐑐𐑼 𐑕𐑐𐑲𐑒𐑕, 𐑘𐑧𐑑, 𐑳𐑯𐑑𐑳𐑗𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑯 𐑦𐑥𐑨𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑩𐑑 𐑑 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑓𐑬𐑤𐑯𐑩𐑕, 𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑻𐑝𐑛 𐑦𐑑𐑕 ·𐑒𐑰𐑑𐑴 𐑜𐑤𐑴. 𐑯𐑹, 𐑞𐑴 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕𐑑 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙𐑕𐑑 𐑩 𐑮𐑵𐑔𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑒𐑮𐑵 𐑯 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑬𐑼 𐑐𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑮𐑵𐑔𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟, 𐑯 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑞 𐑤𐑦𐑝𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑯𐑲𐑑𐑕 𐑖𐑮𐑬𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑔𐑦𐑒 𐑛𐑸𐑒𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑒𐑳𐑝𐑼 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑐𐑦𐑤𐑓𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑐𐑮𐑴𐑗, 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼𐑞𐑩𐑤𐑧𐑕 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑕𐑳𐑯𐑮𐑲𐑟 𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑞 𐑛𐑳𐑚𐑤𐑵𐑯 𐑢𐑺 𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑯𐑕𐑧𐑑 𐑤𐑧𐑓𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑. 𐑓 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑧𐑑 𐑩𐑐𐑸𐑑 𐑯 𐑕𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑓𐑲𐑛 𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑷-𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑧𐑯𐑛; 𐑯 𐑣𐑬𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑢𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑼 𐑢𐑱𐑟, 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑯 𐑷𐑤, 𐑞 𐑥𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑯𐑼𐑟 𐑮𐑦𐑝𐑽𐑛 𐑦𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑤'𐑟 𐑑𐑨𐑤𐑦𐑟𐑥𐑩𐑯. 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑞𐑱 𐑑𐑷𐑒𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑽𐑦 𐑢𐑪𐑗 𐑚𐑲 𐑯𐑲𐑑, 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑵𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑, 𐑯 𐑢𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑤𐑦𐑝 𐑑 𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑑.

𐑯𐑬 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑯𐑴𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑜𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑩𐑯 𐑒𐑶𐑯𐑟 𐑝 ·𐑕𐑬𐑔 ·𐑩𐑥𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑩 𐑸 𐑨𐑟 𐑥𐑧𐑛𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑯 𐑯 𐑑𐑮𐑪𐑐𐑦𐑒 𐑑𐑴𐑒𐑩𐑯-𐑐𐑰𐑕𐑩𐑟. 𐑣𐑽 𐑐𐑭𐑥𐑟, 𐑨𐑤𐑐𐑨𐑒𐑩𐑟, 𐑯 𐑝𐑪𐑤𐑒𐑱𐑯𐑴𐑟; 𐑕𐑳𐑯'𐑟 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑕 𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑟; 𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑦𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑕, 𐑣𐑹𐑯𐑟-𐑝-𐑐𐑤𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑦, 𐑯 𐑮𐑦𐑗 𐑚𐑨𐑯𐑼𐑟 𐑢𐑱𐑝𐑦𐑙, 𐑸 𐑦𐑯 𐑤𐑳𐑜𐑠𐑫𐑼𐑾𐑯𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑓𐑿𐑠𐑩𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑥𐑐𐑑; 𐑕𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑕 𐑜𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑟 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑮𐑲𐑝 𐑩𐑯 𐑨𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑕𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑣𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑜𐑤𐑹𐑦𐑟, 𐑚𐑲 𐑐𐑭𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑓𐑨𐑯𐑕𐑦 𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑕, 𐑕𐑴 ·𐑕𐑐𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑖𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑴𐑧𐑑𐑦𐑒.

𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑴 𐑗𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑛𐑳𐑚𐑤𐑵𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑢𐑧𐑤𐑔𐑦 𐑦𐑜𐑟𐑭𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑟. 𐑪𐑯 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑚𐑹𐑛𐑼 𐑦𐑑 𐑚𐑹 𐑞 𐑤𐑧𐑑𐑼𐑟, ·𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑳𐑚𐑤𐑦𐑒𐑩 ·𐑛𐑧𐑤 ·𐑧𐑒𐑢𐑩𐑛𐑹: ·𐑒𐑰𐑑𐑴. 𐑕𐑴 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑚𐑮𐑲𐑑 𐑒𐑶𐑯 𐑒𐑱𐑥 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑩 𐑒𐑳𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑦 𐑐𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑥𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛, 𐑯 𐑚𐑦𐑯𐑰𐑔 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑦𐑒𐑢𐑱𐑑𐑼, 𐑯 𐑯𐑱𐑥𐑛 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑦𐑑; 𐑯 𐑦𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑒𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑥𐑦𐑛𐑢𐑱 𐑳𐑐 𐑞 ·𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑰𐑟, 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑳𐑯𐑢𐑱𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑒𐑤𐑲𐑥 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑯𐑴𐑟 𐑯𐑴 𐑷𐑑𐑩𐑥. 𐑟𐑴𐑯𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑤𐑧𐑑𐑼𐑟 𐑿 𐑕𐑷 𐑞 𐑤𐑲𐑒𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑔𐑮𐑰 ·𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑰𐑟' 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑦𐑑𐑕; 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑩 𐑓𐑤𐑱𐑥; 𐑩 𐑑𐑬𐑼 𐑪𐑯 𐑩𐑯𐑳𐑞𐑼; 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑔𐑻𐑛 𐑩 𐑒𐑮𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑒𐑪𐑒; 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑸𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑷𐑤 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩 𐑕𐑧𐑜𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑐𐑸𐑑𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑟𐑴𐑛𐑦𐑨𐑒, 𐑞 𐑕𐑲𐑯𐑟 𐑷𐑤 𐑥𐑸𐑒𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞𐑺 𐑿𐑠𐑵𐑩𐑤 𐑒𐑩𐑚𐑨𐑤𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑕, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑒𐑰𐑕𐑑𐑴𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑯 𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑪𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑤 𐑐𐑶𐑯𐑑 𐑨𐑑 ·𐑤𐑲𐑚𐑮𐑩.

𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑧𐑒𐑢𐑩𐑑𐑹𐑾𐑤 𐑒𐑶𐑯, ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚, 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑳𐑯𐑩𐑚𐑟𐑻𐑝𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑳𐑞𐑼𐑟, 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑬 𐑐𐑷𐑟𐑦𐑙.

“𐑞𐑺'𐑟 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑰𐑜𐑴𐑑𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑯-𐑑𐑪𐑐𐑕 𐑯 𐑑𐑬𐑼𐑟, 𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑜𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑯 𐑤𐑪𐑓𐑑𐑦 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑟; 𐑤𐑫𐑒 𐑣𐑽,—𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑕 𐑨𐑟 𐑐𐑮𐑬𐑛 𐑨𐑟 ·𐑤𐑵𐑕𐑦𐑓𐑼. 𐑞 𐑓𐑻𐑥 𐑑𐑬𐑼, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑟 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚; 𐑞 𐑝𐑪𐑤𐑒𐑱𐑯𐑴, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑟 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚; 𐑞 𐑒𐑼𐑱𐑡𐑩𐑕, 𐑞 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑷𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛, 𐑯 𐑝𐑦𐑒𐑑𐑹𐑾𐑕 𐑓𐑬𐑤, 𐑞𐑨𐑑, 𐑑𐑵, 𐑦𐑟 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚; 𐑷𐑤 𐑸 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚; 𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑜𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞 𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑡 𐑝 𐑞 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑜𐑤𐑴𐑚, 𐑢𐑦𐑗, 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑥𐑩𐑡𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯'𐑟 𐑜𐑤𐑭𐑕, 𐑑 𐑰𐑗 𐑯 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑑𐑻𐑯 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑥𐑦𐑮𐑼𐑟 𐑚𐑨𐑒 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑴𐑯 𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑽𐑾𐑕 𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓. 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑐𐑱𐑯𐑟, 𐑕𐑥𐑷𐑤 𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑟 𐑓 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑣𐑵 𐑭𐑕𐑒 𐑞 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛 𐑑 𐑕𐑪𐑤𐑝 𐑞𐑧𐑥; 𐑦𐑑 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑪𐑤𐑝 𐑦𐑑𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓. 𐑥𐑦𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑕 𐑯𐑬 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑒𐑶𐑯𐑛 𐑕𐑳𐑯 𐑢𐑺𐑟 𐑩 𐑮𐑳𐑛𐑦 𐑓𐑱𐑕; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑕𐑰! 𐑲, 𐑣𐑰 𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑟 𐑞 𐑕𐑲𐑯 𐑝 𐑕𐑑𐑹𐑥𐑟, 𐑞 𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑪𐑒𐑕! 𐑯 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑕 𐑥𐑳𐑯𐑔𐑕 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑰𐑤𐑛 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑩 𐑓𐑹𐑥𐑼 𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑪𐑒𐑕 𐑨𐑑 ·𐑺𐑦𐑟! 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑕𐑑𐑹𐑥 𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑹𐑥! 𐑕𐑴 𐑚𐑰 𐑦𐑑, 𐑞𐑧𐑯. 𐑚𐑹𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑔𐑮𐑴𐑟, '𐑑𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑦𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑤𐑦𐑝 𐑦𐑯 𐑐𐑱𐑯𐑟 𐑯 𐑛𐑲 𐑦𐑯 𐑐𐑨𐑙𐑟! 𐑕𐑴 𐑚𐑰 𐑦𐑑, 𐑞𐑧𐑯! 𐑣𐑽'𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑬𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑓 𐑓 𐑢𐑴 𐑑 𐑢𐑻𐑒 𐑪𐑯. 𐑕𐑴 𐑚𐑰 𐑦𐑑, 𐑞𐑧𐑯.”

“𐑯𐑴 𐑓𐑺𐑦 𐑓𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑼𐑟 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑞 𐑜𐑴𐑤𐑛, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑛𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑤'𐑟 𐑒𐑤𐑷𐑟 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑤𐑧𐑓𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑥𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑞𐑺 𐑕𐑦𐑯𐑕 𐑘𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑛𐑱,” 𐑥𐑻𐑥𐑼𐑛 ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓, 𐑤𐑰𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑞 𐑚𐑫𐑤𐑢𐑼𐑒𐑕. “𐑞 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑟 𐑑 𐑮𐑰𐑛 ·𐑚𐑧𐑤𐑖𐑩𐑟𐑸'𐑟 𐑷𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑮𐑲𐑑𐑦𐑙. 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑥𐑸𐑒𐑑 𐑞 𐑒𐑶𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦. 𐑣𐑰 𐑜𐑴𐑟 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑴; 𐑤𐑧𐑑 𐑥𐑰 𐑮𐑰𐑛. 𐑩 𐑛𐑸𐑒 𐑝𐑨𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑢𐑰𐑯 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑥𐑲𐑑𐑦, 𐑣𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑯-𐑩𐑚𐑲𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑕, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑥 𐑞 ·𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑦, 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑓𐑱𐑯𐑑 𐑻𐑔𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑦𐑥𐑚𐑩𐑤. 𐑕𐑴 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑝𐑱𐑤 𐑝 ·𐑛𐑧𐑔, ·𐑜𐑪𐑛 𐑜𐑻𐑛𐑟 𐑳𐑕 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛; 𐑯 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑷𐑤 𐑬𐑼 𐑜𐑤𐑵𐑥, 𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑯 𐑝 ·𐑮𐑲𐑗𐑩𐑕𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑖𐑲𐑯𐑟 𐑩 𐑚𐑰𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑯 𐑩 𐑣𐑴𐑐. 𐑦𐑓 𐑢𐑰 𐑚𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑬𐑼 𐑲𐑟, 𐑞 𐑛𐑸𐑒 𐑝𐑱𐑤 𐑖𐑴𐑟 𐑣𐑻 𐑥𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑦 𐑕𐑶𐑤; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑓 𐑢𐑰 𐑤𐑦𐑓𐑑 𐑞𐑧𐑥, 𐑞 𐑚𐑮𐑲𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑯 𐑥𐑰𐑑𐑕 𐑬𐑼 𐑜𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑕 𐑣𐑭𐑓 𐑢𐑱, 𐑑 𐑗𐑽. 𐑘𐑧𐑑, 𐑴, 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑯 𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑴 𐑓𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑗𐑼; 𐑯 𐑦𐑓, 𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑦𐑛𐑯𐑲𐑑, 𐑢𐑰 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑓𐑱𐑯 𐑕𐑯𐑨𐑗 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑕𐑢𐑰𐑑 𐑕𐑪𐑤𐑦𐑕 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑢𐑰 𐑜𐑱𐑟 𐑓 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑦𐑯 𐑝𐑱𐑯! 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑒𐑶𐑯 𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑕 𐑢𐑲𐑟𐑤𐑦, 𐑥𐑲𐑤𐑛𐑤𐑦, 𐑑𐑮𐑵𐑤𐑦, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑕𐑨𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑑 𐑥𐑰. 𐑲 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑑, 𐑤𐑧𐑕𐑑 ·𐑑𐑮𐑵𐑔 𐑖𐑱𐑒 𐑥𐑰 𐑓𐑷𐑤𐑕𐑤𐑦.”

“𐑞𐑺 𐑯𐑬'𐑟 𐑞 𐑴𐑤𐑛 ·𐑥𐑴𐑜𐑩𐑤,” 𐑕𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑤𐑩𐑒𐑢𐑲𐑟𐑛 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑑𐑮𐑲-𐑢𐑻𐑒𐑕, “𐑣𐑰'𐑟 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑑𐑢𐑦𐑜𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑑; 𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑜𐑴𐑟 ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥, 𐑯 𐑚𐑴𐑔 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑓𐑱𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑲 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑕𐑱 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑢𐑺 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑦𐑯 𐑯𐑲𐑯 𐑓𐑨𐑞𐑩𐑥𐑟 𐑤𐑪𐑙. 𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑨𐑑 𐑩 𐑐𐑰𐑕 𐑝 𐑜𐑴𐑤𐑛, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑦𐑑 𐑯𐑬 𐑪𐑯 ·𐑯𐑰𐑜𐑮𐑴 ·𐑣𐑦𐑤 𐑹 𐑦𐑯 ·𐑒𐑹𐑤𐑩𐑼'𐑟 ·𐑣𐑫𐑒, 𐑲'𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑤𐑫𐑒 𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑺 𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑑. 𐑣𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑓! 𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑲 𐑐𐑫𐑼, 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑜𐑯𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑩𐑐𐑦𐑯𐑘𐑩𐑯, 𐑲 𐑮𐑦𐑜𐑸𐑛 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑨𐑟 𐑒𐑢𐑽. 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑕𐑰𐑯 𐑛𐑳𐑚𐑤𐑵𐑯𐑟 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑯𐑬 𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑲 𐑝𐑶𐑦𐑡𐑦𐑙𐑟; 𐑘𐑹 𐑛𐑳𐑚𐑤𐑵𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑴𐑤𐑛 ·𐑕𐑐𐑱𐑯, 𐑘𐑹 𐑛𐑳𐑚𐑤𐑵𐑯𐑟 𐑝 ·𐑐𐑼𐑵, 𐑘𐑹 𐑛𐑳𐑚𐑤𐑵𐑯𐑟 𐑝 ·𐑗𐑦𐑤𐑦, 𐑘𐑹 𐑛𐑳𐑚𐑤𐑵𐑯𐑟 𐑝 ·𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑝𐑾, 𐑘𐑹 𐑛𐑳𐑚𐑤𐑵𐑯𐑟 𐑝 ·𐑐𐑴𐑐𐑲𐑩𐑯; 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑐𐑤𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑦 𐑝 𐑜𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑥𐑶𐑛𐑹𐑟 𐑯 𐑐𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑴𐑤𐑟, 𐑯 ·𐑡𐑴𐑟, 𐑯 𐑣𐑭𐑓 ·𐑡𐑴𐑟, 𐑯 𐑒𐑢𐑹𐑑𐑼 ·𐑡𐑴𐑟. 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑞𐑺 𐑚𐑰 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑛𐑳𐑚𐑤𐑵𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑦𐑒𐑢𐑱𐑑𐑼 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑴 𐑒𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑓𐑩𐑤? 𐑚𐑲 ·𐑜𐑪𐑤𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑛𐑩! 𐑤𐑧𐑑 𐑥𐑰 𐑮𐑰𐑛 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑕. 𐑣𐑩𐑤𐑴! 𐑣𐑽'𐑟 𐑕𐑲𐑯𐑟 𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑟 𐑑𐑮𐑵𐑤𐑦! 𐑞𐑨𐑑, 𐑯𐑬, 𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑴𐑤𐑛 ·𐑚𐑬𐑛𐑦𐑗 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 ·𐑦𐑐𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑥𐑦 𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑟 𐑞 𐑟𐑴𐑛𐑦𐑨𐑒, 𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑥𐑲 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑨𐑒 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑴 𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑟 𐑛𐑦𐑑𐑴. 𐑲'𐑤 𐑜𐑧𐑑 𐑞 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑨𐑒 𐑯 𐑨𐑟 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑣𐑻𐑛 𐑛𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑚𐑰 𐑮𐑱𐑟𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 ·𐑛𐑨𐑚𐑩𐑤'𐑟 𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑔𐑥𐑧𐑑𐑦𐑒, 𐑲'𐑤 𐑑𐑮𐑲 𐑥𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑨𐑑 𐑮𐑱𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑥𐑰𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑒𐑢𐑽 𐑒𐑻𐑝𐑦𐑒𐑘𐑵𐑟 𐑣𐑽 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 ·𐑥𐑨𐑕𐑩𐑗𐑵𐑕𐑩𐑑𐑕 𐑒𐑨𐑤𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑼. 𐑣𐑽'𐑟 𐑞 𐑚𐑫𐑒. 𐑤𐑧𐑑'𐑕 𐑕𐑰 𐑯𐑬. 𐑕𐑲𐑯𐑟 𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑟; 𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑯, 𐑣𐑰'𐑟 𐑷𐑤𐑢𐑱𐑟 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 '𐑩𐑥. 𐑣𐑧𐑥, 𐑣𐑧𐑥, 𐑣𐑧𐑥; 𐑣𐑽 𐑞𐑱 𐑸—𐑣𐑽 𐑞𐑱 𐑜𐑴—𐑷𐑤 𐑩𐑤𐑲𐑝:—·𐑺𐑦𐑟, 𐑹 𐑞 ·𐑮𐑨𐑥; ·𐑑𐑹𐑩𐑕, 𐑹 𐑞 ·𐑚𐑫𐑤 𐑯 ·𐑡𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑥𐑦! 𐑣𐑽'𐑟 ·𐑡𐑧𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑲 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓, 𐑹 𐑞 ·𐑑𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑟. 𐑢𐑧𐑤; 𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑯 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑰𐑤𐑟 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 '𐑩𐑥. 𐑲, 𐑣𐑽 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑒𐑶𐑯 𐑣𐑰'𐑟 𐑡𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑒𐑮𐑪𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑔𐑮𐑧𐑖𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑢𐑰𐑯 𐑑𐑵 𐑝 𐑑𐑢𐑧𐑤𐑝 𐑕𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑙-𐑮𐑵𐑥𐑟 𐑷𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑮𐑦𐑙. 𐑚𐑫𐑒! 𐑿 𐑤𐑲 𐑞𐑺; 𐑞 𐑓𐑨𐑒𐑑 𐑦𐑟, 𐑿 𐑚𐑫𐑒𐑕 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑯𐑴 𐑘𐑹 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕𐑩𐑟. 𐑿'𐑤 𐑛𐑵 𐑑 𐑜𐑦𐑝 𐑳𐑕 𐑞 𐑚𐑺 𐑢𐑻𐑛𐑟 𐑯 𐑓𐑨𐑒𐑑𐑕, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑰 𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑦𐑯 𐑑 𐑕𐑩𐑐𐑤𐑲 𐑞 𐑔𐑷𐑑𐑕. 𐑞𐑨𐑑'𐑕 𐑥𐑲 𐑕𐑥𐑷𐑤 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑽𐑾𐑯𐑕, 𐑕𐑴 𐑓𐑸 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 ·𐑥𐑨𐑕𐑩𐑗𐑵𐑕𐑩𐑑𐑕 𐑒𐑨𐑤𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑼, 𐑯 ·𐑚𐑬𐑛𐑦𐑗'𐑩𐑟 𐑯𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑜𐑱𐑑𐑼, 𐑯 ·𐑛𐑨𐑚𐑩𐑤'𐑟 𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑔𐑥𐑧𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑜𐑴. 𐑕𐑲𐑯𐑟 𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑟, 𐑱? 𐑐𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑦𐑓 𐑞𐑺 𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑳𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑲𐑯𐑟, 𐑯 𐑕𐑦𐑜𐑯𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑟! 𐑞𐑺'𐑟 𐑩 𐑒𐑤𐑵 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑢𐑺; 𐑢𐑱𐑑 𐑩 𐑚𐑦𐑑; 𐑣𐑦𐑕𐑑—𐑣𐑸𐑒! 𐑚𐑲 ·𐑡𐑴𐑝, 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑦𐑑! 𐑤𐑫𐑒 𐑿, ·𐑛𐑳𐑚𐑤𐑵𐑯, 𐑘𐑹 𐑟𐑴𐑛𐑦𐑨𐑒 𐑣𐑽 𐑦𐑟 𐑞 𐑤𐑲𐑓 𐑝 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼; 𐑯 𐑯𐑬 𐑲'𐑤 𐑮𐑰𐑛 𐑦𐑑 𐑪𐑓, 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑚𐑫𐑒. 𐑒𐑳𐑥, ·𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑨𐑒! 𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑜𐑦𐑯: 𐑞𐑺'𐑟 ·𐑺𐑦𐑟, 𐑹 𐑞 ·𐑮𐑨𐑥—𐑤𐑧𐑗𐑼𐑩𐑕 𐑛𐑪𐑜, 𐑣𐑰 𐑚𐑦𐑜𐑧𐑑𐑕 𐑳𐑕; 𐑞𐑧𐑯, ·𐑑𐑹𐑩𐑕, 𐑹 𐑞 ·𐑚𐑫𐑤—𐑣𐑰 𐑚𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑕 𐑳𐑕 𐑞 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑔𐑦𐑙; 𐑞𐑧𐑯 ·𐑡𐑧𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑲, 𐑹 𐑞 ·𐑑𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑟—𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑟, ·𐑝𐑻𐑗𐑵 𐑯 ·𐑝𐑲𐑕; 𐑢𐑰 𐑑𐑮𐑲 𐑑 𐑮𐑰𐑗 ·𐑝𐑻𐑗𐑵, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑤𐑴! 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑟 ·𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑕𐑼 𐑞 ·𐑒𐑮𐑨𐑚, 𐑯 𐑛𐑮𐑨𐑜𐑟 𐑳𐑕 𐑚𐑨𐑒; 𐑯 𐑣𐑽, 𐑜𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 ·𐑝𐑻𐑗𐑵, ·𐑤𐑰𐑴, 𐑩 𐑮𐑹𐑦𐑙 ·𐑤𐑲𐑩𐑯, 𐑤𐑲𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑐𐑭𐑔—𐑣𐑰 𐑜𐑦𐑝𐑟 𐑩 𐑓𐑿 𐑓𐑽𐑕 𐑚𐑲𐑑𐑕 𐑯 𐑕𐑻𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑨𐑚𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑷; 𐑢𐑰 𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑱𐑐, 𐑯 𐑣𐑱𐑤 ·𐑝𐑻𐑜𐑴, 𐑞 ·𐑝𐑻𐑡𐑦𐑯! 𐑞𐑨𐑑'𐑕 𐑬𐑼 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑤𐑳𐑝; 𐑢𐑰 𐑥𐑨𐑮𐑦 𐑯 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑦 𐑓 𐑲, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑐𐑪𐑐 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑟 ·𐑤𐑲𐑚𐑮𐑩, 𐑹 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑒𐑱𐑤𐑟—𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑢𐑱𐑛 𐑯 𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑢𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑙; 𐑯 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑢𐑰 𐑸 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑕𐑨𐑛 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑, ·𐑤𐑹𐑛! 𐑣𐑬 𐑢𐑰 𐑕𐑳𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑡𐑳𐑥𐑐, 𐑨𐑟 ·𐑕𐑒𐑹𐑐𐑦𐑴, 𐑹 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑒𐑹𐑐𐑾𐑯, 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑳𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑮𐑽; 𐑢𐑰 𐑸 𐑒𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑢𐑵𐑯𐑛, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑢𐑨𐑙 𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑞 𐑨𐑮𐑴𐑟 𐑷𐑤 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛; ·𐑕𐑨𐑡𐑦𐑑𐑺𐑾𐑕, 𐑹 𐑞 ·𐑸𐑗𐑼, 𐑦𐑟 𐑩𐑥𐑿𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓. 𐑨𐑟 𐑢𐑰 𐑐𐑤𐑳𐑒 𐑬𐑑 𐑞 𐑖𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑕, 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑩𐑕𐑲𐑛! 𐑣𐑽'𐑟 𐑞 𐑚𐑨𐑑𐑼𐑦𐑙-𐑮𐑨𐑥, ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑹𐑯𐑩𐑕, 𐑹 𐑞 ·𐑜𐑴𐑑; 𐑓𐑫𐑤 𐑑𐑦𐑤𐑑, 𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑟 𐑮𐑳𐑖𐑦𐑙, 𐑯 𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑢𐑰 𐑸 𐑑𐑪𐑕𐑑; 𐑢𐑧𐑯 ·𐑩𐑒𐑢𐑺𐑾𐑕, 𐑹 𐑞 ·𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼-𐑚𐑺𐑼, 𐑐𐑹𐑟 𐑬𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑴𐑤 𐑛𐑧𐑤𐑿𐑡 𐑯 𐑛𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑟 𐑳𐑕; 𐑯 𐑑 𐑢𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑳𐑐 𐑢𐑦𐑞 ·𐑐𐑲𐑕𐑰𐑟, 𐑹 𐑞 ·𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑟, 𐑢𐑰 𐑕𐑤𐑰𐑐. 𐑞𐑺'𐑟 𐑩 𐑕𐑻𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑯𐑬, 𐑮𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑲 𐑣𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑯, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑯 𐑜𐑴𐑟 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑦𐑑 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑘𐑽, 𐑯 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑟 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑦𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑩𐑤𐑲𐑝 𐑯 𐑣𐑸𐑑𐑦. 𐑡𐑪𐑤𐑦𐑤𐑦 𐑣𐑰, 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑓𐑑 𐑞𐑺, 𐑢𐑰𐑤𐑟 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑑𐑶𐑤 𐑯 𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑚𐑩𐑤; 𐑯 𐑕𐑴, 𐑱𐑤𐑴 𐑣𐑽, 𐑛𐑳𐑟 𐑡𐑪𐑤𐑦 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚. 𐑴, 𐑡𐑪𐑤𐑦'𐑟 𐑞 𐑢𐑻𐑛 𐑓 𐑲! 𐑩𐑛𐑿, ·𐑛𐑳𐑚𐑤𐑵𐑯! 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑪𐑐; 𐑣𐑽 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑟 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 ·𐑒𐑦𐑙-·𐑐𐑴𐑕𐑑; 𐑛𐑪𐑡 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑞 𐑑𐑮𐑲-𐑢𐑻𐑒𐑕, 𐑯𐑬, 𐑯 𐑤𐑧𐑑'𐑕 𐑣𐑽 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑣𐑰'𐑤 𐑣𐑨𐑓 𐑑 𐑕𐑱. 𐑞𐑺; 𐑣𐑰'𐑟 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑦𐑑; 𐑣𐑰'𐑤 𐑬𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦. 𐑕𐑴, 𐑕𐑴; 𐑣𐑰'𐑟 𐑚𐑦𐑜𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑙.”

“𐑲 𐑕𐑰 𐑯𐑳𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑽, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑩 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑝 𐑜𐑴𐑤𐑛, 𐑯 𐑣𐑵𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑮𐑱𐑟𐑩𐑟 𐑩 𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑪𐑙𐑟 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥. 𐑕𐑴, 𐑢𐑪𐑑'𐑕 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑕𐑑𐑺𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑? 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑻𐑔 𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑰𐑯 𐑛𐑪𐑤𐑼𐑟, 𐑞𐑨𐑑'𐑕 𐑑𐑮𐑵; 𐑯 𐑨𐑑 𐑑𐑵 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑞 𐑕𐑦𐑜𐑸, 𐑞𐑨𐑑'𐑕 𐑯𐑲𐑯 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑛 𐑯 𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑦 𐑕𐑦𐑜𐑸𐑟. 𐑲 𐑢𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑕𐑥𐑴𐑒 𐑛𐑻𐑑𐑦 𐑐𐑲𐑐𐑕 𐑤𐑲𐑒 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑲 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑕𐑦𐑜𐑸𐑟, 𐑯 𐑣𐑽'𐑟 𐑯𐑲𐑯 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑛 𐑯 𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑦 𐑝 𐑞𐑧𐑥; 𐑕𐑴 𐑣𐑽 𐑜𐑴𐑟 ·𐑓𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑒 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑓𐑑 𐑑 𐑕𐑐𐑲 '𐑩𐑥 𐑬𐑑.”

“𐑖𐑨𐑤 𐑲 𐑒𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑲𐑟 𐑹 𐑓𐑵𐑤𐑦𐑖, 𐑯𐑬; 𐑦𐑓 𐑦𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑮𐑾𐑤𐑦 𐑢𐑲𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑩 𐑓𐑵𐑤𐑦𐑖 𐑤𐑫𐑒 𐑑 𐑦𐑑; 𐑘𐑧𐑑, 𐑦𐑓 𐑦𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑮𐑾𐑤𐑦 𐑓𐑵𐑤𐑦𐑖, 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑩 𐑕𐑹𐑑 𐑝 𐑢𐑲𐑟𐑦𐑖 𐑤𐑫𐑒 𐑑 𐑦𐑑. 𐑚𐑳𐑑, 𐑩𐑝𐑭𐑕𐑑; 𐑣𐑽 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑟 𐑬𐑼 𐑴𐑤𐑛 ·𐑥𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑕𐑥𐑩𐑯—𐑞 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑣𐑻𐑕-𐑛𐑮𐑲𐑝𐑼, 𐑣𐑰 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑯, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑟, 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑣𐑰 𐑑𐑫𐑒 𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑰. 𐑣𐑰 𐑤𐑳𐑓𐑕 𐑳𐑐 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑞 𐑛𐑳𐑚𐑤𐑵𐑯; 𐑣𐑩𐑤𐑴, 𐑯 𐑜𐑴𐑟 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑝 𐑞 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑; 𐑢𐑲, 𐑞𐑺'𐑟 𐑩 𐑣𐑹𐑕-𐑖𐑵 𐑯𐑱𐑤𐑛 𐑪𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑲𐑛; 𐑯 𐑯𐑬 𐑣𐑰'𐑟 𐑚𐑨𐑒 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯; 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑛𐑳𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑰𐑯? 𐑣𐑸𐑒! 𐑣𐑰'𐑟 𐑥𐑳𐑑𐑼𐑦𐑙—𐑝𐑶𐑕 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩𐑯 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑢𐑹𐑯-𐑬𐑑 𐑒𐑪𐑓𐑦-𐑥𐑦𐑤. 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑒 𐑽𐑟, 𐑯 𐑤𐑦𐑕𐑩𐑯!”

“𐑦𐑓 𐑞 ·𐑢𐑲𐑑 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑚𐑰 𐑮𐑱𐑟𐑛, 𐑦𐑑 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑥𐑳𐑯𐑔 𐑯 𐑩 𐑛𐑱, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑕𐑲𐑯𐑟. 𐑲'𐑝 𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑕𐑲𐑯𐑟, 𐑯 𐑯𐑴 𐑞𐑺 𐑥𐑸𐑒𐑕; 𐑞𐑱 𐑢𐑻 𐑑𐑷𐑑 𐑥𐑰 𐑑𐑵 𐑕𐑒𐑹 𐑘𐑽𐑟 𐑩𐑜𐑴, 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑦𐑯 ·𐑒𐑴𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑣𐑱𐑜𐑦𐑯. 𐑯𐑬, 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑲𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑚𐑰? 𐑞 𐑣𐑹𐑕-𐑖𐑵 𐑕𐑲𐑯; 𐑓 𐑞𐑺 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟, 𐑮𐑲𐑑 𐑪𐑐𐑩𐑟𐑦𐑑 𐑞 𐑜𐑴𐑤𐑛. 𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑑'𐑕 𐑞 𐑣𐑹𐑕-𐑖𐑵 𐑕𐑲𐑯? 𐑞 𐑤𐑲𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑟 𐑞 𐑣𐑹𐑕-𐑖𐑵 𐑕𐑲𐑯—𐑞 𐑮𐑹𐑦𐑙 𐑯 𐑛𐑦𐑝𐑬𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑤𐑲𐑩𐑯. 𐑖𐑦𐑐, 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑖𐑦𐑐! 𐑥𐑲 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑖𐑱𐑒𐑕 𐑑 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒 𐑝 𐑞𐑰.”

“𐑞𐑺'𐑟 𐑩𐑯𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑮𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑯𐑬; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑑𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑. 𐑷𐑤 𐑕𐑹𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑒𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑝 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛, 𐑿 𐑕𐑰. 𐑛𐑪𐑡 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯! 𐑣𐑽 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑟 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜—𐑷𐑤 𐑑𐑩𐑑𐑵𐑦𐑙—𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑕 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑞 𐑕𐑲𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑟𐑴𐑛𐑦𐑨𐑒 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓. 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑧𐑟 𐑞 ·𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑚𐑩𐑤? 𐑨𐑟 𐑲 𐑤𐑦𐑝 𐑣𐑰'𐑟 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑺𐑦𐑙 𐑯𐑴𐑑𐑕; 𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑔𐑲 𐑚𐑴𐑯; 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑕 𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑯 𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑔𐑲, 𐑹 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑒𐑭𐑓, 𐑹 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑬𐑩𐑤𐑟, 𐑲 𐑕𐑩𐑐𐑴𐑟, 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑯 𐑑𐑷𐑒 ·𐑕𐑻𐑡𐑩𐑯'𐑟 ·𐑩𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑪𐑯𐑩𐑥𐑦 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑨𐑒 𐑒𐑳𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑦. 𐑯 𐑚𐑲 ·𐑡𐑴𐑝, 𐑣𐑰'𐑟 𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑺 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑝𐑦𐑕𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑔𐑲—𐑲 𐑜𐑧𐑕 𐑦𐑑'𐑕 ·𐑕𐑨𐑡𐑦𐑑𐑺𐑾𐑕, 𐑹 𐑞 ·𐑸𐑗𐑼. 𐑯𐑴: 𐑣𐑰 𐑛𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑯𐑴 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑑 𐑥𐑱𐑒 𐑝 𐑞 𐑛𐑳𐑚𐑤𐑵𐑯; 𐑣𐑰 𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑕 𐑦𐑑 𐑓 𐑩𐑯 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑚𐑳𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑪𐑓 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑒𐑦𐑙'𐑟 𐑑𐑮𐑴𐑟𐑼𐑟. 𐑚𐑳𐑑, 𐑩𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯! 𐑣𐑽 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑜𐑴𐑕𐑑-𐑛𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑤, ·𐑓𐑧𐑛𐑩𐑤𐑩; 𐑑𐑱𐑤 𐑒𐑶𐑤𐑛 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑕𐑲𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑿𐑠𐑵𐑩𐑤, 𐑴𐑒𐑩𐑥 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑑𐑴𐑟 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑕 𐑨𐑟 𐑿𐑠𐑵𐑩𐑤. 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑛𐑳𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑱, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑫𐑒 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟? 𐑭, 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑥𐑱𐑒𐑕 𐑩 𐑕𐑲𐑯 𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑲𐑯 𐑯 𐑚𐑬𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓; 𐑞𐑺 𐑦𐑟 𐑩 𐑕𐑳𐑯 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑒𐑶𐑯—𐑓𐑲𐑼 𐑢𐑻𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑼, 𐑛𐑦𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑦𐑑. 𐑣𐑴! 𐑥𐑹 𐑯 𐑥𐑹. 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑱 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑟 ·𐑐𐑦𐑐—𐑐𐑫𐑼 𐑚𐑶! 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑛𐑲𐑛, 𐑹 𐑲; 𐑣𐑰'𐑟 𐑣𐑭𐑓 𐑣𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑑 𐑥𐑰. 𐑣𐑰 𐑑𐑵 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑷𐑤 𐑝 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑻𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑑𐑼𐑟—𐑥𐑲𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑤𐑵𐑛𐑩𐑛—𐑯 𐑤𐑫𐑒 𐑯𐑬, 𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑟 𐑑 𐑮𐑰𐑛, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑳𐑯𐑻𐑔𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑛𐑾𐑑 𐑓𐑱𐑕. 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑩𐑢𐑱 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯 𐑯 𐑣𐑽 𐑣𐑦𐑥. 𐑣𐑸𐑒!”

“𐑲 𐑤𐑫𐑒, 𐑿 𐑤𐑫𐑒, 𐑣𐑰 𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑕; 𐑢𐑰 𐑤𐑫𐑒, 𐑘𐑰 𐑤𐑫𐑒, 𐑞𐑱 𐑤𐑫𐑒.”

“𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑥𐑲 𐑕𐑴𐑤, 𐑣𐑰'𐑟 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑛𐑦𐑦𐑙 ·𐑥𐑳𐑮𐑦'𐑟 ·𐑜𐑮𐑨𐑥𐑼! 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑮𐑵𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑲𐑯𐑛, 𐑐𐑫𐑼 𐑓𐑧𐑤𐑴! 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑑'𐑕 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑧𐑟 𐑯𐑬—𐑣𐑦𐑕𐑑!”

“𐑲 𐑤𐑫𐑒, 𐑿 𐑤𐑫𐑒, 𐑣𐑰 𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑕; 𐑢𐑰 𐑤𐑫𐑒, 𐑘𐑰 𐑤𐑫𐑒, 𐑞𐑱 𐑤𐑫𐑒.”

“𐑢𐑲, 𐑣𐑰'𐑟 𐑜𐑧𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑣𐑸𐑑—𐑣𐑦𐑕𐑑! 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯.”

“𐑲 𐑤𐑫𐑒, 𐑿 𐑤𐑫𐑒, 𐑣𐑰 𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑕; 𐑢𐑰 𐑤𐑫𐑒, 𐑘𐑰 𐑤𐑫𐑒, 𐑞𐑱 𐑤𐑫𐑒.”

“𐑢𐑧𐑤, 𐑞𐑨𐑑'𐑕 𐑓𐑳𐑯𐑦.”

“𐑯 𐑲, 𐑿, 𐑯 𐑣𐑰; 𐑯 𐑢𐑰, 𐑘𐑰, 𐑯 𐑞𐑱, 𐑸 𐑷𐑤 𐑚𐑨𐑑𐑕; 𐑯 𐑲'𐑥 𐑩 𐑒𐑮𐑴, 𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑲 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑩'𐑑𐑪𐑐 𐑝 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑐𐑲𐑯 𐑑𐑮𐑰 𐑣𐑽. 𐑒𐑷! 𐑒𐑷! 𐑒𐑷! 𐑒𐑷! 𐑒𐑷! 𐑒𐑷! 𐑱𐑯𐑑 𐑲 𐑩 𐑒𐑮𐑴? 𐑯 𐑢𐑺'𐑟 𐑞 𐑕𐑒𐑺-𐑒𐑮𐑴? 𐑞𐑺 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟; 𐑑𐑵 𐑚𐑴𐑯𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑒 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑩 𐑐𐑺 𐑝 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑑𐑮𐑴𐑟𐑼𐑟, 𐑯 𐑑𐑵 𐑥𐑹 𐑐𐑴𐑒𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑕𐑤𐑰𐑝𐑟 𐑝 𐑩𐑯 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑡𐑨𐑒𐑩𐑑.”

“𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑦𐑓 𐑣𐑰 𐑥𐑰𐑯𐑟 𐑥𐑰?—𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑦𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑦!—𐑐𐑫𐑼 𐑤𐑨𐑛!—𐑲 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑜𐑴 𐑣𐑨𐑙 𐑥𐑲𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓. 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑢𐑱, 𐑓 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑑, 𐑲'𐑤 𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑑 ·𐑐𐑦𐑐'𐑕 𐑝𐑦𐑕𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑦. 𐑲 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑞 𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑑, 𐑓 𐑞𐑱 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑑𐑕; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑣𐑰'𐑟 𐑑𐑵 𐑒𐑮𐑱𐑟𐑦-𐑢𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑓 𐑥𐑲 𐑕𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑦. 𐑕𐑴, 𐑕𐑴, 𐑲 𐑤𐑰𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑥𐑳𐑑𐑼𐑦𐑙.”

“𐑣𐑽'𐑟 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐'𐑕 𐑯𐑱𐑝𐑩𐑤, 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑛𐑳𐑚𐑤𐑵𐑯 𐑣𐑽, 𐑯 𐑞𐑱 𐑸 𐑷𐑤 𐑪𐑯 𐑓𐑲𐑼 𐑑 𐑳𐑯𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑵 𐑦𐑑. 𐑚𐑳𐑑, 𐑳𐑯𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑵 𐑘𐑹 𐑯𐑱𐑝𐑩𐑤, 𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑑'𐑕 𐑞 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑢𐑩𐑯𐑕? 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯, 𐑦𐑓 𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑟 𐑣𐑽, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑳𐑜𐑤𐑦, 𐑑𐑵, 𐑓 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑷𐑑'𐑕 𐑯𐑱𐑤𐑛 𐑑 𐑞 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑑'𐑕 𐑩 𐑕𐑲𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑜𐑮𐑴 𐑛𐑧𐑕𐑐𐑼𐑩𐑑. 𐑣𐑭, 𐑣𐑭! 𐑴𐑤𐑛 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚! 𐑞 ·𐑢𐑲𐑑 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤; 𐑣𐑰'𐑤 𐑯𐑱𐑤 𐑘𐑰! 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑦𐑟 𐑩 𐑐𐑲𐑯 𐑑𐑮𐑰. 𐑥𐑲 𐑓𐑭𐑞𐑼, 𐑦𐑯 𐑴𐑤𐑛 ·𐑑𐑪𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑦, 𐑒𐑳𐑑 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑩 𐑐𐑲𐑯 𐑑𐑮𐑰 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑕, 𐑯 𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑩 𐑕𐑦𐑤𐑝𐑼 𐑮𐑦𐑙 𐑜𐑮𐑴𐑯 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑦𐑯 𐑦𐑑; 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑛𐑸𐑒𐑦'𐑟 𐑢𐑧𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑮𐑦𐑙. 𐑣𐑬 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑦𐑑 𐑜𐑧𐑑 𐑞𐑺? 𐑯 𐑕𐑴 𐑞𐑱'𐑤 𐑕𐑱 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑮𐑧𐑟𐑼𐑧𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑞𐑱 𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑑 𐑓𐑦𐑖 𐑳𐑐 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑, 𐑯 𐑓𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑩 𐑛𐑳𐑚𐑤𐑵𐑯 𐑤𐑪𐑡𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑦𐑑, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑚𐑧𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑶𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑟 𐑓 𐑞 𐑖𐑨𐑜𐑦 𐑚𐑸𐑒. 𐑴, 𐑞 𐑜𐑴𐑤𐑛! 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑕, 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑕, 𐑜𐑴𐑤𐑛! 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑯 𐑥𐑲𐑟𐑼'𐑤 𐑣𐑹𐑛 𐑘𐑰 𐑕𐑵𐑯! ·𐑙𐑦𐑖! ·𐑙𐑦𐑖! 𐑜𐑪𐑛 𐑜𐑴𐑟 '𐑥𐑪𐑙 𐑞 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛𐑟 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑒𐑚𐑼𐑦𐑦𐑙. 𐑒𐑫𐑒! 𐑣𐑴, 𐑒𐑫𐑒! 𐑯 𐑒𐑫𐑒 𐑳𐑕! 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑦! 𐑣𐑱, 𐑣𐑱, 𐑣𐑱, 𐑣𐑱, 𐑣𐑱, ·𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑦, ·𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑦! 𐑯 𐑜𐑧𐑑 𐑘𐑹 𐑣𐑴-𐑒𐑱𐑒 𐑛𐑳𐑯!”

·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 100. 𐑤𐑧𐑜 𐑯 ·𐑸𐑥.

“𐑖𐑦𐑐, 𐑩𐑣𐑶! 𐑣𐑨𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑢𐑲𐑑 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤?”

𐑕𐑴 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚, 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑕 𐑥𐑹 𐑣𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑖𐑴𐑦𐑙 ·𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑤𐑦𐑖 𐑒𐑳𐑤𐑼𐑟, 𐑚𐑺𐑦𐑙 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑻𐑯. 𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑑 𐑑 𐑥𐑬𐑞, 𐑞 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑶𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑒𐑢𐑹𐑑𐑼-𐑚𐑴𐑑, 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑲𐑝𐑼𐑦 𐑤𐑧𐑜 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑦𐑝𐑰𐑤𐑛 𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑼 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯, 𐑣𐑵 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑒𐑺𐑤𐑩𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑲𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑴𐑯 𐑚𐑴𐑑'𐑕 𐑚𐑬. 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩 𐑛𐑸𐑒𐑤𐑦-𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛, 𐑚𐑻𐑤𐑦, 𐑜𐑫𐑛-𐑯𐑱𐑗𐑼𐑛, 𐑓𐑲𐑯-𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑨𐑯, 𐑝 𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑦 𐑹 𐑞𐑺𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑𐑕, 𐑛𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑕𐑐𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑕 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑳𐑙 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑦𐑯 𐑓𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑵𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑚𐑤𐑵 𐑐𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑑-𐑒𐑤𐑪𐑔; 𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑧𐑥𐑐𐑑𐑦 𐑸𐑥 𐑝 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑡𐑨𐑒𐑩𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑚𐑦𐑣𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑞 𐑚𐑮𐑶𐑛𐑼𐑛 𐑸𐑥 𐑝 𐑩 𐑣𐑵𐑕𐑸'𐑟 𐑕𐑻𐑒𐑴𐑑.

“𐑣𐑨𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑢𐑲𐑑 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤?”

“𐑕𐑰 𐑿 𐑞𐑦𐑕?” 𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑛𐑮𐑷𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑓𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑑, 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑛 𐑳𐑐 𐑩 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑸𐑥 𐑝 𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑚𐑴𐑯, 𐑑𐑻𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑱𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑢𐑫𐑛𐑩𐑯 𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑥𐑨𐑤𐑩𐑑.

“𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑥𐑲 𐑚𐑴𐑑!” 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚, 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑧𐑗𐑵𐑩𐑕𐑤𐑦, 𐑯 𐑑𐑪𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑞 𐑹𐑟 𐑯𐑽 𐑣𐑦𐑥—“𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑑 𐑤𐑴𐑼!”

𐑦𐑯 𐑤𐑧𐑕 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑩 𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑑, 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑 𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑒𐑮𐑭𐑓𐑑, 𐑣𐑰 𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑮𐑵 𐑢𐑻 𐑛𐑮𐑪𐑐𐑑 𐑑 𐑞 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼, 𐑯 𐑢𐑻 𐑕𐑵𐑯 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑙𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑼. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑣𐑽 𐑩 𐑒𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑾𐑕 𐑛𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑒𐑳𐑤𐑑𐑦 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑑𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓. 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑲𐑑𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑥𐑴𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑, ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑓𐑼𐑜𐑪𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑦𐑯𐑕 𐑞 𐑤𐑪𐑕 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑤𐑧𐑜 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑕 𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑐𐑑 𐑪𐑯 𐑚𐑹𐑛 𐑝 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑝𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑤 𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑰 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑴𐑯, 𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑷𐑤𐑢𐑱𐑟 𐑚𐑲 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑡𐑰𐑯𐑾𐑕 𐑯 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑦 𐑥𐑦𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑝𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑽 𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛, 𐑯 𐑩 𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑮𐑦𐑜𐑛 𐑯 𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑝𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑤 𐑨𐑑 𐑩 𐑥𐑴𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑'𐑕 𐑢𐑹𐑯𐑦𐑙. 𐑯𐑬, 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑴 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑰𐑟𐑦 𐑥𐑨𐑑𐑼 𐑓 𐑧𐑯𐑦𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦—𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑧𐑐𐑑 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑣𐑵 𐑸 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑬𐑼𐑤𐑦 𐑿𐑟𐑛 𐑑 𐑦𐑑, 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑥𐑧𐑯—𐑑 𐑒𐑤𐑨𐑥𐑚𐑼 𐑳𐑐 𐑩 𐑖𐑦𐑐'𐑕 𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑩 𐑚𐑴𐑑 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑴𐑐𐑩𐑯 𐑕𐑰; 𐑓 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑕𐑢𐑧𐑤𐑟 𐑯𐑬 𐑤𐑦𐑓𐑑 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑 𐑣𐑲 𐑳𐑐 𐑑𐑩𐑢𐑹𐑛𐑟 𐑞 𐑚𐑫𐑤𐑢𐑼𐑒𐑕, 𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑱𐑯𐑾𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑮𐑪𐑐 𐑦𐑑 𐑣𐑭𐑓 𐑢𐑱 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑑 𐑞 𐑒𐑧𐑤𐑕𐑩𐑯. 𐑕𐑴, 𐑛𐑦𐑐𐑮𐑲𐑝𐑛 𐑝 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑤𐑧𐑜, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑝 𐑒𐑹𐑕 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑷𐑤𐑑𐑩𐑜𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑳𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑐𐑤𐑲𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑒𐑲𐑯𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑧𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑯, ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑯𐑬 𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑨𐑚𐑡𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑦𐑛𐑿𐑕𐑑 𐑑 𐑩 𐑒𐑤𐑳𐑥𐑟𐑦 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯; 𐑣𐑴𐑐𐑤𐑩𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑲𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑳𐑯𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑗𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑣𐑲𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑣𐑸𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑣𐑴𐑐 𐑑 𐑩𐑑𐑱𐑯.

𐑦𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛, 𐑐𐑼𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑕, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑳𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑢𐑹𐑛 𐑕𐑻𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑕 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑧𐑤 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑨𐑙 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑤𐑳𐑒𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑣𐑨𐑐, 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑺𐑾𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑹 𐑦𐑜𐑟𐑨𐑕𐑐𐑼𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚. 𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕, 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑣𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑕𐑲𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑑𐑵 𐑪𐑓𐑦𐑕𐑼𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡 𐑖𐑦𐑐, 𐑤𐑰𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑞 𐑕𐑲𐑛, 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑐𐑻𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑼 𐑤𐑨𐑛𐑼 𐑝 𐑯𐑱𐑤𐑛 𐑒𐑤𐑰𐑑𐑕 𐑞𐑺, 𐑯 𐑕𐑢𐑦𐑙𐑦𐑙 𐑑𐑩𐑢𐑹𐑛𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑩 𐑐𐑺 𐑝 𐑑𐑱𐑕𐑑𐑓𐑩𐑤𐑦-𐑹𐑯𐑩𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑥𐑨𐑯-𐑮𐑴𐑐𐑕; 𐑓 𐑨𐑑 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑞𐑱 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑥 𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑩 𐑢𐑳𐑯-𐑤𐑧𐑜𐑩𐑛 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑑𐑵 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑝 𐑩 𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑩𐑤 𐑑 𐑿𐑟 𐑞𐑺 𐑕𐑰 𐑚𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑟. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑷𐑒𐑢𐑼𐑛𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑩 𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑑, 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑪𐑟 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯, 𐑩𐑚𐑟𐑻𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑨𐑑 𐑩 𐑜𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑕 𐑣𐑬 𐑩𐑓𐑺𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑫𐑛, 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 𐑬𐑑, “𐑲 𐑕𐑰, 𐑲 𐑕𐑰!—𐑩𐑝𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑰𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑺! 𐑡𐑳𐑥𐑐, 𐑚𐑶𐑟, 𐑯 𐑕𐑢𐑦𐑙 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑞 𐑒𐑳𐑑𐑦𐑙-𐑑𐑨𐑒𐑩𐑤.”

𐑨𐑟 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑤𐑳𐑒 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑦𐑑, 𐑞𐑱 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑩 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑙𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑩 𐑛𐑱 𐑹 𐑑𐑵 𐑐𐑮𐑰𐑝𐑾𐑕, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑑𐑨𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑓𐑑, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑥𐑨𐑕𐑦𐑝 𐑒𐑻𐑝𐑛 𐑚𐑤𐑳𐑚𐑼-𐑣𐑫𐑒, 𐑯𐑬 𐑒𐑤𐑰𐑯 𐑯 𐑛𐑮𐑲, 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑩𐑑𐑨𐑗𐑑 𐑑 𐑞 𐑧𐑯𐑛. 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑦 𐑤𐑴𐑼𐑛 𐑑 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚, 𐑣𐑵 𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑕 𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑣𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑑 𐑷𐑤, 𐑕𐑤𐑦𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑪𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑼𐑦 𐑔𐑲 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑒𐑻𐑝 𐑝 𐑞 𐑣𐑫𐑒 (𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑕𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑤𐑵𐑒 𐑝 𐑩𐑯 𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑼, 𐑹 𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑪𐑗 𐑝 𐑩𐑯 𐑨𐑐𐑩𐑤 𐑑𐑮𐑰), 𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑜𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑢𐑻𐑛, 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑓𐑭𐑕𐑑, 𐑯 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑷𐑤𐑕𐑴 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑐𐑑 𐑑 𐑣𐑶𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑴𐑯 𐑢𐑱𐑑, 𐑚𐑲 𐑐𐑫𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛-𐑴𐑝𐑼-𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑮𐑳𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑐𐑸𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑑𐑨𐑒𐑩𐑤. 𐑕𐑵𐑯 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑒𐑺𐑓𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑢𐑳𐑙 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑞 𐑣𐑲 𐑚𐑫𐑤𐑢𐑼𐑒𐑕, 𐑯 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑣𐑧𐑛. 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑲𐑝𐑼𐑦 𐑸𐑥 𐑓𐑮𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑤𐑦 𐑔𐑮𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑓𐑹𐑔 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑧𐑤𐑒𐑩𐑥, 𐑞 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 𐑩𐑛𐑝𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑑, 𐑯 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚, 𐑐𐑫𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑬𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑲𐑝𐑼𐑦 𐑤𐑧𐑜, 𐑯 𐑒𐑮𐑪𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑲𐑝𐑼𐑦 𐑸𐑥 (𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑑𐑵 𐑕𐑹𐑛-𐑓𐑦𐑖 𐑚𐑤𐑱𐑛𐑟) 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 𐑬𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑷𐑤𐑮𐑩𐑕 𐑢𐑱, “𐑲, 𐑲, 𐑣𐑸𐑑𐑦! 𐑤𐑧𐑑 𐑳𐑕 𐑖𐑱𐑒 𐑚𐑴𐑯𐑟 𐑑𐑩𐑜𐑧𐑞𐑼!—𐑩𐑯 𐑸𐑥 𐑯 𐑩 𐑤𐑧𐑜!—𐑩𐑯 𐑸𐑥 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑖𐑮𐑦𐑙𐑒, 𐑛'𐑘𐑰 𐑕𐑰; 𐑯 𐑩 𐑤𐑧𐑜 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑮𐑳𐑯. 𐑢𐑺 𐑛𐑲𐑛'𐑕𐑑 𐑞𐑬 𐑕𐑰 𐑞 ·𐑢𐑲𐑑 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤?—𐑣𐑬 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑩𐑜𐑴?”

“𐑞 ·𐑢𐑲𐑑 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤,” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑞 ·𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑤𐑦𐑖𐑥𐑩𐑯, 𐑐𐑶𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑲𐑝𐑼𐑦 𐑸𐑥 𐑑𐑩𐑢𐑹𐑛𐑟 𐑞 ·𐑰𐑕𐑑, 𐑯 𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑮𐑵𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑲𐑑 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑦𐑑, 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑓 𐑦𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑩 𐑑𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑴𐑐; “𐑞𐑺 𐑲 𐑕𐑷 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑤𐑲𐑯, 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑟𐑩𐑯.”

“𐑯 𐑣𐑰 𐑑𐑫𐑒 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑸𐑥 𐑪𐑓, 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑣𐑰?” 𐑭𐑕𐑒𐑑 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚, 𐑯𐑬 𐑕𐑤𐑲𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯, 𐑯 𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑤𐑦𐑖𐑥𐑩𐑯'𐑟 𐑖𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑼, 𐑨𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑕𐑴.

“𐑲, 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞 𐑒𐑷𐑟 𐑝 𐑦𐑑, 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑰𐑕𐑑; 𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑧𐑜, 𐑑𐑵?”

“𐑕𐑐𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑰 𐑞 𐑘𐑸𐑯,” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚; “𐑣𐑬 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑦𐑑?”

“𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑲 𐑤𐑲𐑓 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑲 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑒𐑮𐑵𐑟𐑛 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑤𐑲𐑯,” 𐑚𐑦𐑜𐑨𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑤𐑦𐑖𐑥𐑩𐑯. “𐑲 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑦𐑜𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑢𐑲𐑑 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑑𐑲𐑥. 𐑢𐑧𐑤, 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑛𐑱 𐑢𐑰 𐑤𐑴𐑼𐑛 𐑓 𐑩 𐑐𐑪𐑛 𐑝 𐑓𐑹 𐑹 𐑓𐑲𐑝 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟, 𐑯 𐑥𐑲 𐑚𐑴𐑑 𐑓𐑭𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑞𐑧𐑥; 𐑩 𐑮𐑧𐑜𐑿𐑤𐑼 𐑕𐑻𐑒𐑩𐑕 𐑣𐑹𐑕 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟, 𐑑𐑵, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑥𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑯 𐑥𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑕𐑴, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑲 𐑚𐑴𐑑'𐑕 𐑒𐑮𐑵 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑥 𐑛𐑦𐑖, 𐑚𐑲 𐑕𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑺 𐑕𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑟 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑬𐑑𐑼 𐑜𐑳𐑯𐑩𐑤. 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑳𐑐 𐑚𐑮𐑰𐑗𐑩𐑟 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑚𐑪𐑑𐑩𐑥 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑰 𐑩 𐑚𐑬𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑥𐑦𐑤𐑒𐑦-𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑯 𐑣𐑳𐑥𐑐, 𐑷𐑤 𐑒𐑮𐑴𐑟' 𐑓𐑰𐑑 𐑯 𐑮𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑟.”

“𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑣𐑰, 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑣𐑰!” 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚, 𐑕𐑳𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑤𐑧𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑬𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑩𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑮𐑧𐑔.

“𐑯 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑯𐑽 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑼𐑛 𐑓𐑦𐑯.”

“𐑲, 𐑲—𐑞𐑱 𐑢𐑻 𐑥𐑲𐑯—𐑥𐑲 𐑲𐑼𐑯𐑟,” 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚, 𐑦𐑜𐑟𐑳𐑤𐑑𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦—“𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑪𐑯!”

“𐑜𐑦𐑝 𐑥𐑰 𐑩 𐑗𐑭𐑯𐑕, 𐑞𐑧𐑯,” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑞 ·𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑤𐑦𐑖𐑥𐑩𐑯, 𐑜𐑫𐑛-𐑣𐑿𐑥𐑼𐑩𐑛𐑤𐑦. “𐑢𐑧𐑤, 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑-𐑜𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑓𐑭𐑞𐑼, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑯 𐑣𐑳𐑥𐑐, 𐑮𐑳𐑯𐑟 𐑷𐑤 𐑱𐑓𐑴𐑥 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑐𐑪𐑛, 𐑯 𐑜𐑴𐑟 𐑑 𐑕𐑯𐑨𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑾𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑲 𐑓𐑭𐑕𐑑-𐑤𐑲𐑯!

“𐑲, 𐑲 𐑕𐑰!—𐑢𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑑 𐑐𐑸𐑑 𐑦𐑑; 𐑓𐑮𐑰 𐑞 𐑓𐑭𐑕𐑑-𐑓𐑦𐑖—𐑩𐑯 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑒—𐑲 𐑯𐑴 𐑣𐑦𐑥.”

“𐑣𐑬 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑦𐑜𐑟𐑨𐑒𐑑𐑤𐑦,” 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑿𐑛 𐑞 𐑢𐑳𐑯-𐑸𐑥𐑛 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑭𐑯𐑛𐑼, “𐑲 𐑛𐑵 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑯𐑴; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑚𐑲𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑤𐑲𐑯, 𐑦𐑑 𐑜𐑪𐑑 𐑓𐑬𐑤 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑑𐑰𐑔, 𐑒𐑷𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑣𐑬; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑰 𐑛𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑯𐑴 𐑦𐑑 𐑞𐑧𐑯; 𐑕𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑢𐑰 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼𐑢𐑼𐑛𐑟 𐑐𐑫𐑤𐑛 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑤𐑲𐑯, 𐑚𐑬𐑯𐑕 𐑢𐑰 𐑒𐑱𐑥 𐑐𐑤𐑳𐑥𐑐 𐑪𐑯 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑳𐑥𐑐! 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑛 𐑝 𐑞 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑢𐑱𐑤'𐑟; 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑪𐑓 𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑢𐑼𐑛, 𐑷𐑤 𐑓𐑤𐑵𐑒𐑦𐑙. 𐑕𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑬 𐑥𐑨𐑑𐑼𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑫𐑛, 𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑩 𐑯𐑴𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟—𐑞 𐑯𐑴𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑯 𐑚𐑦𐑜𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑲 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑕𐑷, 𐑕𐑻, 𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑲 𐑤𐑲𐑓—𐑲 𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑪𐑤𐑝𐑛 𐑑 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑗𐑼 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑕𐑐𐑲𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑚𐑶𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑮𐑱𐑡 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑦𐑯. 𐑯 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑣𐑨𐑐-𐑣𐑨𐑟𐑼𐑛 𐑤𐑲𐑯 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑜𐑧𐑑 𐑤𐑵𐑕, 𐑹 𐑞 𐑑𐑵𐑔 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑑𐑨𐑙𐑜𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑑 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑛𐑮𐑷 (𐑓 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑩 𐑛𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑩 𐑚𐑴𐑑'𐑕 𐑒𐑮𐑵 𐑓 𐑩 𐑐𐑫𐑤 𐑪𐑯 𐑩 𐑢𐑱𐑤-𐑤𐑲𐑯); 𐑕𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑦𐑕, 𐑲 𐑕𐑱, 𐑲 𐑡𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑥𐑲 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑥𐑱𐑑'𐑕 𐑚𐑴𐑑—·𐑥𐑼 ·𐑥𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑑𐑪𐑐'𐑕 𐑣𐑽 (𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑢𐑱, ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯—·𐑥𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑑𐑪𐑐; ·𐑥𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑑𐑪𐑐—𐑞 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯);—𐑨𐑟 𐑲 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑱𐑦𐑙, 𐑲 𐑡𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 ·𐑥𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑑𐑪𐑐'𐑕 𐑚𐑴𐑑, 𐑢𐑦𐑗, 𐑛'𐑘𐑰 𐑕𐑰, 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑜𐑳𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑯 𐑜𐑳𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑥𐑲𐑯, 𐑞𐑧𐑯; 𐑯 𐑕𐑯𐑨𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯, 𐑤𐑧𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑-𐑜𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑓𐑭𐑞𐑼 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑦𐑑. 𐑚𐑳𐑑, ·𐑤𐑹𐑛, 𐑤𐑫𐑒 𐑿, 𐑕𐑻—𐑣𐑸𐑑𐑕 𐑯 𐑕𐑴𐑤𐑟 𐑩𐑤𐑲𐑝, 𐑥𐑨𐑯—𐑞 𐑯𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑, 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑡𐑦𐑓, 𐑲 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑚𐑤𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑨𐑟 𐑩 𐑚𐑨𐑑—𐑚𐑴𐑔 𐑲𐑟 𐑬𐑑—𐑷𐑤 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑪𐑜𐑛 𐑯 ·𐑚𐑰𐑛𐑦𐑱𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑒 𐑓𐑴𐑥—𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤'𐑟 𐑑𐑱𐑤 𐑤𐑵𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑳𐑐 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑦𐑑, 𐑐𐑻𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑼 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑺, 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑥𐑸𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑑𐑰𐑐𐑩𐑤. 𐑯𐑴 𐑿𐑕 𐑕𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑷𐑤, 𐑞𐑧𐑯; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑲 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑜𐑮𐑴𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑦𐑛𐑛𐑱, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑚𐑤𐑲𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑳𐑯, 𐑷𐑤 𐑒𐑮𐑬𐑯-𐑡𐑵𐑩𐑤𐑟; 𐑨𐑟 𐑲 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑜𐑮𐑴𐑐𐑦𐑙, 𐑲 𐑕𐑱, 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑞 𐑕𐑧𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑲𐑼𐑯, 𐑑 𐑑𐑪𐑕 𐑦𐑑 𐑴𐑝𐑼𐑚𐑹𐑛—𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑟 𐑞 𐑑𐑱𐑤 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 ·𐑤𐑰𐑥𐑩 𐑑𐑬𐑼, 𐑒𐑳𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑲 𐑚𐑴𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑑𐑵, 𐑤𐑰𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑰𐑗 𐑣𐑭𐑓 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑐𐑤𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑟; 𐑯, 𐑓𐑤𐑵𐑒𐑕 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑, 𐑞 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑣𐑳𐑥𐑐 𐑚𐑨𐑒𐑑 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑞 𐑮𐑧𐑒, 𐑨𐑟 𐑞𐑴 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑷𐑤 𐑗𐑦𐑐𐑕. 𐑢𐑰 𐑷𐑤 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑒 𐑬𐑑. 𐑑 𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑱𐑐 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑑𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑓𐑤𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙𐑟, 𐑲 𐑕𐑰𐑟𐑛 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑝 𐑥𐑲 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯-𐑐𐑴𐑤 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑯 𐑓 𐑩 𐑥𐑴𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑒𐑤𐑳𐑙 𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑕𐑳𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑦𐑖. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑩 𐑒𐑴𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑰 𐑛𐑨𐑖𐑑 𐑥𐑰 𐑪𐑓, 𐑯 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑, 𐑞 𐑓𐑦𐑖, 𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑛𐑸𐑑 𐑓𐑹𐑢𐑼𐑛𐑟, 𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑓𐑤𐑨𐑖; 𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑸𐑚 𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑒𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑧𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑲𐑼𐑯 𐑑𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑯𐑽 𐑥𐑰 𐑒𐑷𐑑 𐑥𐑰 𐑣𐑽” (𐑒𐑤𐑨𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑡𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑴 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑖𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑼); “𐑘𐑧𐑕, 𐑒𐑷𐑑 𐑥𐑰 𐑡𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑽, 𐑲 𐑕𐑱, 𐑯 𐑚𐑹 𐑥𐑰 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑑 ·𐑣𐑧𐑤'𐑟 𐑓𐑤𐑱𐑥𐑟, 𐑲 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑦𐑙; 𐑢𐑧𐑯, 𐑢𐑧𐑯, 𐑷𐑤 𐑝 𐑩 𐑕𐑳𐑛𐑩𐑯, 𐑔𐑨𐑙𐑒 𐑞 𐑜𐑫𐑛 ·𐑜𐑪𐑛, 𐑞 𐑚𐑸𐑚 𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑑 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑢𐑱 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑞 𐑓𐑤𐑧𐑖—𐑒𐑤𐑽 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑞 𐑣𐑴𐑤 𐑤𐑧𐑙𐑔 𐑝 𐑥𐑲 𐑸𐑥—𐑒𐑱𐑥 𐑬𐑑 𐑯𐑲 𐑥𐑲 𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑑, 𐑯 𐑳𐑐 𐑲 𐑓𐑤𐑴𐑑𐑩𐑛;—𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑑𐑧𐑤 𐑿 𐑞 𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑑 (𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑢𐑱, 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯—·𐑛𐑼 ·𐑚𐑳𐑙𐑼, 𐑖𐑦𐑐'𐑕 𐑕𐑻𐑡𐑩𐑯: 𐑚𐑳𐑙𐑼, 𐑥𐑲 𐑤𐑨𐑛,—𐑞 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯). 𐑯𐑬, ·𐑚𐑳𐑙𐑼 𐑚𐑶, 𐑕𐑐𐑦𐑯 𐑘𐑹 𐑐𐑸𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑘𐑸𐑯.”

𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑓𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑞𐑳𐑕 𐑓𐑩𐑥𐑦𐑤𐑽𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑶𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑬𐑑, 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑯𐑽 𐑞𐑧𐑥, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑯𐑳𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑐𐑩𐑕𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑒 𐑝𐑦𐑟𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤, 𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑯𐑴𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑨𐑙𐑒 𐑪𐑯 𐑚𐑹𐑛. 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑱𐑕 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑰𐑛𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑕𐑴𐑚𐑼 𐑢𐑳𐑯; 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑛𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑓𐑱𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑤𐑵 𐑢𐑫𐑤𐑩𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑒 𐑹 𐑖𐑻𐑑, 𐑯 𐑐𐑨𐑗𐑑 𐑑𐑮𐑴𐑟𐑼𐑟; 𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑞𐑳𐑕 𐑓𐑸 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑛𐑦𐑝𐑲𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑩𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑢𐑰𐑯 𐑩 𐑯𐑸𐑤𐑦𐑣𐑕𐑐𐑲𐑒 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛, 𐑯 𐑩 𐑐𐑦𐑤-𐑚𐑪𐑒𐑕 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑳𐑞𐑼, 𐑩𐑒𐑱𐑠𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑜𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑕 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑲𐑝𐑼𐑦 𐑤𐑦𐑥𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑑𐑵 𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑟. 𐑚𐑳𐑑, 𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑵𐑐𐑽𐑽'𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑩𐑛𐑳𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑑 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚, 𐑣𐑰 𐑐𐑩𐑤𐑲𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑬𐑛, 𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑑𐑢𐑱 𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑪𐑯 𐑑 𐑛𐑵 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯'𐑟 𐑚𐑦𐑛𐑦𐑙.

“𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩 𐑖𐑪𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑨𐑛 𐑢𐑵𐑯𐑛,” 𐑚𐑦𐑜𐑨𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤-𐑕𐑻𐑡𐑩𐑯; “𐑯, 𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑲 𐑩𐑛𐑝𐑲𐑕, ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 ·𐑚𐑵𐑥𐑼 𐑣𐑽, 𐑕𐑑𐑫𐑛 𐑬𐑼 𐑴𐑤𐑛 ·𐑕𐑨𐑥𐑦—”

“·𐑕𐑨𐑥𐑿𐑩𐑤 ·𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑸𐑚𐑦 𐑦𐑟 𐑞 𐑯𐑱𐑥 𐑝 𐑥𐑲 𐑖𐑦𐑐,” 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑳𐑐𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑞 𐑢𐑳𐑯-𐑸𐑥𐑛 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯, 𐑩𐑛𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑦𐑙 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚; “𐑜𐑴 𐑪𐑯, 𐑚𐑶.”

“𐑕𐑑𐑫𐑛 𐑬𐑼 𐑴𐑤𐑛 ·𐑕𐑨𐑥𐑦 𐑪𐑓 𐑑 𐑞 𐑯𐑹𐑔𐑢𐑼𐑛, 𐑑 𐑜𐑧𐑑 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑚𐑤𐑱𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑪𐑑 𐑢𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑞𐑺 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑤𐑲𐑯. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑴 𐑿𐑕—𐑲 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑷𐑤 𐑲 𐑒𐑫𐑛; 𐑕𐑨𐑑 𐑳𐑐 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑯𐑲𐑑𐑕; 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑕𐑦𐑝𐑽 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑥𐑨𐑑𐑼 𐑝 𐑛𐑲𐑩𐑑—”

“𐑴, 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑕𐑦𐑝𐑽!” 𐑗𐑲𐑥𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑐𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓; 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑷𐑤𐑑𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑝𐑶𐑕, “𐑛𐑮𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑪𐑑 𐑮𐑳𐑥 𐑑𐑪𐑛𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑥𐑰 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑯𐑲𐑑, 𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑫𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑕𐑰 𐑑 𐑐𐑫𐑑 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑡𐑩𐑟; 𐑯 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑰 𐑑 𐑚𐑧𐑛, 𐑣𐑭𐑓 𐑕𐑰𐑟 𐑴𐑝𐑼, 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑴'𐑒𐑤𐑪𐑒 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑥𐑹𐑯𐑦𐑙. 𐑴, 𐑘𐑰 𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑟! 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑨𐑑 𐑳𐑐 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑥𐑰 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑰𐑛, 𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑕𐑦𐑝𐑽 𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑲 𐑛𐑲𐑩𐑑. 𐑴! 𐑩 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑗𐑼, 𐑯 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑛𐑲𐑩𐑑𐑧𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑦𐑝𐑽, 𐑦𐑟 ·𐑛𐑼 ·𐑚𐑳𐑙𐑼. (𐑚𐑳𐑙𐑼, 𐑿 𐑛𐑪𐑜, 𐑤𐑭𐑓 𐑬𐑑! 𐑢𐑲 𐑛𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑘𐑰? 𐑿 𐑯𐑴 𐑿'𐑼 𐑩 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑕 𐑡𐑪𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑭𐑕𐑒𐑩𐑤.) 𐑚𐑳𐑑, 𐑣𐑰𐑝 𐑩𐑣𐑧𐑛, 𐑚𐑶, 𐑲'𐑛 𐑮𐑭𐑞𐑼 𐑚𐑰 𐑒𐑦𐑤𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑿 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑒𐑧𐑐𐑑 𐑩𐑤𐑲𐑝 𐑚𐑲 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑥𐑨𐑯.”

“𐑥𐑲 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯, 𐑿 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑺 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑐𐑼𐑕𐑰𐑝𐑛, 𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑕𐑻”—𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑞 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑼𐑑𐑻𐑚𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑜𐑪𐑛𐑤𐑦-𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑦𐑙 ·𐑚𐑳𐑙𐑼, 𐑕𐑤𐑲𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑬𐑦𐑙 𐑑 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚—“𐑦𐑟 𐑨𐑐𐑑 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑓𐑩𐑕𐑰𐑖𐑩𐑕 𐑨𐑑 𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟; 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑐𐑦𐑯𐑟 𐑳𐑕 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑒𐑤𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑹𐑑. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑲 𐑥𐑱 𐑨𐑟 𐑢𐑧𐑤 𐑕𐑱—𐑧𐑯 𐑐𐑭𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑑, 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 ·𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑯𐑗 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑸𐑒—𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑲 𐑥𐑲𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓—𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑑 𐑕𐑱, ·𐑡𐑨𐑒 ·𐑚𐑳𐑙𐑼, 𐑤𐑱𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑮𐑧𐑝𐑼𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑒𐑤𐑻𐑡𐑦—𐑨𐑥 𐑩 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑑 𐑑𐑴𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑨𐑚𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑥𐑨𐑯; 𐑲 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑛𐑮𐑦𐑙𐑒—”

“𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼!” 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 𐑞 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯; “𐑣𐑰 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑛𐑮𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑕 𐑦𐑑; 𐑦𐑑'𐑕 𐑩 𐑕𐑹𐑑 𐑝 𐑓𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥; 𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑖 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼 𐑔𐑮𐑴𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑣𐑲𐑛𐑮𐑴𐑓𐑴𐑚𐑾; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑜𐑴 𐑪𐑯—𐑜𐑴 𐑪𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑸𐑥 𐑕𐑑𐑹𐑦.”

“𐑘𐑧𐑕, 𐑲 𐑥𐑱 𐑨𐑟 𐑢𐑧𐑤,” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑞 𐑕𐑻𐑡𐑩𐑯, 𐑒𐑵𐑤𐑦. “𐑲 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑩𐑚𐑟𐑻𐑝𐑦𐑙, 𐑕𐑻, 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 ·𐑚𐑵𐑥𐑼'𐑟 𐑓𐑩𐑕𐑰𐑖𐑩𐑕 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑳𐑐𐑖𐑩𐑯, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑐𐑲𐑑 𐑝 𐑥𐑲 𐑚𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑯 𐑕𐑦𐑝𐑽𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑧𐑝𐑼𐑟, 𐑞 𐑢𐑵𐑯𐑛 𐑒𐑧𐑐𐑑 𐑜𐑧𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑻𐑕 𐑯 𐑢𐑻𐑕; 𐑞 𐑑𐑮𐑵𐑔 𐑢𐑪𐑟, 𐑕𐑻, 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑨𐑟 𐑳𐑜𐑤𐑦 𐑜𐑱𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑵𐑯𐑛 𐑨𐑟 𐑕𐑻𐑡𐑩𐑯 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑕𐑷; 𐑥𐑹 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑑𐑵 𐑓𐑰𐑑 𐑯 𐑕𐑧𐑝𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑯𐑗𐑩𐑟 𐑤𐑪𐑙. 𐑲 𐑥𐑧𐑠𐑼𐑛 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑤𐑧𐑛 𐑤𐑲𐑯. 𐑦𐑯 𐑖𐑹𐑑, 𐑦𐑑 𐑜𐑮𐑵 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑒; 𐑲 𐑯𐑿 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑔𐑮𐑧𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑛, 𐑯 𐑪𐑓 𐑦𐑑 𐑒𐑱𐑥. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑯𐑴 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑲𐑝𐑼𐑦 𐑸𐑥 𐑞𐑺; 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑟 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑮𐑵𐑤”—𐑐𐑶𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑯𐑸𐑤𐑦𐑣𐑕𐑐𐑲𐑒—“𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑞 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯'𐑟 𐑢𐑻𐑒, 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑥𐑲𐑯; 𐑣𐑰 𐑹𐑛𐑼𐑛 𐑞 𐑒𐑸𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑼 𐑑 𐑥𐑱𐑒 𐑦𐑑; 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑒𐑤𐑳𐑚-𐑣𐑨𐑥𐑼 𐑞𐑺 𐑐𐑫𐑑 𐑑 𐑞 𐑧𐑯𐑛, 𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑒 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑢𐑳𐑯'𐑟 𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑟 𐑬𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞, 𐑲 𐑕𐑩𐑐𐑴𐑟, 𐑨𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑛 𐑥𐑲𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑕. 𐑣𐑰 𐑓𐑤𐑲𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑛𐑲𐑩𐑚𐑪𐑤𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑐𐑭𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟. 𐑛𐑵 𐑘𐑰 𐑕𐑰 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑛𐑧𐑯𐑑, 𐑕𐑻”—𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑵𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑑, 𐑯 𐑚𐑮𐑳𐑖𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑺, 𐑯 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑴𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑚𐑴𐑤-𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑒𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑒𐑳𐑤, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑚𐑹 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑤𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑒𐑸𐑦 𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑕, 𐑹 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑑𐑴𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑣𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑩 𐑢𐑵𐑯𐑛—“𐑢𐑧𐑤, 𐑞 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑑𐑧𐑤 𐑿 𐑣𐑬 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑒𐑱𐑥 𐑣𐑽; 𐑣𐑰 𐑯𐑴𐑟.”

“𐑯𐑴, 𐑲 𐑛𐑴𐑯𐑑,” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑞 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯, “𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑛𐑦𐑛; 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑚𐑹𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑦𐑑. 𐑴, 𐑿 𐑕𐑪𐑤𐑩𐑥 𐑮𐑴𐑜, 𐑿—𐑿 ·𐑚𐑳𐑙𐑼! 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞𐑺 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩𐑯𐑳𐑞𐑼 ·𐑚𐑳𐑙𐑼 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼𐑦 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛? 𐑚𐑳𐑙𐑼, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑿 𐑛𐑲, 𐑿 𐑷𐑑 𐑑 𐑛𐑲 𐑦𐑯 𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤, 𐑿 𐑛𐑪𐑜; 𐑿 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑚𐑰 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑻𐑝𐑛 𐑑 𐑓𐑿𐑗𐑼 𐑱𐑡𐑩𐑟, 𐑿 𐑮𐑭𐑕𐑒𐑩𐑤.”

“𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑱𐑥 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑢𐑲𐑑 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤?” 𐑯𐑬 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚, 𐑣𐑵 𐑞𐑳𐑕 𐑓𐑸 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑤𐑦𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑚𐑲-𐑐𐑤𐑱 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑢𐑰𐑯 𐑞 𐑑𐑵 ·𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑤𐑦𐑖𐑥𐑧𐑯.

“𐑴!” 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 𐑞 𐑢𐑳𐑯-𐑸𐑥𐑛 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯, “𐑴, 𐑘𐑧𐑕! 𐑢𐑧𐑤; 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛, 𐑢𐑰 𐑛𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑕𐑰 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯 𐑓 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑑𐑲𐑥; 𐑦𐑯 𐑓𐑨𐑒𐑑, 𐑨𐑟 𐑲 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑣𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛, 𐑲 𐑛𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑯𐑴 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑕𐑻𐑝𐑛 𐑥𐑰 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩 𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑒, 𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼𐑢𐑼𐑛𐑟, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑨𐑒 𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑤𐑲𐑯, 𐑢𐑰 𐑣𐑻𐑛 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 ·𐑥𐑪𐑚𐑦 ·𐑛𐑦𐑒—𐑨𐑟 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑒𐑷𐑤 𐑣𐑦𐑥—𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑲 𐑯𐑿 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑣𐑰.”

“𐑛𐑲𐑛'𐑕𐑑 𐑞𐑬 𐑒𐑮𐑪𐑕 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑱𐑒 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯?”

“𐑑𐑢𐑲𐑕.”

“𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑓𐑭𐑕𐑩𐑯?”

“𐑛𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑯𐑑 𐑑 𐑑𐑮𐑲 𐑑: 𐑱𐑯𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑤𐑦𐑥 𐑦𐑯𐑳𐑓? 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑲 𐑛𐑵 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑸𐑥? 𐑯 𐑲'𐑥 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑦𐑙 ·𐑥𐑪𐑚𐑦 ·𐑛𐑦𐑒 𐑛𐑳𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑚𐑲𐑑 𐑕𐑴 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑨𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑢𐑪𐑤𐑴𐑟.”

“𐑢𐑧𐑤, 𐑞𐑧𐑯,” 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑳𐑐𐑑𐑩𐑛 ·𐑚𐑳𐑙𐑼, “𐑜𐑦𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑘𐑹 𐑤𐑧𐑓𐑑 𐑸𐑥 𐑓 𐑚𐑱𐑑 𐑑 𐑜𐑧𐑑 𐑞 𐑮𐑲𐑑. 𐑛𐑵 𐑿 𐑯𐑴, 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑥𐑧𐑯”—𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑝𐑤𐑦 𐑯 𐑥𐑨𐑔𐑩𐑥𐑨𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑬𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑰𐑗 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑩𐑒𐑕𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑯—“𐑛𐑵 𐑿 𐑯𐑴, 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑥𐑧𐑯, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑛𐑲𐑡𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑝 𐑹𐑜𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑸 𐑕𐑴 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑵𐑑𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑲 ·𐑛𐑦𐑝𐑲𐑯 ·𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑝𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑕, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑪𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑓 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑑 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑰𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑲𐑡𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑩 𐑥𐑨𐑯'𐑟 𐑸𐑥? 𐑯 𐑣𐑰 𐑯𐑴𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑑𐑵. 𐑕𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑿 𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑓 𐑞 ·𐑢𐑲𐑑 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤'𐑟 𐑥𐑨𐑤𐑦𐑕 𐑦𐑟 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑷𐑒𐑢𐑼𐑛𐑯𐑩𐑕. 𐑓 𐑣𐑰 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑥𐑰𐑯𐑟 𐑑 𐑕𐑢𐑪𐑤𐑴 𐑩 𐑕𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑩𐑤 𐑤𐑦𐑥; 𐑣𐑰 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑕 𐑑 𐑑𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑓𐑲 𐑚𐑲 𐑓𐑱𐑯𐑑𐑕. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑦𐑟 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑞 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑡𐑳𐑜𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑧𐑤𐑴, 𐑓𐑹𐑥𐑼𐑤𐑦 𐑩 𐑐𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑥𐑲𐑯 𐑦𐑯 ·𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑪𐑯, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑱𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑰𐑝 𐑕𐑢𐑪𐑤𐑴 𐑡𐑨𐑒-𐑯𐑲𐑝𐑟, 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑕 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑩 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑤𐑧𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑛𐑮𐑪𐑐 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑦𐑯 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑻𐑯𐑩𐑕𐑑, 𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑛 𐑓 𐑩 𐑑𐑢𐑧𐑤𐑝𐑥𐑳𐑯𐑔 𐑹 𐑥𐑹; 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑲 𐑜𐑱𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑥𐑧𐑑𐑦𐑒, 𐑯 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑰𐑝𐑛 𐑦𐑑 𐑳𐑐 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑥𐑷𐑤 𐑑𐑨𐑒𐑕, 𐑛'𐑘𐑰 𐑕𐑰. 𐑯𐑴 𐑐𐑪𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑱 𐑓 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑑 𐑛𐑲𐑡𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑡𐑨𐑒-𐑯𐑲𐑓, 𐑯 𐑓𐑫𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑹𐑐𐑼𐑱𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑥. 𐑘𐑧𐑕, ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 ·𐑚𐑵𐑥𐑼, 𐑦𐑓 𐑿 𐑸 𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑒 𐑦𐑯𐑳𐑓 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑦𐑑, 𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑩 𐑥𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑑 𐑐𐑷𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑸𐑥 𐑓 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑒 𐑝 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑡 𐑝 𐑜𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑛𐑰𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑚𐑧𐑮𐑾𐑤 𐑑 𐑞 𐑳𐑞𐑼, 𐑢𐑲 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑒𐑱𐑕 𐑞 𐑸𐑥 𐑦𐑟 𐑘𐑹𐑟; 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑤𐑧𐑑 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑩𐑯𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑗𐑭𐑯𐑕 𐑨𐑑 𐑿 𐑖𐑹𐑑𐑤𐑦, 𐑞𐑨𐑑'𐑕 𐑷𐑤.”

“𐑯𐑴, 𐑔𐑨𐑙𐑒 𐑘𐑰, ·𐑚𐑳𐑙𐑼,” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑞 ·𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑤𐑦𐑖 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯, “𐑣𐑰'𐑟 𐑢𐑧𐑤𐑒𐑩𐑥 𐑑 𐑞 𐑸𐑥 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑟, 𐑕𐑦𐑯𐑕 𐑲 𐑒𐑭𐑯𐑑 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑐 𐑦𐑑, 𐑯 𐑛𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑯𐑴 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑞𐑧𐑯; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑑 𐑩𐑯𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑢𐑳𐑯. 𐑯𐑴 𐑥𐑹 ·𐑢𐑲𐑑 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑓 𐑥𐑰; 𐑲'𐑝 𐑤𐑴𐑼𐑛 𐑓 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑕, 𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑕𐑨𐑑𐑦𐑕𐑓𐑲𐑛 𐑥𐑰. 𐑞𐑺 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑚𐑰 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑜𐑤𐑹𐑦 𐑦𐑯 𐑒𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑲 𐑯𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑; 𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑦𐑟 𐑩 𐑖𐑦𐑐-𐑤𐑴𐑛 𐑝 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑕 𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑚𐑳𐑑, 𐑣𐑸𐑒 𐑘𐑰, 𐑣𐑰'𐑟 𐑚𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑤𐑧𐑑 𐑩𐑤𐑴𐑯; 𐑛𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑿 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒 𐑕𐑴, ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯?”—𐑜𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑲𐑝𐑼𐑦 𐑤𐑧𐑜.

“𐑣𐑰 𐑦𐑟. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑚𐑰 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛, 𐑓 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑨𐑑. 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑤𐑧𐑑 𐑩𐑤𐑴𐑯, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑩𐑒𐑻𐑕𐑩𐑛 𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑷𐑤𐑢𐑱𐑟 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑤𐑰𐑕𐑑 𐑩𐑤𐑫𐑼𐑟. 𐑣𐑰'𐑟 𐑷𐑤 𐑩 𐑥𐑨𐑜𐑯𐑩𐑑! 𐑣𐑬 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑕𐑦𐑯𐑕 𐑞𐑬 𐑕𐑷'𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑? 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑢𐑱 𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑦𐑙?”

“𐑚𐑤𐑧𐑕 𐑥𐑲 𐑕𐑴𐑤, 𐑯 𐑒𐑻𐑕 𐑞 𐑓𐑬𐑤 𐑓𐑰𐑯𐑛'𐑟,” 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 ·𐑚𐑳𐑙𐑼, 𐑕𐑑𐑵𐑐𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑢𐑷𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚, 𐑯 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑛𐑪𐑜, 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑯𐑳𐑓𐑦𐑙; “𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑥𐑨𐑯'𐑟 𐑚𐑤𐑳𐑛—𐑚𐑮𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑔𐑼𐑥𐑪𐑥𐑦𐑑𐑼!—𐑦𐑑'𐑕 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑚𐑶𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑐𐑶𐑯𐑑!—𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑳𐑤𐑕 𐑥𐑱𐑒𐑕 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑐𐑤𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑕 𐑚𐑰𐑑!—𐑕𐑻!”—𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑪𐑒𐑩𐑑, 𐑯 𐑛𐑮𐑷𐑦𐑙 𐑯𐑽 𐑑 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚'𐑟 𐑸𐑥.

“𐑩𐑝𐑭𐑕𐑑!” 𐑮𐑹𐑛 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚, 𐑛𐑨𐑖𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑞 𐑚𐑫𐑤𐑢𐑼𐑒𐑕—“𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑! 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑢𐑱 𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑦𐑙?”

“𐑜𐑫𐑛 ·𐑜𐑪𐑛!” 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 𐑞 ·𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑤𐑦𐑖 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯, 𐑑 𐑣𐑵𐑥 𐑞 𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑕𐑗𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑐𐑫𐑑. “𐑢𐑪𐑑'𐑕 𐑞 𐑥𐑨𐑑𐑼? 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑰𐑕𐑑, 𐑲 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒.—𐑦𐑟 𐑘𐑹 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 𐑒𐑮𐑱𐑟𐑦?” 𐑢𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑼𐑦𐑙 ·𐑓𐑧𐑛𐑩𐑤𐑩.

𐑚𐑳𐑑 ·𐑓𐑧𐑛𐑩𐑤𐑩, 𐑐𐑫𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑓𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑼 𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑤𐑦𐑐, 𐑕𐑤𐑦𐑛 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑞 𐑚𐑫𐑤𐑢𐑼𐑒𐑕 𐑑 𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑'𐑕 𐑕𐑑𐑽𐑦𐑙 𐑹, 𐑯 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚, 𐑕𐑢𐑦𐑙𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑒𐑳𐑑𐑦𐑙-𐑑𐑨𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑑𐑩𐑢𐑹𐑛𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑭𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐'𐑕 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑼𐑟 𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑑 𐑤𐑴𐑼.

𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑥𐑴𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑'𐑕 𐑕𐑑𐑻𐑯, 𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑤𐑩 𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑢𐑻 𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑙𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑹𐑟. 𐑦𐑯 𐑝𐑱𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑤𐑦𐑖 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑱𐑤𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥. 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑚𐑨𐑒 𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑼 𐑖𐑦𐑐, 𐑯 𐑓𐑱𐑕 𐑕𐑧𐑑 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑓𐑤𐑦𐑯𐑑 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑴𐑯, ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑕𐑑𐑫𐑛 𐑳𐑐𐑮𐑲𐑑 𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑙𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛.

·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 101. 𐑞 ·𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑼.

𐑺 𐑞 ·𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑤𐑦𐑖 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑓𐑱𐑛𐑟 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑕𐑲𐑑, 𐑚𐑰 𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑧𐑑 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑣𐑽, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑖𐑰 𐑣𐑱𐑤𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 ·𐑤𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑯, 𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑱𐑥𐑛 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑞 𐑤𐑱𐑑 ·𐑕𐑨𐑥𐑿𐑩𐑤 ·𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑸𐑚𐑦, 𐑥𐑻𐑗𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑦𐑑𐑦, 𐑞 𐑼𐑦𐑡𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑞 𐑓𐑱𐑥𐑩𐑕 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑬𐑕 𐑝 ·𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑸𐑚𐑦 & ·𐑕𐑳𐑯𐑟; 𐑩 𐑣𐑬𐑕 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑲 𐑐𐑫𐑼 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑥𐑩𐑯'𐑟 𐑩𐑐𐑦𐑯𐑘𐑩𐑯, 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑓𐑸 𐑚𐑦𐑣𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑞 𐑿𐑯𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑮𐑶𐑩𐑤 𐑣𐑬𐑟𐑩𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑑𐑿𐑛𐑼𐑟 𐑯 ·𐑚𐑻𐑚𐑩𐑯𐑟, 𐑦𐑯 𐑐𐑶𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑮𐑾𐑤 𐑣𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑩𐑕𐑑. 𐑣𐑬 𐑤𐑪𐑙, 𐑐𐑮𐑲𐑼 𐑑 𐑞 𐑘𐑽 𐑝 𐑬𐑼 ·𐑤𐑹𐑛 1775, 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑬𐑕 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑦𐑜𐑟𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕, 𐑥𐑲 𐑯𐑿𐑥𐑼𐑩𐑕 𐑓𐑦𐑖-𐑛𐑪𐑒𐑿𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑛𐑵 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑥𐑱𐑒 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑯; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑘𐑽 (1775) 𐑦𐑑 𐑓𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑬𐑑 𐑞 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 ·𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑤𐑦𐑖 𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑕 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑮𐑧𐑜𐑿𐑤𐑼𐑤𐑦 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤; 𐑞𐑴 𐑓 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑕𐑒𐑹 𐑝 𐑘𐑽𐑟 𐑐𐑮𐑰𐑝𐑾𐑕 (𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑕𐑦𐑯𐑕 1726) 𐑬𐑼 𐑝𐑨𐑤𐑾𐑯𐑑 ·𐑒𐑪𐑓𐑦𐑯𐑟 𐑯 ·𐑥𐑱𐑕𐑦𐑟 𐑝 ·𐑯𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑑 𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑝𐑦𐑯𐑘𐑼𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑤𐑸𐑡 𐑓𐑤𐑰𐑑𐑕 𐑐𐑼𐑕𐑿𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 ·𐑤𐑩𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑔𐑩𐑯, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑯𐑹𐑔 𐑯 ·𐑕𐑬𐑔 ·𐑩𐑑𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑒: 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑧𐑤𐑕𐑢𐑺. 𐑚𐑰 𐑦𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑹𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑣𐑽, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑯𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑑𐑼𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑞 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑥𐑨𐑯𐑒𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑑 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑕𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑤𐑲𐑟𐑛 𐑕𐑑𐑰𐑤 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 ·𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤; 𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑓 𐑣𐑭𐑓 𐑩 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑗𐑼𐑦 𐑞𐑱 𐑢𐑻 𐑞 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑰𐑐𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑞 𐑣𐑴𐑤 𐑜𐑤𐑴𐑚 𐑣𐑵 𐑕𐑴 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥.

𐑦𐑯 1778, 𐑩 𐑓𐑲𐑯 𐑖𐑦𐑐, 𐑞 ·𐑩𐑥𐑰𐑤𐑾, 𐑓𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑬𐑑 𐑓 𐑞 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑕 𐑐𐑻𐑐𐑩𐑕, 𐑯 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑴𐑤 𐑗𐑸𐑡 𐑝 𐑞 𐑝𐑦𐑜𐑼𐑩𐑕 ·𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑸𐑚𐑦𐑟, 𐑚𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 ·𐑒𐑱𐑐 ·𐑣𐑹𐑯, 𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑞 𐑯𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑑 𐑤𐑴𐑼 𐑩 𐑢𐑱𐑤-𐑚𐑴𐑑 𐑝 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑕𐑹𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 ·𐑕𐑬𐑔 ·𐑕𐑰. 𐑞 𐑝𐑶𐑦𐑡 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩 𐑕𐑒𐑦𐑤𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑯 𐑤𐑳𐑒𐑦 𐑢𐑳𐑯; 𐑯 𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑣𐑻 𐑚𐑻𐑔 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑻 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑓𐑫𐑤 𐑝 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑕 𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥, 𐑞 ·𐑩𐑥𐑰𐑤𐑾'𐑟 𐑦𐑜𐑟𐑭𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑵𐑯 𐑓𐑪𐑤𐑴𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑕, ·𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑤𐑦𐑖 𐑯 ·𐑩𐑥𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑯, 𐑯 𐑞𐑳𐑕 𐑞 𐑝𐑭𐑕𐑑 ·𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑜𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑩𐑕𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑒 𐑢𐑻 𐑔𐑮𐑴𐑯 𐑴𐑐𐑩𐑯. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑛𐑰𐑛, 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑓𐑨𐑑𐑦𐑜𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑣𐑬𐑕 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯 𐑚𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑻𐑛 𐑦𐑑𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓: ·𐑕𐑨𐑥𐑿𐑩𐑤 𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑣𐑦𐑟 ·𐑕𐑳𐑯𐑟—𐑣𐑬 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦, 𐑞𐑺 𐑥𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑯𐑴𐑟—𐑯 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑞𐑺 𐑦𐑥𐑰𐑛𐑾𐑑 𐑷𐑕𐑐𐑦𐑕𐑩𐑟, 𐑯 𐑐𐑸𐑑𐑤𐑦, 𐑲 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒, 𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑕, 𐑞 ·𐑚𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑖 𐑜𐑳𐑝𐑼𐑯𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑿𐑕𐑑 𐑑 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑞 𐑕𐑤𐑵𐑐-𐑝-𐑢𐑹 ·𐑮𐑨𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑼 𐑪𐑯 𐑩 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑝𐑶𐑦𐑡 𐑝 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑳𐑝𐑼𐑦 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑬𐑔 ·𐑕𐑰. 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑭𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑩 𐑯𐑱𐑝𐑩𐑤 ·𐑐𐑴𐑕𐑑-·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯, 𐑞 ·𐑮𐑨𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑼 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑩 𐑮𐑨𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑝𐑶𐑦𐑡 𐑝 𐑦𐑑, 𐑯 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑕𐑻𐑝𐑦𐑕; 𐑣𐑬 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑛𐑳𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑩𐑐𐑽. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑷𐑤. 𐑦𐑯 1819, 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑣𐑬𐑕 𐑓𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑬𐑑 𐑩 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑳𐑝𐑼𐑦 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑝 𐑞𐑺 𐑴𐑯, 𐑑 𐑜𐑴 𐑪𐑯 𐑩 𐑑𐑱𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑒𐑮𐑵𐑟 𐑑 𐑞 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑴𐑑 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼𐑟 𐑝 ·𐑡𐑩𐑐𐑨𐑯. 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑖𐑦𐑐—𐑢𐑧𐑤 𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑛 𐑞 “·𐑕𐑽𐑩𐑯”—𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑩 𐑯𐑴𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑒𐑮𐑵𐑟; 𐑯 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞𐑳𐑕 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 ·𐑡𐑨𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑰𐑟 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙 ·𐑜𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑱𐑥 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑯𐑴𐑯. 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑽𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑓𐑱𐑥𐑩𐑕 𐑝𐑶𐑦𐑡 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑭𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑩 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 ·𐑒𐑪𐑓𐑦𐑯, 𐑩 ·𐑯𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑑𐑼.

𐑷𐑤 𐑪𐑯𐑼 𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑸𐑚𐑦𐑟, 𐑞𐑺𐑓𐑹, 𐑣𐑵𐑟 𐑣𐑬𐑕, 𐑲 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒, 𐑦𐑜𐑟𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑕 𐑑 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑛𐑱; 𐑞𐑴 𐑛𐑬𐑑𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑞 𐑼𐑦𐑡𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑤 ·𐑕𐑨𐑥𐑿𐑩𐑤 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑩𐑜𐑴 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑕𐑤𐑦𐑐𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑱𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑓 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 ·𐑕𐑬𐑔 ·𐑕𐑰 𐑝 𐑞 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛.

𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑯𐑱𐑥𐑛 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑢𐑻𐑞𐑦 𐑝 𐑞 𐑪𐑯𐑼, 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑓𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑼 𐑯 𐑩 𐑯𐑴𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑒𐑮𐑭𐑓𐑑 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑢𐑱. 𐑲 𐑚𐑹𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑣𐑻 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑕 𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑦𐑛𐑯𐑲𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑢𐑺 𐑪𐑓 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑨𐑑𐑩𐑜𐑴𐑯𐑾𐑯 𐑒𐑴𐑕𐑑, 𐑯 𐑛𐑮𐑨𐑙𐑒 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑓𐑤𐑦𐑐 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑴𐑒𐑕𐑩𐑤. 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩 𐑓𐑲𐑯 𐑜𐑨𐑥 𐑢𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛, 𐑯 𐑞𐑱 𐑢𐑻 𐑷𐑤 𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑕—𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑕𐑴𐑤 𐑪𐑯 𐑚𐑹𐑛. 𐑩 𐑖𐑹𐑑 𐑤𐑲𐑓 𐑑 𐑞𐑧𐑥, 𐑯 𐑩 𐑡𐑪𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑧𐑔. 𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑓𐑲𐑯 𐑜𐑨𐑥 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑛—𐑤𐑪𐑙, 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑴𐑤𐑛 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑑𐑳𐑗𐑑 𐑣𐑻 𐑐𐑤𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑕 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑲𐑝𐑼𐑦 𐑣𐑰𐑤—𐑦𐑑 𐑥𐑲𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑥𐑰 𐑝 𐑞 𐑯𐑴𐑚𐑩𐑤, 𐑕𐑪𐑤𐑦𐑛, ·𐑕𐑨𐑒𐑕𐑩𐑯 𐑣𐑪𐑕𐑐𐑦𐑑𐑨𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑖𐑦𐑐; 𐑯 𐑥𐑱 𐑥𐑲 𐑐𐑸𐑟𐑩𐑯 𐑓𐑼𐑜𐑧𐑑 𐑥𐑰, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑤 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑧𐑥𐑚𐑼 𐑥𐑰, 𐑦𐑓 𐑲 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑤𐑵𐑟 𐑕𐑲𐑑 𐑝 𐑦𐑑. 𐑓𐑤𐑦𐑐? 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑲 𐑕𐑱 𐑢𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑓𐑤𐑦𐑐? 𐑘𐑧𐑕, 𐑯 𐑢𐑰 𐑓𐑤𐑦𐑐𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑝 𐑑𐑧𐑯 𐑜𐑨𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑞 𐑬𐑼; 𐑯 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑒𐑢𐑷𐑤 𐑒𐑱𐑥 (𐑓 𐑦𐑑'𐑕 𐑕𐑒𐑢𐑷𐑤𐑦 𐑪𐑓 𐑞𐑺 𐑚𐑲 ·𐑐𐑨𐑑𐑩𐑜𐑴𐑯𐑾), 𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟—𐑝𐑦𐑟𐑦𐑑𐑼𐑟 𐑯 𐑷𐑤—𐑢𐑻 𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑛 𐑑 𐑮𐑰𐑓 𐑑𐑪𐑐𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑟, 𐑢𐑰 𐑢𐑻 𐑕𐑴 𐑑𐑪𐑐-𐑣𐑧𐑝𐑦 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑑 𐑕𐑢𐑦𐑙 𐑰𐑗 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑓𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑚𐑴𐑤𐑦𐑯𐑟; 𐑯 𐑢𐑰 𐑦𐑜𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑓𐑻𐑤𐑛 𐑞 𐑕𐑒𐑻𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑬𐑼 𐑡𐑨𐑒𐑩𐑑𐑕 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑟, 𐑕𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑰 𐑣𐑳𐑙 𐑞𐑺, 𐑮𐑰𐑓𐑑 𐑓𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑣𐑬𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑜𐑱𐑤, 𐑩 𐑢𐑹𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑜𐑟𐑭𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑤 𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑛𐑮𐑳𐑙𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑑𐑸𐑟. 𐑣𐑬𐑧𐑝𐑼, 𐑞 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑕 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑜𐑴 𐑴𐑝𐑼𐑚𐑹𐑛; 𐑯 𐑚𐑲 𐑯 𐑚𐑲 𐑢𐑰 𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑨𐑥𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑛𐑬𐑯, 𐑕𐑴 𐑕𐑴𐑚𐑼, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑑 𐑐𐑭𐑕 𐑞 𐑓𐑤𐑦𐑐 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯, 𐑞𐑴 𐑞 𐑕𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑡 𐑕𐑷𐑤𐑑 𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑱 𐑚𐑻𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑴𐑒𐑕𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑒𐑳𐑑𐑩𐑤, 𐑮𐑭𐑞𐑼 𐑑𐑵 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑛𐑲𐑤𐑵𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑯 𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑦𐑑 𐑑 𐑥𐑲 𐑑𐑱𐑕𐑑.

𐑞 𐑚𐑰𐑓 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑓𐑲𐑯—𐑑𐑳𐑓, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦 𐑦𐑯 𐑦𐑑. 𐑞𐑱 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑚𐑫𐑤-𐑚𐑰𐑓; 𐑳𐑞𐑼𐑟, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑛𐑮𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑛𐑼𐑦 𐑚𐑰𐑓; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑲 𐑛𐑵 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑯𐑴, 𐑓 𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑯, 𐑣𐑬 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟. 𐑞𐑱 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑛𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑑𐑵; 𐑕𐑥𐑷𐑤, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑤, 𐑕𐑦𐑥𐑧𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑦 𐑜𐑤𐑪𐑚𐑿𐑤𐑼, 𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑛𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑦𐑙𐑟. 𐑲 𐑓𐑨𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑿 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑓𐑰𐑤 𐑞𐑧𐑥, 𐑯 𐑮𐑴𐑤 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑿 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑞𐑱 𐑢𐑻 𐑕𐑢𐑪𐑤𐑴𐑛. 𐑦𐑓 𐑿 𐑕𐑑𐑵𐑐𐑑 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑑𐑵 𐑓𐑸 𐑓𐑹𐑢𐑼𐑛, 𐑿 𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑐𐑦𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑿 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑘𐑼𐑛-𐑚𐑷𐑤𐑟. 𐑞 𐑚𐑮𐑧𐑛—𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑒𐑫𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑐𐑑; 𐑚𐑦𐑕𐑲𐑛𐑟, 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩𐑯 𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑦-𐑕𐑒𐑹𐑚𐑿𐑑𐑦𐑒; 𐑦𐑯 𐑖𐑹𐑑, 𐑞 𐑚𐑮𐑧𐑛 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑱𐑯𐑛 𐑞 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑖 𐑓𐑺 𐑞𐑱 𐑣𐑨𐑛. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞 𐑓𐑴𐑒𐑕𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑤𐑲𐑑, 𐑯 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑰𐑟𐑦 𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑐 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑩 𐑛𐑸𐑒 𐑒𐑹𐑯𐑼 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑿 𐑱𐑑 𐑦𐑑. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑷𐑤, 𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑻 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑒 𐑑 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑥, 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑛𐑦𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑒𐑫𐑒'𐑕 𐑚𐑶𐑤𐑼𐑟, 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑤𐑵𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑴𐑯 𐑤𐑲𐑝 𐑐𐑸𐑗𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑚𐑶𐑤𐑼𐑟; 𐑓𐑹 𐑯 𐑭𐑓𐑑, 𐑲 𐑕𐑱, 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑨𐑥𐑿𐑩𐑤 ·𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑸𐑚𐑦 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩 𐑡𐑪𐑤𐑦 𐑖𐑦𐑐; 𐑝 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑓𐑺 𐑯 𐑐𐑤𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑦; 𐑓𐑲𐑯 𐑓𐑤𐑦𐑐 𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑪𐑙; 𐑒𐑮𐑨𐑒 𐑓𐑧𐑤𐑴𐑟 𐑷𐑤, 𐑯 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑚𐑵𐑑 𐑣𐑰𐑤𐑟 𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑑-𐑚𐑨𐑯𐑛.

𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑲 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑦𐑑, 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒 𐑘𐑰, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑨𐑥𐑿𐑩𐑤 ·𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑸𐑚𐑦, 𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑳𐑞𐑼 ·𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑤𐑦𐑖 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑼𐑟 𐑲 𐑯𐑴 𐑝—𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑴—𐑢𐑻 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑓𐑱𐑥𐑩𐑕, 𐑣𐑪𐑕𐑐𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑕; 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑐𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑞 𐑚𐑰𐑓, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑮𐑧𐑛, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑒𐑨𐑯, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑡𐑴𐑒; 𐑯 𐑢𐑻 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑵𐑯 𐑢𐑽𐑦 𐑝 𐑰𐑑𐑦𐑙, 𐑯 𐑛𐑮𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑦𐑙, 𐑯 𐑤𐑭𐑓𐑦𐑙? 𐑲 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑑𐑧𐑤 𐑿. 𐑞 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑗𐑽 𐑝 𐑞𐑰𐑟 ·𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑤𐑦𐑖 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑼𐑟 𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑨𐑑𐑼 𐑓 𐑣𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑮𐑰𐑕𐑻𐑗. 𐑯𐑹 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑲 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑨𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑕𐑐𐑺𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑮𐑰𐑕𐑻𐑗, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑦𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑯𐑰𐑛𐑩𐑛.

𐑞 ·𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑤𐑦𐑖 𐑢𐑻 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑰𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑼𐑦 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 ·𐑣𐑪𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑟, ·𐑟𐑰𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑟, 𐑯 ·𐑛𐑱𐑯𐑟; 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑣𐑵𐑥 𐑞𐑱 𐑛𐑦𐑮𐑲𐑝𐑛 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑑𐑻𐑥𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑼𐑦; 𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑥𐑹, 𐑞𐑺 𐑓𐑨𐑑 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑓𐑨𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟, 𐑑𐑳𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑐𐑤𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑦 𐑑 𐑰𐑑 𐑯 𐑛𐑮𐑦𐑙𐑒. 𐑓, 𐑨𐑟 𐑩 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑔𐑦𐑙, 𐑞 ·𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑤𐑦𐑖 𐑥𐑻𐑗𐑩𐑯𐑑-𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑕 𐑣𐑻 𐑒𐑮𐑵; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑴 𐑞 ·𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑤𐑦𐑖 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑼. 𐑣𐑧𐑯𐑕, 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑤𐑦𐑖, 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑗𐑽 𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑯𐑹𐑥𐑩𐑤 𐑯 𐑯𐑨𐑗𐑼𐑩𐑤, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑯 𐑐𐑼𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑼; 𐑯, 𐑞𐑺𐑓𐑹, 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑤 𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑡𐑦𐑯, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑽 𐑐𐑶𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑬𐑑, 𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑚𐑰 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑓𐑻𐑞𐑼 𐑦𐑤𐑵𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛.

𐑛𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑲 𐑮𐑰𐑕𐑻𐑗𐑩𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑤𐑩𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑔𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑒 𐑣𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑦𐑟, 𐑲 𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑥𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑩𐑯 𐑱𐑯𐑗𐑩𐑯𐑑 ·𐑛𐑳𐑗 𐑝𐑪𐑤𐑿𐑥, 𐑢𐑦𐑗, 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑𐑦 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑥𐑧𐑤 𐑝 𐑦𐑑, 𐑲 𐑯𐑿 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑼𐑟. 𐑞 𐑑𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑪𐑟, “𐑛𐑨𐑯 ·𐑒𐑵𐑐𐑥𐑩𐑯,” 𐑢𐑺𐑓𐑹 𐑲 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑒𐑤𐑵𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑨𐑤𐑿𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑥𐑧𐑥𐑢𐑸𐑟 𐑝 𐑕𐑳𐑥 ·𐑨𐑥𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑛𐑨𐑥 𐑒𐑵𐑐𐑼 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑼𐑦, 𐑨𐑟 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑒𐑨𐑮𐑦 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑒𐑵𐑐𐑼. 𐑲 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑮𐑰𐑦𐑯𐑓𐑹𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑩𐑐𐑦𐑯𐑘𐑩𐑯 𐑚𐑲 𐑕𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑛𐑳𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑢𐑳𐑯 “𐑓𐑦𐑑𐑕 ·𐑕𐑢𐑨𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑼.” 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑥𐑲 𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑯𐑛 ·𐑛𐑼 ·𐑕𐑯𐑪𐑛𐑣𐑧𐑛, 𐑩 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑤𐑻𐑯𐑛 𐑥𐑨𐑯, 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑓𐑧𐑕𐑼 𐑝 ·𐑤𐑴 ·𐑛𐑳𐑗 𐑯 ·𐑣𐑲 ·𐑡𐑻𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑒𐑪𐑤𐑦𐑡 𐑝 ·𐑕𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑩 ·𐑒𐑤𐑷𐑟 𐑯 ·𐑕𐑑 ·𐑐𐑪𐑑'𐑕, 𐑑 𐑣𐑵𐑥 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑞 𐑢𐑻𐑒 𐑓 𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑟𐑤𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯, 𐑜𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑩 𐑚𐑪𐑒𐑕 𐑝 𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑓 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑚𐑩𐑤—𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑕𐑱𐑥 ·𐑛𐑼 ·𐑕𐑯𐑪𐑛𐑣𐑧𐑛, 𐑕𐑴 𐑕𐑵𐑯 𐑨𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑐𐑲𐑛 𐑞 𐑚𐑫𐑒, 𐑩𐑖𐑫𐑼𐑛 𐑥𐑰 𐑞𐑨𐑑 “𐑛𐑨𐑯 ·𐑒𐑵𐑐𐑥𐑩𐑯” 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑥𐑰𐑯 “𐑞 ·𐑒𐑵𐑐𐑼,” 𐑚𐑳𐑑 “𐑞 ·𐑥𐑻𐑗𐑩𐑯𐑑.” 𐑦𐑯 𐑖𐑹𐑑, 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑱𐑯𐑗𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑯 𐑤𐑻𐑯𐑛 ·𐑤𐑴 ·𐑛𐑳𐑗 𐑚𐑫𐑒 𐑑𐑮𐑰𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑝 𐑞 𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑻𐑕 𐑝 ·𐑣𐑪𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛; 𐑯, 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑕𐑳𐑚𐑡𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑕, 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑱𐑯𐑛 𐑩 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑩𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑼𐑦. 𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟, 𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑩𐑛, “𐑕𐑥𐑽,” 𐑹 “𐑓𐑨𐑑,” 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑲 𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑩 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑛𐑰𐑑𐑱𐑤𐑛 𐑤𐑦𐑕𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑬𐑑𐑓𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑓 𐑞 𐑤𐑸𐑛𐑼𐑟 𐑯 𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑼𐑟 𐑝 180 𐑕𐑱𐑤 𐑝 ·𐑛𐑳𐑗 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑥𐑧𐑯; 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑤𐑦𐑕𐑑, 𐑨𐑟 𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑟𐑤𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑲 ·𐑛𐑼 ·𐑕𐑯𐑪𐑛𐑣𐑧𐑛, 𐑲 𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑚 𐑞 𐑓𐑪𐑤𐑴𐑦𐑙:

400,000 𐑐𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑟. 𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑓. 60,000 𐑐𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑟. 𐑓𐑮𐑲𐑟𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑐𐑹𐑒. 150,000 𐑐𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑟. 𐑝 𐑕𐑑𐑪𐑒 𐑓𐑦𐑖. 550,000 𐑐𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑟. 𐑝 𐑚𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑦𐑑. 72,000 𐑐𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑟. 𐑝 𐑕𐑪𐑓𐑑 𐑚𐑮𐑧𐑛. 2,800 𐑓𐑻𐑒𐑦𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑚𐑳𐑑𐑼. 20,000 𐑐𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑟. ·𐑑𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑩𐑤 & ·𐑤𐑱𐑛𐑩𐑯 𐑗𐑰𐑟. 144,000 𐑐𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑟. 𐑗𐑰𐑟 (𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑚𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑓𐑽𐑽 𐑸𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤). 550 ·𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑼𐑟 𐑝 ·𐑡𐑦𐑯𐑰𐑝𐑩. 10,800 𐑚𐑨𐑮𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑝 𐑚𐑽.

𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑑𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑑𐑱𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑸 𐑐𐑸𐑗𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑮𐑲 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑮𐑰𐑛𐑦𐑙; 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑴 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑒𐑱𐑕, 𐑣𐑬𐑧𐑝𐑼, 𐑢𐑺 𐑞 𐑮𐑰𐑛𐑼 𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑤𐑳𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑴𐑤 𐑐𐑲𐑐𐑕, 𐑚𐑨𐑮𐑩𐑤𐑟, 𐑒𐑢𐑹𐑑𐑕, 𐑯 𐑜𐑦𐑤𐑟 𐑝 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑡𐑦𐑯 𐑯 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑗𐑽.

𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑑𐑲𐑥, 𐑲 𐑛𐑦𐑝𐑴𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑛𐑱𐑟 𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑿𐑛𐑾𐑕 𐑛𐑲𐑡𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑚𐑽, 𐑚𐑰𐑓, 𐑯 𐑚𐑮𐑧𐑛, 𐑛𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑔𐑷𐑑𐑕 𐑢𐑻 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑩𐑡𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑑 𐑥𐑰, 𐑒𐑱𐑐𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑩 𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑯 ·𐑐𐑤𐑩𐑑𐑪𐑯𐑦𐑒 𐑨𐑐𐑤𐑦𐑒𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯; 𐑯, 𐑓𐑻𐑞𐑼𐑥𐑹, 𐑲 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑲𐑤𐑛 𐑕𐑳𐑐𐑤𐑦𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑦 𐑑𐑱𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑝 𐑥𐑲 𐑴𐑯, 𐑑𐑳𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑚𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑝 𐑕𐑑𐑪𐑒-𐑓𐑦𐑖, 𐑧𐑑𐑕, 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑿𐑥𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 ·𐑤𐑴 ·𐑛𐑳𐑗 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑽 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑱𐑯𐑗𐑩𐑯𐑑 ·𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑯𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑯 ·𐑕𐑐𐑦𐑑𐑕𐑚𐑼𐑜𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑼𐑦. 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕, 𐑞 𐑩𐑥𐑬𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑚𐑳𐑑𐑼, 𐑯 ·𐑑𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑩𐑤 𐑯 ·𐑤𐑱𐑛𐑩𐑯 𐑗𐑰𐑟 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑿𐑥𐑛, 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑟 𐑩𐑥𐑱𐑟𐑦𐑙. 𐑲 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑿𐑑 𐑦𐑑, 𐑞𐑴, 𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑯𐑨𐑗𐑼𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑳𐑙𐑒𐑗𐑵𐑩𐑕 𐑯𐑱𐑗𐑼𐑟, 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑮𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑛 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑥𐑹 𐑳𐑙𐑒𐑗𐑵𐑩𐑕 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑯𐑱𐑗𐑼 𐑝 𐑞𐑺 𐑝𐑴𐑒𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯, 𐑯 𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑲 𐑞𐑺 𐑐𐑼𐑕𐑿𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑺 𐑜𐑱𐑥 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑓𐑮𐑦𐑡𐑦𐑛 ·𐑐𐑴𐑤𐑼 ·𐑕𐑰𐑟, 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑒𐑴𐑕𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑 ·𐑧𐑕𐑒𐑦𐑥𐑴 𐑒𐑳𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑦 𐑢𐑺 𐑞 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑝𐑦𐑝𐑾𐑤 𐑯𐑱𐑑𐑦𐑝𐑟 𐑐𐑤𐑧𐑡 𐑰𐑗 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑦𐑯 𐑚𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑼𐑟 𐑝 𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯 𐑶𐑤.

𐑞 𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑝 𐑚𐑽, 𐑑𐑵, 𐑦𐑟 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑤𐑸𐑡, 10,800 𐑚𐑨𐑮𐑩𐑤𐑟. 𐑯𐑬, 𐑨𐑟 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑐𐑴𐑤𐑼 𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑼𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑰 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑖𐑹𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑼 𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑒𐑤𐑲𐑥𐑩𐑑, 𐑕𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑣𐑴𐑤 𐑒𐑮𐑵𐑟 𐑝 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑞𐑰𐑟 ·𐑛𐑳𐑗 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑥𐑧𐑯, 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑤𐑵𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑖𐑹𐑑 𐑝𐑶𐑦𐑡 𐑑 𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑐𐑦𐑑𐑕𐑚𐑼𐑜𐑩𐑯 𐑕𐑰, 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑰𐑛 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑥𐑳𐑯𐑔𐑕, 𐑕𐑱, 𐑯 𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑙 30 𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑑 𐑰𐑗 𐑝 𐑞𐑺 𐑓𐑤𐑰𐑑 𐑝 180 𐑕𐑱𐑤, 𐑢𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑝 5,400 ·𐑤𐑴 ·𐑛𐑳𐑗 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑷𐑤; 𐑞𐑺𐑓𐑹, 𐑲 𐑕𐑱, 𐑢𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑲𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑑𐑵 𐑚𐑨𐑮𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑝 𐑚𐑽 𐑐𐑻 𐑥𐑨𐑯, 𐑓 𐑩 𐑑𐑢𐑧𐑤𐑝 𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑕' 𐑩𐑤𐑬𐑩𐑯𐑕, 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑒𐑤𐑵𐑕𐑦𐑝 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑺 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑐𐑹𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑 550 ·𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑼𐑟 𐑝 𐑡𐑦𐑯. 𐑯𐑬, 𐑢𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑡𐑦𐑯 𐑯 𐑚𐑽 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑽𐑟, 𐑕𐑴 𐑓𐑳𐑛𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑨𐑟 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑓𐑨𐑯𐑕𐑦 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑯, 𐑢𐑻 𐑞 𐑮𐑲𐑑 𐑕𐑹𐑑 𐑝 𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑳𐑐 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑚𐑴𐑑'𐑕 𐑣𐑧𐑛, 𐑯 𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑱𐑥 𐑨𐑑 𐑓𐑤𐑲𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟; 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑕𐑰𐑥 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑚𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤. 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑞𐑱 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑱𐑥 𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑧𐑥, 𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑑 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑑𐑵. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑓𐑸 ·𐑯𐑹𐑔, 𐑚𐑰 𐑦𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑧𐑥𐑚𐑼𐑛, 𐑢𐑺 𐑚𐑽 𐑩𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑟 𐑢𐑧𐑤 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑑𐑿𐑖𐑩𐑯; 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑦𐑒𐑢𐑱𐑑𐑼, 𐑦𐑯 𐑬𐑼 𐑕𐑳𐑞𐑼𐑯 𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑼𐑦, 𐑚𐑽 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑚𐑰 𐑨𐑐𐑑 𐑑 𐑥𐑱𐑒 𐑞 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑽 𐑕𐑤𐑰𐑐𐑦 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑-𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑯 𐑚𐑵𐑟𐑦 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑴𐑑; 𐑯 𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑕 𐑤𐑪𐑕 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑿 𐑑 ·𐑯𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑑 𐑯 ·𐑯𐑿 ·𐑚𐑧𐑛𐑓𐑼𐑛.

𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑯𐑴 𐑥𐑹; 𐑦𐑯𐑳𐑓 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑑 𐑖𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑴𐑤𐑛 ·𐑛𐑳𐑗 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑼𐑟 𐑝 𐑑𐑵 𐑹 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑗𐑼𐑦𐑟 𐑩𐑜𐑴 𐑢𐑻 𐑣𐑲 𐑤𐑦𐑝𐑼𐑟; 𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑤𐑦𐑖 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑼𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑯𐑦𐑜𐑤𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑕𐑴 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑩𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑜𐑟𐑭𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑤. 𐑓, 𐑕𐑱 𐑞𐑱, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑒𐑮𐑵𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑩𐑯 𐑧𐑥𐑐𐑑𐑦 𐑖𐑦𐑐, 𐑦𐑓 𐑿 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑜𐑧𐑑 𐑯𐑳𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑧𐑑𐑼 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛, 𐑜𐑧𐑑 𐑩 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑛𐑦𐑯𐑼 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑦𐑑, 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑰𐑕𐑑. 𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑧𐑥𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑟 𐑞 𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑼.

·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 102. 𐑩 ·𐑚𐑬𐑼 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑸𐑕𐑩𐑕𐑲𐑛𐑟.

𐑣𐑦𐑞𐑼𐑑𐑵, 𐑦𐑯 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑝𐑤𐑦 𐑑𐑮𐑰𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑗𐑰𐑓𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑢𐑧𐑤𐑑 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑥𐑸𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑬𐑑𐑼 𐑨𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑; 𐑹 𐑕𐑧𐑐𐑼𐑩𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑛𐑰𐑑𐑱𐑤 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑓𐑿 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑽𐑽 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑒𐑗𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑓𐑰𐑗𐑼𐑟. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑑 𐑩 𐑤𐑸𐑡 𐑯 𐑔𐑳𐑮𐑴 𐑕𐑢𐑰𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑣𐑧𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑦𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑣𐑵𐑝𐑟 𐑥𐑰 𐑯𐑬 𐑑 𐑳𐑯𐑚𐑳𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑓𐑻𐑞𐑼, 𐑯 𐑳𐑯𐑑𐑨𐑜𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑐𐑶𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑴𐑟, 𐑳𐑯𐑚𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑜𐑸𐑑𐑼𐑟, 𐑯 𐑒𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑤𐑵𐑕 𐑞 𐑣𐑫𐑒𐑕 𐑯 𐑞 𐑲𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑡𐑶𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑼𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑴𐑯𐑟, 𐑕𐑧𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑿 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑳𐑤𐑑𐑦𐑥𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑥; 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑑 𐑕𐑱, 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑳𐑯𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑒𐑧𐑤𐑩𐑑𐑩𐑯.

𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑣𐑬 𐑯𐑬, ·𐑦𐑖𐑥𐑱𐑩𐑤? 𐑣𐑬 𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑑, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑿, 𐑩 𐑥𐑽 𐑹𐑟𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑼𐑦, 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑑 𐑯𐑴 𐑷𐑑 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑚𐑑𐑼𐑱𐑯𐑾𐑯 𐑐𐑸𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤? 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑧𐑮𐑫𐑛𐑲𐑑 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚, 𐑥𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑘𐑹 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯, 𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑝𐑼 𐑤𐑧𐑒𐑗𐑼𐑟 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑩𐑯𐑨𐑑𐑩𐑥𐑦 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑧𐑑𐑱𐑖𐑩; 𐑯 𐑚𐑲 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑐 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑤𐑩𐑕, 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑳𐑐 𐑩 𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑮𐑦𐑚 𐑓 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑦𐑚𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯? 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑯 𐑞𐑲𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓, ·𐑦𐑖𐑥𐑱𐑩𐑤. 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑿 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑩 𐑓𐑫𐑤-𐑜𐑮𐑴𐑯 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑪𐑯 𐑘𐑹 𐑛𐑧𐑒 𐑓 𐑦𐑜𐑟𐑨𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯, 𐑨𐑟 𐑩 𐑒𐑫𐑒 𐑛𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑟 𐑩 𐑮𐑴𐑕𐑑-𐑐𐑦𐑜? 𐑖𐑫𐑼𐑤𐑦 𐑯𐑪𐑑. 𐑩 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑦𐑑𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑿 𐑣𐑦𐑞𐑼𐑑𐑵 𐑚𐑰𐑯, ·𐑦𐑖𐑥𐑱𐑩𐑤; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑩 𐑒𐑺 𐑣𐑬 𐑿 𐑕𐑰𐑟 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑡 𐑝 ·𐑡𐑴𐑯𐑩 𐑩𐑤𐑴𐑯; 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑡 𐑝 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑹𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑡𐑶𐑕𐑑𐑕 𐑯 𐑚𐑰𐑥𐑟; 𐑞 𐑮𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼𐑟, 𐑮𐑦𐑡-𐑐𐑴𐑤, 𐑕𐑤𐑰𐑐𐑼𐑟, 𐑯 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼-𐑐𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑙𐑟, 𐑥𐑱𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑳𐑐 𐑞 𐑓𐑮𐑱𐑥-𐑢𐑻𐑒 𐑝 𐑤𐑩𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑔𐑩𐑯; 𐑯 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑝 𐑞 𐑑𐑨𐑤𐑴-𐑝𐑨𐑑𐑕, 𐑛𐑺𐑦-𐑮𐑵𐑥𐑟, 𐑚𐑳𐑑𐑼𐑦𐑟, 𐑯 𐑗𐑰𐑟𐑼𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑬𐑩𐑤𐑟.

𐑲 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑓𐑧𐑕, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑦𐑯𐑕 ·𐑡𐑴𐑯𐑩, 𐑓𐑿 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑓𐑸 𐑚𐑦𐑯𐑰𐑔 𐑞 𐑕𐑒𐑦𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑨𐑛𐑳𐑤𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑤; 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼𐑞𐑩𐑤𐑧𐑕, 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑚𐑤𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩𐑯 𐑪𐑐𐑼𐑑𐑿𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑧𐑒𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑗𐑼. 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑲 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑪𐑙𐑛 𐑑, 𐑩 𐑕𐑥𐑷𐑤 𐑒𐑳𐑚 ·𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑕 𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑦 𐑣𐑶𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑑 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑒 𐑓 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑴𐑒 𐑹 𐑚𐑨𐑜, 𐑑 𐑥𐑱𐑒 𐑖𐑰𐑞𐑟 𐑓 𐑞 𐑚𐑸𐑚𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑟, 𐑯 𐑓 𐑞 𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟. 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒 𐑿 𐑲 𐑤𐑧𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑗𐑭𐑯𐑕 𐑜𐑴, 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑 𐑿𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑲 𐑚𐑴𐑑-𐑣𐑨𐑗𐑩𐑑 𐑯 𐑡𐑨𐑒-𐑯𐑲𐑓, 𐑯 𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑕𐑰𐑤 𐑯 𐑮𐑰𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑘𐑳𐑙 𐑒𐑳𐑚?

𐑯 𐑨𐑟 𐑓 𐑥𐑲 𐑦𐑜𐑟𐑨𐑒𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑤𐑦𐑡 𐑝 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑤𐑩𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑔𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑡𐑲𐑜𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑒, 𐑓𐑫𐑤 𐑜𐑮𐑴𐑯 𐑛𐑦𐑝𐑧𐑤𐑩𐑐𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑, 𐑓 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑮𐑺 𐑯𐑪𐑤𐑦𐑡 𐑲 𐑨𐑥 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑧𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑑 𐑥𐑲 𐑤𐑱𐑑 𐑮𐑶𐑩𐑤 𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑯𐑛 ·𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑒𐑢𐑴, 𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑝 ·𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑒𐑱, 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑸𐑕𐑩𐑕𐑲𐑛𐑟. 𐑓 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑨𐑑 ·𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑒𐑱, 𐑘𐑽𐑟 𐑩𐑜𐑴, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑩𐑑𐑨𐑗𐑑 𐑑 𐑞 𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑛𐑦𐑙-𐑖𐑦𐑐 ·𐑛𐑱 𐑝 ·𐑨𐑤𐑜𐑽𐑟, 𐑲 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑑 𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑐𐑸𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑸𐑕𐑩𐑕𐑲𐑛𐑾𐑯 𐑣𐑪𐑤𐑦𐑛𐑱𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑤𐑹𐑛 𐑝 ·𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑒𐑱, 𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑲𐑼𐑛 𐑐𐑭𐑥 𐑝𐑦𐑤𐑩 𐑨𐑑 ·𐑐𐑿𐑐𐑤𐑩; 𐑩 𐑕𐑰-𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑜𐑤𐑧𐑯 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑓𐑸 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑬𐑼 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑼𐑟 𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑛 ·𐑚𐑨𐑥𐑚𐑵-·𐑑𐑬𐑯, 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤.

𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑓𐑲𐑯 𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑟, 𐑥𐑲 𐑮𐑶𐑩𐑤 𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑯𐑛 ·𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑒𐑢𐑴, 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑜𐑦𐑓𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑛𐑦𐑝𐑬𐑑 𐑤𐑳𐑝 𐑓 𐑷𐑤 𐑥𐑨𐑑𐑼𐑟 𐑝 𐑚𐑸𐑚𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑒 ·𐑝𐑻𐑑𐑵, 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑮𐑷𐑑 𐑑𐑩𐑜𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑦𐑯 ·𐑐𐑿𐑐𐑤𐑩 𐑢𐑪𐑑𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑮𐑺 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑞 𐑥𐑹 𐑦𐑯𐑡𐑰𐑯𐑾𐑕 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑰𐑐𐑩𐑤 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑧𐑯𐑑; 𐑗𐑰𐑓𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑸𐑝𐑛 𐑢𐑫𐑛𐑟 𐑝 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑛𐑦𐑝𐑲𐑕𐑩𐑟, 𐑗𐑦𐑟𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑖𐑧𐑤𐑟, 𐑦𐑯𐑤𐑱𐑛 𐑕𐑐𐑽𐑟, 𐑒𐑪𐑕𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑨𐑛𐑩𐑤𐑟, 𐑨𐑮𐑩𐑥𐑨𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑵𐑟; 𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑚𐑿𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑢𐑪𐑑𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑯𐑨𐑗𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑟, 𐑞 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼-𐑓𐑮𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛, 𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑚𐑿𐑑-𐑮𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑱𐑝𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑒𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑖𐑹𐑟.

𐑗𐑰𐑓 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑤𐑨𐑑𐑼 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 ·𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑢𐑦𐑗, 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑩𐑯 𐑳𐑯𐑿𐑠𐑵𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑮𐑱𐑡𐑦𐑙 𐑜𐑱𐑤, 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑛𐑧𐑛 𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑩 𐑒𐑴𐑒𐑴-𐑯𐑳𐑑 𐑑𐑮𐑰, 𐑣𐑵𐑟 𐑐𐑤𐑵𐑥𐑦𐑡-𐑤𐑲𐑒, 𐑑𐑳𐑓𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑛𐑮𐑵𐑐𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑝𐑻𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑡𐑧𐑑. 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑞 𐑝𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑑 𐑝 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑓𐑨𐑞𐑩𐑥-𐑛𐑰𐑐 𐑦𐑯𐑓𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑦𐑙𐑟, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑯𐑟 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑛𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑛𐑮𐑲 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑯, 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑒𐑧𐑤𐑩𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑒𐑺𐑓𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑕𐑐𐑹𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑳𐑐 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑿𐑐𐑤𐑩 𐑜𐑤𐑧𐑯, 𐑢𐑺 𐑩 𐑜𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑑𐑧𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑤𐑹𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑭𐑥𐑟 𐑯𐑬 𐑖𐑧𐑤𐑑𐑼𐑛 𐑦𐑑.

𐑞 𐑮𐑦𐑚𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑣𐑳𐑙 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑑𐑮𐑴𐑓𐑦𐑟; 𐑞 𐑝𐑻𐑑𐑦𐑚𐑮𐑦 𐑢𐑻 𐑒𐑸𐑝𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 ·𐑸𐑕𐑩𐑕𐑲𐑛𐑾𐑯 𐑨𐑯𐑩𐑤𐑟, 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡 𐑣𐑲𐑮𐑩𐑜𐑤𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑒𐑕; 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑒𐑳𐑤, 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑰𐑕𐑑𐑕 𐑒𐑧𐑐𐑑 𐑳𐑐 𐑩𐑯 𐑳𐑯𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑢𐑦𐑖𐑑 𐑨𐑮𐑩𐑥𐑨𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑓𐑤𐑱𐑥, 𐑕𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑓𐑹𐑔 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑝𐑱𐑐𐑼𐑦 𐑕𐑐𐑬𐑑; 𐑢𐑲𐑤, 𐑕𐑩𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑩 𐑚𐑬, 𐑞 𐑑𐑼𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑒 𐑤𐑴𐑼 𐑡𐑷 𐑝𐑲𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑑𐑰𐑟, 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑞 𐑣𐑺-𐑣𐑳𐑙 𐑕𐑹𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑴 𐑩𐑓𐑮𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑛 ·𐑛𐑨𐑥𐑩𐑒𐑤𐑰𐑟.

𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑕 𐑕𐑲𐑑. 𐑞 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑯 𐑨𐑟 𐑥𐑪𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑲𐑕𐑦 ·𐑜𐑤𐑧𐑯; 𐑞 𐑑𐑮𐑰𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑫𐑛 𐑣𐑲 𐑯 𐑣𐑷𐑑𐑦, 𐑓𐑰𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑺 𐑤𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑨𐑐; 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑳𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑾𐑕 𐑻𐑔 𐑚𐑦𐑯𐑰𐑔 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑨𐑟 𐑩 𐑢𐑰𐑝𐑼'𐑟 𐑤𐑵𐑥, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑜𐑹𐑡𐑩𐑕 𐑒𐑸𐑐𐑩𐑑 𐑪𐑯 𐑦𐑑, 𐑢𐑺𐑪𐑝 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛-𐑝𐑲𐑯 𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑓𐑹𐑥𐑛 𐑞 𐑢𐑹𐑐 𐑯 𐑢𐑵𐑓, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑤𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑤𐑬𐑼𐑟 𐑞 𐑓𐑦𐑜𐑼𐑟. 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑑𐑮𐑰𐑟, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑺 𐑤𐑱𐑛𐑩𐑯 𐑚𐑮𐑭𐑯𐑗𐑩𐑟; 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑖𐑮𐑳𐑚𐑟, 𐑯 𐑓𐑻𐑯𐑟, 𐑯 𐑜𐑮𐑭𐑕𐑩𐑟; 𐑞 𐑥𐑧𐑕𐑦𐑡-𐑒𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑦𐑙 𐑺; 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑳𐑯𐑕𐑰𐑕𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑢𐑻 𐑨𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑝. 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑞 𐑤𐑱𐑕𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑤𐑰𐑝𐑟, 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑯 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑩 𐑓𐑤𐑲𐑦𐑙 𐑖𐑳𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑰𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑳𐑯𐑢𐑽𐑦𐑛 𐑝𐑻𐑡𐑼. 𐑴, 𐑚𐑦𐑟𐑦 𐑢𐑰𐑝𐑼! 𐑳𐑯𐑕𐑰𐑯 𐑢𐑰𐑝𐑼!—𐑐𐑷𐑟!—𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑢𐑻𐑛!—𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑼 𐑓𐑤𐑴𐑟 𐑞 𐑓𐑨𐑚𐑮𐑦𐑒? 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑐𐑨𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑥𐑱 𐑦𐑑 𐑛𐑧𐑒? 𐑢𐑺𐑓𐑹 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑕𐑰𐑕𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑑𐑶𐑤𐑦𐑙𐑟? 𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑒, 𐑢𐑰𐑝𐑼!—𐑕𐑑𐑱 𐑞𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛!—𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑕𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑻𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞𐑰! 𐑯𐑱—𐑞 𐑖𐑳𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑓𐑤𐑲𐑟—𐑞 𐑓𐑦𐑜𐑼𐑟 𐑓𐑤𐑴𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑓𐑹𐑔 𐑞 𐑤𐑵𐑥; 𐑞 𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑑-𐑮𐑳𐑖𐑦𐑙 𐑒𐑸𐑐𐑩𐑑 𐑓 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑕𐑤𐑲𐑛𐑟 𐑩𐑢𐑱. 𐑞 𐑢𐑰𐑝𐑼-𐑜𐑪𐑛, 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑰𐑝𐑟; 𐑯 𐑚𐑲 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑰𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑛𐑧𐑓𐑩𐑯𐑛, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑽𐑟 𐑯𐑴 𐑥𐑹𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑝𐑶𐑕; 𐑯 𐑚𐑲 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑳𐑥𐑦𐑙, 𐑢𐑰, 𐑑𐑵, 𐑣𐑵 𐑤𐑫𐑒 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑤𐑵𐑥 𐑸 𐑛𐑧𐑓𐑩𐑯𐑛; 𐑯 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑢𐑰 𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑱𐑐 𐑦𐑑 𐑖𐑨𐑤 𐑢𐑰 𐑣𐑽 𐑞 𐑔𐑬𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑝𐑶𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑒 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑦𐑑. 𐑓 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑕𐑴 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑥𐑩𐑑𐑽𐑾𐑤 𐑓𐑨𐑒𐑑𐑼𐑦𐑟. 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑴𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑻𐑛𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑸 𐑦𐑯𐑷𐑛𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑞 𐑓𐑤𐑲𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑐𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑤𐑟; 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑢𐑻𐑛𐑟 𐑸 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑣𐑻𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑 𐑞 𐑢𐑷𐑤𐑟, 𐑚𐑻𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑴𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑒𐑱𐑕𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕. 𐑞𐑺𐑚𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑝𐑦𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑛𐑦𐑑𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑛. 𐑭, 𐑥𐑹𐑑𐑩𐑤! 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑚𐑰 𐑣𐑰𐑛𐑓𐑩𐑤; 𐑓 𐑕𐑴, 𐑦𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑛𐑦𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛'𐑟 𐑤𐑵𐑥, 𐑞𐑲 𐑕𐑳𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑥𐑱 𐑚𐑰 𐑴𐑝𐑼𐑣𐑻𐑛 𐑩𐑓𐑸.

𐑯𐑬, 𐑩𐑥𐑦𐑛 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑯, 𐑤𐑲𐑓-𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑤𐑵𐑥 𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑 ·𐑸𐑕𐑩𐑕𐑲𐑛𐑾𐑯 𐑢𐑫𐑛, 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑, 𐑢𐑲𐑑, 𐑢𐑻𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑑 𐑕𐑒𐑧𐑤𐑩𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑤𐑱 𐑤𐑬𐑯𐑡𐑦𐑙—𐑩 𐑡𐑲𐑜𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑲𐑛𐑩𐑤𐑼! 𐑘𐑧𐑑, 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑧𐑝𐑼-𐑢𐑴𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑝𐑻𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑢𐑹𐑐 𐑯 𐑢𐑵𐑓 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑥𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑑 𐑯 𐑣𐑳𐑥𐑛 𐑼𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑞 𐑥𐑲𐑑𐑦 𐑲𐑛𐑩𐑤𐑼 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑞 𐑒𐑳𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑰𐑝𐑼; 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑷𐑤 𐑢𐑴𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑝𐑲𐑯𐑟; 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑥𐑳𐑯𐑔 𐑩𐑕𐑿𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑯𐑼, 𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑖𐑼 𐑝𐑻𐑡𐑼; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑩 𐑕𐑒𐑧𐑤𐑩𐑑𐑩𐑯. 𐑤𐑲𐑓 𐑓𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑩𐑛 ·𐑛𐑧𐑔; ·𐑛𐑧𐑔 𐑑𐑮𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑕𐑑 ·𐑤𐑲𐑓; 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑦𐑥 𐑜𐑪𐑛 𐑢𐑲𐑝𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑿𐑔𐑓𐑩𐑤 ·𐑤𐑲𐑓, 𐑯 𐑚𐑦𐑜𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑒𐑻𐑤𐑦-𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑜𐑤𐑹𐑦𐑟.

𐑯𐑬, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑮𐑶𐑩𐑤 ·𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑒𐑢𐑴 𐑲 𐑝𐑦𐑟𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑕 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑯 𐑕𐑷 𐑞 𐑕𐑒𐑳𐑤 𐑩𐑯 𐑷𐑤𐑑𐑼, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑸𐑑𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑥𐑴𐑒 𐑩𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑢𐑺 𐑞 𐑮𐑾𐑤 𐑡𐑧𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑦𐑖𐑿𐑛, 𐑲 𐑥𐑸𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑮𐑦𐑜𐑸𐑛 𐑩 𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑩𐑤 𐑨𐑟 𐑩𐑯 𐑪𐑚𐑡𐑧𐑒𐑑 𐑝 ·𐑝𐑻𐑑𐑵. 𐑣𐑰 𐑤𐑭𐑓𐑑. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑥𐑹 𐑲 𐑥𐑸𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑰𐑕𐑑𐑕 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑕𐑢𐑺 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑥𐑴𐑒𐑦 𐑡𐑧𐑑 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑿𐑦𐑯. 𐑑 𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑴 𐑲 𐑐𐑱𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑕𐑒𐑧𐑤𐑩𐑑𐑩𐑯—𐑚𐑮𐑳𐑖𐑑 𐑞 𐑝𐑲𐑯𐑟 𐑩𐑕𐑲𐑛—𐑚𐑮𐑴𐑒 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑞 𐑮𐑦𐑚𐑟—𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑚𐑷𐑤 𐑝 ·𐑸𐑕𐑩𐑕𐑲𐑛𐑾𐑯 𐑑𐑢𐑲𐑯, 𐑢𐑪𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑛, 𐑧𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑩𐑥𐑦𐑛 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑢𐑲𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙, 𐑖𐑱𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑒𐑪𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑱𐑛𐑟 𐑯 𐑸𐑚𐑼𐑟. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑕𐑵𐑯 𐑥𐑲 𐑤𐑲𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑬𐑑; 𐑯 𐑓𐑪𐑤𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑑 𐑚𐑨𐑒, 𐑲 𐑦𐑥𐑻𐑡𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑴𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑺 𐑲 𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑛. 𐑲 𐑕𐑷 𐑯𐑴 𐑤𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑦𐑯; 𐑯𐑷𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞𐑺 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑚𐑴𐑯𐑟.

𐑒𐑳𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑰 𐑩 𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑯 𐑥𐑧𐑠𐑼𐑦𐑙-𐑮𐑪𐑛, 𐑲 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑕 𐑥𐑹 𐑛𐑲𐑝𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑒𐑧𐑤𐑩𐑑𐑩𐑯. 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞𐑺 𐑨𐑮𐑴-𐑕𐑤𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑒𐑳𐑤, 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑰𐑕𐑑𐑕 𐑐𐑼𐑕𐑰𐑝𐑛 𐑥𐑰 𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑨𐑤𐑑𐑦𐑑𐑿𐑛 𐑝 𐑞 𐑓𐑲𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑮𐑦𐑚, “𐑣𐑬 𐑯𐑬!” 𐑞𐑱 𐑖𐑬𐑑𐑩𐑛; “·𐑛𐑺𐑕𐑑 𐑞𐑬 𐑥𐑧𐑠𐑼 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑬𐑼 𐑜𐑪𐑛! 𐑞𐑨𐑑'𐑕 𐑓 𐑳𐑕.” “𐑲, 𐑐𐑮𐑰𐑕𐑑𐑕—𐑢𐑧𐑤, 𐑣𐑬 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑛𐑵 𐑘𐑰 𐑥𐑱𐑒 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑞𐑧𐑯?” 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑣𐑽𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑩 𐑓𐑽𐑕 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑮𐑴𐑟 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑞𐑧𐑥, 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑰𐑑 𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑗𐑩𐑟; 𐑞𐑱 𐑒𐑮𐑨𐑒𐑑 𐑰𐑗 𐑳𐑞𐑼'𐑟 𐑕𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞𐑺 𐑘𐑸𐑛-𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑕—𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑕𐑒𐑳𐑤 𐑧𐑒𐑴𐑛—𐑯 𐑕𐑰𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑳𐑒𐑦 𐑗𐑭𐑯𐑕, 𐑲 𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑒𐑤𐑵𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑥𐑲 𐑴𐑯 𐑩𐑛𐑥𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑕.

𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑩𐑛𐑥𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑲 𐑯𐑬 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑐𐑴𐑟 𐑑 𐑕𐑧𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑿. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑, 𐑚𐑰 𐑦𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑹𐑛𐑩𐑛, 𐑞𐑨𐑑, 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑥𐑨𐑑𐑼, 𐑲 𐑨𐑥 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑰 𐑑 𐑳𐑑𐑼 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑓𐑨𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑛 𐑥𐑧𐑠𐑼𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑲 𐑐𐑤𐑰𐑟. 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑪𐑟 𐑞𐑺 𐑸 𐑕𐑒𐑧𐑤𐑩𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑷𐑔𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑟 𐑿 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑮𐑦𐑓𐑻 𐑑, 𐑑 𐑑𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑥𐑲 𐑨𐑒𐑘𐑼𐑩𐑕𐑦. 𐑞𐑺 𐑦𐑟 𐑩 ·𐑤𐑩𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑔𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑒 ·𐑥𐑿𐑟𐑾𐑥, 𐑞𐑱 𐑑𐑧𐑤 𐑥𐑰, 𐑦𐑯 ·𐑣𐑳𐑤, ·𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛, 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑐𐑹𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑒𐑳𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑦, 𐑢𐑺 𐑞𐑱 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑓𐑲𐑯 𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑓𐑦𐑯-𐑚𐑨𐑒𐑕 𐑯 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟. 𐑤𐑲𐑒𐑢𐑲𐑟, 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑣𐑻𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑥𐑿𐑟𐑾𐑥 𐑝 ·𐑥𐑨𐑯𐑗𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑼, 𐑦𐑯 ·𐑯𐑿 ·𐑣𐑨𐑥𐑐𐑖𐑼, 𐑞𐑱 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑐𐑮𐑲𐑩𐑑𐑼𐑟 𐑒𐑷𐑤 “𐑞 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑻𐑓𐑦𐑒𐑑 𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑩 ·𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑯𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑹 ·𐑮𐑦𐑝𐑼 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑿𐑯𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑛 ·𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑑𐑕.” 𐑥𐑹𐑴𐑝𐑼, 𐑨𐑑 𐑩 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕 𐑦𐑯 ·𐑘𐑹𐑒𐑖𐑼, ·𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛, ·𐑚𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑯 ·𐑒𐑳𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑚𐑲 𐑯𐑱𐑥, 𐑩 𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑯 ·𐑕𐑻 ·𐑒𐑤𐑦𐑓𐑼𐑛 ·𐑒𐑳𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑩𐑟𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑒𐑧𐑤𐑩𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑩 ·𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑝 𐑥𐑪𐑛𐑼𐑩𐑑 𐑕𐑲𐑟, 𐑚𐑲 𐑯𐑴 𐑥𐑰𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑓𐑫𐑤-𐑜𐑮𐑴𐑯 𐑥𐑨𐑜𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑿𐑛 𐑝 𐑥𐑲 𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑯𐑛 ·𐑒𐑦𐑙 ·𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑒𐑢𐑴'𐑟.

𐑦𐑯 𐑚𐑴𐑔 𐑒𐑱𐑕𐑩𐑟, 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑑𐑵 𐑕𐑒𐑧𐑤𐑩𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑪𐑙𐑛, 𐑢𐑻 𐑼𐑦𐑡𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑤𐑱𐑥𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑞𐑺 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑐𐑮𐑲𐑩𐑑𐑼𐑟 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑕𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑤𐑼 𐑜𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑟. 𐑒𐑦𐑙 ·𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑒𐑢𐑴 𐑕𐑰𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑪𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑑; 𐑯 ·𐑕𐑻 ·𐑒𐑤𐑦𐑓𐑼𐑛, 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑪𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑤𐑹𐑛 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑯𐑘𐑼𐑦𐑟 𐑝 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑐𐑸𐑑𐑕. 𐑕𐑻 ·𐑒𐑤𐑦𐑓𐑼𐑛'𐑟 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑸𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑔𐑮𐑵𐑬𐑑; 𐑕𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑, 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑗𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑝 𐑛𐑮𐑷𐑼𐑟, 𐑿 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑴𐑐𐑩𐑯 𐑯 𐑖𐑳𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑦𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑴𐑯𐑦 𐑒𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑟—𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑛 𐑬𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑮𐑦𐑚𐑟 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑡𐑲𐑜𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑓𐑨𐑯—𐑯 𐑕𐑢𐑦𐑙 𐑷𐑤 𐑛𐑱 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑤𐑴𐑼 𐑡𐑷. 𐑤𐑪𐑒𐑕 𐑸 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑐𐑫𐑑 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑐-𐑛𐑹𐑟 𐑯 𐑖𐑳𐑑𐑼𐑟; 𐑯 𐑩 𐑓𐑫𐑑𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑖𐑴 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑓𐑿𐑗𐑼 𐑝𐑦𐑟𐑦𐑑𐑼𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑚𐑳𐑯𐑗 𐑝 𐑒𐑰𐑟 𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑲𐑛. 𐑕𐑻 ·𐑒𐑤𐑦𐑓𐑼𐑛 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑕 𐑝 𐑗𐑸𐑡𐑦𐑙 𐑑𐑳𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑓 𐑩 𐑐𐑰𐑐 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑢𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑜𐑨𐑤𐑼𐑦 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑲𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑒𐑪𐑤𐑩𐑥; 𐑔𐑮𐑧𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑑 𐑣𐑽 𐑞 𐑧𐑒𐑴 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑣𐑪𐑤𐑴 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑧𐑮𐑩𐑚𐑧𐑤𐑩𐑥; 𐑯 𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑓 𐑞 𐑳𐑯𐑮𐑲𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑝𐑿 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑛.

𐑞 𐑕𐑒𐑧𐑤𐑩𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑛𐑦𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑲 𐑖𐑨𐑤 𐑯𐑬 𐑐𐑮𐑴𐑕𐑰𐑛 𐑑 𐑕𐑧𐑑 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑸 𐑒𐑪𐑐𐑦𐑛 𐑝𐑼𐑚𐑱𐑑𐑦𐑥 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑥𐑲 𐑮𐑲𐑑 𐑸𐑥, 𐑢𐑺 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑑𐑩𐑑𐑵𐑛; 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑲 𐑢𐑲𐑤𐑛 𐑢𐑪𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑐𐑽𐑾𐑛, 𐑞𐑺 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑴 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑘𐑫𐑼 𐑢𐑱 𐑝 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑻𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑝𐑨𐑤𐑿𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑑𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑕. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑲 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑒𐑮𐑬𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑓 𐑕𐑐𐑱𐑕, 𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑖𐑑 𐑞 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑐𐑸𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑥𐑲 𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦 𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑱𐑯 𐑩 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑙𐑒 𐑐𐑱𐑡 𐑓 𐑩 𐑐𐑴𐑩𐑥 𐑲 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑴𐑟𐑦𐑙—𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑰𐑕𐑑, 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑳𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑑𐑵𐑛 𐑐𐑸𐑑𐑕 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑱𐑯—𐑲 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑥𐑲𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑪𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑗𐑩𐑟; 𐑯𐑹, 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑰𐑛, 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑗𐑩𐑟 𐑨𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑼 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑩 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑡𐑰𐑯𐑾𐑤 𐑩𐑛𐑥𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤.

·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 103. 𐑥𐑧𐑠𐑼𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤'𐑟 ·𐑕𐑒𐑧𐑤𐑩𐑑𐑩𐑯.

𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕, 𐑲 𐑢𐑦𐑖 𐑑 𐑤𐑱 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑿 𐑩 𐑐𐑼𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑼, 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑑𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑, 𐑑𐑳𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑤𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑳𐑤𐑒 𐑝 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑤𐑩𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑔𐑩𐑯, 𐑣𐑵𐑟 𐑕𐑒𐑧𐑤𐑩𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑰 𐑸 𐑚𐑮𐑰𐑓𐑤𐑦 𐑑 𐑦𐑜𐑟𐑦𐑚𐑦𐑑. 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩 𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑑𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑥𐑱 𐑐𐑮𐑵𐑝 𐑿𐑕𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑣𐑽.

𐑩𐑒𐑹𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑩 𐑒𐑺𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑒𐑨𐑤𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑥𐑱𐑛, 𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑲 𐑐𐑸𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑱𐑕 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 ·𐑕𐑒𐑹𐑟𐑚𐑦'𐑟 𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑥𐑩𐑑, 𐑝 𐑕𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑦 𐑑𐑳𐑯𐑟 𐑓 𐑞 𐑤𐑸𐑡𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑲𐑟𐑛 ·𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑯𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑝 𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑦 𐑓𐑰𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑤𐑧𐑙𐑔; 𐑩𐑒𐑹𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑥𐑲 𐑒𐑺𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑒𐑨𐑤𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯, 𐑲 𐑕𐑱, 𐑩 ·𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑝 𐑞 𐑤𐑸𐑡𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑥𐑨𐑜𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑿𐑛, 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑢𐑰𐑯 𐑱𐑑𐑦-𐑓𐑲𐑝 𐑯 𐑯𐑲𐑯𐑑𐑦 𐑓𐑰𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑤𐑧𐑙𐑔, 𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑤𐑧𐑕 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑓𐑹𐑑𐑦 𐑓𐑰𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑓𐑫𐑤𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑼𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑓𐑼𐑩𐑯𐑕, 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑢𐑱 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑰𐑕𐑑 𐑯𐑲𐑯𐑑𐑦 𐑑𐑳𐑯𐑟; 𐑕𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑, 𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑔𐑻𐑑𐑰𐑯 𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑑 𐑩 𐑑𐑳𐑯, 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑼𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑬𐑑𐑢𐑱 𐑞 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑚𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑐𐑪𐑐𐑿𐑤𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑩 𐑣𐑴𐑤 𐑝𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑡 𐑝 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑔𐑬𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑣𐑨𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕.

𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒 𐑿 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑟, 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑘𐑴𐑒𐑑 𐑒𐑨𐑑𐑩𐑤, 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑚𐑰 𐑐𐑫𐑑 𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑤𐑩𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑔𐑩𐑯, 𐑑 𐑥𐑱𐑒 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑨𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑚𐑳𐑡 𐑑 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟𐑥𐑩𐑯'𐑟 𐑦𐑥𐑨𐑡𐑦𐑯𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯?

𐑣𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑷𐑤𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑦 𐑦𐑯 𐑝𐑺𐑾𐑕 𐑢𐑱𐑟 𐑐𐑫𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑿 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑒𐑳𐑤, 𐑕𐑐𐑬𐑑-𐑣𐑴𐑤, 𐑡𐑷, 𐑑𐑰𐑔, 𐑑𐑱𐑤, 𐑓𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑛, 𐑓𐑦𐑯𐑟, 𐑯 𐑛𐑲𐑝𐑼𐑟 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑐𐑸𐑑𐑕, 𐑲 𐑖𐑨𐑤 𐑯𐑬 𐑕𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑶𐑯𐑑 𐑬𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑩𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑚𐑳𐑤𐑒 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑳𐑯𐑩𐑚𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑴𐑯𐑟. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑕𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑒𐑳𐑤 𐑦𐑥𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑕𐑴 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑤𐑸𐑡 𐑩 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑐𐑹𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑲𐑼 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑒𐑧𐑤𐑩𐑑𐑩𐑯; 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑲 𐑓𐑸 𐑞 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑦𐑒𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑐𐑸𐑑; 𐑯 𐑨𐑟 𐑯𐑳𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑟 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑰𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼, 𐑿 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑓𐑱𐑤 𐑑 𐑒𐑨𐑮𐑦 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑘𐑹 𐑥𐑲𐑯𐑛, 𐑹 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑘𐑹 𐑸𐑥, 𐑨𐑟 𐑢𐑰 𐑐𐑮𐑴𐑕𐑰𐑛, 𐑳𐑞𐑼𐑢𐑲𐑟 𐑿 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑜𐑱𐑯 𐑩 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑰𐑑 𐑯𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑒𐑗𐑼 𐑢𐑰 𐑸 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑑 𐑝𐑿.

𐑦𐑯 𐑤𐑧𐑙𐑔, 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤'𐑟 𐑕𐑒𐑧𐑤𐑩𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑨𐑑 ·𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑒𐑱 𐑥𐑧𐑠𐑼𐑛 𐑕𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑦-𐑑𐑵 𐑓𐑰𐑑; 𐑕𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑓𐑫𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑯 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑤𐑲𐑓, 𐑣𐑰 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑯𐑲𐑯𐑑𐑦 𐑓𐑰𐑑 𐑤𐑪𐑙; 𐑓 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑞 𐑕𐑒𐑧𐑤𐑩𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑤𐑵𐑟𐑩𐑟 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑓𐑦𐑓𐑔 𐑦𐑯 𐑤𐑧𐑙𐑔 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑺𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑤𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦. 𐑝 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑕𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑦-𐑑𐑵 𐑓𐑰𐑑, 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑒𐑳𐑤 𐑯 𐑡𐑷 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑮𐑲𐑟𐑛 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑑𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑦 𐑓𐑰𐑑, 𐑤𐑰𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑓𐑦𐑓𐑑𐑦 𐑓𐑰𐑑 𐑝 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑯 𐑚𐑨𐑒-𐑚𐑴𐑯. 𐑩𐑑𐑨𐑗𐑑 𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑚𐑨𐑒-𐑚𐑴𐑯, 𐑓 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑤𐑧𐑕 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑩 𐑔𐑻𐑛 𐑝 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑤𐑧𐑙𐑔, 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞 𐑥𐑲𐑑𐑦 𐑕𐑻𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑼 𐑚𐑭𐑕𐑒𐑩𐑑 𐑝 𐑮𐑦𐑚𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑕 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑤𐑴𐑟𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑝𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑟.

𐑑 𐑥𐑰 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑝𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑲𐑝𐑼𐑦-𐑮𐑦𐑚𐑛 𐑗𐑧𐑕𐑑, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑤𐑪𐑙, 𐑳𐑯𐑮𐑦𐑤𐑰𐑝𐑛 𐑕𐑐𐑲𐑯, 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑸 𐑩𐑢𐑱 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑤𐑲𐑯, 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑩 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑧𐑥𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑞 𐑣𐑳𐑤 𐑝 𐑩 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑯𐑿-𐑤𐑱𐑛 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑪𐑒𐑕, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑑𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑦 𐑝 𐑣𐑻 𐑯𐑱𐑒𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑬-𐑮𐑦𐑚𐑟 𐑸 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑛, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑒𐑰𐑤 𐑦𐑟 𐑳𐑞𐑼𐑢𐑲𐑟, 𐑓 𐑞 𐑑𐑲𐑥, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑩 𐑤𐑪𐑙, 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑑𐑦𐑥𐑚𐑼.

𐑞 𐑮𐑦𐑚𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑑𐑧𐑯 𐑪𐑯 𐑩 𐑕𐑲𐑛. 𐑞 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑, 𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑜𐑦𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑯𐑧𐑒, 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑽𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑕 𐑓𐑰𐑑 𐑤𐑪𐑙; 𐑞 𐑕𐑧𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑛, 𐑔𐑻𐑛, 𐑯 𐑓𐑹𐑔 𐑢𐑻 𐑰𐑗 𐑕𐑩𐑒𐑕𐑧𐑕𐑦𐑝𐑤𐑦 𐑤𐑪𐑙𐑜𐑼, 𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑿 𐑒𐑱𐑥 𐑑 𐑞 𐑒𐑤𐑲𐑥𐑨𐑒𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑓𐑦𐑓𐑔, 𐑹 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑥𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑤 𐑮𐑦𐑚𐑟, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑥𐑧𐑠𐑼𐑛 𐑱𐑑 𐑓𐑰𐑑 𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑦𐑯𐑗𐑩𐑟. 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑐𐑸𐑑, 𐑞 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑱𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑮𐑦𐑚𐑟 𐑛𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑖𐑑, 𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑞 𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑔 𐑯 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑐𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑓𐑲𐑝 𐑓𐑰𐑑 𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑦𐑯𐑗𐑩𐑟. 𐑦𐑯 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑔𐑦𐑒𐑯𐑩𐑕, 𐑞𐑱 𐑷𐑤 𐑚𐑹 𐑩 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑪𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑤𐑧𐑙𐑔. 𐑞 𐑥𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑤 𐑮𐑦𐑚𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑞 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑸𐑗𐑑. 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑸𐑕𐑩𐑕𐑲𐑛𐑟 𐑞𐑱 𐑸 𐑿𐑟𐑛 𐑓 𐑚𐑰𐑥𐑟 𐑢𐑺𐑪𐑯 𐑑 𐑤𐑱 𐑓𐑫𐑑𐑐𐑭𐑔 𐑚𐑮𐑦𐑡𐑩𐑟 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑕𐑥𐑷𐑤 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑰𐑥𐑟.

𐑦𐑯 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑮𐑦𐑚𐑟, 𐑲 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑒 𐑩𐑯𐑿 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑕𐑻𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑕, 𐑕𐑴 𐑝𐑺𐑾𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑰𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑚𐑫𐑒, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑒𐑧𐑤𐑩𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑲 𐑯𐑴 𐑥𐑰𐑯𐑟 𐑞 𐑥𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑓𐑹𐑥. 𐑞 𐑤𐑸𐑡𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑒𐑱 𐑮𐑦𐑚𐑟, 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑥𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑟, 𐑪𐑒𐑿𐑐𐑲𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑐𐑸𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑓𐑦𐑖 𐑢𐑦𐑗, 𐑦𐑯 𐑤𐑲𐑓, 𐑦𐑟 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑛𐑧𐑐𐑔. 𐑯𐑬, 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑛𐑧𐑐𐑔 𐑝 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦 𐑝 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑐𐑼𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑼 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑰𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑰𐑯 𐑓𐑰𐑑; 𐑢𐑺𐑨𐑟, 𐑞 𐑒𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑪𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑮𐑦𐑚 𐑥𐑧𐑠𐑼𐑛 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑥𐑹 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑱𐑑 𐑓𐑰𐑑. 𐑕𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑮𐑦𐑚 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑝𐑱𐑛 𐑣𐑭𐑓 𐑝 𐑞 𐑑𐑮𐑵 𐑯𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑤𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑨𐑜𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑿𐑛 𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑐𐑸𐑑. 𐑚𐑦𐑕𐑲𐑛𐑟, 𐑓 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑢𐑱, 𐑢𐑺 𐑲 𐑯𐑬 𐑕𐑷 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑩 𐑯𐑱𐑒𐑩𐑛 𐑕𐑐𐑲𐑯, 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑕 𐑮𐑨𐑐𐑑 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑑𐑳𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑨𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑳𐑤𐑒 𐑦𐑯 𐑓𐑤𐑧𐑖, 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑩𐑤, 𐑚𐑤𐑳𐑛, 𐑯 𐑚𐑬𐑩𐑤𐑟. 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑥𐑹, 𐑓 𐑞 𐑨𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑤 𐑓𐑦𐑯𐑟, 𐑲 𐑣𐑽 𐑕𐑷 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑩 𐑓𐑿 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑹𐑛𐑼𐑛 𐑡𐑶𐑯𐑑𐑕; 𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑑𐑦 𐑯 𐑥𐑩𐑡𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑒, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑚𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑓𐑤𐑵𐑒𐑕, 𐑩𐑯 𐑳𐑑𐑼 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑙𐑒!

𐑣𐑬 𐑝𐑱𐑯 𐑯 𐑓𐑵𐑤𐑦𐑖, 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑔𐑷𐑑 𐑲, 𐑓 𐑑𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑛 𐑳𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑑 𐑑𐑮𐑲 𐑑 𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑣𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑼𐑲𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑕 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑚𐑲 𐑥𐑽𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑹𐑦𐑙 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑛𐑧𐑛 𐑩𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑿𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑕𐑒𐑧𐑤𐑩𐑑𐑩𐑯, 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑧𐑗𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑐𐑰𐑕𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑫𐑛. 𐑯𐑴. 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑣𐑸𐑑 𐑝 𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑐𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑤𐑟; 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑧𐑛𐑦𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑨𐑙𐑜𐑮𐑦 𐑓𐑤𐑵𐑒𐑕; 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑳𐑯𐑚𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑕𐑰, 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑫𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑚𐑰 𐑑𐑮𐑵𐑤𐑦 𐑯 𐑤𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑬𐑑.

𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑲𐑯. 𐑓 𐑞𐑨𐑑, 𐑞 𐑚𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑢𐑱 𐑢𐑰 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑼 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑒𐑮𐑱𐑯, 𐑑 𐑐𐑲𐑤 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑚𐑴𐑯𐑟 𐑣𐑲 𐑳𐑐 𐑪𐑯 𐑧𐑯𐑛. 𐑯𐑴 𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑛𐑦 𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑐𐑮𐑲𐑟. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑯𐑬 𐑦𐑑'𐑕 𐑛𐑳𐑯, 𐑦𐑑 𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑕 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑤𐑲𐑒 ·𐑐𐑪𐑥𐑐𐑦'𐑟 ·𐑐𐑦𐑤𐑼.

𐑞𐑺 𐑸 𐑓𐑹𐑑𐑦 𐑯 𐑪𐑛 𐑝𐑻𐑑𐑦𐑚𐑮𐑦 𐑦𐑯 𐑷𐑤, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑒𐑧𐑤𐑩𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑸 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑤𐑪𐑒𐑑 𐑑𐑩𐑜𐑧𐑞𐑼. 𐑞𐑱 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑤𐑲 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑚𐑛 𐑚𐑤𐑪𐑒𐑕 𐑪𐑯 𐑩 ·𐑜𐑪𐑔𐑦𐑒 𐑕𐑐𐑲𐑼, 𐑓𐑹𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑪𐑤𐑦𐑛 𐑒𐑹𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑝 𐑣𐑧𐑝𐑦 𐑥𐑱𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑼𐑦. 𐑞 𐑤𐑸𐑡𐑩𐑕𐑑, 𐑩 𐑥𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑳𐑯, 𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑛𐑔 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑤𐑧𐑕 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑓𐑰𐑑, 𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑛𐑧𐑐𐑔 𐑥𐑹 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑓𐑹. 𐑞 𐑕𐑥𐑷𐑤𐑩𐑕𐑑, 𐑢𐑺 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑲𐑯 𐑑𐑱𐑐𐑼𐑟 𐑩𐑢𐑱 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑑𐑱𐑤, 𐑦𐑟 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑑𐑵 𐑦𐑯𐑗𐑩𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑛𐑔, 𐑯 𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑕 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑘𐑼𐑛-𐑚𐑷𐑤. 𐑲 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑑𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑢𐑻 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑕𐑥𐑷𐑤𐑼 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑟, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞𐑱 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑤𐑪𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑻𐑗𐑦𐑯𐑟, 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑰𐑕𐑑'𐑕 𐑗𐑦𐑤𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑯, 𐑣𐑵 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑕𐑑𐑴𐑤𐑩𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑑 𐑐𐑤𐑱 𐑥𐑸𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑞. 𐑞𐑳𐑕 𐑢𐑰 𐑕𐑰 𐑣𐑬 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑲𐑯 𐑝 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑞 𐑣𐑿𐑡𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑝 𐑤𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑑𐑱𐑐𐑼𐑟 𐑪𐑓 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑕𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑤 𐑗𐑲𐑤𐑛'𐑟 𐑐𐑤𐑱.

·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 104. 𐑞 ·𐑓𐑪𐑕𐑩𐑤 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤.

𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑲𐑑𐑦 𐑚𐑳𐑤𐑒 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑩𐑓𐑹𐑛𐑟 𐑩 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑡𐑰𐑯𐑾𐑤 𐑔𐑰𐑥 𐑢𐑺𐑪𐑯 𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑤𐑸𐑡, 𐑨𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑦𐑓𐑲, 𐑯 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑱𐑖𐑦𐑱𐑑. 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑿, 𐑿 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑕 𐑣𐑦𐑥. 𐑚𐑲 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑮𐑲𐑑𐑕 𐑣𐑰 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑰 𐑑𐑮𐑰𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑝 𐑦𐑯 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑽𐑾𐑤 𐑓𐑴𐑤𐑦𐑴. 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑑 𐑑𐑧𐑤 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑻𐑤𐑪𐑙𐑟 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑕𐑐𐑦𐑮𐑩𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑑 𐑑𐑱𐑤, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑘𐑸𐑛𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑥𐑧𐑠𐑼𐑟 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑕𐑑; 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒 𐑝 𐑞 𐑡𐑲𐑜𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑵𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑟, 𐑢𐑺 𐑞𐑱 𐑤𐑲 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑒𐑱𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑯 𐑣𐑷𐑟𐑼𐑟 𐑒𐑶𐑤𐑛 𐑩𐑢𐑱 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑚𐑑𐑼𐑱𐑯𐑾𐑯 𐑹𐑤𐑪𐑐-𐑛𐑧𐑒 𐑝 𐑩 𐑤𐑲𐑯-𐑝-𐑚𐑨𐑑𐑩𐑤-𐑖𐑦𐑐.

𐑕𐑦𐑯𐑕 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑑 𐑥𐑨𐑯𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑤 𐑞𐑦𐑕 ·𐑤𐑩𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑔𐑩𐑯, 𐑦𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑣𐑵𐑝𐑟 𐑥𐑰 𐑑 𐑩𐑐𐑮𐑵𐑝 𐑥𐑲𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑪𐑥𐑯𐑦𐑕𐑾𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑜𐑟𐑷𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑝 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑐𐑮𐑲𐑟; 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑴𐑝𐑼𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑥𐑲𐑯𐑿𐑑𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑧𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑡𐑻𐑥𐑟 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑤𐑳𐑛, 𐑯 𐑕𐑐𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑬𐑑 𐑑 𐑞 𐑳𐑑𐑼𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑒𐑶𐑤 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑬𐑩𐑤𐑟. 𐑣𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑷𐑤𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑦 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑚𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑑𐑼𐑦 𐑯 𐑨𐑯𐑩𐑑𐑪𐑥𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑦𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑟, 𐑦𐑑 𐑯𐑬 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑱𐑯𐑟 𐑑 𐑥𐑨𐑜𐑯𐑦𐑓𐑲 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑦𐑯 𐑩𐑯 𐑸𐑒𐑾𐑤𐑪𐑡𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤, 𐑓𐑪𐑕𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑓𐑼𐑩𐑕, 𐑯 𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑵𐑝𐑾𐑯 𐑐𐑶𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑝𐑿. 𐑩𐑐𐑤𐑲𐑛 𐑑 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑒𐑮𐑰𐑗𐑼 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑤𐑩𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑔𐑩𐑯—𐑑 𐑩𐑯 𐑨𐑯𐑑 𐑹 𐑩 𐑓𐑤𐑰—𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑐𐑹𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑑𐑻𐑥𐑟 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑡𐑳𐑕𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑰 𐑛𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑳𐑯𐑢𐑪𐑮𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑜𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑩𐑒𐑢𐑩𐑯𐑑. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑧𐑯 ·𐑤𐑩𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑔𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑟 𐑞 𐑑𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑, 𐑞 𐑒𐑱𐑕 𐑦𐑟 𐑷𐑤𐑑𐑼𐑛. 𐑓𐑱𐑯 𐑨𐑥 𐑲 𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑜𐑼 𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑮𐑲𐑟 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑑𐑾𐑕𐑑 𐑢𐑻𐑛𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑼𐑦. 𐑯 𐑣𐑽 𐑚𐑰 𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑧𐑛, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑦𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑝𐑰𐑯𐑾𐑯𐑑 𐑑 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑳𐑤𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑒𐑹𐑕 𐑝 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑼𐑑𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟, 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑺𐑾𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑿𐑟𐑛 𐑩 𐑣𐑿𐑡 𐑒𐑢𐑹𐑑𐑴 𐑧𐑛𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 ·𐑡𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑯, 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑻𐑗𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑓 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑐𐑻𐑐𐑩𐑕; 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑪𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑓𐑱𐑥𐑩𐑕 𐑤𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑪𐑜𐑮𐑩𐑓𐑼'𐑟 𐑳𐑯𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑐𐑻𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑚𐑳𐑤𐑒 𐑥𐑹 𐑓𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑑 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑲𐑤 𐑩 𐑤𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑪𐑯 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑿𐑟𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑩 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑷𐑔𐑼 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑥𐑰.

𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑪𐑓𐑩𐑯 𐑣𐑽𐑟 𐑝 𐑮𐑲𐑑𐑼𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑮𐑲𐑟 𐑯 𐑕𐑢𐑧𐑤 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞𐑺 𐑕𐑳𐑚𐑡𐑧𐑒𐑑, 𐑞𐑴 𐑦𐑑 𐑥𐑱 𐑕𐑰𐑥 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑩𐑯 𐑹𐑛𐑦𐑯𐑼𐑦 𐑢𐑳𐑯. 𐑣𐑬, 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑥𐑰, 𐑮𐑲𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑞𐑦𐑕 ·𐑤𐑩𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑔𐑩𐑯? 𐑳𐑯𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑥𐑲 𐑒𐑲𐑮𐑪𐑜𐑮𐑩𐑓𐑦 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑐𐑤𐑨𐑒𐑸𐑛 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑟. 𐑜𐑦𐑝 𐑥𐑰 𐑩 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑛𐑹'𐑟 𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑤! 𐑜𐑦𐑝 𐑥𐑰 ·𐑝𐑧𐑕𐑵𐑝𐑾𐑕' 𐑒𐑮𐑱𐑑𐑼 𐑓 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛! 𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑟, 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑥𐑲 𐑸𐑥𐑟! 𐑓 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑥𐑽 𐑨𐑒𐑑 𐑝 𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑲 𐑔𐑷𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑞𐑦𐑕 ·𐑤𐑩𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑔𐑩𐑯, 𐑞𐑱 𐑢𐑽𐑦 𐑥𐑰, 𐑯 𐑥𐑱𐑒 𐑥𐑰 𐑓𐑱𐑯𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞𐑺 𐑬𐑑𐑮𐑰𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑣𐑧𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑝𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑕𐑢𐑰𐑐, 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑓 𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑤𐑵𐑛 𐑞 𐑣𐑴𐑤 𐑕𐑻𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑲𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟, 𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑼𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟, 𐑯 𐑥𐑧𐑯, 𐑯 𐑥𐑨𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛𐑪𐑯𐑟, 𐑐𐑭𐑕𐑑, 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑑, 𐑯 𐑑 𐑒𐑳𐑥, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑮𐑦𐑝𐑪𐑤𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑐𐑨𐑯𐑼𐑭𐑥𐑩𐑟 𐑝 𐑧𐑥𐑐𐑲𐑼 𐑪𐑯 𐑻𐑔, 𐑯 𐑔𐑮𐑵𐑬𐑑 𐑞 𐑣𐑴𐑤 𐑿𐑯𐑦𐑝𐑻𐑕, 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑒𐑤𐑵𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑕𐑳𐑚𐑼𐑚𐑟. 𐑕𐑳𐑗, 𐑯 𐑕𐑴 𐑥𐑨𐑜𐑯𐑦𐑓𐑲𐑦𐑙, 𐑦𐑟 𐑞 𐑝𐑻𐑗𐑵 𐑝 𐑩 𐑤𐑸𐑡 𐑯 𐑤𐑦𐑚𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑔𐑰𐑥! 𐑢𐑰 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑑 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑚𐑳𐑤𐑒. 𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑛𐑿𐑕 𐑩 𐑥𐑲𐑑𐑦 𐑚𐑫𐑒, 𐑿 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑗𐑵𐑟 𐑩 𐑥𐑲𐑑𐑦 𐑔𐑰𐑥. 𐑯𐑴 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑻𐑦𐑙 𐑝𐑪𐑤𐑿𐑥 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑚𐑰 𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑤𐑰, 𐑞𐑴 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑞𐑺 𐑚𐑰 𐑣𐑵 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑛 𐑦𐑑.

𐑺 𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑚𐑡𐑧𐑒𐑑 𐑝 ·𐑓𐑪𐑕𐑩𐑤 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟, 𐑲 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑥𐑲 𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑛𐑧𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑨𐑟 𐑩 𐑡𐑦𐑪𐑤𐑩𐑡𐑦𐑕𐑑, 𐑚𐑲 𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑲 𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑩𐑤𐑱𐑯𐑾𐑕 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑩 𐑕𐑑𐑴𐑯-𐑥𐑱𐑕𐑩𐑯, 𐑯 𐑷𐑤𐑕𐑴 𐑩 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑜𐑼 𐑝 𐑛𐑦𐑗𐑩𐑟, 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑨𐑤𐑟 𐑯 𐑢𐑧𐑤𐑟, 𐑢𐑲𐑯-𐑝𐑷𐑤𐑑𐑕, 𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑼𐑟, 𐑯 𐑕𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑷𐑤 𐑕𐑹𐑑𐑕. 𐑤𐑲𐑒𐑢𐑲𐑟, 𐑚𐑲 𐑢𐑱 𐑝 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑼𐑦, 𐑲 𐑛𐑦𐑟𐑲𐑼 𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑞 𐑮𐑰𐑛𐑼, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑻𐑤𐑽 𐑡𐑾𐑤𐑪𐑡𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑭𐑑𐑩 𐑞𐑺 𐑸 𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑞 𐑓𐑪𐑕𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑝 𐑥𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑟 𐑯𐑬 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑰𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑑; 𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑚𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑢𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑮𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑒𐑕 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑳𐑝𐑼𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑸 𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑛 𐑞 ·𐑑𐑻𐑖𐑼𐑦 𐑓𐑹𐑥𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑕𐑰𐑥 𐑞 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑙, 𐑹 𐑨𐑑 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑕𐑧𐑐𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑤𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑕, 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑢𐑰𐑯 𐑞 𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑮𐑪𐑯𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑒𐑮𐑰𐑗𐑼𐑟, 𐑯 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑣𐑵𐑟 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑴𐑑 𐑐𐑪𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑸 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑛 𐑞 ·𐑸𐑒; 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 ·𐑓𐑪𐑕𐑩𐑤 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑞𐑼𐑑𐑵 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑳𐑝𐑼𐑛 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑑𐑻𐑖𐑼𐑦 𐑐𐑽𐑾𐑛, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑦𐑟 𐑞 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑰𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑕𐑵𐑐𐑼𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑤 𐑓𐑹𐑥𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟. 𐑯 𐑞𐑴 𐑯𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑲𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑼 𐑑 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑯𐑴𐑯 𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑖𐑰𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑑𐑲𐑥, 𐑞𐑱 𐑸 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑕𐑩𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑩𐑒𐑦𐑯 𐑑 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑦𐑯 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑕, 𐑑 𐑡𐑳𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑓𐑲 𐑞𐑺 𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑮𐑨𐑙𐑒 𐑨𐑟 ·𐑕𐑩𐑑𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑓𐑪𐑕𐑩𐑤𐑟.

𐑛𐑦𐑑𐑨𐑗𐑑 𐑚𐑮𐑴𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑓𐑪𐑕𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑝 𐑐𐑮𐑰-𐑨𐑛𐑩𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟, 𐑓𐑮𐑨𐑜𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑞𐑺 𐑚𐑴𐑯𐑟 𐑯 𐑕𐑒𐑧𐑤𐑩𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑟, 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑦𐑯 𐑔𐑻𐑑𐑦 𐑘𐑽𐑟 𐑐𐑭𐑕𐑑, 𐑨𐑑 𐑝𐑺𐑾𐑕 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑟, 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑚𐑱𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑨𐑤𐑐𐑕, 𐑦𐑯 ·𐑤𐑴𐑥𐑚𐑸𐑛𐑦, 𐑦𐑯 ·𐑓𐑮𐑭𐑯𐑕, 𐑦𐑯 ·𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛, 𐑦𐑯 ·𐑕𐑒𐑪𐑑𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛, 𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑑𐑕 𐑝 ·𐑤𐑵𐑰𐑟𐑦𐑨𐑯𐑩, ·𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑦𐑕𐑦𐑐𐑦, 𐑯 ·𐑨𐑤𐑩𐑚𐑨𐑥𐑩. 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑞 𐑥𐑹 𐑒𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑾𐑕 𐑝 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑱𐑯𐑟 𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑸𐑑 𐑝 𐑩 𐑕𐑒𐑳𐑤, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑘𐑽 1779 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑻𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑮𐑵 ·𐑛𐑴𐑓𐑨 𐑦𐑯 ·𐑐𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑕, 𐑩 𐑖𐑹𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑰𐑑 𐑴𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑐𐑨𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑑𐑵𐑦𐑤𐑼𐑦𐑟; 𐑯 𐑚𐑴𐑯𐑟 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑻𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑒𐑩𐑝𐑱𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑛𐑪𐑒𐑕 𐑝 ·𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑢𐑼𐑐, 𐑦𐑯 ·𐑯𐑩𐑐𐑴𐑤𐑾𐑯'𐑟 𐑑𐑲𐑥. ·𐑒𐑿𐑝𐑽 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑯𐑬𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑓𐑮𐑨𐑜𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑪𐑙𐑛 𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑳𐑑𐑼𐑤𐑦 𐑳𐑯𐑯𐑴𐑯 ·𐑤𐑩𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑔𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑒 𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑖𐑰𐑟.

𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑓𐑸 𐑞 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑷𐑤 ·𐑕𐑩𐑑𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑮𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑒𐑕 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑰𐑑 𐑝𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑒𐑧𐑤𐑩𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑩𐑯 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑑 𐑥𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑼, 𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑘𐑽 1842, 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑐𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑑𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 ·𐑡𐑳𐑡 ·𐑒𐑮𐑱, 𐑦𐑯 ·𐑨𐑤𐑩𐑚𐑨𐑥𐑩. 𐑞 𐑷-𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑒𐑮𐑧𐑡𐑵𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑕𐑤𐑱𐑝𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑝𐑦𐑕𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑑𐑫𐑒 𐑦𐑑 𐑓 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑓𐑷𐑤𐑩𐑯 𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑩𐑤𐑟. 𐑞 ·𐑨𐑤𐑩𐑚𐑨𐑥𐑩 𐑛𐑪𐑒𐑑𐑼𐑟 𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑺𐑛 𐑦𐑑 𐑩 𐑣𐑿𐑡 𐑮𐑧𐑐𐑑𐑲𐑤, 𐑯 𐑚𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑴𐑛 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑦𐑑 𐑞 𐑯𐑱𐑥 𐑝 ·𐑚𐑨𐑟𐑩𐑤𐑴𐑕𐑹𐑩𐑕. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑚𐑴𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑦𐑑 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑩𐑒𐑮𐑪𐑕 𐑞 𐑕𐑰 𐑑 ·𐑴𐑢𐑧𐑯, 𐑞 ·𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑤𐑦𐑖 ·𐑩𐑯𐑨𐑑𐑩𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑑, 𐑦𐑑 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑛 𐑬𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑩𐑤𐑧𐑡𐑛 𐑮𐑧𐑐𐑑𐑲𐑤 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑞𐑴 𐑝 𐑩 𐑛𐑦𐑐𐑸𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑖𐑰𐑟. 𐑩 𐑕𐑦𐑜𐑯𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑦𐑤𐑳𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑓𐑨𐑒𐑑, 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯 𐑯 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯 𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑰𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑚𐑫𐑒, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑒𐑧𐑤𐑩𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑓𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑟 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑒𐑤𐑵 𐑑 𐑞 𐑖𐑱𐑐 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑫𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦. 𐑕𐑴 ·𐑴𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑮𐑰𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑞 𐑥𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑼 ·𐑟𐑰𐑳𐑜𐑤𐑴𐑛𐑩𐑯; 𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑱𐑐𐑼 𐑮𐑰𐑛 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑞 ·𐑤𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑯 ·𐑡𐑾𐑤𐑪𐑡𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 ·𐑕𐑩𐑕𐑲𐑩𐑑𐑦, 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑯𐑬𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑑, 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑚𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕, 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑹𐑛𐑦𐑯𐑼𐑦 𐑒𐑮𐑰𐑗𐑼𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑞 𐑥𐑿𐑑𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑜𐑤𐑴𐑚 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑚𐑤𐑪𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑦𐑜𐑟𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕.

𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑲 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑥𐑲𐑑𐑦 ·𐑤𐑩𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑔𐑩𐑯 𐑕𐑒𐑧𐑤𐑩𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑟, 𐑕𐑒𐑳𐑤𐑟, 𐑑𐑳𐑕𐑒𐑕, 𐑡𐑷𐑟, 𐑮𐑦𐑚𐑟, 𐑯 𐑝𐑻𐑑𐑦𐑚𐑮𐑦, 𐑷𐑤 𐑒𐑨𐑮𐑩𐑒𐑑𐑼𐑲𐑟𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑐𐑸𐑖𐑩𐑤 𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑧𐑥𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑑 𐑞 𐑦𐑜𐑟𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑮𐑰𐑛𐑟 𐑝 𐑕𐑰-𐑥𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑟; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑚𐑺𐑦𐑙 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑕𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑤𐑼 𐑩𐑓𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑟 𐑑 𐑞 𐑩𐑯𐑲𐑩𐑤𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑮𐑪𐑯𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 ·𐑤𐑩𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑔𐑩𐑯𐑟, 𐑞𐑺 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑨𐑤𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑰𐑯𐑽𐑟; 𐑲 𐑨𐑥, 𐑚𐑲 𐑩 𐑓𐑤𐑳𐑛, 𐑚𐑹𐑯 𐑚𐑨𐑒 𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑕 𐑐𐑽𐑾𐑛, 𐑺 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑦𐑑𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑚𐑰 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑚𐑦𐑜𐑳𐑯; 𐑓 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑚𐑦𐑜𐑨𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑥𐑨𐑯. 𐑣𐑽 ·𐑕𐑨𐑑𐑼𐑯'𐑟 𐑜𐑮𐑱 𐑒𐑱𐑪𐑕 𐑮𐑴𐑤𐑟 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑥𐑰, 𐑯 𐑲 𐑩𐑚𐑑𐑱𐑯 𐑛𐑦𐑥, 𐑖𐑳𐑛𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑜𐑤𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞𐑴𐑟 ·𐑐𐑴𐑤𐑼 𐑦𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑟; 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑢𐑧𐑡𐑛 𐑚𐑨𐑕𐑑𐑾𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑲𐑕 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑸𐑛 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑸 𐑯𐑬 𐑞 ·𐑑𐑮𐑪𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑕; 𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 25,000 𐑥𐑲𐑤𐑟 𐑝 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛'𐑟 𐑕𐑼𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑓𐑼𐑩𐑯𐑕, 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑣𐑨𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛'𐑟 𐑚𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑔 𐑝 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑝𐑦𐑟𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤. 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑞 𐑣𐑴𐑤 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤'𐑟; 𐑯, 𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯, 𐑣𐑰 𐑤𐑧𐑓𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑱𐑒 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑤𐑲𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑰𐑟 𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑙𐑦𐑥𐑩𐑤𐑱𐑟. 𐑣𐑵 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑖𐑴 𐑩 𐑐𐑧𐑛𐑦𐑜𐑮𐑰 𐑤𐑲𐑒 ·𐑤𐑩𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑔𐑩𐑯? 𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚'𐑟 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑖𐑧𐑛 𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑼 𐑚𐑤𐑳𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑓𐑺𐑴'𐑟. ·𐑥𐑦𐑔𐑵𐑟𐑩𐑤𐑩 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑟 𐑩 𐑕𐑒𐑵𐑤-𐑚𐑶. 𐑲 𐑤𐑫𐑒 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑑 𐑖𐑱𐑒 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑞 ·𐑖𐑧𐑥. 𐑲 𐑨𐑥 𐑣𐑪𐑮𐑼-𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑒 𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑥𐑴𐑟𐑱𐑦𐑒, 𐑳𐑯𐑕𐑹𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑜𐑟𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑳𐑯𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑑𐑧𐑮𐑼𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑢𐑦𐑗, 𐑣𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑷𐑤 𐑑𐑲𐑥, 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑯𐑰𐑛𐑟 𐑦𐑜𐑟𐑦𐑕𐑑 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑷𐑤 𐑣𐑿𐑥𐑱𐑯 𐑱𐑡𐑩𐑟 𐑸 𐑴𐑝𐑼.

𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑩𐑤𐑴𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑞𐑦𐑕 ·𐑤𐑩𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑔𐑩𐑯 𐑤𐑧𐑓𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑮𐑰-𐑨𐑛𐑩𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑴𐑑𐑲𐑐 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑯𐑱𐑗𐑼, 𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑤𐑲𐑥𐑕𐑑𐑴𐑯 𐑯 𐑥𐑸𐑤 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑞𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑱𐑯𐑗𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑚𐑳𐑕𐑑; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 ·𐑦𐑡𐑦𐑐𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑑𐑨𐑚𐑤𐑩𐑑𐑕, 𐑣𐑵𐑟 𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑟 𐑑 𐑒𐑤𐑱𐑥 𐑓 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑩𐑯 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑓𐑪𐑕𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑓𐑼𐑩𐑕 𐑒𐑨𐑮𐑩𐑒𐑑𐑼, 𐑢𐑰 𐑓𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑞 𐑳𐑯𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑦𐑯. 𐑦𐑯 𐑩𐑯 𐑩𐑐𐑸𐑑𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑑𐑧𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑤 𐑝 ·𐑛𐑰𐑛𐑼𐑩, 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑓𐑦𐑓𐑑𐑦 𐑘𐑽𐑟 𐑩𐑜𐑴, 𐑞𐑺 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑳𐑝𐑼𐑛 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑕𐑒𐑳𐑤𐑐𐑗𐑼𐑛 𐑯 𐑐𐑱𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑯𐑦𐑕𐑓𐑽, 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑹𐑟, 𐑜𐑮𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑯𐑟, 𐑯 𐑛𐑪𐑤𐑓𐑦𐑯𐑟, 𐑕𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑤𐑼 𐑑 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑴𐑑𐑧𐑕𐑒 𐑓𐑦𐑜𐑼𐑟 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑦𐑤𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑾𐑤 𐑜𐑤𐑴𐑚 𐑝 𐑞 𐑥𐑪𐑛𐑼𐑯𐑟. 𐑜𐑤𐑲𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑞𐑧𐑥, 𐑴𐑤𐑛 ·𐑤𐑩𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑔𐑩𐑯 𐑕𐑢𐑨𐑥 𐑨𐑟 𐑝 𐑘𐑹; 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞𐑺 𐑕𐑢𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑯𐑦𐑕𐑓𐑽, 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑗𐑼𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 ·𐑕𐑪𐑤𐑩𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑒𐑮𐑱𐑛𐑩𐑤𐑛.

𐑯𐑹 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑚𐑰 𐑴𐑥𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑩𐑯𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡 𐑩𐑑𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑴𐑯 𐑪𐑕𐑾𐑕 𐑐𐑴𐑕𐑑-𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑵𐑝𐑾𐑯 𐑮𐑦𐑨𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑦, 𐑨𐑟 𐑕𐑧𐑑 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑝𐑧𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 ·𐑡𐑪𐑯 ·𐑤𐑰𐑴, 𐑞 𐑴𐑤𐑛 ·𐑚𐑸𐑚𐑸𐑦 𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑼.

“𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑓𐑸 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑰-𐑕𐑲𐑛, 𐑞𐑱 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑩 ·𐑑𐑧𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑤, 𐑞 ·𐑮𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼𐑟 𐑯 ·𐑚𐑰𐑥𐑟 𐑝 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑸 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑝 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤-·𐑚𐑴𐑯𐑟; 𐑓 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑝 𐑩 𐑥𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑩𐑕 𐑕𐑲𐑟 𐑸 𐑪𐑓𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑒𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑳𐑐 𐑛𐑧𐑛 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑖𐑹. 𐑞 ·𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑯 ·𐑐𐑰𐑐𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑥𐑨𐑡𐑦𐑯, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑩 𐑕𐑰𐑒𐑮𐑩𐑑 ·𐑐𐑬𐑼 𐑚𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑴𐑛 𐑚𐑲 ·𐑜𐑪𐑛 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑑𐑧𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑤, 𐑯𐑴 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑐𐑭𐑕 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑 𐑦𐑥𐑰𐑛𐑾𐑑 𐑛𐑧𐑔. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞 𐑑𐑮𐑵𐑔 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑥𐑨𐑑𐑼 𐑦𐑟, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑪𐑯 𐑲𐑞𐑼 𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑑𐑧𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑤, 𐑞𐑺 𐑸 ·𐑮𐑪𐑒𐑕 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑖𐑵𐑑 𐑑𐑵 ·𐑥𐑲𐑤𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑰, 𐑯 𐑢𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑞 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑞𐑱 𐑤𐑲𐑑 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 '𐑩𐑥. 𐑞𐑱 𐑒𐑰𐑐 𐑩 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤'𐑟 ·𐑮𐑦𐑚 𐑝 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑤𐑧𐑙𐑔 𐑓 𐑩 ·𐑥𐑦𐑮𐑩𐑒𐑩𐑤, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑤𐑲𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑜𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑝𐑧𐑒𐑕 𐑐𐑸𐑑 𐑳𐑐𐑼𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑, 𐑥𐑱𐑒𐑕 𐑩𐑯 ·𐑸𐑗, 𐑞 ·𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑝 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑮𐑰𐑗𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑩 ·𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑩 ·𐑒𐑨𐑥𐑩𐑤'𐑟 𐑚𐑨𐑒. 𐑞𐑦𐑕 ·𐑮𐑦𐑚 (𐑕𐑧𐑟 ·𐑡𐑪𐑯 ·𐑤𐑰𐑴) 𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑤𐑱𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑩 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑛 ·𐑘𐑽𐑟 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑲 𐑕𐑷 𐑦𐑑. 𐑞𐑺 ·𐑣𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑹𐑾𐑯𐑟 𐑩𐑓𐑻𐑥, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑩 ·𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑓𐑩𐑑 𐑣𐑵 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑓𐑩𐑕𐑦'𐑛 𐑝 ·𐑥𐑩𐑣𐑪𐑥𐑦𐑑, 𐑒𐑱𐑥 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞𐑦𐑕 ·𐑑𐑧𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑤, 𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑛𐑵 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑑 𐑩𐑕𐑻𐑑, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑓𐑩𐑑 ·𐑡𐑴𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑒𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑓𐑹𐑔 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑚𐑱𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑑𐑧𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑤.”

𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 ·𐑨𐑓𐑮𐑦𐑒 ·𐑑𐑧𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑲 𐑤𐑰𐑝 𐑿, 𐑮𐑰𐑛𐑼, 𐑯 𐑦𐑓 𐑿 𐑚𐑰 𐑩 ·𐑯𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑑𐑼, 𐑯 𐑩 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑥𐑩𐑯, 𐑿 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑕𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑢𐑻𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑞𐑺.

·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 105. 𐑛𐑳𐑟 𐑞 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤'𐑟 ·𐑥𐑨𐑜𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑿𐑛 ·𐑛𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑖?—𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑣𐑰 ·𐑐𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑖?

𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑟𐑥𐑳𐑗, 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑨𐑟 𐑞𐑦𐑕 ·𐑤𐑩𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑔𐑩𐑯 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑟 𐑓𐑤𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑳𐑕 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑣𐑧𐑛-𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑦𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑟, 𐑦𐑑 𐑥𐑱 𐑚𐑰 𐑓𐑦𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑢𐑲𐑼𐑛, 𐑢𐑧𐑞𐑼, 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑒𐑹𐑕 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑼𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟, 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑼𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑼𐑦𐑡𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑚𐑳𐑤𐑒 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑲𐑼𐑟.

𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑜𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑰 𐑓𐑲𐑯𐑛, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑸 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑛𐑱 𐑕𐑵𐑐𐑽𐑽 𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑨𐑜𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑿𐑛 𐑑 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑣𐑵𐑟 𐑓𐑪𐑕𐑩𐑤 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑱𐑯𐑟 𐑸 𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑑𐑻𐑖𐑼𐑦 𐑕𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑥 (𐑦𐑥𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑑 𐑡𐑾𐑤𐑪𐑡𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑐𐑽𐑾𐑛 𐑐𐑮𐑲𐑼 𐑑 𐑥𐑨𐑯), 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 ·𐑑𐑻𐑖𐑼𐑦 𐑕𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑥, 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑪𐑙𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑤𐑨𐑑𐑼 𐑓𐑹𐑥𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑰𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑲𐑟 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑝 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑻𐑤𐑽 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑟.

𐑝 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑰-𐑨𐑛𐑩𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑣𐑿𐑥𐑛, 𐑚𐑲 𐑓𐑸 𐑞 𐑤𐑸𐑡𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑞 ·𐑨𐑤𐑩𐑚𐑨𐑥𐑩 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼, 𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑤𐑧𐑕 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑕𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑦 𐑓𐑰𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑤𐑧𐑙𐑔 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑒𐑧𐑤𐑩𐑑𐑩𐑯. 𐑢𐑺𐑨𐑟, 𐑢𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑷𐑤𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑦 𐑕𐑰𐑯, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑑𐑱𐑐-𐑥𐑧𐑠𐑼 𐑜𐑦𐑝𐑟 𐑕𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑦-𐑑𐑵 𐑓𐑰𐑑 𐑓 𐑞 𐑕𐑒𐑧𐑤𐑩𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑩 𐑤𐑸𐑡 𐑕𐑲𐑟𐑛 𐑥𐑪𐑛𐑼𐑯 𐑢𐑱𐑤. 𐑯 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑣𐑻𐑛, 𐑪𐑯 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑥𐑧𐑯'𐑟 𐑷𐑔𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑦, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 ·𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑗𐑼𐑛 𐑯𐑽 𐑩 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑛 𐑓𐑰𐑑 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑝 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑗𐑼.

𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑥𐑱 𐑦𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑚𐑰, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑬𐑼 𐑸 𐑩𐑯 𐑩𐑛𐑝𐑭𐑯𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑨𐑜𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑿𐑛 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑝 𐑷𐑤 𐑐𐑮𐑰𐑝𐑾𐑕 𐑡𐑾𐑤𐑪𐑡𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑐𐑽𐑾𐑛𐑟; 𐑥𐑱 𐑦𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑚𐑰, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑦𐑯𐑕 ·𐑨𐑛𐑩𐑥'𐑟 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑞𐑱 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑛𐑦𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑼𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛?

𐑩𐑖𐑫𐑼𐑩𐑛𐑤𐑦, 𐑢𐑰 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑒𐑤𐑵𐑛 𐑕𐑴, 𐑦𐑓 𐑢𐑰 𐑸 𐑑 𐑒𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑦𐑑 𐑞 𐑩𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑨𐑟 ·𐑐𐑤𐑲𐑯𐑦, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑱𐑯𐑗𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑯𐑨𐑗𐑼𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑕 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑤𐑦. 𐑓 ·𐑐𐑤𐑲𐑯𐑦 𐑑𐑧𐑤𐑟 𐑳𐑕 𐑝 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑥𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑕𐑑 𐑱𐑒𐑼𐑟 𐑝 𐑤𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑳𐑤𐑒, 𐑯 ·𐑷𐑤𐑛𐑮𐑴𐑝𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑳𐑞𐑼𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑥𐑧𐑠𐑼𐑛 𐑱𐑑 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑛 𐑓𐑰𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑤𐑧𐑙𐑔—·𐑮𐑴𐑐 ·𐑢𐑷𐑒𐑕 𐑯 ·𐑑𐑧𐑥𐑟 ·𐑑𐑳𐑯𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑝 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟! 𐑯 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑛𐑱𐑟 𐑝 ·𐑚𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑕 𐑯 ·𐑕𐑴𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛𐑼, ·𐑒𐑫𐑒'𐑕 𐑯𐑨𐑗𐑼𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑕, 𐑢𐑰 𐑓𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑩 ·𐑛𐑱𐑯𐑦𐑖 𐑥𐑧𐑥𐑚𐑼 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑩𐑒𐑨𐑛𐑩𐑥𐑦 𐑝 ·𐑕𐑲𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑕𐑧𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑯 ·𐑲𐑕𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 (·𐑮𐑰𐑰𐑛𐑧𐑩𐑯-siskur, 𐑹 ·𐑮𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑛 ·𐑚𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑟) 𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑛 𐑯 𐑑𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑦 𐑘𐑸𐑛𐑟; 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑟, 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑛 𐑯 𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑦 𐑓𐑰𐑑. 𐑯 ·𐑤𐑱𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑛, 𐑞 ·𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑯𐑗 𐑯𐑨𐑗𐑼𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑕𐑑, 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑤𐑨𐑚𐑼𐑩𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑦 𐑝 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟, 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑚𐑦𐑜𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑻𐑒 (𐑐𐑱𐑡 3), 𐑕𐑧𐑑𐑕 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑮𐑲𐑑 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑛 𐑥𐑰𐑑𐑼𐑟, 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑛 𐑯 𐑑𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑦-𐑱𐑑 𐑓𐑰𐑑. 𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑻𐑒 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑐𐑳𐑚𐑤𐑦𐑖𐑑 𐑕𐑴 𐑤𐑱𐑑 𐑨𐑟 ⸰𐑱𐑛 1825.

𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑰𐑝 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑹𐑦𐑟? 𐑯𐑴. 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑝 𐑑-𐑛𐑱 𐑦𐑟 𐑨𐑟 𐑚𐑦𐑜 𐑨𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑨𐑯𐑕𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑟 𐑦𐑯 ·𐑐𐑤𐑲𐑯𐑦'𐑟 𐑑𐑲𐑥. 𐑯 𐑦𐑓 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑲 𐑜𐑴 𐑢𐑺 ·𐑐𐑤𐑲𐑯𐑦 𐑦𐑟, 𐑲, 𐑩 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑥𐑩𐑯 (𐑥𐑹 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟), 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑥𐑱𐑒 𐑚𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑑 𐑑𐑧𐑤 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑕𐑴. 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑪𐑟 𐑲 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑣𐑬 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑞 ·𐑦𐑡𐑦𐑐𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑥𐑳𐑥𐑦𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑻 𐑚𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑛 𐑔𐑬𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑝 𐑘𐑽𐑟 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 ·𐑐𐑤𐑲𐑯𐑦 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑚𐑹𐑯, 𐑛𐑵 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑥𐑧𐑠𐑼 𐑕𐑴 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑒𐑪𐑓𐑦𐑯𐑟 𐑨𐑟 𐑩 𐑥𐑪𐑛𐑼𐑯 ·𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑳𐑒𐑾𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑪𐑒𐑕; 𐑯 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑞 𐑒𐑨𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑯 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑥𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑕𐑒𐑳𐑤𐑐𐑗𐑼𐑛 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑩𐑕𐑑 ·𐑦𐑡𐑦𐑐𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑯 ·𐑯𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑝𐑩 𐑑𐑨𐑚𐑤𐑩𐑑𐑕, 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑮𐑧𐑤𐑩𐑑𐑦𐑝 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑐𐑹𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑞𐑱 𐑸 𐑛𐑮𐑷𐑯, 𐑡𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑮𐑵𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑣𐑲-𐑚𐑮𐑧𐑛, 𐑕𐑑𐑷𐑤-𐑓𐑧𐑛, 𐑐𐑮𐑲𐑟 𐑒𐑨𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑝 ·𐑕𐑥𐑦𐑔𐑓𐑰𐑤𐑛, 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑩𐑤, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑓𐑸 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑰𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑨𐑜𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑿𐑛 𐑞 𐑓𐑨𐑑𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑝 ·𐑓𐑺𐑴'𐑟 𐑓𐑨𐑑 𐑒𐑲𐑯; 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑱𐑕 𐑝 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑦𐑕, 𐑲 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑩𐑛𐑥𐑦𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑝 𐑷𐑤 𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑥𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑩𐑤𐑴𐑯 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑛𐑦𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑼𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛.

𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑩𐑯𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑢𐑲𐑼𐑦 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑱𐑯𐑟; 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑪𐑓𐑩𐑯 𐑨𐑡𐑦𐑑𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑥𐑹 𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑛𐑲𐑑 ·𐑯𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑑𐑼𐑟. 𐑢𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑞 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑪𐑥𐑯𐑦𐑕𐑾𐑯𐑑 𐑤𐑫𐑒-𐑬𐑑𐑕 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑-𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤-𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑕, 𐑯𐑬 𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑔𐑮𐑵 ·𐑚𐑺𐑦𐑙'𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑑𐑕, 𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑴𐑑𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑒𐑮𐑩𐑑 𐑛𐑮𐑷𐑼𐑟 𐑯 𐑤𐑪𐑒𐑼𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛; 𐑯 𐑞 𐑔𐑬𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑟 𐑯 𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑛𐑸𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑷𐑤 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑒𐑴𐑕𐑑𐑕; 𐑞 𐑥𐑵𐑑 𐑐𐑶𐑯𐑑 𐑦𐑟, 𐑢𐑧𐑞𐑼 ·𐑤𐑩𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑔𐑩𐑯 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑻 𐑕𐑴 𐑢𐑲𐑛 𐑩 𐑗𐑱𐑕, 𐑯 𐑕𐑴 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑹𐑕𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑩 𐑣𐑨𐑝𐑩𐑒; 𐑢𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑣𐑰 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑻𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼𐑟, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑞 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑥𐑨𐑯, 𐑕𐑥𐑴𐑒 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑐𐑲𐑐, 𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑦𐑝𐑨𐑐𐑼𐑱𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑲𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑐𐑳𐑓.

𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑺𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑣𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑑 𐑣𐑻𐑛𐑟 𐑝 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑣𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑑 𐑣𐑻𐑛𐑟 𐑝 𐑚𐑳𐑓𐑩𐑤𐑴, 𐑢𐑦𐑗, 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑓𐑹𐑑𐑦 𐑘𐑽𐑟 𐑩𐑜𐑴, 𐑴𐑝𐑼𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑔𐑬𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑺𐑦𐑟 𐑝 ·𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑯𐑶 𐑯 ·𐑥𐑦𐑟𐑫𐑼𐑦, 𐑯 𐑖𐑫𐑒 𐑞𐑺 𐑲𐑼𐑯 𐑥𐑱𐑯𐑟 𐑯 𐑕𐑒𐑬𐑤𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞𐑺 𐑔𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼-𐑒𐑤𐑪𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑮𐑬𐑟 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑲𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑐𐑪𐑐𐑿𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑮𐑦𐑝𐑼-𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑟, 𐑢𐑺 𐑯𐑬 𐑞 𐑐𐑩𐑤𐑲𐑑 𐑚𐑮𐑴𐑒𐑼 𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑟 𐑿 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑨𐑑 𐑩 𐑛𐑪𐑤𐑼 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑗; 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑩𐑯 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑸𐑜𐑿𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑕𐑰𐑥 𐑓𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑖𐑑, 𐑑 𐑖𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑯𐑬 𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑱𐑐 𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑛𐑦 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯.

𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑿 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑤𐑫𐑒 𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑥𐑨𐑑𐑼 𐑦𐑯 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑤𐑲𐑑. 𐑞𐑴 𐑕𐑴 𐑖𐑹𐑑 𐑩 𐑐𐑽𐑾𐑛 𐑩𐑜𐑴—𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑩 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑤𐑲𐑓𐑑𐑲𐑥—𐑞 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑚𐑳𐑓𐑩𐑤𐑴 𐑦𐑯 ·𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑯𐑶 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑰𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑞 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑯𐑬 𐑦𐑯 ·𐑤𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑯, 𐑯 𐑞𐑴 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑛𐑱 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑣𐑹𐑯 𐑹 𐑣𐑵𐑓 𐑝 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑱𐑯𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑮𐑰𐑡𐑩𐑯; 𐑯 𐑞𐑴 𐑞 𐑒𐑷𐑟 𐑝 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑕 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑻𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑽 𐑝 𐑥𐑨𐑯; 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑞 𐑓𐑸 𐑛𐑦𐑓𐑼𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑯𐑱𐑗𐑼 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤-𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑑 𐑐𐑼𐑧𐑥𐑐𐑑𐑼𐑦𐑤𐑦 𐑓𐑼𐑚𐑦𐑛𐑟 𐑕𐑴 𐑦𐑯𐑜𐑤𐑹𐑾𐑕 𐑩𐑯 𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑤𐑩𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑔𐑩𐑯. 𐑓𐑹𐑑𐑦 𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑓 𐑓𐑹𐑑𐑦-𐑱𐑑 𐑥𐑳𐑯𐑔𐑕 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒 𐑞𐑱 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑛𐑳𐑯 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑰𐑥𐑤𐑦 𐑢𐑧𐑤, 𐑯 𐑔𐑨𐑙𐑒 ·𐑜𐑪𐑛, 𐑦𐑓 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑞𐑱 𐑒𐑨𐑮𐑦 𐑣𐑴𐑥 𐑞 𐑶𐑤 𐑝 𐑓𐑹𐑑𐑦 𐑓𐑦𐑖. 𐑢𐑺𐑨𐑟, 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑛𐑱𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑴𐑤𐑛 ·𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑱𐑛𐑾𐑯 𐑯 ·𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑾𐑯 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑟 𐑯 𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑐𐑼𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑢𐑧𐑕𐑑, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑸 𐑢𐑧𐑕𐑑 (𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑵𐑟 𐑕𐑳𐑯𐑕𐑧𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑯𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑮𐑲𐑟) 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩 𐑢𐑦𐑤𐑛𐑼𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑯 𐑩 𐑝𐑻𐑡𐑦𐑯, 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑯𐑳𐑥𐑚𐑼 𐑝 𐑥𐑪𐑒𐑩𐑕𐑦𐑯𐑛 𐑥𐑧𐑯, 𐑓 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑯𐑳𐑥𐑚𐑼 𐑝 𐑥𐑳𐑯𐑔𐑕, 𐑥𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑹𐑕 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑛 𐑝 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑕, 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑕𐑤𐑱𐑯 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑓𐑹𐑑𐑦, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑓𐑹𐑑𐑦 𐑔𐑬𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑯 𐑥𐑹 𐑚𐑳𐑓𐑩𐑤𐑴𐑟; 𐑩 𐑓𐑨𐑒𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑, 𐑦𐑓 𐑯𐑰𐑛 𐑢𐑻, 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑚𐑰 𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑑𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛.

𐑯𐑹, 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑼𐑛 𐑼𐑲𐑑, 𐑛𐑳𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑥 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑸𐑜𐑿𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑓𐑱𐑝𐑼 𐑝 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑨𐑡𐑵𐑩𐑤 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑓 𐑦𐑜𐑟𐑭𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑤, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑓𐑹𐑥𐑼 𐑘𐑽𐑟 (𐑞 𐑤𐑨𐑑𐑼 𐑐𐑸𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑗𐑼𐑦, 𐑕𐑱) 𐑞𐑰𐑟 ·𐑤𐑩𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑔𐑩𐑯𐑟, 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑥𐑷𐑤 𐑐𐑪𐑛𐑟, 𐑢𐑻 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑛 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑪𐑓𐑩𐑯𐑼 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑨𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑑, 𐑯, 𐑦𐑯 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑢𐑩𐑯𐑕, 𐑞 𐑝𐑶𐑦𐑡𐑩𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑴 𐑐𐑮𐑴𐑤𐑪𐑙𐑛, 𐑯 𐑢𐑻 𐑷𐑤𐑕𐑴 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑥𐑹 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑿𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑑𐑦𐑝. 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑪𐑟, 𐑨𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑧𐑤𐑕𐑢𐑺 𐑯𐑴𐑑𐑦𐑕𐑑, 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟, 𐑦𐑯𐑓𐑤𐑵𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑝𐑿𐑟 𐑑 𐑕𐑱𐑓𐑑𐑦, 𐑯𐑬 𐑕𐑢𐑦𐑥 𐑞 𐑕𐑰𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑦𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑕 𐑒𐑨𐑮𐑩𐑝𐑨𐑯𐑟, 𐑕𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑑 𐑩 𐑤𐑸𐑡 𐑛𐑦𐑜𐑮𐑰 𐑞 𐑕𐑒𐑨𐑑𐑼𐑛 𐑕𐑪𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑼𐑦𐑟, 𐑘𐑴𐑒𐑕, 𐑯 𐑐𐑪𐑛𐑟, 𐑯 𐑕𐑒𐑵𐑤𐑟 𐑝 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑛𐑱𐑟 𐑸 𐑯𐑬 𐑨𐑜𐑮𐑦𐑜𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑝𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑲𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑧𐑐𐑼𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛, 𐑳𐑯𐑓𐑮𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑸𐑥𐑦𐑟. 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑷𐑤. 𐑯 𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑓𐑩𐑤𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑕 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑟 𐑞 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑰𐑑, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑪𐑟 𐑞 𐑕𐑴-𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑛 𐑢𐑱𐑤-𐑚𐑴𐑯 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑯𐑴 𐑤𐑪𐑙𐑜𐑼 𐑣𐑷𐑯𐑑 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑜𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑓𐑹𐑥𐑼 𐑘𐑽𐑟 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞𐑧𐑥, 𐑣𐑧𐑯𐑕 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑖𐑰𐑟 𐑷𐑤𐑕𐑴 𐑦𐑟 𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑲𐑯𐑦𐑙. 𐑓 𐑞𐑱 𐑸 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑛𐑮𐑦𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑦 𐑑 𐑒𐑱𐑐; 𐑯 𐑦𐑓 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑒𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑴 𐑤𐑪𐑙𐑜𐑼 𐑦𐑯𐑤𐑲𐑝𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞𐑺 𐑡𐑧𐑑𐑕, 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑚𐑰 𐑖𐑫𐑼, 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑯 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑴𐑑𐑼 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑮𐑰𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑳𐑯𐑓𐑩𐑥𐑦𐑤𐑽 𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑒𐑩𐑤.

𐑓𐑻𐑞𐑼𐑥𐑹: 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑛 ·𐑤𐑩𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑔𐑩𐑯𐑟, 𐑞𐑱 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑑𐑵 𐑓𐑻𐑥 𐑓𐑹𐑑𐑮𐑩𐑕𐑩𐑟, 𐑢𐑦𐑗, 𐑦𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑣𐑿𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑚𐑩𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑦, 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑓 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑱𐑯 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑜𐑯𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤. 𐑯 𐑨𐑟 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑭𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑞𐑺 𐑝𐑨𐑤𐑦𐑟, 𐑞 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑕𐑑𐑦 ·𐑕𐑢𐑦𐑕 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑮𐑰𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑥𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑟; 𐑕𐑴, 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑕𐑩𐑝𐑨𐑯𐑩𐑟 𐑯 𐑜𐑤𐑱𐑛𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑥𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑰𐑟, 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤-𐑚𐑴𐑯 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑹𐑑 𐑑 𐑞𐑺 ·𐑐𐑴𐑤𐑼 𐑕𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑛𐑧𐑤𐑟, 𐑯 𐑛𐑲𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑞 𐑳𐑤𐑑𐑦𐑥𐑩𐑑 𐑜𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑦 𐑚𐑨𐑮𐑽𐑟 𐑯 𐑢𐑷𐑤𐑟 𐑞𐑺, 𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑳𐑐 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑲𐑕𐑦 𐑓𐑰𐑤𐑛𐑟 𐑯 𐑓𐑤𐑴𐑟; 𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑗𐑸𐑥𐑛 𐑕𐑻𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑧𐑝𐑼𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑧𐑥𐑚𐑼, 𐑚𐑦𐑛 𐑛𐑦𐑓𐑲𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑐𐑼𐑕𐑿𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑥𐑨𐑯.

𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑐𐑼𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑕 𐑓𐑦𐑓𐑑𐑦 𐑝 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑢𐑱𐑤-𐑚𐑴𐑯 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑸 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑛 𐑓 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑒𐑨𐑖𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑑, 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑓𐑦𐑤𐑪𐑕𐑩𐑓𐑼𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑓𐑴𐑒𐑕𐑩𐑤 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑒𐑤𐑵𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑐𐑪𐑟𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑝 𐑣𐑨𐑝𐑩𐑒 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑷𐑤𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑦 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑕𐑽𐑾𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑖𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑚𐑩𐑑𐑨𐑤𐑾𐑯𐑟. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞𐑴 𐑓 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑐𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑩 𐑯𐑳𐑥𐑚𐑼 𐑝 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟, 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑤𐑧𐑕 𐑞𐑨𐑯 13,000, 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑨𐑯𐑿𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑤𐑱𐑯 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑯𐑹' 𐑢𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑒𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 ·𐑩𐑥𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑩𐑤𐑴𐑯; 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑸 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑼𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑮𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑕𐑻𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑕 𐑝 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑹 𐑯𐑴 𐑩𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑩𐑯 𐑩𐑐𐑴𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑸𐑜𐑿𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑥𐑨𐑑𐑼.

𐑯𐑨𐑗𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑮𐑧𐑡𐑵𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑐𐑪𐑐𐑿𐑤𐑩𐑕𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑥𐑹 𐑦𐑯𐑹𐑥𐑩𐑕 𐑒𐑮𐑰𐑗𐑼𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑜𐑤𐑴𐑚, 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑖𐑨𐑤 𐑢𐑰 𐑕𐑱 𐑑 ·𐑣𐑸𐑑𐑴, 𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑹𐑾𐑯 𐑝 ·𐑜𐑴𐑩, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑣𐑰 𐑑𐑧𐑤𐑟 𐑳𐑕 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑞 ·𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑝 ·𐑕𐑲𐑨𐑥 𐑑𐑫𐑒 4,000 𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑓𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕; 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑮𐑰𐑡𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑓𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑸 𐑯𐑿𐑥𐑼𐑩𐑕 𐑨𐑟 𐑛𐑮𐑴𐑝𐑟 𐑝 𐑒𐑨𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑑𐑧𐑥𐑐𐑼𐑩𐑑 𐑒𐑤𐑲𐑥𐑟. 𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑟 𐑯𐑴 𐑮𐑰𐑟𐑩𐑯 𐑑 𐑛𐑬𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑓 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑓𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑯𐑬 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑓 𐑔𐑬𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑝 𐑘𐑽𐑟, 𐑚𐑲 ·𐑕𐑩𐑥𐑽𐑩𐑥𐑩𐑕, 𐑚𐑲 ·𐑐𐑹𐑩𐑕, 𐑚𐑲 ·𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑚𐑩𐑤, 𐑯 𐑚𐑲 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑕𐑩𐑒𐑕𐑧𐑕𐑦𐑝 𐑥𐑪𐑯𐑸𐑒𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑰𐑕𐑑—𐑦𐑓 𐑞𐑱 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑕𐑼𐑝𐑲𐑝 𐑞𐑺 𐑦𐑯 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑯𐑳𐑥𐑚𐑼𐑟, 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑥𐑹 𐑥𐑱 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑬𐑑𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑙, 𐑕𐑦𐑯𐑕 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑩 𐑐𐑭𐑕𐑗𐑼 𐑑 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑱𐑖𐑦𐑱𐑑 𐑦𐑯, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑲𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑑𐑢𐑲𐑕 𐑨𐑟 𐑤𐑸𐑡 𐑨𐑟 𐑷𐑤 ·𐑱𐑖𐑩, 𐑚𐑴𐑔 ·𐑩𐑥𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑟, ·𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑩𐑐 𐑯 ·𐑨𐑓𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑩, ·𐑯𐑿 ·𐑣𐑪𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛, 𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 ·𐑲𐑤𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑰 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑚𐑲𐑯𐑛.

𐑥𐑹𐑴𐑝𐑼: 𐑢𐑰 𐑸 𐑑 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑼, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑿𐑥𐑛 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑤𐑪𐑯𐑡𐑧𐑝𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑝 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟, 𐑞𐑺 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑚𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑩𐑑𐑱𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑱𐑡 𐑝 𐑩 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑗𐑼𐑦 𐑯 𐑥𐑹, 𐑞𐑺𐑓𐑹 𐑨𐑑 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑐𐑽𐑾𐑛 𐑝 𐑑𐑲𐑥, 𐑕𐑧𐑝𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑑 𐑨𐑛𐑳𐑤𐑑 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑼𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑥𐑐𐑼𐑼𐑦. 𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑟, 𐑢𐑰 𐑥𐑱 𐑕𐑵𐑯 𐑜𐑱𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑲𐑛𐑾 𐑝, 𐑚𐑲 𐑦𐑥𐑨𐑡𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑝-𐑘𐑸𐑛𐑟, 𐑕𐑧𐑥𐑩𐑑𐑼𐑦𐑟, 𐑯 𐑓𐑨𐑥𐑤𐑦 𐑝𐑷𐑤𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑘𐑰𐑤𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑳𐑐 𐑞 𐑤𐑲𐑝 𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦𐑟 𐑝 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑥𐑧𐑯, 𐑢𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑯, 𐑯 𐑗𐑦𐑤𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑯 𐑣𐑵 𐑢𐑻 𐑩𐑤𐑲𐑝 𐑕𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑦-𐑓𐑲𐑝 𐑘𐑽𐑟 𐑩𐑜𐑴; 𐑯 𐑨𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑣𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑑 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑣𐑿𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑐𐑪𐑐𐑿𐑤𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑜𐑤𐑴𐑚.

𐑢𐑺𐑓𐑹, 𐑓 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑟, 𐑢𐑰 𐑩𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑦𐑥𐑹𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑖𐑰𐑟, 𐑣𐑬𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑐𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑡𐑵𐑨𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑦. 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑢𐑨𐑥 𐑞 𐑕𐑰𐑟 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑞 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑚𐑮𐑴𐑒 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼; 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑕 𐑕𐑢𐑨𐑥 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑞 𐑕𐑲𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑑𐑵𐑦𐑤𐑼𐑦𐑟, 𐑯 ·𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑟𐑼 ·𐑒𐑭𐑕𐑩𐑤, 𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑒𐑮𐑧𐑥𐑤𐑦𐑯. 𐑦𐑯 ·𐑯𐑴𐑩'𐑟 𐑓𐑤𐑳𐑛 𐑣𐑰 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑲𐑟𐑛 ·𐑯𐑴𐑩'𐑟 ·𐑸𐑒; 𐑯 𐑦𐑓 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑞 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛 𐑦𐑟 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯 𐑓𐑤𐑳𐑛𐑩𐑛, 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑞 ·𐑯𐑧𐑞𐑼𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛𐑟, 𐑑 𐑒𐑦𐑤 𐑪𐑓 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑮𐑨𐑑𐑕, 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑞 𐑦𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑕𐑼𐑝𐑲𐑝, 𐑯 𐑮𐑽𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑑𐑪𐑐𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑒𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑧𐑒𐑢𐑩𐑑𐑹𐑾𐑤 𐑓𐑤𐑳𐑛, 𐑕𐑐𐑬𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑔𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑓𐑲𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑒𐑲𐑟.

·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 106. 𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚'𐑟 ·𐑤𐑧𐑜.

𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑦𐑐𐑦𐑑𐑱𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑨𐑯𐑼 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑗 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑨𐑥𐑿𐑩𐑤 ·𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑸𐑚𐑦 𐑝 ·𐑤𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑯, 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑳𐑯𐑩𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑕𐑥𐑷𐑤 𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑴𐑯 𐑐𐑻𐑕𐑩𐑯. 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑤𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑧𐑯𐑼𐑡𐑦 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑩 𐑔𐑢𐑹𐑑 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑴𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑲𐑝𐑼𐑦 𐑤𐑧𐑜 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑰𐑝𐑛 𐑩 𐑣𐑭𐑓-𐑕𐑐𐑤𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑖𐑪𐑒. 𐑯 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑴𐑯 𐑛𐑧𐑒, 𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑴𐑯 𐑐𐑦𐑝𐑩𐑑-𐑣𐑴𐑤 𐑞𐑺, 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑴 𐑝𐑾𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑢𐑰𐑤𐑛 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩𐑯 𐑻𐑡𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑭𐑯𐑛 𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑽𐑟𐑥𐑩𐑯 (𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟, 𐑨𐑟 𐑧𐑝𐑼, 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑽𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯𐑓𐑤𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑯𐑳𐑓); 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑞 𐑷𐑤𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑦 𐑖𐑱𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑲𐑝𐑼𐑦 𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑰𐑝𐑛 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩𐑯 𐑩𐑛𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑑𐑢𐑦𐑕𐑑 𐑯 𐑮𐑧𐑯𐑗, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑴 𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑱𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑲𐑼, 𐑯 𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑩𐑐𐑽𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑤𐑳𐑕𐑑𐑦, 𐑘𐑧𐑑 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑛𐑰𐑥 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑲𐑼𐑤𐑦 𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑕𐑑𐑢𐑻𐑞𐑦.

𐑯, 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑰𐑛, 𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑕𐑥𐑷𐑤 𐑥𐑨𐑑𐑼 𐑓 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑓 𐑷𐑤 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑼𐑝𐑱𐑛𐑦𐑙, 𐑥𐑨𐑛 𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑤𐑩𐑕𐑯𐑩𐑕, ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑨𐑑 𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑜𐑦𐑝 𐑒𐑺𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑣𐑰𐑛 𐑑 𐑞 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑛𐑧𐑛 𐑚𐑴𐑯 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑣𐑰 𐑐𐑸𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑑𐑫𐑛. 𐑓 𐑦𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑐𐑮𐑲𐑼 𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛'𐑟 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 ·𐑯𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑑, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑯𐑲𐑑 𐑤𐑲𐑦𐑙 𐑐𐑮𐑴𐑯 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛, 𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤; 𐑚𐑲 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑳𐑯𐑯𐑴𐑯, 𐑯 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑤𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤, 𐑳𐑯𐑦𐑥𐑨𐑡𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑒𐑨𐑠𐑵𐑩𐑤𐑑𐑦, 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑲𐑝𐑼𐑦 𐑤𐑦𐑥 𐑣𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑕𐑴 𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕𐑑, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑒-𐑢𐑲𐑟 𐑕𐑥𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑯, 𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑐𐑽𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑜𐑮𐑶𐑯; 𐑯𐑹 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑰𐑥 𐑛𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑒𐑳𐑤𐑑𐑦 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑨𐑜𐑩𐑯𐑲𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑵𐑯𐑛 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑲𐑼𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑛.

𐑯𐑹, 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑑𐑲𐑥, 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑦𐑑 𐑓𐑱𐑤𐑛 𐑑 𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑼 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑪𐑯𐑩𐑥𐑱𐑯𐑦𐑨𐑒 𐑥𐑲𐑯𐑛, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑨𐑙𐑜𐑢𐑦𐑖 𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑓𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞 𐑛𐑦𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑑 𐑦𐑖𐑿 𐑝 𐑩 𐑓𐑹𐑥𐑼 𐑢𐑴; 𐑯 𐑣𐑰 𐑑𐑵 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑑 𐑕𐑰, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑐𐑶𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑮𐑧𐑐𐑑𐑲𐑤 𐑝 𐑞 𐑥𐑸𐑖 𐑐𐑼𐑐𐑧𐑗𐑵𐑱𐑑𐑕 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑕𐑢𐑰𐑑𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑪𐑙𐑕𐑑𐑼 𐑝 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑴𐑝; 𐑕𐑴, 𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑓𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑕𐑦𐑑𐑦, 𐑷𐑤 𐑥𐑦𐑟𐑼𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑝𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑛𐑵 𐑯𐑨𐑗𐑼𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑦𐑜𐑧𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑤𐑲𐑒. 𐑘𐑱, 𐑥𐑹 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑩𐑤𐑦, 𐑔𐑷𐑑 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚; 𐑕𐑦𐑯𐑕 𐑚𐑴𐑔 𐑞 𐑨𐑯𐑕𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑦 𐑯 𐑐𐑪𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑝 ·𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑓 𐑜𐑴 𐑓𐑻𐑞𐑼 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑞 𐑨𐑯𐑕𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑦 𐑯 𐑐𐑪𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑝 ·𐑡𐑶. 𐑓, 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑞𐑦𐑕: 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑓𐑼𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑪𐑯𐑦𐑒 𐑑𐑰𐑗𐑦𐑙𐑟, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑯𐑨𐑗𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑯𐑡𐑶𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑣𐑽 𐑖𐑨𐑤 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑯𐑴 𐑗𐑦𐑤𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑯 𐑚𐑹𐑯 𐑑 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑓 𐑞 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛, 𐑚𐑳𐑑, 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑺𐑦, 𐑖𐑨𐑤 𐑚𐑰 𐑓𐑪𐑤𐑴𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑡𐑶-𐑗𐑲𐑤𐑛𐑤𐑩𐑕𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑷𐑤 𐑣𐑧𐑤'𐑟 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑺; 𐑢𐑺𐑨𐑟, 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑜𐑦𐑤𐑑𐑦 𐑥𐑹𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑥𐑦𐑟𐑼𐑦𐑟 𐑖𐑨𐑤 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑓𐑻𐑑𐑲𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑦𐑜𐑧𐑑 𐑑 𐑞𐑧𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑝𐑟 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑮𐑴𐑜𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑦𐑝 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑡𐑩𐑯𐑦 𐑝 𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑓𐑕 𐑚𐑦𐑘𐑪𐑯𐑛 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑝; 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑞𐑦𐑕, 𐑞𐑺 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑟 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑛𐑰𐑐𐑼 𐑩𐑯𐑨𐑤𐑩𐑕𐑦𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑔𐑦𐑙. 𐑓, 𐑔𐑷𐑑 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚, 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑞 𐑣𐑲𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑻𐑔𐑤𐑦 𐑓𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑕𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑟 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑩 𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑳𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑜𐑯𐑦𐑓𐑲𐑦𐑙 𐑐𐑧𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑤𐑻𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑥, 𐑚𐑳𐑑, 𐑨𐑑 𐑚𐑪𐑑𐑩𐑥, 𐑷𐑤 𐑣𐑸𐑑𐑢𐑴𐑟, 𐑩 𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑕𐑦𐑜𐑯𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕, 𐑯, 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑥𐑧𐑯, 𐑩𐑯 𐑸𐑒𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑒 𐑜𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑡𐑼; 𐑕𐑴 𐑛𐑵 𐑞𐑺 𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑡𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑕𐑦𐑙𐑟-𐑬𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑲 𐑞 𐑪𐑚𐑝𐑾𐑕 𐑛𐑦𐑛𐑳𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯. 𐑑 𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑤 𐑞 𐑡𐑰𐑯𐑦𐑨𐑤𐑩𐑡𐑦𐑟 𐑝 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑣𐑲 𐑥𐑹𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑥𐑦𐑟𐑼𐑦𐑟, 𐑒𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑟 𐑳𐑕 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑞 𐑕𐑹𐑕𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑐𐑮𐑲𐑥𐑴𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑦𐑗𐑼𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑜𐑪𐑛𐑟; 𐑕𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑, 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑱𐑕 𐑝 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑜𐑤𐑨𐑛, 𐑣𐑱-𐑥𐑱𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑳𐑯𐑟, 𐑯 𐑕𐑪𐑓𐑑 𐑕𐑦𐑥𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙, 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑣𐑸𐑝𐑦𐑕𐑑-𐑥𐑵𐑯𐑟, 𐑢𐑰 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑯𐑰𐑛𐑟 𐑜𐑦𐑝 𐑦𐑯 𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕: 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑜𐑪𐑛𐑟 𐑞𐑧𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑝𐑟 𐑸 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑓 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑜𐑤𐑨𐑛. 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑓𐑱𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤, 𐑕𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑻𐑔-𐑥𐑸𐑒 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑮𐑬 𐑝 𐑥𐑨𐑯, 𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑥𐑐 𐑝 𐑕𐑪𐑮𐑴 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑲𐑯𐑼𐑟.

𐑳𐑯𐑢𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑣𐑽 𐑩 𐑕𐑰𐑒𐑮𐑩𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑛𐑲𐑝𐑳𐑤𐑡𐑛, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑐𐑼𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑕 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑥𐑹 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑐𐑼𐑤𐑦, 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑧𐑑 𐑢𐑱, 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑤𐑴𐑟𐑛 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹. 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑐𐑼𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑼𐑟 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑙 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚, 𐑷𐑤𐑢𐑱𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑦𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑱𐑯𐑛 𐑩 𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑦 𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑥, 𐑢𐑲 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑓 𐑩 𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑐𐑽𐑾𐑛, 𐑚𐑴𐑔 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑯 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛, 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑩𐑢𐑱 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑗 ·𐑜𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑛-·𐑤𐑭𐑥𐑩-𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑒𐑤𐑵𐑕𐑦𐑝𐑯𐑩𐑕; 𐑯, 𐑓 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑝𐑩𐑤, 𐑕𐑷𐑑 𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑗𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑮𐑧𐑓𐑿𐑡, 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑻, 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑞 𐑥𐑸𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑩𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑛. 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 ·𐑐𐑰𐑤𐑧𐑜'𐑟 𐑚𐑮𐑵𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑮𐑰𐑟𐑩𐑯 𐑓 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑐𐑽𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑯𐑴 𐑥𐑰𐑯𐑟 𐑨𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑢𐑩𐑑; 𐑞𐑴, 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑰𐑛, 𐑨𐑟 𐑑𐑳𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑷𐑤 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚'𐑟 𐑛𐑰𐑐𐑼 𐑐𐑸𐑑, 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑮𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑐𐑸𐑑𐑫𐑒 𐑥𐑹 𐑝 𐑕𐑦𐑜𐑯𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑛𐑸𐑒𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑝 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑩𐑑𐑼𐑦 𐑤𐑲𐑑. 𐑚𐑳𐑑, 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑧𐑯𐑛, 𐑦𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑒𐑱𐑥 𐑬𐑑; 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑥𐑨𐑑𐑼 𐑛𐑦𐑛, 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑰𐑕𐑑. 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑛𐑲𐑼𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑣𐑨𐑐 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑚𐑪𐑑𐑩𐑥 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑑𐑧𐑥𐑐𐑼𐑼𐑦 𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑵𐑕𐑯𐑩𐑕. 𐑯 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑞𐑦𐑕, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑧𐑝𐑼-𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑙, 𐑛𐑮𐑪𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑻𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑩𐑖𐑹, 𐑣𐑵, 𐑓 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑮𐑰𐑟𐑩𐑯, 𐑐𐑩𐑟𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑡 𐑝 𐑩 𐑤𐑧𐑕 𐑚𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑩𐑐𐑮𐑴𐑗 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥; 𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑑𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑛 𐑕𐑻𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑞 𐑩𐑚𐑳𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑒𐑨𐑠𐑵𐑩𐑤𐑑𐑦—𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑱𐑯𐑦𐑙, 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑛, 𐑥𐑵𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑦 𐑳𐑯𐑩𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑓 𐑚𐑲 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚—𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑑𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑑𐑧𐑮𐑼𐑟, 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑲𐑼𐑤𐑦 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑮𐑲𐑝𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑝 𐑕𐑐𐑦𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑯 𐑝 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟. 𐑕𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑, 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑞𐑺 𐑟𐑰𐑤 𐑓 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑞𐑱 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑷𐑤 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑐𐑲𐑼𐑛, 𐑕𐑴 𐑓𐑸 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑤𐑱, 𐑑 𐑥𐑳𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑳𐑐 𐑞 𐑯𐑪𐑤𐑦𐑡 𐑝 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑳𐑞𐑼𐑟; 𐑯 𐑣𐑧𐑯𐑕 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑩 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑼𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑝𐑩𐑤 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑦𐑤𐑨𐑐𐑕𐑑, 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑦𐑑 𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑕𐑐𐑲𐑼 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛'𐑟 𐑛𐑧𐑒𐑕.

𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑥𐑱; 𐑤𐑧𐑑 𐑞 𐑳𐑯𐑕𐑰𐑯, 𐑨𐑥𐑚𐑦𐑜𐑿𐑩𐑕 𐑕𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑺, 𐑹 𐑞 𐑝𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑝 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑯 𐑐𐑴𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑱𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑓𐑲𐑼, 𐑣𐑨𐑓 𐑑 𐑛𐑵 𐑹 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑻𐑔𐑤𐑦 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚, 𐑘𐑧𐑑, 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑥𐑨𐑑𐑼 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑤𐑧𐑜, 𐑣𐑰 𐑑𐑫𐑒 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑯 𐑐𐑮𐑨𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑐𐑮𐑴𐑕𐑰𐑡𐑼𐑟;—𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑛 𐑞 𐑒𐑸𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑼.

𐑯 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑓𐑳𐑙𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑼𐑦 𐑩𐑐𐑽𐑛 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑣𐑰 𐑚𐑨𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑱 𐑕𐑧𐑑 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑥𐑱𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑯𐑿 𐑤𐑧𐑜, 𐑯 𐑛𐑦𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑞 𐑥𐑱𐑑𐑕 𐑑 𐑕𐑰 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑕𐑩𐑐𐑤𐑲𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑛𐑟 𐑯 𐑡𐑶𐑕𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑡𐑷-𐑲𐑝𐑼𐑦 (·𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤) 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑞𐑳𐑕 𐑓𐑸 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑩𐑒𐑿𐑥𐑿𐑤𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑝𐑶𐑦𐑡, 𐑦𐑯 𐑹𐑛𐑼 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑩 𐑒𐑺𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑦𐑤𐑧𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑬𐑑𐑩𐑕𐑑, 𐑒𐑤𐑽𐑩𐑕𐑑-𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑛 𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑓 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑛. 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑛𐑳𐑯, 𐑞 𐑒𐑸𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑼 𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑰𐑝𐑛 𐑹𐑛𐑼𐑟 𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑞 𐑤𐑧𐑜 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑰𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑯𐑲𐑑; 𐑯 𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑝𐑲𐑛 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑓𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑓 𐑦𐑑, 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑐𐑼𐑑𐑱𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑞 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑿𐑕. 𐑥𐑹𐑴𐑝𐑼, 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐'𐑕 𐑓𐑹𐑡 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑹𐑛𐑼𐑛 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑣𐑶𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑑𐑧𐑥𐑐𐑼𐑼𐑦 𐑲𐑛𐑩𐑤𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛; 𐑯, 𐑑 𐑩𐑒𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑼𐑱𐑑 𐑞 𐑩𐑓𐑺, 𐑞 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑒𐑕𐑥𐑦𐑔 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑭𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑴𐑕𐑰𐑛 𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑕 𐑑 𐑞 𐑓𐑹𐑡𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑢𐑪𐑑𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑲𐑼𐑯 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑝𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑯𐑰𐑛𐑩𐑛.

·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 107. 𐑞 ·𐑒𐑸𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑼.

𐑕𐑰𐑑 𐑞𐑲𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑕𐑳𐑤𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑦 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑞 𐑥𐑵𐑯𐑟 𐑝 ·𐑕𐑨𐑑𐑼𐑯, 𐑯 𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑣𐑲 𐑨𐑚𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑩𐑤𐑴𐑯; 𐑯 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑟 𐑩 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼, 𐑩 𐑜𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑡𐑼, 𐑯 𐑩 𐑢𐑴. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑐𐑶𐑯𐑑, 𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑥𐑨𐑯𐑒𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑨𐑕, 𐑯 𐑓 𐑞 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑐𐑸𐑑, 𐑞𐑱 𐑕𐑰𐑥 𐑩 𐑥𐑪𐑚 𐑝 𐑳𐑯𐑯𐑧𐑕𐑦𐑕𐑺𐑦 𐑛𐑿𐑐𐑤𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑑𐑕, 𐑚𐑴𐑔 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑥𐑐𐑼𐑼𐑦 𐑯 𐑣𐑼𐑧𐑛𐑦𐑑𐑼𐑦. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑳𐑥𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑞𐑴 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟, 𐑯 𐑓𐑸 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑓𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑖𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑜𐑟𐑭𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑞 𐑣𐑲, 𐑣𐑿𐑥𐑱𐑯 𐑨𐑚𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯; 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛'𐑟 𐑒𐑸𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑼 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑴 𐑛𐑿𐑐𐑤𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑑; 𐑣𐑧𐑯𐑕, 𐑣𐑰 𐑯𐑬 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑐𐑻𐑕𐑩𐑯 𐑪𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑡.

𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑷𐑤 𐑕𐑰-𐑜𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑒𐑸𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑟, 𐑯 𐑥𐑹 𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑪𐑙𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑝𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑤𐑟, 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟, 𐑑 𐑩 𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑪𐑓-𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛, 𐑐𐑮𐑨𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑑, 𐑩𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑽𐑾𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑯𐑿𐑥𐑼𐑩𐑕 𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑛𐑟 𐑯 𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑨𐑑𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑴𐑯; 𐑞 𐑒𐑸𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑼'𐑟 𐑐𐑼𐑕𐑿𐑑 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑱𐑯𐑗𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑯 𐑬𐑑𐑚𐑮𐑭𐑯𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑙𐑒 𐑝 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑯𐑿𐑥𐑼𐑩𐑕 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑮𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑕 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑥𐑹 𐑹 𐑤𐑧𐑕 𐑣𐑨𐑓 𐑑 𐑛𐑵 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑨𐑟 𐑩𐑯 𐑷𐑜𐑟𐑦𐑤𐑽𐑦 𐑥𐑩𐑑𐑽𐑾𐑤. 𐑚𐑳𐑑, 𐑚𐑦𐑕𐑲𐑛𐑟 𐑞 𐑨𐑐𐑤𐑦𐑒𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑝 𐑞 𐑡𐑦𐑯𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑒 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑸𐑒 𐑩𐑚𐑳𐑝, 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑒𐑸𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑼 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑿𐑤𐑼𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑔𐑬𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑯𐑱𐑥𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑥𐑦𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑥𐑻𐑡𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑿𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑳𐑮𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑤𐑸𐑡 𐑖𐑦𐑐, 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑩 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑹 𐑓𐑹 𐑘𐑽𐑟' 𐑝𐑶𐑦𐑡, 𐑦𐑯 𐑳𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑤𐑲𐑟𐑛 𐑯 𐑓𐑸-𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑟. 𐑓 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑑 𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑒 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑹𐑛𐑦𐑯𐑼𐑦 𐑛𐑿𐑑𐑦𐑟:—𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑺𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑑𐑴𐑝 𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕, 𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑳𐑙 𐑕𐑐𐑸𐑟, 𐑮𐑦𐑓𐑹𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑖𐑱𐑐 𐑝 𐑒𐑤𐑳𐑥𐑟𐑦-𐑚𐑤𐑱𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑹𐑟, 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑫𐑤'𐑟 𐑲𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑒, 𐑹 𐑯𐑿 𐑑𐑮𐑰-𐑯𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑐𐑤𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑕, 𐑯 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑩𐑤𐑱𐑯𐑾𐑕 𐑥𐑨𐑑𐑼𐑟 𐑥𐑹 𐑛𐑦𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑼𐑑𐑱𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑤 𐑚𐑦𐑟𐑯𐑩𐑕; 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑥𐑹𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑳𐑯𐑣𐑧𐑟𐑦𐑑𐑱𐑑𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑼𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑥𐑨𐑯𐑼 𐑝 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑓𐑤𐑦𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑑𐑿𐑛𐑟, 𐑚𐑴𐑔 𐑿𐑕𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑯 𐑒𐑩𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑕.

𐑞 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑜𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑡 𐑢𐑺 𐑣𐑰 𐑦𐑯𐑨𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑷𐑤 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑝𐑺𐑾𐑕 𐑐𐑸𐑑𐑕 𐑕𐑴 𐑥𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑓𐑴𐑤𐑛, 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑝𐑲𐑕-𐑚𐑧𐑯𐑗; 𐑩 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑮𐑵𐑛 𐑐𐑪𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑩𐑕 𐑑𐑱𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑓𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑖𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑕𐑧𐑝𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑝𐑲𐑕𐑩𐑟, 𐑝 𐑛𐑦𐑓𐑼𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑕𐑲𐑟𐑩𐑟, 𐑯 𐑚𐑴𐑔 𐑝 𐑲𐑼𐑯 𐑯 𐑝 𐑢𐑫𐑛. 𐑨𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑧𐑐𐑑 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑙𐑕𐑲𐑛, 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑚𐑧𐑯𐑗 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑤𐑦 𐑤𐑨𐑖𐑑 𐑩𐑔𐑢𐑹𐑑𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑕 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑞 𐑮𐑽 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑑𐑮𐑲-𐑢𐑻𐑒𐑕.

𐑩 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑱𐑦𐑙 𐑐𐑦𐑯 𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑑𐑵 𐑤𐑸𐑡 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑰𐑟𐑦𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑣𐑴𐑤: 𐑞 𐑒𐑸𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑼 𐑒𐑤𐑨𐑐𐑕 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑧𐑝𐑼-𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑦 𐑝𐑲𐑕𐑩𐑟, 𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑑𐑢𐑱 𐑓𐑲𐑤𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑥𐑷𐑤𐑼. 𐑩 𐑤𐑪𐑕𐑑 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛-𐑚𐑻𐑛 𐑝 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡 𐑐𐑤𐑵𐑥𐑦𐑡 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑟 𐑪𐑯 𐑚𐑹𐑛, 𐑯 𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑩 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑝: 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑒𐑤𐑰𐑯 𐑖𐑱𐑝𐑛 𐑮𐑪𐑛𐑟 𐑝 𐑮𐑲𐑑-𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑚𐑴𐑯, 𐑯 𐑒𐑮𐑪𐑕-𐑚𐑰𐑥𐑟 𐑝 𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑲𐑝𐑼𐑦, 𐑞 𐑒𐑸𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑼 𐑥𐑱𐑒𐑕 𐑩 𐑐𐑩𐑜𐑴𐑛𐑩-𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑒𐑱𐑡 𐑓 𐑦𐑑. 𐑩𐑯 𐑹𐑟𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑑: 𐑞 𐑒𐑸𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑼 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑒𐑪𐑒𐑑𐑕 𐑩 𐑕𐑵𐑞𐑦𐑙 𐑤𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯. 𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚 𐑤𐑪𐑙𐑛 𐑓 𐑝𐑼𐑥𐑦𐑤𐑾𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑟 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑐𐑱𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑤𐑱𐑛 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑹; 𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑵𐑦𐑙 𐑰𐑗 𐑹 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑦𐑜 𐑝𐑲𐑕 𐑝 𐑢𐑫𐑛, 𐑞 𐑒𐑸𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑼 𐑕𐑦𐑥𐑧𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑩𐑐𐑤𐑲𐑟 𐑞 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯. 𐑩 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑼 𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑕 𐑩 𐑓𐑨𐑯𐑕𐑦 𐑑 𐑢𐑺 𐑖𐑸𐑒-𐑚𐑴𐑯 𐑽-𐑮𐑦𐑙𐑟: 𐑞 𐑒𐑸𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑼 𐑛𐑮𐑦𐑤𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑽𐑟. 𐑩𐑯𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑑𐑵𐑔𐑱𐑒: 𐑞 𐑒𐑸𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑼 𐑬𐑑 𐑐𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑼𐑟, 𐑯 𐑒𐑤𐑨𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑧𐑯𐑗 𐑚𐑦𐑛𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑚𐑰 𐑕𐑰𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑞𐑺; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞 𐑐𐑫𐑼 𐑓𐑧𐑤𐑴 𐑳𐑯𐑥𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑡𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑞 𐑳𐑯𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑒𐑤𐑵𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑪𐑐𐑼𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯; 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑞 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑫𐑛𐑩𐑯 𐑝𐑲𐑕, 𐑞 𐑒𐑸𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑼 𐑕𐑲𐑯𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑑 𐑒𐑤𐑨𐑐 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑡𐑷 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑, 𐑦𐑓 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑛𐑮𐑷 𐑞 𐑑𐑵𐑔.

𐑞𐑳𐑕, 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑒𐑸𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑼 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑺𐑛 𐑨𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑐𐑶𐑯𐑑𐑕, 𐑯 𐑩𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑓𐑼𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑷𐑤. 𐑑𐑰𐑔 𐑣𐑰 𐑩𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑲𐑝𐑼𐑦; 𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑛𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑑𐑪𐑐-𐑚𐑤𐑪𐑒𐑕; 𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑝𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑤𐑲𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑛 𐑓 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑟. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑯𐑬 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑕𐑴 𐑢𐑲𐑛 𐑩 𐑓𐑰𐑤𐑛 𐑞𐑳𐑕 𐑝𐑺𐑾𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑩𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑦𐑖𐑑 𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑤𐑲𐑝𐑤𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑼𐑑𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑑𐑵; 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑕𐑰𐑥 𐑑 𐑸𐑜𐑿 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑳𐑯𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑝𐑦𐑝𐑨𐑕𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑝 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑡𐑩𐑯𐑕. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑲𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑴. 𐑓 𐑯𐑳𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑥𐑹 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑸𐑒𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤, 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑓 𐑩 𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑻𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑛𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑻; 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑻𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑤, 𐑲 𐑕𐑱; 𐑓 𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑴 𐑖𐑱𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑪𐑓 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑕𐑼𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯𐑓𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑑 𐑝 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑟, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑛𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑻𐑯𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑣𐑴𐑤 𐑝𐑦𐑟𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛; 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑐𐑷𐑟𐑤𐑩𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑨𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑝 𐑦𐑯 𐑳𐑯𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑥𐑴𐑛𐑟, 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑦𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑟 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑐𐑰𐑕, 𐑯 𐑦𐑜𐑯𐑹𐑟 𐑿, 𐑞𐑴 𐑿 𐑛𐑦𐑜 𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑓 𐑒𐑩𐑔𐑰𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑤𐑟. 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑣𐑭𐑓-𐑣𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑛𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑪𐑤𐑝𐑦𐑙, 𐑑𐑵, 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑩𐑐𐑽𐑛, 𐑩𐑯 𐑷𐑤-𐑮𐑨𐑥𐑦𐑓𐑲𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑸𐑑𐑤𐑩𐑕𐑯𐑩𐑕;—𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑪𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑨𐑖𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩𐑯 𐑴𐑤𐑛, 𐑒𐑮𐑳𐑗-𐑤𐑲𐑒, 𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑵𐑝𐑾𐑯, 𐑢𐑰𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑿𐑥𐑼𐑩𐑕𐑯𐑩𐑕, 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑳𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑰𐑒𐑑 𐑯𐑬 𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑜𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑕; 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑨𐑟 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑕𐑻𐑝𐑛 𐑑 𐑐𐑭𐑕 𐑞 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑛𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑥𐑦𐑛𐑯𐑲𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑗 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑽𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑓𐑴𐑒𐑕𐑩𐑤 𐑝 ·𐑯𐑴𐑩'𐑟 𐑸𐑒. 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑒𐑸𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑼 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑩 𐑤𐑲𐑓-𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑢𐑪𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑼, 𐑣𐑵𐑟 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑮𐑴𐑤𐑦𐑙, 𐑑 𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑴, 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑜𐑨𐑞𐑼𐑛 𐑯𐑴 𐑥𐑪𐑕; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑹, 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑮𐑳𐑚𐑛 𐑪𐑓 𐑢𐑪𐑑𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑕𐑥𐑷𐑤 𐑬𐑑𐑢𐑼𐑛 𐑒𐑤𐑦𐑙𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑼𐑦𐑡𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑼𐑑𐑱𐑯𐑛 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥? 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑑 𐑨𐑚𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑒𐑑; 𐑩𐑯 𐑳𐑯𐑓𐑮𐑨𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑜𐑮𐑩𐑤; 𐑳𐑯𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑥𐑲𐑟𐑛 𐑨𐑟 𐑩 𐑯𐑿-𐑚𐑹𐑯 𐑚𐑱𐑚; 𐑤𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑰𐑥𐑧𐑛𐑦𐑑𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑮𐑧𐑓𐑼𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛 𐑹 𐑞 𐑯𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑. 𐑿 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑱, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡 𐑳𐑯𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑥𐑲𐑟𐑩𐑛𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑪𐑤𐑝𐑛 𐑩 𐑕𐑹𐑑 𐑝 𐑳𐑯𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑡𐑩𐑯𐑕; 𐑓 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑿𐑥𐑼𐑩𐑕 𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑛𐑟, 𐑣𐑰 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑥 𐑑 𐑢𐑻𐑒 𐑕𐑴 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑚𐑲 𐑮𐑰𐑟𐑩𐑯 𐑹 𐑚𐑲 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑑, 𐑹 𐑕𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑪𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑑𐑿𐑑𐑼𐑛 𐑑 𐑦𐑑, 𐑹 𐑚𐑲 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑥𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑗𐑼 𐑝 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑰𐑟, 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑹 𐑳𐑯𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑥𐑽𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑲 𐑩 𐑒𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑝 𐑛𐑧𐑓 𐑯 𐑛𐑳𐑥, 𐑕𐑐𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑱𐑯𐑾𐑕 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑐𐑮𐑴𐑕𐑧𐑕. 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩 𐑐𐑘𐑫𐑼 𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑐𐑿𐑤𐑱𐑑𐑼; 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑯, 𐑦𐑓 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑢𐑳𐑯, 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑻𐑤𐑦 𐑵𐑟𐑛 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑼𐑟. 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑳𐑯𐑮𐑰𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑣𐑲𐑤𐑦 𐑿𐑕𐑓𐑩𐑤, 𐑥𐑫𐑤𐑑𐑩𐑥 𐑦𐑯 𐑐𐑸𐑝𐑴, ·𐑖𐑧𐑓𐑰𐑤𐑛 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑝𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟, 𐑩𐑕𐑿𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑽𐑽—𐑞𐑴 𐑩 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑢𐑧𐑤𐑛—𐑝 𐑩 𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑐𐑪𐑒𐑩𐑑 𐑯𐑲𐑓; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑱𐑯𐑦𐑙, 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑤𐑱𐑛𐑟 𐑝 𐑝𐑺𐑾𐑕 𐑕𐑲𐑟𐑩𐑟, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑷𐑤𐑕𐑴 𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑵-𐑛𐑮𐑲𐑝𐑼𐑟, 𐑒𐑹𐑒-𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑵𐑟, 𐑑𐑢𐑰𐑟𐑼𐑟, 𐑷𐑤𐑟, 𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑟, 𐑮𐑵𐑤𐑼𐑟, 𐑯𐑱𐑤-𐑓𐑲𐑤𐑼𐑟, 𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑕𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑼𐑟. 𐑕𐑴, 𐑦𐑓 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑵𐑐𐑽𐑽𐑟 𐑢𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑑 𐑿𐑟 𐑞 𐑒𐑸𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑼 𐑓 𐑩 𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑵-𐑛𐑮𐑲𐑝𐑼, 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑱 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑑 𐑛𐑵 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑑 𐑴𐑐𐑩𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑐𐑸𐑑 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑵 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑓𐑭𐑕𐑑: 𐑹 𐑦𐑓 𐑓 𐑑𐑢𐑰𐑟𐑼𐑟, 𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑳𐑐 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑤𐑧𐑜𐑟, 𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑞𐑱 𐑢𐑻.

𐑘𐑧𐑑, 𐑨𐑟 𐑐𐑮𐑰𐑝𐑾𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑣𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛, 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑪𐑥𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑵𐑤𐑛, 𐑴𐑐𐑩𐑯-𐑯-𐑖𐑳𐑑 𐑒𐑸𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑼, 𐑢𐑪𐑟, 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑷𐑤, 𐑯𐑴 𐑥𐑽 𐑥𐑩𐑖𐑰𐑯 𐑝 𐑩𐑯 𐑷𐑑𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑑𐑪𐑯. 𐑦𐑓 𐑣𐑰 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑩 𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑕𐑴𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑩 𐑕𐑳𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑣𐑬 𐑩𐑯𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑤𐑩𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑛𐑿𐑑𐑦. 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟, 𐑢𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑝 𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑦𐑤𐑝𐑼, 𐑹 𐑩 𐑓𐑿 𐑛𐑮𐑪𐑐𐑕 𐑝 𐑣𐑸𐑑𐑕𐑣𐑹𐑯, 𐑞𐑺 𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑴 𐑑𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑙. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟; 𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑦𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑩𐑚𐑲𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑓 𐑯𐑬 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑦 𐑘𐑽𐑟 𐑹 𐑥𐑹. 𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟, 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑳𐑯𐑩𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤, 𐑒𐑳𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑤𐑲𐑓-𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑐𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥; 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑒𐑧𐑐𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑩 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑐𐑸𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑕𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑤𐑩𐑒𐑢𐑲𐑟𐑦𐑙; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩𐑯 𐑳𐑯𐑮𐑰𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑰𐑤, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑷𐑤𐑕𐑴 𐑣𐑳𐑥𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑤𐑩𐑒𐑢𐑲𐑟𐑩𐑟; 𐑹 𐑮𐑭𐑞𐑼, 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑦-𐑚𐑪𐑒𐑕 𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑕𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑤𐑩𐑒𐑢𐑲𐑟𐑼 𐑪𐑯 𐑜𐑸𐑛 𐑞𐑺, 𐑯 𐑑𐑷𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑑 𐑒𐑰𐑐 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑩𐑢𐑱𐑒.

·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 108. 𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑒𐑸𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑼.

(𐑒𐑸𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑼 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑝𐑲𐑕-𐑚𐑧𐑯𐑗, 𐑯 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑤𐑲𐑑 𐑝 𐑑𐑵 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑯𐑟 𐑚𐑦𐑟𐑦𐑤𐑦 𐑓𐑲𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑲𐑝𐑼𐑦 𐑡𐑶𐑕𐑑 𐑓 𐑞 𐑤𐑧𐑜, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑡𐑶𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑻𐑥𐑤𐑦 𐑓𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑝𐑲𐑕. 𐑕𐑤𐑨𐑚𐑟 𐑝 𐑲𐑝𐑼𐑦, 𐑤𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑐𐑕, 𐑐𐑨𐑛𐑟, 𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑵𐑟, 𐑯 𐑝𐑺𐑾𐑕 𐑑𐑵𐑤𐑟 𐑝 𐑷𐑤 𐑕𐑹𐑑𐑕 𐑤𐑲𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑞 𐑚𐑧𐑯𐑗. 𐑓𐑹𐑢𐑼𐑛, 𐑞 𐑮𐑧𐑛 𐑓𐑤𐑱𐑥 𐑝 𐑞 𐑓𐑹𐑡 𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑰𐑯, 𐑢𐑺 𐑞 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑒𐑕𐑥𐑦𐑔 𐑦𐑟 𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑻𐑒.)

𐑛𐑮𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑓𐑲𐑤, 𐑯 𐑛𐑮𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑯! 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑸𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑚𐑰 𐑕𐑪𐑓𐑑, 𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑪𐑓𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑚𐑰 𐑣𐑸𐑛. 𐑕𐑴 𐑢𐑰 𐑜𐑴, 𐑣𐑵 𐑓𐑲𐑤 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑡𐑷𐑟 𐑯 𐑖𐑦𐑯𐑚𐑴𐑯𐑟. 𐑤𐑧𐑑'𐑕 𐑑𐑮𐑲 𐑩𐑯𐑳𐑞𐑼. 𐑲, 𐑯𐑬, 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑻𐑒𐑕 𐑚𐑧𐑑𐑼 (𐑕𐑯𐑰𐑟𐑩𐑟). 𐑣𐑩𐑤𐑴, 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑚𐑴𐑯 𐑛𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑟 (𐑕𐑯𐑰𐑟𐑩𐑟)—𐑢𐑲 𐑦𐑑'𐑕 (𐑕𐑯𐑰𐑟𐑩𐑟)—𐑘𐑧𐑕 𐑦𐑑'𐑕 (𐑕𐑯𐑰𐑟𐑩𐑟)—𐑚𐑤𐑧𐑕 𐑥𐑲 𐑕𐑴𐑤, 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑤𐑧𐑑 𐑥𐑰 𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑒! 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑩𐑯 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑓𐑧𐑤𐑴 𐑜𐑧𐑑𐑕 𐑯𐑬 𐑓 𐑢𐑻𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑛𐑧𐑛 𐑤𐑳𐑥𐑚𐑼. 𐑕𐑷 𐑩 𐑤𐑲𐑝 𐑑𐑮𐑰, 𐑯 𐑿 𐑛𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑜𐑧𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑛𐑳𐑕𐑑; 𐑨𐑥𐑐𐑿𐑑𐑱𐑑 𐑩 𐑤𐑲𐑝 𐑚𐑴𐑯, 𐑯 𐑿 𐑛𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑜𐑧𐑑 𐑦𐑑 (𐑕𐑯𐑰𐑟𐑩𐑟). 𐑒𐑳𐑥, 𐑒𐑳𐑥, 𐑿 𐑴𐑤𐑛 ·𐑕𐑥𐑳𐑑, 𐑞𐑺, 𐑚𐑺 𐑩 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛, 𐑯 𐑤𐑧𐑑'𐑕 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑓𐑧𐑮𐑵𐑤 𐑯 𐑚𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑤-𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑵; 𐑲'𐑤 𐑚𐑰 𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑦 𐑓 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦. 𐑤𐑳𐑒𐑦 𐑯𐑬 (𐑕𐑯𐑰𐑟𐑩𐑟) 𐑞𐑺'𐑟 𐑯𐑴 𐑯𐑰-𐑡𐑶𐑯𐑑 𐑑 𐑥𐑱𐑒; 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑐𐑳𐑟𐑩𐑤 𐑩 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑩 𐑥𐑽 𐑖𐑦𐑯𐑚𐑴𐑯—𐑢𐑲 𐑦𐑑'𐑕 𐑰𐑟𐑦 𐑨𐑟 𐑥𐑱𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑪𐑐-𐑐𐑴𐑤𐑟; 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑲 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑑 𐑐𐑫𐑑 𐑩 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑓𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑖 𐑪𐑯. 𐑑𐑲𐑥, 𐑑𐑲𐑥; 𐑦𐑓 𐑲 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑞 𐑑𐑲𐑥, 𐑲 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑑𐑻𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑬𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑯𐑰𐑑 𐑩 𐑤𐑧𐑜 𐑯𐑬 𐑨𐑟 𐑧𐑝𐑼 (𐑕𐑯𐑰𐑟𐑩𐑟) 𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑱𐑐𐑑 𐑑 𐑩 𐑤𐑱𐑛𐑦 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑐𐑸𐑤𐑼. 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑚𐑳𐑒𐑕𐑒𐑦𐑯 𐑤𐑧𐑜𐑟 𐑯 𐑒𐑭𐑝𐑟 𐑝 𐑤𐑧𐑜𐑟 𐑲'𐑝 𐑕𐑰𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑖𐑪𐑐 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑴𐑟 𐑢𐑫𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑺 𐑨𐑑 𐑷𐑤. 𐑞𐑱 𐑕𐑴𐑒 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼, 𐑞𐑱 𐑛𐑵; 𐑯 𐑝 𐑒𐑹𐑕 𐑜𐑧𐑑 𐑮𐑵𐑥𐑨𐑑𐑦𐑒, 𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑓 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑛𐑪𐑒𐑑𐑼𐑛 (𐑕𐑯𐑰𐑟𐑩𐑟) 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑢𐑪𐑖𐑩𐑟 𐑯 𐑤𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟, 𐑡𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑤𐑲𐑝 𐑤𐑧𐑜𐑟. 𐑞𐑺; 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑲 𐑕𐑷 𐑦𐑑 𐑪𐑓, 𐑯𐑬, 𐑲 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑒𐑷𐑤 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑴𐑤𐑛 ·𐑥𐑴𐑜𐑩𐑤𐑖𐑦𐑐, 𐑯 𐑕𐑰 𐑢𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑞 𐑤𐑧𐑙𐑔 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑚𐑰 𐑷𐑤 𐑮𐑲𐑑; 𐑑𐑵 𐑖𐑹𐑑, 𐑦𐑓 𐑧𐑯𐑦𐑔𐑦𐑙, 𐑲 𐑜𐑧𐑕. 𐑣𐑭! 𐑞𐑨𐑑'𐑕 𐑞 𐑣𐑰𐑤; 𐑢𐑰 𐑸 𐑦𐑯 𐑤𐑳𐑒; 𐑣𐑽 𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑟, 𐑹 𐑦𐑑'𐑕 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦 𐑧𐑤𐑕, 𐑞𐑨𐑑'𐑕 𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑯.

·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 (𐑩𐑛𐑝𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑙). (𐑛𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑿𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑰𐑯, 𐑞 𐑒𐑸𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑼 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑿𐑟 𐑕𐑯𐑰𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑨𐑑 𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟.)

𐑢𐑧𐑤, 𐑥𐑨𐑯𐑥𐑱𐑒𐑼!

𐑡𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑑𐑲𐑥, 𐑕𐑻. 𐑦𐑓 𐑞 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 𐑐𐑤𐑰𐑟𐑩𐑟, 𐑲 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑯𐑬 𐑥𐑸𐑒 𐑞 𐑤𐑧𐑙𐑔. 𐑤𐑧𐑑 𐑥𐑰 𐑥𐑧𐑠𐑼, 𐑕𐑻.

𐑥𐑧𐑠𐑼𐑛 𐑓 𐑩 𐑤𐑧𐑜! 𐑜𐑫𐑛. 𐑢𐑧𐑤, 𐑦𐑑'𐑕 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑞 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑑𐑲𐑥. 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑦𐑑! 𐑞𐑺; 𐑒𐑰𐑐 𐑞𐑲 𐑓𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑼 𐑪𐑯 𐑦𐑑. 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑦𐑟 𐑩 𐑒𐑴𐑡𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑝𐑲𐑕 𐑞𐑬 𐑣𐑨𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑽, 𐑒𐑸𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑼; 𐑤𐑧𐑑 𐑥𐑰 𐑓𐑰𐑤 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑜𐑮𐑦𐑐 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑕. 𐑕𐑴, 𐑕𐑴; 𐑦𐑑 𐑛𐑳𐑟 𐑐𐑦𐑯𐑗 𐑕𐑳𐑥.

𐑴, 𐑕𐑻, 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑒 𐑚𐑴𐑯𐑟—𐑚𐑦𐑢𐑺, 𐑚𐑦𐑢𐑺!

𐑯𐑴 𐑓𐑽; 𐑲 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑜𐑮𐑦𐑐; 𐑲 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑑 𐑓𐑰𐑤 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑕𐑤𐑦𐑐𐑼𐑦 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛, 𐑥𐑨𐑯. 𐑢𐑪𐑑'𐑕 ·𐑐𐑮𐑴𐑥𐑰𐑔𐑾𐑕 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑞𐑺?—𐑞 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑒𐑕𐑥𐑦𐑔, 𐑲 𐑥𐑰𐑯—𐑢𐑪𐑑'𐑕 𐑣𐑰 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑?

𐑣𐑰 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑓𐑹𐑡𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑚𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑤-𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑵, 𐑕𐑻, 𐑯𐑬.

𐑮𐑲𐑑. 𐑦𐑑'𐑕 𐑩 𐑐𐑸𐑑𐑯𐑼𐑖𐑦𐑐; 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑩𐑐𐑤𐑲𐑟 𐑞 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑩𐑤 𐑐𐑸𐑑. 𐑣𐑰 𐑥𐑱𐑒𐑕 𐑩 𐑓𐑽𐑕 𐑮𐑧𐑛 𐑓𐑤𐑱𐑥 𐑞𐑺!

𐑲, 𐑕𐑻; 𐑣𐑰 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑣𐑰𐑑 𐑓 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑒𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑝 𐑓𐑲𐑯 𐑢𐑻𐑒.

𐑳𐑥-m. 𐑕𐑴 𐑣𐑰 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑. 𐑲 𐑛𐑵 𐑛𐑰𐑥 𐑦𐑑 𐑯𐑬 𐑩 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑥𐑰𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑔𐑦𐑙, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑴𐑤𐑛 ·𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑒, ·𐑐𐑮𐑴𐑥𐑰𐑔𐑾𐑕, 𐑣𐑵 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑥𐑧𐑯, 𐑞𐑱 𐑕𐑱, 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑩 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑒𐑕𐑥𐑦𐑔, 𐑯 𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑥𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑓𐑲𐑼; 𐑓 𐑢𐑪𐑑'𐑕 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑓𐑲𐑼 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑐𐑼𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑑 𐑓𐑲𐑼; 𐑯 𐑕𐑴 𐑣𐑧𐑤'𐑟 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑚𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤. 𐑣𐑬 𐑞 𐑕𐑫𐑑 𐑓𐑤𐑲𐑟! 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑞 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑱𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑞 ·𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑒 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑞 ·𐑨𐑓𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑝. 𐑒𐑸𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑼, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑣𐑰'𐑟 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑚𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑤, 𐑑𐑧𐑤 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑑 𐑓𐑹𐑡 𐑩 𐑐𐑺 𐑝 𐑕𐑑𐑰𐑤 𐑖𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑼-𐑚𐑤𐑱𐑛𐑟; 𐑞𐑺'𐑟 𐑩 𐑐𐑧𐑛𐑤𐑼 𐑩𐑚𐑹𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑒𐑮𐑳𐑖𐑦𐑙 𐑐𐑨𐑒.

𐑕𐑻?

𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛; 𐑢𐑲𐑤 ·𐑐𐑮𐑴𐑥𐑰𐑔𐑾𐑕 𐑦𐑟 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑦𐑑, 𐑲'𐑤 𐑹𐑛𐑼 𐑩 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑰𐑑 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑩 𐑛𐑦𐑟𐑲𐑼𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑐𐑨𐑑𐑼𐑯. 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑮𐑲𐑥𐑦𐑕, 𐑓𐑦𐑓𐑑𐑦 𐑓𐑰𐑑 𐑣𐑲 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑪𐑒𐑕; 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑗𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑥𐑪𐑛𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑞 ·𐑑𐑧𐑥𐑟 ·𐑑𐑳𐑯𐑩𐑤; 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑤𐑧𐑜𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑮𐑵𐑑𐑕 𐑑 '𐑩𐑥, 𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑱 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕; 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑸𐑥𐑟 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑓𐑰𐑑 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑞 𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑑; 𐑯𐑴 𐑣𐑸𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑷𐑤, 𐑚𐑮𐑭𐑕 𐑓𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑛, 𐑯 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑩 𐑒𐑢𐑹𐑑𐑼 𐑝 𐑩𐑯 𐑱𐑒𐑼 𐑝 𐑓𐑲𐑯 𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑟; 𐑯 𐑤𐑧𐑑 𐑥𐑰 𐑕𐑰—𐑖𐑨𐑤 𐑲 𐑹𐑛𐑼 𐑲𐑟 𐑑 𐑕𐑰 𐑬𐑑𐑢𐑼𐑛𐑟? 𐑯𐑴, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑐𐑫𐑑 𐑩 𐑕𐑒𐑲-𐑤𐑲𐑑 𐑪𐑯 𐑑𐑪𐑐 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑑 𐑦𐑤𐑵𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑱𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑢𐑼𐑛𐑟. 𐑞𐑺, 𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑞 𐑹𐑛𐑼, 𐑯 𐑩𐑢𐑱.

𐑯𐑬, 𐑢𐑪𐑑'𐑕 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑, 𐑯 𐑣𐑵'𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑑, 𐑲 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑑 𐑯𐑴? 𐑖𐑨𐑤 𐑲 𐑒𐑰𐑐 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑽? (𐑩𐑕𐑲𐑛).

'𐑑𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑓𐑼𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑸𐑒𐑦𐑑𐑧𐑒𐑗𐑼 𐑑 𐑥𐑱𐑒 𐑩 𐑚𐑤𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑛𐑴𐑥; 𐑣𐑽'𐑟 𐑢𐑳𐑯. 𐑯𐑴, 𐑯𐑴, 𐑯𐑴; 𐑲 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑩 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑯.

𐑣𐑴, 𐑣𐑴! 𐑞𐑨𐑑'𐑕 𐑦𐑑, 𐑣𐑱? 𐑣𐑽 𐑸 𐑑𐑵, 𐑕𐑻; 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑕𐑻𐑝 𐑥𐑲 𐑑𐑻𐑯.

𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑸𐑑 𐑞𐑬 𐑔𐑮𐑳𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑔𐑰𐑓-𐑒𐑨𐑗𐑼 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑥𐑲 𐑓𐑱𐑕 𐑓, 𐑥𐑨𐑯? 𐑔𐑮𐑳𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑤𐑲𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑻𐑕 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑐𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑟.

𐑲 𐑔𐑷𐑑, 𐑕𐑻, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑿 𐑕𐑐𐑴𐑒 𐑑 𐑒𐑸𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑼.

𐑒𐑸𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑼? 𐑢𐑲 𐑞𐑨𐑑'𐑕—𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑯𐑴;—𐑩 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑑𐑲𐑛𐑦, 𐑯, 𐑲 𐑥𐑱 𐑕𐑱, 𐑩𐑯 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑰𐑥𐑤𐑦 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑕𐑹𐑑 𐑝 𐑚𐑦𐑟𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑞𐑬 𐑸𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑽, 𐑒𐑸𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑼;—𐑹 𐑢𐑫𐑛'𐑕𐑑 𐑞𐑬 𐑮𐑭𐑞𐑼 𐑢𐑻𐑒 𐑦𐑯 𐑒𐑤𐑱?

𐑕𐑻?—𐑒𐑤𐑱? 𐑒𐑤𐑱, 𐑕𐑻? 𐑞𐑨𐑑'𐑕 𐑥𐑳𐑛; 𐑢𐑰 𐑤𐑰𐑝 𐑒𐑤𐑱 𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑗𐑼𐑟, 𐑕𐑻.

𐑞 𐑓𐑧𐑤𐑴'𐑟 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑲𐑩𐑕! 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑸𐑑 𐑞𐑬 𐑕𐑯𐑰𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑?

𐑚𐑴𐑯 𐑦𐑟 𐑮𐑭𐑞𐑼 𐑛𐑳𐑕𐑑𐑦, 𐑕𐑻.

𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑯𐑑, 𐑞𐑧𐑯; 𐑯 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑞𐑬 𐑸𐑑 𐑛𐑧𐑛, 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑚𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑞𐑲𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑤𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑐𐑰𐑐𐑩𐑤'𐑟 𐑯𐑴𐑟𐑩𐑟.

𐑕𐑻?—𐑴! 𐑭!—𐑲 𐑜𐑧𐑕 𐑕𐑴;—𐑘𐑧𐑕—𐑴, 𐑛𐑽!

𐑤𐑫𐑒 𐑘𐑰, 𐑒𐑸𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑼, 𐑲 𐑛𐑺 𐑕𐑱 𐑞𐑬 𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑞𐑲𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑩 𐑮𐑲𐑑 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑢𐑻𐑒𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑢𐑻𐑒𐑥𐑩𐑯, 𐑱? 𐑢𐑧𐑤, 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑒 𐑔𐑳𐑮𐑴𐑤𐑦 𐑢𐑧𐑤 𐑓 𐑞𐑲 𐑢𐑻𐑒, 𐑦𐑓, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑲 𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑑 𐑥𐑬𐑯𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑤𐑧𐑜 𐑞𐑬 𐑥𐑱𐑒𐑩𐑕𐑑, 𐑲 𐑖𐑨𐑤 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼𐑞𐑩𐑤𐑧𐑕 𐑓𐑰𐑤 𐑩𐑯𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑤𐑧𐑜 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑲𐑛𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑦𐑑; 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑟, 𐑒𐑸𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑼, 𐑥𐑲 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑤𐑪𐑕𐑑 𐑤𐑧𐑜; 𐑞 𐑓𐑤𐑧𐑖 𐑯 𐑚𐑤𐑳𐑛 𐑢𐑳𐑯, 𐑲 𐑥𐑰𐑯. 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑞𐑬 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑛𐑮𐑲𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑴𐑤𐑛 ·𐑨𐑛𐑩𐑥 𐑩𐑢𐑱?

𐑑𐑮𐑵𐑤𐑦, 𐑕𐑻, 𐑲 𐑚𐑦𐑜𐑦𐑯 𐑑 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑯𐑬. 𐑘𐑧𐑕, 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑣𐑻𐑛 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑒𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑾𐑕 𐑪𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑒𐑹, 𐑕𐑻; 𐑣𐑬 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑩 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑲𐑼𐑤𐑦 𐑤𐑵𐑟𐑩𐑟 𐑞 𐑓𐑰𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑕𐑐𐑸, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑚𐑰 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑨𐑑 𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟. 𐑥𐑱 𐑲 𐑣𐑳𐑥𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑭𐑕𐑒 𐑦𐑓 𐑦𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑮𐑾𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑴, 𐑕𐑻?

𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟, 𐑥𐑨𐑯. 𐑤𐑫𐑒, 𐑐𐑫𐑑 𐑞𐑲 𐑤𐑲𐑝 𐑤𐑧𐑜 𐑣𐑽 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕 𐑢𐑺 𐑥𐑲𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑕 𐑢𐑪𐑟; 𐑕𐑴, 𐑯𐑬, 𐑣𐑽 𐑦𐑟 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑑 𐑤𐑧𐑜 𐑑 𐑞 𐑲, 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑑𐑵 𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑴𐑤. 𐑢𐑺 𐑞𐑬 𐑓𐑰𐑤𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑑𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑤𐑲𐑓; 𐑞𐑺, 𐑦𐑜𐑟𐑨𐑒𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑞𐑺, 𐑞𐑺 𐑑 𐑩 𐑣𐑺, 𐑛𐑵 𐑲. ·𐑦𐑕'𐑑 𐑩 𐑮𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑤?

𐑲 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑣𐑳𐑥𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑷𐑤 𐑦𐑑 𐑩 𐑐𐑴𐑟𐑼, 𐑕𐑻.

𐑣𐑦𐑕𐑑, 𐑞𐑧𐑯. 𐑣𐑬 𐑛𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑞𐑬 𐑯𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑲𐑼, 𐑤𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑙, 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑱 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑦𐑟𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑯 𐑳𐑯𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑻𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑑𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑲𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑢𐑺 𐑞𐑬 𐑯𐑬 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑕𐑑; 𐑲, 𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑺 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑲 𐑕𐑐𐑲𐑑? 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑲 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑪𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑼𐑦 𐑬𐑼𐑟, 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑛𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑞𐑬 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑓𐑽 𐑰𐑝𐑟𐑛𐑮𐑪𐑐𐑼𐑟? 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛, 𐑛𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑒! 𐑯 𐑦𐑓 𐑲 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑓𐑰𐑤 𐑞 𐑕𐑥𐑸𐑑 𐑝 𐑥𐑲 𐑒𐑮𐑳𐑖𐑑 𐑤𐑧𐑜, 𐑞𐑴 𐑦𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑯𐑬 𐑕𐑴 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑛𐑦𐑟𐑪𐑤𐑝𐑛; 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑢𐑲 𐑥𐑳'𐑕𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑞𐑬, 𐑒𐑸𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑼, 𐑓𐑰𐑤 𐑞 𐑓𐑲𐑼𐑦 𐑐𐑱𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑣𐑧𐑤 𐑓 𐑧𐑝𐑼, 𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑 𐑩 𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦? 𐑣𐑭!

𐑜𐑫𐑛 ·𐑤𐑹𐑛! 𐑑𐑮𐑵𐑤𐑦, 𐑕𐑻, 𐑦𐑓 𐑦𐑑 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑟 𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑, 𐑲 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑒𐑨𐑤𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑱𐑑 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯; 𐑲 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒 𐑲 𐑛𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑒𐑨𐑮𐑦 𐑩 𐑕𐑥𐑷𐑤 𐑓𐑦𐑜𐑼, 𐑕𐑻.

𐑤𐑫𐑒 𐑘𐑰, 𐑐𐑫𐑛𐑦𐑙-𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑟 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑜𐑮𐑭𐑯𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑩𐑟.—𐑣𐑬 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑞 𐑤𐑧𐑜 𐑦𐑟 𐑛𐑳𐑯?

𐑐𐑼𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑕 𐑩𐑯 𐑬𐑼, 𐑕𐑻.

𐑚𐑳𐑙𐑜𐑩𐑤 𐑩𐑢𐑱 𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑯 𐑚𐑮𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑑 𐑑 𐑥𐑰 (𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑟 𐑑 𐑜𐑴). 𐑴, ·𐑤𐑲𐑓! 𐑣𐑽 𐑲 𐑨𐑥, 𐑐𐑮𐑬𐑛 𐑨𐑟 ·𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑒 𐑜𐑪𐑛, 𐑯 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑛𐑧𐑑𐑼 𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑚𐑤𐑪𐑒𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑓 𐑩 𐑚𐑴𐑯 𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑪𐑯! 𐑒𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑹𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼-𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑧𐑑𐑩𐑛𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑛𐑵 𐑩𐑢𐑱 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑤𐑧𐑡𐑼𐑟. 𐑲 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑚𐑰 𐑓𐑮𐑰 𐑨𐑟 𐑺; 𐑯 𐑲'𐑥 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑣𐑴𐑤 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛'𐑟 𐑚𐑫𐑒𐑕. 𐑲 𐑨𐑥 𐑕𐑴 𐑮𐑦𐑗, 𐑲 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑜𐑦𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑚𐑦𐑛 𐑓 𐑚𐑦𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑢𐑧𐑤𐑔𐑾𐑕𐑑 ·𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑹𐑾𐑯𐑟 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑷𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑮𐑴𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑧𐑥𐑐𐑲𐑼 (𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛'𐑟); 𐑯 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑲 𐑴 𐑓 𐑞 𐑓𐑤𐑧𐑖 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑑𐑳𐑙 𐑲 𐑚𐑮𐑨𐑜 𐑢𐑦𐑞. 𐑚𐑲 𐑣𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑯𐑟! 𐑲'𐑤 𐑜𐑧𐑑 𐑩 𐑒𐑮𐑵𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤, 𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑦𐑑, 𐑯 𐑛𐑦𐑟𐑪𐑤𐑝 𐑥𐑲𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑕𐑥𐑷𐑤, 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑾𐑕 𐑝𐑻𐑑𐑦𐑚𐑮𐑩. 𐑕𐑴.

·𐑒𐑸𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑼 (𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑿𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑻𐑒).

𐑢𐑧𐑤, 𐑢𐑧𐑤, 𐑢𐑧𐑤! 𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚 𐑯𐑴𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑚𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑝 𐑷𐑤, 𐑯 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚 𐑷𐑤𐑢𐑱𐑟 𐑕𐑧𐑟 𐑣𐑰'𐑟 𐑒𐑢𐑽; 𐑕𐑧𐑟 𐑯𐑳𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑕𐑩𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑻𐑛 𐑒𐑢𐑽; 𐑣𐑰'𐑟 𐑒𐑢𐑽, 𐑕𐑧𐑟 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚; 𐑣𐑰'𐑟 𐑒𐑢𐑽—𐑒𐑢𐑽, 𐑒𐑢𐑽; 𐑯 𐑒𐑰𐑐𐑕 𐑛𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 ·𐑥𐑼 ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑑𐑲𐑥—𐑒𐑢𐑽—𐑕𐑻—𐑒𐑢𐑽, 𐑒𐑢𐑽, 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑒𐑢𐑽. 𐑯 𐑣𐑽'𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑤𐑧𐑜! 𐑘𐑧𐑕, 𐑯𐑬 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑲 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒 𐑝 𐑦𐑑, 𐑣𐑽'𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑧𐑛𐑓𐑧𐑤𐑴! 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑩 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑝 𐑢𐑱𐑤'𐑟 𐑡𐑷-𐑚𐑴𐑯 𐑓 𐑩 𐑢𐑲𐑓! 𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑤𐑧𐑜; 𐑣𐑰'𐑤 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑪𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕. 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑯𐑬 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑤𐑧𐑜 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕𐑩𐑟, 𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑣𐑧𐑤—𐑣𐑬 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑? 𐑴! 𐑲 𐑛𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑣𐑰 𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑑 𐑕𐑴 𐑕𐑒𐑹𐑯𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑰! 𐑲'𐑥 𐑩 𐑕𐑹𐑑 𐑝 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡-𐑔𐑷𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟, 𐑞𐑱 𐑕𐑱; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑'𐑕 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑣𐑨𐑟𐑼𐑛-𐑤𐑲𐑒. 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑩 𐑖𐑹𐑑, 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑥𐑰, 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑛 𐑬𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑛𐑰𐑐 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑑𐑷𐑤, 𐑣𐑧𐑮𐑩𐑯-𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑑 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑟; 𐑞 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼 𐑗𐑳𐑒𐑕 𐑿 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑞 𐑗𐑦𐑯 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑒, 𐑯 𐑞𐑺'𐑟 𐑩 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑒𐑮𐑲 𐑓 𐑤𐑲𐑓-𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕. 𐑯 𐑣𐑽'𐑟 𐑞 𐑣𐑧𐑮𐑩𐑯'𐑟 𐑤𐑧𐑜! 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑯 𐑕𐑤𐑦𐑥, 𐑖𐑫𐑼 𐑦𐑯𐑳𐑓! 𐑯𐑬, 𐑓 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑓𐑴𐑒𐑕 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑐𐑺 𐑝 𐑤𐑧𐑜𐑟 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑕 𐑩 𐑤𐑲𐑓𐑑𐑲𐑥, 𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑪𐑟 𐑞𐑱 𐑿𐑟 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑥𐑻𐑕𐑦𐑓𐑩𐑤𐑦, 𐑨𐑟 𐑩 𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑼-𐑣𐑸𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑤𐑱𐑛𐑦 𐑿𐑟𐑩𐑟 𐑣𐑻 𐑮𐑴𐑤𐑦-𐑐𐑪𐑤𐑦 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑒𐑴𐑗-𐑣𐑹𐑕𐑩𐑟. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚; 𐑴 𐑣𐑰'𐑟 𐑩 𐑣𐑸𐑛 𐑛𐑮𐑲𐑝𐑼. 𐑤𐑫𐑒, 𐑛𐑮𐑦𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑤𐑧𐑜 𐑑 𐑛𐑧𐑔, 𐑯 𐑕𐑐𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑯𐑛 𐑞 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑓 𐑤𐑲𐑓, 𐑯 𐑯𐑬 𐑢𐑺𐑟 𐑬𐑑 𐑚𐑴𐑯 𐑤𐑧𐑜𐑟 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑒𐑹𐑛. 𐑣𐑩𐑤𐑴, 𐑞𐑺, 𐑿 ·𐑕𐑥𐑳𐑑! 𐑚𐑺 𐑩 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑞𐑺 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑵𐑟, 𐑯 𐑤𐑧𐑑'𐑕 𐑓𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑖 𐑦𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑞 𐑮𐑧𐑟𐑼𐑧𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑓𐑧𐑤𐑴 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑟 𐑩-𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑹𐑯 𐑓 𐑷𐑤 𐑤𐑧𐑜𐑟, 𐑑𐑮𐑵 𐑹 𐑓𐑷𐑤𐑕, 𐑨𐑟 𐑚𐑮𐑵𐑼𐑦-𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑜𐑴 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑚𐑽 𐑚𐑨𐑮𐑩𐑤𐑟, 𐑑 𐑓𐑦𐑤 '𐑩𐑥 𐑳𐑐 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯. 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑩 𐑤𐑧𐑜 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑦𐑟! 𐑦𐑑 𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑕 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑮𐑾𐑤 𐑤𐑲𐑝 𐑤𐑧𐑜, 𐑓𐑲𐑤𐑛 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑑 𐑯𐑳𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞 𐑒𐑹; 𐑣𐑰'𐑤 𐑚𐑰 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑪𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑑-𐑥𐑪𐑮𐑴; 𐑣𐑰'𐑤 𐑚𐑰 𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑨𐑤𐑑𐑦𐑑𐑿𐑛𐑟 𐑪𐑯 𐑦𐑑. 𐑣𐑩𐑤𐑴! 𐑲 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑓𐑼𐑜𐑪𐑑 𐑞 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑴𐑝𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑤𐑱𐑑, 𐑕𐑥𐑵𐑞𐑛 𐑲𐑝𐑼𐑦, 𐑢𐑺 𐑣𐑰 𐑓𐑦𐑜𐑼𐑟 𐑳𐑐 𐑞 𐑤𐑨𐑑𐑦𐑑𐑿𐑛. 𐑕𐑴, 𐑕𐑴; 𐑗𐑦𐑟𐑩𐑤, 𐑓𐑲𐑤, 𐑯 𐑕𐑨𐑯𐑛-𐑐𐑱𐑐𐑼, 𐑯𐑬!

·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 109. 𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑯 ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑒𐑨𐑚𐑦𐑯.

𐑩𐑒𐑹𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑿𐑕𐑦𐑡 𐑞𐑱 𐑢𐑻 𐑐𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑯𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑 𐑥𐑹𐑯𐑦𐑙; 𐑯 𐑤𐑴! 𐑯𐑴 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑼𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑶𐑤 𐑒𐑱𐑥 𐑳𐑐 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼; 𐑞 𐑒𐑭𐑕𐑒𐑕 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑴 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑳𐑙 𐑩 𐑚𐑨𐑛 𐑤𐑰𐑒. 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑻𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑖𐑴𐑯; 𐑯 ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒 𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑒𐑨𐑚𐑦𐑯 𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑹𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑳𐑯𐑓𐑱𐑝𐑼𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑩𐑓𐑺.*

*𐑦𐑯 ·𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥-𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑼𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑝 𐑶𐑤 𐑪𐑯 𐑚𐑹𐑛, 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑩 𐑮𐑧𐑜𐑿𐑤𐑼 𐑕𐑧𐑥𐑦-𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑿𐑑𐑦 𐑑 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑛𐑳𐑒𐑑 𐑩 𐑣𐑴𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛, 𐑯 𐑛𐑮𐑧𐑯𐑗 𐑞 𐑒𐑭𐑕𐑒𐑕 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑕𐑰-𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼; 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼𐑢𐑼𐑛𐑟, 𐑨𐑑 𐑝𐑺𐑦𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑟, 𐑦𐑟 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑵𐑝𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐'𐑕 𐑐𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑕. 𐑣𐑽𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑒𐑭𐑕𐑒𐑕 𐑸 𐑕𐑷𐑑 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑒𐑧𐑐𐑑 𐑛𐑨𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑦 𐑑𐑲𐑑; 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑗𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑛 𐑒𐑨𐑮𐑩𐑒𐑑𐑼 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑛𐑮𐑷𐑯 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼, 𐑞 𐑥𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑯𐑼𐑟 𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑦𐑑𐑧𐑒𐑑 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑕𐑽𐑾𐑕 𐑤𐑰𐑒𐑦𐑡 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑕 𐑒𐑸𐑜𐑴.

𐑯𐑬, 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑬𐑔 𐑯 ·𐑢𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑛𐑮𐑷𐑦𐑙 𐑯𐑲 𐑑 ·𐑓𐑹𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑩 𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑚𐑨𐑖𐑰 ·𐑲𐑤𐑟, 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑢𐑰𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑤𐑲𐑟 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑑𐑮𐑪𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑬𐑑𐑤𐑧𐑑𐑕 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 ·𐑗𐑲𐑯𐑩 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑩𐑕𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑒. 𐑯 𐑕𐑴 ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒 𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑗𐑸𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑹𐑦𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑸𐑒𐑦𐑐𐑧𐑤𐑩𐑜𐑴𐑟 𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑛 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑣𐑦𐑥; 𐑯 𐑩𐑯𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑕𐑧𐑐𐑼𐑩𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑮𐑧𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑰𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑯 𐑒𐑴𐑕𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑡𐑨𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑰𐑟 𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛𐑟—·𐑯𐑦𐑓𐑪𐑯, ·𐑥𐑨𐑑𐑕𐑥𐑱, 𐑯 ·𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑴𐑒. 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑯𐑴-𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑯𐑿 𐑲𐑝𐑼𐑦 𐑤𐑧𐑜 𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑕𐑑 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑵𐑛 𐑤𐑧𐑜 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑑𐑱𐑚𐑩𐑤, 𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑐𐑮𐑵𐑯𐑦𐑙-𐑣𐑫𐑒 𐑝 𐑩 𐑡𐑨𐑒-𐑯𐑲𐑓 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛, 𐑞 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑕 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑥𐑨𐑯, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑨𐑒 𐑑 𐑞 𐑜𐑨𐑙𐑢𐑱 𐑛𐑹, 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑮𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑮𐑬, 𐑯 𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑒𐑹𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯.

“𐑣𐑵'𐑟 𐑞𐑺?” 𐑣𐑽𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑓𐑫𐑑𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑐 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑛𐑹, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑑 𐑦𐑑. “𐑪𐑯 𐑛𐑧𐑒! 𐑚𐑦𐑜𐑪𐑯!”

“𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑕; 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑲. 𐑞 𐑶𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑦𐑟 𐑤𐑰𐑒𐑦𐑙, 𐑕𐑻. 𐑢𐑰 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑳𐑐 ·𐑚𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑯 𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑒 𐑬𐑑.”

“𐑳𐑐 ·𐑚𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑯 𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑒 𐑬𐑑? 𐑯𐑬 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑰 𐑸 𐑯𐑽𐑦𐑙 ·𐑡𐑩𐑐𐑨𐑯; 𐑣𐑰𐑝-𐑑 𐑣𐑽 𐑓 𐑩 𐑢𐑰𐑒 𐑑 𐑑𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑼 𐑩 𐑐𐑸𐑕𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑣𐑵𐑐𐑕?”

“𐑲𐑞𐑼 𐑛𐑵 𐑞𐑨𐑑, 𐑕𐑻, 𐑹 𐑢𐑱𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑛𐑱 𐑥𐑹 𐑶𐑤 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑢𐑰 𐑥𐑱 𐑥𐑱𐑒 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑘𐑽. 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑢𐑰 𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑑𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑦 𐑔𐑬𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑥𐑲𐑤𐑟 𐑑 𐑜𐑧𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑻𐑔 𐑕𐑱𐑝𐑦𐑙, 𐑕𐑻.”

“𐑕𐑴 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟, 𐑕𐑴 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟; 𐑦𐑓 𐑢𐑰 𐑜𐑧𐑑 𐑦𐑑.”

“𐑲 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑞 𐑶𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛, 𐑕𐑻.”

“𐑯 𐑲 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑹 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑷𐑤. 𐑚𐑦𐑜𐑪𐑯! 𐑤𐑧𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑤𐑰𐑒! 𐑲'𐑥 𐑷𐑤 𐑱𐑤𐑰𐑒 𐑥𐑲𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓. 𐑲! 𐑤𐑰𐑒𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑤𐑰𐑒𐑕! 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑓𐑫𐑤 𐑝 𐑤𐑰𐑒𐑦 𐑒𐑭𐑕𐑒𐑕, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑤𐑰𐑒𐑦 𐑒𐑭𐑕𐑒𐑕 𐑸 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑤𐑰𐑒𐑦 𐑖𐑦𐑐; 𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑'𐑕 𐑩 𐑓𐑸 𐑢𐑻𐑕 𐑐𐑤𐑲𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛'𐑟, 𐑥𐑨𐑯. 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑲 𐑛𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑪𐑐 𐑑 𐑐𐑤𐑳𐑜 𐑥𐑲 𐑤𐑰𐑒; 𐑓 𐑣𐑵 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑓𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑛𐑰𐑐-𐑤𐑴𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑣𐑳𐑤; 𐑹 𐑣𐑬 𐑣𐑴𐑐 𐑑 𐑐𐑤𐑳𐑜 𐑦𐑑, 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑓 𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛, 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑤𐑲𐑓'𐑕 𐑣𐑬𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑜𐑱𐑤? 𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒! 𐑲'𐑤 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑚𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑣𐑶𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛.”

“𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑞 𐑴𐑯𐑼𐑟 𐑕𐑱, 𐑕𐑻?”

“𐑤𐑧𐑑 𐑞 𐑴𐑯𐑼𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑪𐑯 ·𐑯𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑑 𐑚𐑰𐑗 𐑯 𐑬𐑑𐑦𐑧𐑤 𐑞 ·𐑑𐑲𐑓𐑵𐑯𐑟. 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑒𐑺𐑟 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚? 𐑴𐑯𐑼𐑟, 𐑴𐑯𐑼𐑟? 𐑞𐑬 𐑸𐑑 𐑷𐑤𐑢𐑱𐑟 𐑐𐑮𐑱𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑥𐑰, ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒, 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑥𐑲𐑟𐑼𐑤𐑦 𐑴𐑯𐑼𐑟, 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑓 𐑞 𐑴𐑯𐑼𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑥𐑲 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑕. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑤𐑫𐑒 𐑘𐑰, 𐑞 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑾𐑤 𐑴𐑯𐑼 𐑝 𐑧𐑯𐑦𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑭𐑯𐑛𐑼; 𐑯 𐑣𐑸𐑒 𐑘𐑰, 𐑥𐑲 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑖𐑦𐑐'𐑕 𐑒𐑰𐑤.—𐑪𐑯 𐑛𐑧𐑒!”

“𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚,” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑞 𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑱𐑑, 𐑥𐑵𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑻𐑞𐑼 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑒𐑨𐑚𐑦𐑯, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑛𐑺𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑴 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑯 𐑒𐑷𐑖𐑩𐑕 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑢𐑱 𐑕𐑰𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑩𐑝𐑶𐑛 𐑞 𐑕𐑤𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑬𐑑𐑢𐑼𐑛 𐑥𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑓𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑦𐑑𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑦𐑯 𐑷𐑤𐑕𐑴 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑥𐑹 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑣𐑭𐑓 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑕𐑑𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑦𐑑𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓; “𐑩 𐑚𐑧𐑑𐑼 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑲 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑢𐑧𐑤 𐑐𐑭𐑕 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑯𐑳𐑓 𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑘𐑳𐑙𐑜𐑼 𐑥𐑨𐑯; 𐑲, 𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑽, ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚.”

“𐑛𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑟! 𐑛𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑞𐑬 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑕𐑴 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑨𐑟 𐑛𐑺 𐑑 𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑦 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒 𐑝 𐑥𐑰?—𐑪𐑯 𐑛𐑧𐑒!”

“𐑯𐑱, 𐑕𐑻, 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑘𐑧𐑑; 𐑲 𐑛𐑵 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑰𐑑. 𐑯 𐑲 𐑛𐑵 𐑛𐑺, 𐑕𐑻—𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑓𐑹𐑚𐑺𐑦𐑙! 𐑖𐑨𐑤 𐑢𐑰 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑰𐑗 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑚𐑧𐑑𐑼 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑞𐑼𐑑𐑵, ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚?”

𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑕𐑰𐑟𐑛 𐑩 𐑤𐑴𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑒𐑩𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑮𐑨𐑒 (𐑓𐑹𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑐𐑸𐑑 𐑝 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 ·𐑕𐑬𐑔-·𐑕𐑰-𐑥𐑧𐑯'𐑟 𐑒𐑨𐑚𐑦𐑯 𐑓𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑗𐑼), 𐑯 𐑐𐑶𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑑 𐑑𐑩𐑢𐑹𐑛𐑟 ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒, 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑒𐑤𐑱𐑥𐑛: “𐑞𐑺 𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑳𐑯 ·𐑜𐑪𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑟 ·𐑤𐑹𐑛 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑞 𐑻𐑔, 𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑤𐑹𐑛 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛.—𐑪𐑯 𐑛𐑧𐑒!”

𐑓 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑤𐑨𐑖𐑦𐑙 𐑲𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑥𐑱𐑑, 𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑲𐑼𐑦 𐑗𐑰𐑒𐑕, 𐑿 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑔𐑷𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑮𐑾𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑰𐑝𐑛 𐑞 𐑚𐑤𐑱𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑤𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑑𐑿𐑚. 𐑚𐑳𐑑, 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑥𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯, 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑭𐑓 𐑒𐑭𐑥𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑴𐑟, 𐑯 𐑨𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑞 𐑒𐑨𐑚𐑦𐑯, 𐑐𐑷𐑟𐑛 𐑓 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑯 𐑕𐑧𐑛: “𐑞𐑬 𐑣𐑨𐑕𐑑 𐑬𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑡𐑛, 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑳𐑤𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑥𐑰, 𐑕𐑻; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑓 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑲 𐑭𐑕𐑒 𐑞𐑰 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑢𐑺 𐑝 ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒; 𐑞𐑬 𐑢𐑫𐑛𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑓; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑤𐑧𐑑 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑚𐑦𐑢𐑺 𐑝 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚; 𐑚𐑦𐑢𐑺 𐑝 𐑞𐑲𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓, 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑥𐑨𐑯.”

“𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑨𐑒𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑝, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼𐑞𐑩𐑤𐑧𐑕 𐑴𐑚𐑱𐑟; 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑒𐑺𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑝𐑼𐑦 𐑞𐑨𐑑!” 𐑥𐑻𐑥𐑼𐑛 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚, 𐑨𐑟 ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑩𐑐𐑽𐑛. “𐑢𐑪𐑑'𐑕 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑧𐑛—·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑚𐑦𐑢𐑺 𐑝 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚—𐑞𐑺'𐑟 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑺!” 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑳𐑯𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑿𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑒𐑩𐑑 𐑓 𐑩 𐑕𐑑𐑭𐑓, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩𐑯 𐑲𐑼𐑯 𐑚𐑮𐑬 𐑣𐑰 𐑐𐑱𐑕𐑑 𐑑 𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑴 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑒𐑨𐑚𐑦𐑯; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑞 𐑔𐑦𐑒 𐑐𐑤𐑨𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑛 𐑮𐑦𐑤𐑨𐑒𐑕𐑑, 𐑯 𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑜𐑳𐑯 𐑑 𐑞 𐑮𐑨𐑒, 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑑 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑒.

“𐑞𐑬 𐑸𐑑 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑑𐑵 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑩 𐑓𐑧𐑤𐑴, ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒,” 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑤𐑴𐑤𐑦 𐑑 𐑞 𐑥𐑱𐑑; 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑮𐑱𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑝𐑶𐑕 𐑑 𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑵: “𐑓𐑻𐑤 𐑞 𐑑'𐑜𐑨𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑑-𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑟, 𐑯 𐑒𐑤𐑴𐑕-𐑮𐑰𐑓 𐑞 𐑑𐑪𐑐-𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑟, 𐑓𐑹 𐑯 𐑭𐑓𐑑; 𐑚𐑨𐑒 𐑞 𐑥𐑱𐑯-𐑘𐑸𐑛; 𐑳𐑐 ·𐑚𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑯, 𐑯 𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑒 𐑬𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑥𐑱𐑯-𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛.”

𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑻 𐑐𐑼𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑕 𐑝𐑱𐑯 𐑑 𐑕𐑼𐑥𐑲𐑟 𐑦𐑜𐑟𐑨𐑒𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑢𐑲 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑙 ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒, ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑞𐑳𐑕 𐑨𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑛. 𐑦𐑑 𐑥𐑱 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑩 𐑓𐑤𐑨𐑖 𐑝 𐑪𐑯𐑩𐑕𐑑𐑦 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥; 𐑹 𐑥𐑽 𐑐𐑮𐑵𐑛𐑧𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑤 𐑐𐑪𐑤𐑩𐑕𐑦 𐑢𐑦𐑗, 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑞 𐑕𐑻𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑕, 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑽𐑾𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑓𐑼𐑚𐑨𐑛 𐑞 𐑕𐑤𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑑𐑩𐑥 𐑝 𐑴𐑐𐑩𐑯 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑩𐑓𐑧𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯, 𐑣𐑬𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑟𐑾𐑯𐑑, 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑹𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑗𐑰𐑓 𐑪𐑓𐑦𐑕𐑼 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑖𐑦𐑐. 𐑣𐑬𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟, 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑹𐑛𐑼𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑑𐑩𐑛; 𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑚𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑣𐑶𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛.

·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 110. ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 ·𐑒𐑪𐑓𐑦𐑯.

𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑕𐑻𐑗𐑦𐑙, 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑒𐑭𐑕𐑒𐑕 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑒 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑢𐑻 𐑐𐑻𐑓𐑦𐑒𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑬𐑯𐑛, 𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑤𐑰𐑒 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑓𐑻𐑞𐑼 𐑪𐑓. 𐑕𐑴, 𐑦𐑑 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑒𐑭𐑥 𐑢𐑧𐑞𐑼, 𐑞𐑱 𐑚𐑮𐑴𐑒 𐑬𐑑 𐑛𐑰𐑐𐑼 𐑯 𐑛𐑰𐑐𐑼, 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑻𐑚𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑕𐑤𐑳𐑥𐑚𐑼𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑣𐑿𐑡 𐑜𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛-𐑑𐑽 𐑚𐑳𐑑𐑕; 𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑒 𐑥𐑦𐑛𐑯𐑲𐑑 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑡𐑲𐑜𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑥𐑴𐑤𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑛𐑱𐑤𐑲𐑑 𐑩𐑚𐑳𐑝. 𐑕𐑴 𐑛𐑰𐑐 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑞𐑱 𐑜𐑴; 𐑯 𐑕𐑴 𐑱𐑯𐑗𐑩𐑯𐑑, 𐑯 𐑒𐑼𐑴𐑛𐑩𐑛, 𐑯 𐑢𐑰𐑛𐑦 𐑞 𐑨𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑤𐑴𐑼𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑐𐑳𐑯𐑗𐑩𐑯𐑕, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑿 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑑 𐑯𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑 𐑓 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑥𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑦 𐑒𐑹𐑯𐑼-𐑕𐑑𐑴𐑯 𐑒𐑭𐑕𐑒 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑱𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑒𐑶𐑯𐑟 𐑝 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 ·𐑯𐑴𐑩, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑒𐑪𐑐𐑦𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑐𐑴𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑐𐑤𐑨𐑒𐑸𐑛𐑟, 𐑝𐑱𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑢𐑹𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑓𐑨𐑗𐑵𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑓𐑤𐑳𐑛. 𐑑𐑽𐑕 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑑𐑽𐑕, 𐑑𐑵, 𐑝 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼, 𐑯 𐑚𐑮𐑧𐑛, 𐑯 𐑚𐑰𐑓, 𐑯 𐑖𐑫𐑒𐑕 𐑝 𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑝𐑟, 𐑯 𐑲𐑼𐑯 𐑚𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑝 𐑣𐑵𐑐𐑕, 𐑢𐑻 𐑣𐑶𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑬𐑑, 𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑞 𐑐𐑲𐑤𐑛 𐑛𐑧𐑒𐑕 𐑢𐑻 𐑣𐑸𐑛 𐑑 𐑜𐑧𐑑 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑; 𐑯 𐑞 𐑣𐑪𐑤𐑴 𐑣𐑳𐑤 𐑧𐑒𐑴𐑛 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑓𐑫𐑑, 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑓 𐑿 𐑢𐑻 𐑑𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑧𐑥𐑐𐑑𐑦 𐑒𐑨𐑑𐑩𐑒𐑵𐑥𐑟, 𐑯 𐑮𐑰𐑤𐑛 𐑯 𐑮𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑰 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩𐑯 𐑺-𐑓𐑮𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑛𐑧𐑥𐑦𐑡𐑪𐑯. 𐑑𐑪𐑐-𐑣𐑧𐑝𐑦 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑨𐑟 𐑩 𐑛𐑦𐑯𐑼𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑕𐑑𐑿𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑷𐑤 ·𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑪𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑧𐑛. 𐑢𐑧𐑤 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑑𐑲𐑓𐑵𐑯𐑟 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑝𐑦𐑟𐑦𐑑 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑞𐑧𐑯.

𐑯𐑬, 𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑲 𐑐𐑫𐑼 𐑐𐑱𐑜𐑩𐑯 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑨𐑯𐑘𐑩𐑯, 𐑯 𐑓𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑫𐑟𐑩𐑥-𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑯𐑛, ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜, 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑰𐑟𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑓𐑰𐑝𐑼, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑚𐑮𐑷𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑯𐑲 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑧𐑯𐑛.

𐑚𐑰 𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑧𐑛, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑝𐑴𐑒𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙, 𐑕𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑒𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑟 𐑸 𐑳𐑯𐑯𐑴𐑯; 𐑛𐑦𐑜𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑯 𐑛𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑼 𐑜𐑴 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛; 𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑿 𐑜𐑧𐑑 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯, 𐑞 𐑣𐑲𐑼 𐑿 𐑮𐑲𐑟 𐑞 𐑣𐑸𐑛𐑼 𐑿 𐑑𐑶𐑤. 𐑕𐑴 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑐𐑫𐑼 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜, 𐑣𐑵, 𐑨𐑟 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑽, 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑓𐑱𐑕 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑮𐑱𐑡 𐑝 𐑞 𐑤𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑚𐑳𐑑—𐑨𐑟 𐑢𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑧𐑤𐑕𐑢𐑺 𐑕𐑰𐑯—𐑥𐑬𐑯𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑛𐑧𐑛 𐑚𐑨𐑒 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑮𐑴𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑰; 𐑯 𐑓𐑲𐑯𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑜𐑤𐑵𐑥 𐑝 𐑞 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛, 𐑯 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑼𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑢𐑧𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑷𐑤 𐑛𐑱 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑚𐑑𐑼𐑱𐑯𐑾𐑕 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑓𐑲𐑯𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑, 𐑮𐑧𐑟𐑩𐑤𐑵𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑥𐑨𐑯𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑤 𐑞 𐑒𐑤𐑳𐑥𐑟𐑾𐑕𐑑 𐑒𐑭𐑕𐑒𐑕 𐑯 𐑕𐑰 𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑕𐑑𐑴𐑦𐑡. 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑖𐑹𐑑, 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑥𐑧𐑯, 𐑞 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑽𐑟 𐑸 𐑞 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑼𐑟, 𐑕𐑴 𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑛.

𐑐𐑫𐑼 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜! 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑣𐑭𐑓 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑦𐑥𐑚𐑬𐑩𐑤𐑛, 𐑿 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑕𐑑𐑵𐑐𐑑 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑞 𐑣𐑨𐑗𐑢𐑱, 𐑯 𐑐𐑽𐑛 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑞𐑺; 𐑢𐑺, 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑑 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑫𐑤𐑩𐑯 𐑛𐑮𐑷𐑼𐑟, 𐑞 𐑑𐑩𐑑𐑵𐑛 𐑕𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑡 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑒𐑮𐑷𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑩𐑥𐑦𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑛𐑨𐑥𐑐𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑯 𐑕𐑤𐑲𐑥, 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑯 𐑕𐑐𐑪𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑤𐑦𐑟𐑼𐑛 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑚𐑪𐑑𐑩𐑥 𐑝 𐑩 𐑢𐑧𐑤. 𐑯 𐑩 𐑢𐑧𐑤, 𐑹 𐑩𐑯 𐑲𐑕-𐑣𐑬𐑕, 𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑣𐑬 𐑐𐑮𐑵𐑝𐑛 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑐𐑫𐑼 𐑐𐑱𐑜𐑩𐑯; 𐑢𐑺, 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡 𐑑 𐑕𐑱, 𐑓 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑣𐑰𐑑 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑢𐑧𐑑𐑦𐑙𐑟, 𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑷𐑑 𐑩 𐑑𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑗𐑦𐑤 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑤𐑨𐑐𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑩 𐑓𐑰𐑝𐑼; 𐑯 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑, 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑛𐑱𐑟' 𐑕𐑳𐑓𐑼𐑦𐑙, 𐑤𐑱𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑥𐑩𐑒, 𐑒𐑤𐑴𐑕 𐑑 𐑞 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑕𐑦𐑤 𐑝 𐑞 𐑛𐑹 𐑝 𐑛𐑧𐑔. 𐑣𐑬 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑱𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑯 𐑢𐑱𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑩𐑢𐑱 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑓𐑿 𐑤𐑪𐑙-𐑤𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑛𐑱𐑟, 𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑞𐑺 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑤𐑧𐑓𐑑 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑮𐑱𐑥 𐑯 𐑑𐑩𐑑𐑵𐑦𐑙. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑷𐑤 𐑧𐑤𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑔𐑦𐑯𐑛, 𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑗𐑰𐑒-𐑚𐑴𐑯𐑟 𐑜𐑮𐑵 𐑖𐑸𐑐𐑼, 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑲𐑟, 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼𐑞𐑩𐑤𐑧𐑕, 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑜𐑮𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑫𐑤𐑼 𐑯 𐑓𐑫𐑤𐑼; 𐑞𐑱 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑱𐑥 𐑝 𐑩 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡 𐑕𐑪𐑓𐑑𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑤𐑳𐑕𐑑𐑼; 𐑯 𐑥𐑲𐑤𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑛𐑰𐑐𐑤𐑦 𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑑 𐑬𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑿 𐑞𐑺 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑯𐑩𐑕, 𐑩 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑕 𐑑𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑦 𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑥𐑹𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑔 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑛𐑲, 𐑹 𐑚𐑰 𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑛. 𐑯 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑕𐑻𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼, 𐑢𐑦𐑗, 𐑨𐑟 𐑞𐑱 𐑜𐑮𐑴 𐑓𐑱𐑯𐑑𐑼, 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑨𐑯𐑛; 𐑕𐑴 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑲𐑟 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑯 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙, 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑞 𐑮𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑝 ·𐑦𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑦. 𐑩𐑯 𐑷 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑯𐑱𐑥𐑛 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑕𐑑𐑰𐑤 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑿 𐑨𐑟 𐑿 𐑕𐑨𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑝 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑱𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑡, 𐑯 𐑕𐑷 𐑨𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑱𐑕, 𐑨𐑟 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑚𐑦𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑛 𐑣𐑵 𐑢𐑻 𐑚𐑲𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑟 𐑢𐑧𐑯 ·𐑟𐑹𐑴𐑨𐑕𐑑𐑼 𐑛𐑲𐑛. 𐑓 𐑢𐑪𐑑𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑦𐑟 𐑑𐑮𐑵𐑤𐑦 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑕 𐑯 𐑓𐑽𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑨𐑯, 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑐𐑫𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑢𐑻𐑛𐑟 𐑹 𐑚𐑫𐑒𐑕. 𐑯 𐑞 𐑛𐑮𐑷𐑦𐑙 𐑯𐑽 𐑝 ·𐑛𐑧𐑔, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑩𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑤𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑷𐑤, 𐑩𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑷𐑤 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑮𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑩𐑯 𐑷𐑔𐑼 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑛 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑨𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑢𐑩𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑑𐑧𐑤. 𐑕𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑—𐑤𐑧𐑑 𐑳𐑕 𐑕𐑱 𐑦𐑑 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯—𐑯𐑴 𐑛𐑲𐑦𐑙 ·𐑗𐑭𐑤𐑛𐑰 𐑹 ·𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑒 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑣𐑲𐑼 𐑯 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑽 𐑔𐑷𐑑𐑕 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑞𐑴𐑟, 𐑣𐑵𐑟 𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑽𐑾𐑕 𐑖𐑱𐑛𐑟 𐑿 𐑕𐑷 𐑒𐑮𐑰𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑞 𐑓𐑱𐑕 𐑝 𐑐𐑫𐑼 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜, 𐑨𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑢𐑲𐑩𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑤𐑱 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑢𐑱𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑨𐑥𐑩𐑒, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑮𐑴𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑰 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑪𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑲𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑑, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯'𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑦𐑟𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑓𐑤𐑳𐑛-𐑑𐑲𐑛 𐑤𐑦𐑓𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑣𐑲𐑼 𐑯 𐑣𐑲𐑼 𐑑𐑩𐑢𐑹𐑛𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑛𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑛 𐑣𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑯.

𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑩 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑵 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑜𐑱𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑳𐑐; 𐑯, 𐑨𐑟 𐑓 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓, 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑔𐑷𐑑 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑱𐑕 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑓𐑹𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑖𐑴𐑯 𐑚𐑲 𐑩 𐑒𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑾𐑕 𐑓𐑱𐑝𐑼 𐑣𐑰 𐑭𐑕𐑒𐑑. 𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑛 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑱 𐑥𐑹𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑪𐑗, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑞 𐑛𐑱 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑡𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑒𐑦𐑙, 𐑯 𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛, 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑦𐑯 ·𐑯𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑗𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑑 𐑕𐑰 𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑵𐑟 𐑝 𐑛𐑸𐑒 𐑢𐑫𐑛, 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑞 𐑮𐑦𐑗 𐑢𐑹-𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑱𐑑𐑦𐑝 𐑲𐑤; 𐑯 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑢𐑲𐑼𐑦, 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑤𐑻𐑯𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑣𐑵 𐑛𐑲𐑛 𐑦𐑯 ·𐑯𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑑, 𐑢𐑻 𐑤𐑱𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑛𐑸𐑒 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑵𐑟, 𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑓𐑨𐑯𐑕𐑦 𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑴 𐑤𐑱𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑐𐑤𐑰𐑟𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥; 𐑓 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑳𐑯𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑞 𐑒𐑳𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑥 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑴𐑯 𐑮𐑱𐑕, 𐑣𐑵, 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑦𐑥𐑚𐑭𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑛𐑧𐑛 𐑢𐑹𐑽, 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑧𐑗𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑬𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑵, 𐑯 𐑕𐑴 𐑤𐑧𐑓𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑓𐑤𐑴𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑩𐑢𐑱 𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑦 𐑸𐑒𐑦𐑐𐑧𐑤𐑩𐑜𐑴𐑟; 𐑓 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑵 𐑞𐑱 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑰𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑟 𐑸 𐑲𐑤𐑟, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑓𐑸 𐑚𐑦𐑘𐑪𐑯𐑛 𐑷𐑤 𐑝𐑦𐑟𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑣𐑼𐑲𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑟, 𐑞𐑺 𐑴𐑯 𐑥𐑲𐑤𐑛, 𐑳𐑯𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑕𐑰𐑟, 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑓𐑤𐑴 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑚𐑤𐑵 𐑣𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑯𐑟; 𐑯 𐑕𐑴 𐑓𐑹𐑥 𐑞 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑒𐑼𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑥𐑦𐑤𐑒𐑦 𐑢𐑱. 𐑣𐑰 𐑨𐑛𐑩𐑛, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑖𐑳𐑛𐑼𐑛 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑔𐑷𐑑 𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑥𐑩𐑒, 𐑩𐑒𐑹𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑞 𐑿𐑠𐑵𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑰-𐑒𐑳𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑥, 𐑑𐑪𐑕𐑑 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑝𐑲𐑤 𐑑 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑔-𐑛𐑦𐑝𐑬𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑖𐑸𐑒𐑕. 𐑯𐑴: 𐑣𐑰 𐑛𐑦𐑟𐑲𐑼𐑛 𐑩 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑵 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑝 ·𐑯𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑑, 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑥𐑹 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑡𐑰𐑯𐑾𐑤 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑥𐑩𐑯, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑢𐑱𐑤-𐑚𐑴𐑑 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑒𐑪𐑓𐑦𐑯-𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑵𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑 𐑩 𐑒𐑰𐑤; 𐑞𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑪𐑤𐑝𐑛 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑳𐑯𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑽𐑦𐑙, 𐑯 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑤𐑰-𐑢𐑱 𐑱𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑞 𐑛𐑦𐑥 𐑱𐑡𐑩𐑟.

𐑯𐑬, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡 𐑕𐑻𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑕 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑯𐑴𐑯 𐑭𐑓𐑑, 𐑞 𐑒𐑸𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑼 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑕 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑭𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑑 𐑛𐑵 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜'𐑟 𐑚𐑦𐑛𐑦𐑙, 𐑢𐑪𐑑𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑦𐑑 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑤𐑵𐑛. 𐑞𐑺 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑣𐑰𐑞𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑖, 𐑒𐑪𐑓𐑦𐑯-𐑒𐑳𐑤𐑼𐑛 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑤𐑳𐑥𐑚𐑼 𐑩𐑚𐑹𐑛, 𐑢𐑦𐑗, 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑩 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑐𐑮𐑰𐑝𐑾𐑕 𐑝𐑶𐑦𐑡, 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑒𐑳𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑨𐑚𐑼𐑦𐑡𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑜𐑮𐑴𐑝𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑤𐑨𐑒𐑩𐑛𐑱 𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛𐑟, 𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑛𐑸𐑒 𐑐𐑤𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑕 𐑞 𐑒𐑪𐑓𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑥𐑱𐑛. 𐑯𐑴 𐑕𐑵𐑯𐑼 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞 𐑒𐑸𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑼 𐑩𐑐𐑮𐑲𐑟𐑛 𐑝 𐑞 𐑹𐑛𐑼, 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑮𐑵𐑤, 𐑣𐑰 𐑓𐑹𐑔𐑢𐑦𐑔 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑓𐑼𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑥𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑑𐑿𐑛 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑨𐑮𐑩𐑒𐑑𐑼, 𐑐𐑮𐑴𐑕𐑰𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑓𐑴𐑒𐑕𐑩𐑤 𐑯 𐑑𐑫𐑒 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜'𐑟 𐑥𐑧𐑠𐑼 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑨𐑒𐑘𐑼𐑩𐑕𐑦, 𐑮𐑧𐑜𐑿𐑤𐑼𐑤𐑦 𐑗𐑷𐑒𐑦𐑙 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜'𐑟 𐑐𐑻𐑕𐑩𐑯 𐑨𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑖𐑦𐑓𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑞 𐑮𐑵𐑤.

“𐑭! 𐑐𐑫𐑼 𐑓𐑧𐑤𐑴! 𐑣𐑰'𐑤 𐑣𐑨𐑓 𐑑 𐑛𐑲 𐑯𐑬,” 𐑦𐑡𐑨𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑞 ·𐑤𐑪𐑙 ·𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑼.

𐑜𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑝𐑲𐑕-𐑚𐑧𐑯𐑗, 𐑞 𐑒𐑸𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑼 𐑓 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑝𐑰𐑯𐑾𐑯𐑕 𐑕𐑱𐑒 𐑯 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑮𐑧𐑓𐑼𐑩𐑯𐑕, 𐑯𐑬 𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑕𐑓𐑻𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑥𐑧𐑠𐑼𐑛 𐑪𐑯 𐑦𐑑 𐑞 𐑦𐑜𐑟𐑨𐑒𐑑 𐑤𐑧𐑙𐑔 𐑞 𐑒𐑪𐑓𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑑 𐑚𐑰, 𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑞 𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑕𐑓𐑻 𐑐𐑻𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑒𐑳𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑑𐑵 𐑯𐑪𐑗𐑩𐑟 𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑧𐑥𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑟. 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑛𐑳𐑯, 𐑣𐑰 𐑥𐑸𐑖𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑞 𐑐𐑤𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑕 𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑑𐑵𐑤𐑟, 𐑯 𐑑 𐑢𐑻𐑒.

𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑞 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑯𐑱𐑤 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑛𐑮𐑦𐑝𐑩𐑯, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑤𐑦𐑛 𐑛𐑵𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑯𐑛 𐑯 𐑓𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑛, 𐑣𐑰 𐑤𐑲𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑖𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑼𐑛 𐑞 𐑒𐑪𐑓𐑦𐑯 𐑯 𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑓𐑹𐑢𐑼𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑦𐑑, 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑢𐑲𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑞𐑱 𐑢𐑻 𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑦 𐑓 𐑦𐑑 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯.

𐑴𐑝𐑼𐑣𐑽𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑜𐑯𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑣𐑭𐑓-𐑣𐑿𐑥𐑼𐑩𐑕 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑞 𐑐𐑰𐑐𐑩𐑤 𐑪𐑯 𐑛𐑧𐑒 𐑚𐑦𐑜𐑨𐑯 𐑑 𐑛𐑮𐑲𐑝 𐑞 𐑒𐑪𐑓𐑦𐑯 𐑩𐑢𐑱, ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜, 𐑑 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑢𐑳𐑯'𐑟 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑯𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯, 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑭𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑚𐑰 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑮𐑷𐑑 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑯𐑹 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞𐑺 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑛𐑦𐑯𐑲𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑥; 𐑕𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑨𐑑, 𐑝 𐑷𐑤 𐑥𐑹𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑟, 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑛𐑲𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑸 𐑞 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑑𐑦𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤; 𐑯 𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑦, 𐑕𐑦𐑯𐑕 𐑞𐑱 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑖𐑹𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑳𐑕 𐑕𐑴 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑓 𐑧𐑝𐑼𐑥𐑹, 𐑞 𐑐𐑫𐑼 𐑓𐑧𐑤𐑴𐑟 𐑷𐑑 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑳𐑤𐑡𐑛.

𐑤𐑰𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑥𐑩𐑒, ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑮𐑦𐑜𐑸𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑞 𐑒𐑪𐑓𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩𐑯 𐑩𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑝 𐑲. 𐑣𐑰 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑛 𐑓 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯, 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑞 𐑢𐑫𐑛𐑩𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑪𐑒 𐑛𐑮𐑷𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑦𐑑, 𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑞 𐑲𐑼𐑯 𐑐𐑸𐑑 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑒𐑪𐑓𐑦𐑯 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑐𐑨𐑛𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑴𐑑. 𐑷𐑤 𐑚𐑲 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑴𐑯 𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑕𐑑, 𐑷𐑤𐑕𐑴, 𐑚𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑢𐑻 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑛 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑞 𐑕𐑲𐑛𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑦𐑯: 𐑩 𐑓𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑒 𐑝 𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑖 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑣𐑧𐑛, 𐑯 𐑩 𐑕𐑥𐑷𐑤 𐑚𐑨𐑜 𐑝 𐑢𐑫𐑛𐑦 𐑻𐑔 𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑱𐑐𐑑 𐑳𐑐 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑓𐑫𐑑; 𐑯 𐑩 𐑐𐑰𐑕 𐑝 𐑕𐑱𐑤-𐑒𐑤𐑪𐑔 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑮𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑳𐑐 𐑓 𐑩 𐑐𐑦𐑤𐑴, ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜 𐑯𐑬 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑰𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑤𐑦𐑓𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑲𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑚𐑧𐑛, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑥𐑱𐑒 𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑓𐑼𐑑𐑕, 𐑦𐑓 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑦𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑛. 𐑣𐑰 𐑤𐑱 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑 𐑥𐑵𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑓𐑿 𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑕, 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑑𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑑 𐑜𐑴 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑨𐑜 𐑯 𐑚𐑮𐑦𐑙 𐑬𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑜𐑪𐑛, ·𐑘𐑴𐑡𐑴. 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑒𐑮𐑪𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑸𐑥𐑟 𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 ·𐑘𐑴𐑡𐑴 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑢𐑰𐑯, 𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑛 𐑓 𐑞 𐑒𐑪𐑓𐑦𐑯 𐑤𐑦𐑛 (𐑣𐑨𐑗 𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑛 𐑦𐑑) 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕𐑑 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑣𐑦𐑥. 𐑞 𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑐𐑸𐑑 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑛 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑤𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑣𐑦𐑯𐑡, 𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑤𐑱 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑪𐑓𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑴𐑟𐑛 𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑝𐑿. “·𐑮𐑸𐑥𐑲” (𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑛𐑵; 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑰𐑟𐑦), 𐑣𐑰 𐑥𐑻𐑥𐑼𐑛 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑, 𐑯 𐑕𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑥𐑩𐑒.

𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑺 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑛𐑳𐑯, ·𐑐𐑦𐑐, 𐑣𐑵 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑕𐑤𐑲𐑤𐑦 𐑣𐑪𐑝𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑯𐑽 𐑚𐑲 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑲𐑤, 𐑛𐑮𐑵 𐑯𐑲 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑢𐑺 𐑣𐑰 𐑤𐑱, 𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑕𐑪𐑓𐑑 𐑕𐑪𐑚𐑦𐑙𐑟, 𐑑𐑫𐑒 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛; 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑳𐑞𐑼, 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑑𐑨𐑥𐑚𐑼𐑰𐑯.

“𐑐𐑫𐑼 𐑮𐑴𐑝𐑼! 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑘𐑰 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑛𐑳𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑽𐑦 𐑮𐑴𐑝𐑦𐑙? 𐑢𐑺 𐑜𐑴 𐑘𐑰 𐑯𐑬? 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑓 𐑞 𐑒𐑳𐑮𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑒𐑨𐑮𐑦 𐑘𐑰 𐑑 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑕𐑢𐑰𐑑 ·𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑺 𐑞 𐑚𐑰𐑗𐑩𐑟 𐑸 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑰𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼-𐑤𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑟, 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑘𐑰 𐑛𐑵 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑧𐑮𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑓 𐑥𐑰? 𐑕𐑰𐑒 𐑬𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯 ·𐑐𐑦𐑐, 𐑣𐑵'𐑟 𐑯𐑬 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑤𐑪𐑙: 𐑲 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒 𐑣𐑰'𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑓𐑸 ·𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑟. 𐑦𐑓 𐑘𐑰 𐑓𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑓𐑼𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥; 𐑓 𐑣𐑰 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑕𐑨𐑛; 𐑓 𐑤𐑫𐑒! 𐑣𐑰'𐑟 𐑤𐑧𐑓𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑑𐑨𐑥𐑚𐑼𐑰𐑯 𐑚𐑦𐑣𐑲𐑯𐑛;—𐑲 𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑑. 𐑮𐑦𐑜-𐑩-𐑛𐑦𐑜, 𐑛𐑦𐑜, 𐑛𐑦𐑜! 𐑯𐑬, ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜, 𐑛𐑲; 𐑯 𐑲'𐑤 𐑚𐑰𐑑 𐑘𐑰 𐑘𐑹 𐑛𐑲𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑸𐑗.”

“𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑣𐑻𐑛,” 𐑥𐑻𐑥𐑼𐑛 ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒, 𐑜𐑱𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑒𐑳𐑑𐑩𐑤, “𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑓𐑰𐑝𐑼𐑟, 𐑥𐑧𐑯, 𐑷𐑤 𐑦𐑜𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑯𐑕, 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑑𐑷𐑒𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑱𐑯𐑗𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑑𐑳𐑙𐑟; 𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑞 𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑦 𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑮𐑴𐑚𐑛, 𐑦𐑑 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑟 𐑬𐑑 𐑷𐑤𐑢𐑱𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑦 𐑓𐑼𐑜𐑪𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑗𐑲𐑤𐑛𐑣𐑫𐑛 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑱𐑯𐑗𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑑𐑳𐑙𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑮𐑾𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑐𐑴𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑣𐑽𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑲 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑤𐑪𐑓𐑑𐑦 𐑕𐑒𐑪𐑤𐑼𐑟. 𐑕𐑴, 𐑑 𐑥𐑲 𐑓𐑪𐑯𐑛 𐑓𐑱𐑔, 𐑐𐑫𐑼 ·𐑐𐑦𐑐, 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡 𐑕𐑢𐑰𐑑𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑤𐑵𐑯𐑩𐑕𐑦, 𐑚𐑮𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑣𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑝𐑬𐑗𐑼𐑟 𐑝 𐑷𐑤 𐑬𐑼 𐑣𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑣𐑴𐑥𐑟. 𐑢𐑺 𐑤𐑻𐑯𐑛 𐑣𐑰 𐑞𐑨𐑑, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞𐑺?—𐑣𐑸𐑒! 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑕 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯: 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑥𐑹 𐑢𐑲𐑤𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑯𐑬.”

“𐑓𐑹𐑥 𐑑𐑵 𐑯 𐑑𐑵! 𐑤𐑧𐑑'𐑕 𐑥𐑱𐑒 𐑩 ·𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑥! 𐑣𐑴, 𐑢𐑺'𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯? 𐑤𐑱 𐑦𐑑 𐑩𐑒𐑮𐑪𐑕 𐑣𐑽.—𐑮𐑦𐑜-𐑩-𐑛𐑦𐑜, 𐑛𐑦𐑜, 𐑛𐑦𐑜! 𐑣𐑩𐑟𐑭! 𐑴 𐑓 𐑩 𐑜𐑱𐑥 𐑒𐑪𐑒 𐑯𐑬 𐑑 𐑕𐑦𐑑 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑯 𐑒𐑮𐑴! ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜 𐑛𐑲𐑟 𐑜𐑱𐑥!—𐑥𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑘𐑰 𐑞𐑨𐑑; ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜 𐑛𐑲𐑟 𐑜𐑱𐑥!—𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑘𐑰 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑣𐑰𐑛 𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑; ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜 𐑛𐑲𐑟 𐑜𐑱𐑥! 𐑲 𐑕𐑱; 𐑜𐑱𐑥, 𐑜𐑱𐑥, 𐑜𐑱𐑥! 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑚𐑱𐑕 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 ·𐑐𐑦𐑐, 𐑣𐑰 𐑛𐑲𐑛 𐑩 𐑒𐑬𐑼𐑛; 𐑛𐑲𐑛 𐑷𐑤 𐑩'𐑖𐑦𐑝𐑼;—𐑬𐑑 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 ·𐑐𐑦𐑐! 𐑣𐑸𐑒 𐑘𐑰; 𐑦𐑓 𐑘𐑰 𐑓𐑲𐑯𐑛 ·𐑐𐑦𐑐, 𐑑𐑧𐑤 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 ·𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑰'𐑟 𐑩 𐑮𐑳𐑯𐑩𐑢𐑱; 𐑩 𐑒𐑬𐑼𐑛, 𐑩 𐑒𐑬𐑼𐑛, 𐑩 𐑒𐑬𐑼𐑛! 𐑑𐑧𐑤 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑣𐑰 𐑡𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑩 𐑢𐑱𐑤-𐑚𐑴𐑑! 𐑲'𐑛 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑚𐑰𐑑 𐑥𐑲 𐑑𐑨𐑥𐑚𐑼𐑰𐑯 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑚𐑱𐑕 ·𐑐𐑦𐑐, 𐑯 𐑣𐑱𐑤 𐑣𐑦𐑥 ·𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑤, 𐑦𐑓 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑻 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑕 𐑥𐑹 𐑛𐑲𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑽. 𐑯𐑴, 𐑯𐑴! 𐑖𐑱𐑥 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑒𐑬𐑼𐑛𐑟—𐑖𐑱𐑥 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑥! 𐑤𐑧𐑑 '𐑩𐑥 𐑜𐑴 𐑛𐑮𐑬𐑯 𐑤𐑲𐑒 ·𐑐𐑦𐑐, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑡𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑩 𐑢𐑱𐑤-𐑚𐑴𐑑. 𐑖𐑱𐑥! 𐑖𐑱𐑥!”

𐑛𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑦𐑕, ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜 𐑤𐑱 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑒𐑤𐑴𐑟𐑛 𐑲𐑟, 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑓 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑛𐑮𐑰𐑥. 𐑐𐑦𐑐 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑤𐑧𐑛 𐑩𐑢𐑱, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑦𐑒 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑥𐑩𐑒.

𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑯𐑬 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑩𐑐𐑨𐑮𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑐𐑼𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑓 𐑛𐑧𐑔; 𐑯𐑬 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑪𐑓𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑐𐑮𐑵𐑝𐑛 𐑩 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑓𐑦𐑑, ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜 𐑕𐑳𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑨𐑤𐑦𐑛; 𐑕𐑵𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑯𐑴 𐑯𐑰𐑛 𐑝 𐑞 𐑒𐑸𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑼'𐑟 𐑚𐑪𐑒𐑕: 𐑯 𐑞𐑺𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑕𐑼𐑐𐑮𐑲𐑟, 𐑣𐑰, 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑚𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕, 𐑕𐑧𐑛, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑒𐑷𐑟 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑳𐑛𐑩𐑯 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞𐑦𐑕;—𐑨𐑑 𐑩 𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑥𐑴𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑, 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑡𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑛 𐑩 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑛𐑿𐑑𐑦 𐑩𐑖𐑹, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑤𐑰𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑳𐑯; 𐑯 𐑞𐑺𐑓𐑹 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑗𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑛𐑲𐑦𐑙: 𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑛𐑲 𐑘𐑧𐑑, 𐑣𐑰 𐑩𐑝𐑻𐑛. 𐑞𐑱 𐑭𐑕𐑒𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑢𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑑 𐑤𐑦𐑝 𐑹 𐑛𐑲 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩 𐑥𐑨𐑑𐑼 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑴𐑯 𐑕𐑪𐑝𐑮𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑯 𐑐𐑤𐑧𐑠𐑼. 𐑣𐑰 𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑼𐑛, 𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑦. 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑢𐑻𐑛, 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜'𐑟 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑰𐑑, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑓 𐑩 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑳𐑐 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑑 𐑤𐑦𐑝, 𐑥𐑽 𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑒𐑦𐑤 𐑣𐑦𐑥: 𐑯𐑳𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑩 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑹 𐑩 𐑜𐑱𐑤, 𐑹 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑑, 𐑳𐑯𐑜𐑳𐑝𐑼𐑯𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤, 𐑳𐑯𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑡𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑶𐑼 𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑹𐑑.

𐑯𐑬, 𐑞𐑺 𐑦𐑟 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑯𐑴𐑑𐑢𐑻𐑞𐑦 𐑛𐑦𐑓𐑼𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑢𐑰𐑯 𐑕𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑡 𐑯 𐑕𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑤𐑲𐑟𐑛; 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑩 𐑕𐑦𐑒, 𐑕𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑤𐑲𐑟𐑛 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑥𐑱 𐑚𐑰 𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑕 𐑥𐑳𐑯𐑔𐑕 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑧𐑕𐑦𐑙, 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑦𐑙, 𐑩 𐑕𐑦𐑒 𐑕𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑡 𐑦𐑟 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑭𐑓-𐑢𐑧𐑤 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑛𐑱. 𐑕𐑴, 𐑦𐑯 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑥𐑲 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜 𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑛 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑧𐑙𐑔; 𐑯 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑧𐑙𐑔 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑕𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑓 𐑩 𐑓𐑿 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑛𐑱𐑟 (𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑰𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑝𐑦𐑜𐑼𐑩𐑕 𐑨𐑐𐑩𐑑𐑲𐑑) 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑳𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑤𐑰𐑐𐑑 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑰𐑑, 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑬𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑸𐑥𐑟 𐑯 𐑤𐑧𐑜𐑟, 𐑜𐑱𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑩 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑧𐑗𐑦𐑙, 𐑘𐑷𐑯𐑛 𐑩 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑚𐑦𐑑, 𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑙𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑶𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑴𐑑, 𐑯 𐑐𐑶𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯, 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑯𐑬𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑓𐑦𐑑 𐑓 𐑩 𐑓𐑲𐑑.

𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑢𐑲𐑤𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑥𐑟𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑕, 𐑣𐑰 𐑯𐑬 𐑿𐑟𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑪𐑓𐑦𐑯 𐑓 𐑩 𐑕𐑰-𐑗𐑧𐑕𐑑; 𐑯 𐑧𐑥𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑦𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑝𐑩𐑕 𐑚𐑨𐑜 𐑝 𐑒𐑤𐑴𐑞𐑟, 𐑕𐑧𐑑 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑦𐑯 𐑹𐑛𐑼 𐑞𐑺. 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑕𐑐𐑺 𐑬𐑼𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑑, 𐑦𐑯 𐑒𐑸𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑤𐑦𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑷𐑤 𐑥𐑨𐑯𐑼 𐑝 𐑜𐑮𐑴𐑑𐑧𐑕𐑒 𐑓𐑦𐑜𐑼𐑟 𐑯 𐑛𐑮𐑷𐑦𐑙𐑟; 𐑯 𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑽𐑚𐑲 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑝𐑦𐑙, 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑮𐑵𐑛 𐑢𐑱, 𐑑 𐑒𐑪𐑐𐑦 𐑐𐑸𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑑𐑢𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑑𐑩𐑑𐑵𐑦𐑙 𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦. 𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑑𐑩𐑑𐑵𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑻𐑒 𐑝 𐑩 𐑛𐑦𐑐𐑸𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑓𐑩𐑑 𐑯 𐑕𐑰𐑼 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛, 𐑣𐑵, 𐑚𐑲 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑣𐑲𐑮𐑩𐑜𐑤𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑒 𐑥𐑸𐑒𐑕, 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑬𐑑 𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦 𐑩 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑰𐑑 𐑔𐑽𐑦 𐑝 𐑞 𐑣𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑯 𐑞 𐑻𐑔, 𐑯 𐑩 𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑑𐑮𐑰𐑑𐑦𐑟 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑸𐑑 𐑝 𐑩𐑑𐑱𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑑𐑮𐑵𐑔; 𐑕𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑴𐑯 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑐𐑼 𐑐𐑻𐑕𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩 𐑮𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑤 𐑑 𐑳𐑯𐑓𐑴𐑤𐑛; 𐑩 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑕 𐑢𐑻𐑒 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝𐑪𐑤𐑿𐑥; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑣𐑵𐑟 𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑮𐑰𐑛, 𐑞𐑴 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑴𐑯 𐑤𐑲𐑝 𐑣𐑸𐑑 𐑚𐑰𐑑 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑞𐑧𐑥; 𐑯 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑞𐑺𐑓𐑹 𐑛𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑑 𐑥𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑼 𐑩𐑢𐑱 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑤𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑐𐑸𐑗𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑢𐑺𐑪𐑯 𐑞𐑱 𐑢𐑻 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑚𐑛, 𐑯 𐑕𐑴 𐑚𐑰 𐑳𐑯𐑕𐑪𐑤𐑝𐑛 𐑑 𐑞 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑. 𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑔𐑷𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑕𐑩𐑡𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑑 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑲𐑤𐑛 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑒𐑤𐑩𐑥𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑥𐑹𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑢𐑱 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑕𐑼𐑝𐑱𐑦𐑙 𐑐𐑫𐑼 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜—“𐑴, 𐑛𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑖 𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑲𐑟𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑜𐑪𐑛𐑟!”

·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 111. 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑩𐑕𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑒.

𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑜𐑤𐑲𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 ·𐑚𐑨𐑖𐑰 𐑲𐑤𐑟 𐑢𐑰 𐑦𐑥𐑻𐑡𐑛 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 ·𐑕𐑬𐑔 ·𐑕𐑰; 𐑢𐑻 𐑦𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑓 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑟, 𐑲 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑥𐑲 𐑛𐑽 ·𐑐𐑩𐑕𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑒 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑳𐑯𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑔𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑕, 𐑓 𐑯𐑬 𐑞 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑕𐑳𐑐𐑤𐑦𐑒𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑥𐑲 𐑿𐑔 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑼𐑛; 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑼𐑰𐑯 𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑮𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑰𐑕𐑑𐑢𐑼𐑛𐑟 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑥𐑰 𐑩 𐑔𐑬𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑤𐑰𐑜𐑟 𐑝 𐑚𐑤𐑵.

𐑞𐑺 𐑦𐑟, 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑯𐑴𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑢𐑰𐑑 𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑦 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑕𐑰, 𐑣𐑵𐑟 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑷𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑑𐑻𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑕𐑰𐑥 𐑑 𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑒 𐑝 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑣𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑯 𐑕𐑴𐑤 𐑚𐑦𐑯𐑰𐑔; 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑓𐑱𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑳𐑯𐑡𐑩𐑤𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑦𐑓𐑰𐑠𐑩𐑯 𐑕𐑪𐑛 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑞 𐑚𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑛 ·𐑦𐑝𐑨𐑯𐑡𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑕𐑑 ·𐑕𐑑 ·𐑡𐑪𐑯. 𐑯 𐑥𐑰𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑕𐑰-𐑐𐑭𐑕𐑗𐑼𐑟, 𐑢𐑲𐑛-𐑮𐑴𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼𐑦 𐑐𐑮𐑺𐑦𐑟 𐑯 ·𐑐𐑪𐑑𐑼𐑟' ·𐑓𐑰𐑤𐑛𐑟 𐑝 𐑷𐑤 𐑓𐑹 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕, 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑝𐑟 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑮𐑲𐑟 𐑯 𐑓𐑷𐑤, 𐑯 𐑧𐑚 𐑯 𐑓𐑤𐑴 𐑳𐑯𐑕𐑰𐑕𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦; 𐑓 𐑣𐑽, 𐑥𐑦𐑤𐑾𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑥𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑑 𐑖𐑱𐑛𐑟 𐑯 𐑖𐑨𐑛𐑴𐑟, 𐑛𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑛𐑮𐑰𐑥𐑟, 𐑕𐑪𐑥𐑯𐑨𐑥𐑚𐑿𐑤𐑦𐑟𐑩𐑥𐑟, 𐑮𐑧𐑝𐑼𐑦𐑟; 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑰 𐑒𐑷𐑤 𐑤𐑲𐑝𐑟 𐑯 𐑕𐑴𐑤𐑟, 𐑤𐑲 𐑛𐑮𐑰𐑥𐑦𐑙, 𐑛𐑮𐑰𐑥𐑦𐑙, 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤; 𐑑𐑪𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑕𐑤𐑳𐑥𐑚𐑼𐑼𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑚𐑧𐑛𐑟; 𐑞 𐑧𐑝𐑼-𐑮𐑴𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑱𐑝𐑟 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑕𐑴 𐑚𐑲 𐑞𐑺 𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑤𐑩𐑕𐑯𐑩𐑕.

𐑑 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑥𐑧𐑛𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑑𐑦𐑝 ·𐑥𐑱𐑡𐑾𐑯 𐑮𐑴𐑝𐑼, 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑕𐑼𐑰𐑯 ·𐑐𐑩𐑕𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑒, 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑕 𐑚𐑦𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑛, 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑚𐑰 𐑞 𐑕𐑰 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑩𐑛𐑪𐑐𐑖𐑩𐑯. 𐑦𐑑 𐑮𐑴𐑤𐑟 𐑞 𐑥𐑦𐑛𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛, 𐑞 ·𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑾𐑯 𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑯 ·𐑩𐑑𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑸𐑥𐑟. 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑢𐑱𐑝𐑟 𐑢𐑪𐑖 𐑞 𐑥𐑴𐑤𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑯𐑿-𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑑 ·𐑒𐑨𐑤𐑦𐑓𐑹𐑯𐑾𐑯 𐑑𐑬𐑯𐑟, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑘𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑛𐑱 𐑐𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑮𐑰𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑮𐑱𐑕 𐑝 𐑥𐑧𐑯, 𐑯 𐑤𐑱𐑝 𐑞 𐑓𐑱𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑜𐑹𐑡𐑩𐑕 𐑕𐑒𐑻𐑑𐑕 𐑝 ·𐑱𐑠𐑦𐑨𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟, 𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑼 𐑞𐑨𐑯 ·𐑱𐑚𐑮𐑩𐑣𐑨𐑥; 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑷𐑤 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑢𐑰𐑯 𐑓𐑤𐑴𐑑 𐑥𐑦𐑤𐑒𐑦-𐑢𐑱𐑟 𐑝 𐑒𐑪𐑮𐑩𐑤 𐑲𐑤𐑟, 𐑯 𐑤𐑴-𐑤𐑲𐑦𐑙, 𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑤𐑩𐑕, 𐑳𐑯𐑯𐑴𐑯 ·𐑸𐑒𐑦𐑐𐑧𐑤𐑩𐑜𐑴𐑟, 𐑯 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑮𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 ·𐑡𐑩𐑐𐑨𐑯𐑟. 𐑞𐑳𐑕 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑽𐑾𐑕, 𐑛𐑦𐑝𐑲𐑯 ·𐑐𐑩𐑕𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑒 𐑟𐑴𐑯𐑟 𐑞 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛'𐑟 𐑣𐑴𐑤 𐑚𐑳𐑤𐑒 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑; 𐑥𐑱𐑒𐑕 𐑷𐑤 𐑒𐑴𐑕𐑑𐑕 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑚𐑱 𐑑 𐑦𐑑; 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑟 𐑞 𐑑𐑲𐑛-𐑚𐑰𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑸𐑑 𐑝 𐑻𐑔. 𐑤𐑦𐑓𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑦𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑢𐑧𐑤𐑟, 𐑿 𐑯𐑰𐑛𐑟 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑴𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑳𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑝 𐑜𐑪𐑛, 𐑚𐑬𐑦𐑙 𐑘𐑹 𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑑 ·𐑐𐑨𐑯.

𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑓𐑿 𐑔𐑷𐑑𐑕 𐑝 ·𐑐𐑨𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑻𐑛 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚'𐑟 𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑯, 𐑨𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩𐑯 𐑲𐑼𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑗𐑿 𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑩𐑒𐑳𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑥𐑛 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕 𐑚𐑦𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑞 𐑥𐑦𐑟𐑩𐑯 𐑮𐑦𐑜𐑦𐑙, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑯𐑪𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑩𐑤 𐑣𐑰 𐑳𐑯𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑯𐑳𐑓𐑑 𐑞 𐑖𐑫𐑜𐑼𐑦 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑒 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 ·𐑚𐑨𐑖𐑰 𐑲𐑤𐑟 (𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑵𐑟 𐑕𐑢𐑰𐑑 𐑢𐑫𐑛𐑟 𐑥𐑲𐑤𐑛 𐑤𐑳𐑝𐑼𐑟 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑢𐑷𐑒𐑦𐑙), 𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑯𐑣𐑱𐑤𐑛 𐑞 𐑕𐑷𐑤𐑑 𐑚𐑮𐑧𐑔 𐑝 𐑞 𐑯𐑿 𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑕𐑰; 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑰 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑞 𐑣𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 ·𐑢𐑲𐑑 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑚𐑰 𐑕𐑢𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑙. 𐑤𐑷𐑯𐑗𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑧𐑙𐑔 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑓𐑲𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼𐑟, 𐑯 𐑜𐑤𐑲𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑑𐑩𐑢𐑹𐑛𐑟 𐑞 ·𐑡𐑨𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑰𐑟 𐑒𐑮𐑵𐑟𐑦𐑙-𐑜𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛, 𐑞 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑥𐑨𐑯'𐑟 𐑐𐑻𐑐𐑩𐑕 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑓𐑲𐑛 𐑦𐑑𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓. 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑻𐑥 𐑤𐑦𐑐𐑕 𐑥𐑧𐑑 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑞 𐑤𐑦𐑐𐑕 𐑝 𐑩 𐑝𐑲𐑕; 𐑞 ·𐑛𐑧𐑤𐑑𐑩 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑛'𐑟 𐑝𐑱𐑯𐑟 𐑕𐑢𐑧𐑤𐑛 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑴𐑝𐑼𐑤𐑱𐑛𐑩𐑯 𐑚𐑮𐑫𐑒𐑕; 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑕𐑤𐑰𐑐, 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑮𐑦𐑙𐑦𐑙 𐑒𐑮𐑲 𐑮𐑨𐑯 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑞 𐑝𐑷𐑤𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑣𐑳𐑤, “𐑕𐑑𐑻𐑯 𐑷𐑤! 𐑞 ·𐑢𐑲𐑑 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑕𐑐𐑬𐑑𐑕 𐑔𐑦𐑒 𐑚𐑤𐑳𐑛!”

·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 112. 𐑞 ·𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑒𐑕𐑥𐑦𐑔.

𐑩𐑝𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑝 𐑞 𐑥𐑲𐑤𐑛, 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑼-𐑒𐑵𐑤 𐑢𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑯𐑬 𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑤𐑨𐑑𐑦𐑑𐑿𐑛𐑟, 𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑐𐑼𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑓 𐑞 𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑽𐑤𐑦 𐑨𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑝 𐑐𐑼𐑕𐑿𐑑𐑕 𐑖𐑹𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑕𐑦𐑐𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛, ·𐑐𐑻𐑔, 𐑞 𐑚𐑦𐑜𐑮𐑲𐑥𐑛, 𐑚𐑤𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑛 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑒𐑕𐑥𐑦𐑔, 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑵𐑝𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑹𐑑𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑓𐑹𐑡 𐑑 𐑞 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯, 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑒𐑤𐑵𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑚𐑿𐑑𐑼𐑦 𐑢𐑻𐑒 𐑓 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚'𐑟 𐑤𐑧𐑜, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑱𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑑 𐑪𐑯 𐑛𐑧𐑒, 𐑓𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑤𐑨𐑖𐑑 𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑙𐑚𐑴𐑤𐑑𐑕 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑓𐑹𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑; 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑯𐑬 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑴𐑒𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑟𐑥𐑧𐑯, 𐑯 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑽𐑟, 𐑯 𐑚𐑬𐑟𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑑 𐑛𐑵 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑡𐑪𐑚 𐑓 𐑞𐑧𐑥; 𐑷𐑤𐑑𐑼𐑦𐑙, 𐑹 𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑺𐑦𐑙, 𐑹 𐑯𐑿 𐑖𐑱𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑺 𐑝𐑺𐑾𐑕 𐑢𐑧𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑯 𐑚𐑴𐑑 𐑓𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑗𐑼. 𐑪𐑓𐑩𐑯 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑚𐑰 𐑕𐑼𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑩𐑯 𐑰𐑜𐑼 𐑕𐑻𐑒𐑩𐑤, 𐑷𐑤 𐑢𐑱𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑕𐑻𐑝𐑛; 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑴𐑑-𐑕𐑐𐑱𐑛𐑟, 𐑐𐑲𐑒-𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑟, 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑟, 𐑯 𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟, 𐑯 𐑡𐑧𐑤𐑩𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑢𐑪𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑕𐑫𐑑𐑦 𐑥𐑵𐑝𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑, 𐑨𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑑𐑶𐑤𐑛. 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼𐑞𐑩𐑤𐑧𐑕, 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑥𐑨𐑯'𐑟 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩 𐑐𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑥𐑼 𐑢𐑰𐑤𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑩 𐑐𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑸𐑥. 𐑯𐑴 𐑥𐑻𐑥𐑼, 𐑯𐑴 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑕, 𐑯𐑴 𐑐𐑧𐑑𐑿𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑣𐑦𐑥. 𐑕𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑑, 𐑕𐑤𐑴, 𐑯 𐑕𐑪𐑤𐑩𐑥; 𐑚𐑬𐑦𐑙 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑓𐑻𐑞𐑼 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑮𐑪𐑯𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑮𐑴𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑚𐑨𐑒, 𐑣𐑰 𐑑𐑶𐑤𐑛 𐑩𐑢𐑱, 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑓 𐑑𐑶𐑤 𐑢𐑻 𐑤𐑲𐑓 𐑦𐑑𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑣𐑧𐑝𐑦 𐑚𐑰𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑥𐑼 𐑞 𐑣𐑧𐑝𐑦 𐑚𐑰𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑸𐑑. 𐑯 𐑕𐑴 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟.—𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑥𐑦𐑟𐑼𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤!

𐑩 𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑽 𐑢𐑷𐑒 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑥𐑨𐑯, 𐑩 𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑕𐑤𐑲𐑑 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑐𐑱𐑯𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑩𐑐𐑽𐑦𐑙 𐑘𐑷𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑜𐑱𐑑, 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑨𐑑 𐑩𐑯 𐑻𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑽𐑾𐑛 𐑝 𐑞 𐑝𐑶𐑦𐑡 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑞 𐑒𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑦𐑪𐑕𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑝 𐑞 𐑥𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑯𐑼𐑟. 𐑯 𐑑 𐑞 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑼𐑑𐑿𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑝 𐑞𐑺 𐑐𐑼𐑕𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑕𐑗𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑓𐑲𐑯𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑜𐑦𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯; 𐑯 𐑕𐑴 𐑦𐑑 𐑒𐑱𐑥 𐑑 𐑐𐑭𐑕 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑯𐑬 𐑯𐑿 𐑞 𐑖𐑱𐑥𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑑𐑹𐑦 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑮𐑧𐑗𐑩𐑛 𐑓𐑱𐑑.

𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛, 𐑯 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦, 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑼 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼'𐑟 𐑥𐑦𐑛𐑯𐑲𐑑, 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑮𐑴𐑛 𐑮𐑳𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑢𐑰𐑯 𐑑𐑵 𐑒𐑳𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑦 𐑑𐑬𐑯𐑟, 𐑞 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑒𐑕𐑥𐑦𐑔 𐑣𐑭𐑓-𐑕𐑑𐑵𐑐𐑦𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑓𐑧𐑤𐑑 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑯𐑳𐑥𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑕𐑑𐑰𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑯 𐑕𐑷𐑑 𐑮𐑧𐑓𐑿𐑡 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑤𐑰𐑯𐑦𐑙, 𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑨𐑐𐑦𐑛𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑸𐑯. 𐑞 𐑦𐑖𐑿 𐑢𐑪𐑟, 𐑞 𐑤𐑪𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑧𐑥𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑟 𐑝 𐑚𐑴𐑔 𐑓𐑰𐑑. 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑮𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯, 𐑐𐑸𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑐𐑸𐑑, 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑒𐑱𐑥 𐑬𐑑 𐑞 𐑓𐑹 𐑨𐑒𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑜𐑤𐑨𐑛𐑯𐑩𐑕, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑤𐑪𐑙, 𐑯 𐑨𐑟 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑳𐑯𐑒𐑩𐑑𐑨𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑩𐑓𐑦𐑦𐑛 𐑓𐑦𐑓𐑔 𐑨𐑒𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑓 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑤𐑲𐑓'𐑕 𐑛𐑮𐑭𐑥𐑩.

𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩𐑯 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑥𐑨𐑯, 𐑣𐑵, 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑱𐑡 𐑝 𐑯𐑽𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑦, 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑐𐑴𐑕𐑑𐑐𐑴𐑯𐑩𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑪𐑮𐑴'𐑟 𐑑𐑧𐑒𐑯𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑛 𐑮𐑵𐑦𐑯. 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑩𐑯 𐑸𐑑𐑦𐑟𐑨𐑯 𐑝 𐑓𐑱𐑥𐑛 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑩𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑕, 𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑐𐑤𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑦 𐑑 𐑛𐑵; 𐑴𐑯𐑛 𐑩 𐑣𐑬𐑕 𐑯 𐑜𐑸𐑛𐑩𐑯; 𐑦𐑥𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑕𐑑 𐑩 𐑿𐑔𐑓𐑩𐑤, 𐑛𐑷𐑑𐑼-𐑤𐑲𐑒, 𐑤𐑳𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑲𐑓, 𐑯 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑚𐑤𐑲𐑞, 𐑮𐑳𐑛𐑦 𐑗𐑦𐑤𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑯; 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑕𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑱 𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑑 𐑩 𐑗𐑽𐑓𐑩𐑤-𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑗𐑻𐑗, 𐑐𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑜𐑮𐑴𐑝. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑯𐑲𐑑, 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑒𐑳𐑝𐑼 𐑝 𐑛𐑸𐑒𐑯𐑩𐑕, 𐑯 𐑓𐑻𐑞𐑼 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑰𐑤𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑒𐑳𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑜𐑲𐑟𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑, 𐑩 𐑛𐑧𐑕𐑐𐑼𐑩𐑑 𐑚𐑻𐑜𐑩𐑤𐑼 𐑕𐑤𐑦𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑦 𐑣𐑴𐑥, 𐑯 𐑮𐑪𐑚𐑛 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑷𐑤 𐑝 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦𐑔𐑦𐑙. 𐑯 𐑛𐑸𐑒𐑼 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑑 𐑑𐑧𐑤, 𐑞 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑒𐑕𐑥𐑦𐑔 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑦𐑜𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑛𐑳𐑒𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑚𐑻𐑜𐑩𐑤𐑼 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑨𐑥𐑤𐑦'𐑟 𐑣𐑸𐑑. 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞 ·𐑚𐑪𐑑𐑩𐑤 ·𐑒𐑳𐑯𐑡𐑼𐑼! 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑴𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑓𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑒𐑹𐑒, 𐑓𐑹𐑔 𐑓𐑤𐑵 𐑞 𐑓𐑰𐑯𐑛, 𐑯 𐑖𐑮𐑦𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑳𐑐 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑴𐑥. 𐑯𐑬, 𐑓 𐑐𐑮𐑵𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑑, 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑢𐑲𐑟, 𐑯 𐑰𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑪𐑥𐑦𐑒 𐑮𐑰𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑟, 𐑞 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑒𐑕𐑥𐑦𐑔'𐑕 𐑖𐑪𐑐 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑱𐑕𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑛𐑢𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑙, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑕𐑧𐑐𐑼𐑩𐑑 𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑑 𐑦𐑑; 𐑕𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑷𐑤𐑢𐑱𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑞 𐑘𐑳𐑙 𐑯 𐑤𐑳𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑔𐑦 𐑢𐑲𐑓 𐑤𐑦𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑯𐑴 𐑳𐑯𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑦 𐑯𐑻𐑝𐑩𐑕𐑯𐑩𐑕, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑝𐑦𐑜𐑼𐑩𐑕 𐑐𐑤𐑧𐑠𐑼, 𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑬𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑙𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑣𐑻 𐑘𐑳𐑙-𐑸𐑥𐑛 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑣𐑳𐑟𐑚𐑩𐑯𐑛'𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑥𐑼; 𐑣𐑵𐑟 𐑮𐑦𐑝𐑻𐑚𐑼𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟, 𐑥𐑳𐑓𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑐𐑭𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑞 𐑓𐑤𐑹𐑟 𐑯 𐑢𐑷𐑤𐑟, 𐑒𐑱𐑥 𐑳𐑐 𐑑 𐑣𐑻, 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑳𐑯𐑕𐑢𐑰𐑑𐑤𐑦, 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑻 𐑯𐑻𐑕𐑼𐑦; 𐑯 𐑕𐑴, 𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑬𐑑 ·𐑤𐑱𐑚𐑼'𐑟 𐑲𐑼𐑯 𐑤𐑳𐑤𐑩𐑚𐑲, 𐑞 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑒𐑕𐑥𐑦𐑔'𐑕 𐑦𐑯𐑓𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑢𐑻 𐑮𐑪𐑒𐑑 𐑑 𐑕𐑤𐑳𐑥𐑚𐑼.

𐑴, 𐑢𐑴 𐑪𐑯 𐑢𐑴! 𐑴, ·𐑛𐑧𐑔, 𐑢𐑲 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑞𐑬 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑚𐑰 𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑤𐑦? 𐑣𐑨𐑛𐑕𐑑 𐑞𐑬 𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑒𐑕𐑥𐑦𐑔 𐑑 𐑞𐑲𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑺 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑫𐑤 𐑮𐑵𐑦𐑯 𐑒𐑱𐑥 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑞 𐑘𐑳𐑙 𐑢𐑦𐑛𐑴 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑩 𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑕 𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑓, 𐑯 𐑣𐑻 𐑹𐑓𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑩 𐑑𐑮𐑵𐑤𐑦 𐑝𐑧𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤, 𐑤𐑧𐑡𐑩𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑦 𐑕𐑲𐑼 𐑑 𐑛𐑮𐑰𐑥 𐑝 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑘𐑽𐑟; 𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑝 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑩 𐑒𐑺-𐑒𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑐𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 ·𐑛𐑧𐑔 𐑐𐑤𐑳𐑒𐑑 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑝𐑻𐑗𐑵𐑩𐑕 𐑧𐑤𐑛𐑼 𐑚𐑮𐑳𐑞𐑼, 𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑵𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑕𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑛𐑱𐑤𐑦 𐑑𐑶𐑤 𐑕𐑴𐑤𐑦 𐑣𐑳𐑙 𐑞 𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑟 𐑝 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑓𐑨𐑥𐑤𐑦, 𐑯 𐑤𐑧𐑓𐑑 𐑞 𐑢𐑻𐑕 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑿𐑕𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙, 𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑛𐑾𐑕 𐑮𐑪𐑑 𐑝 𐑤𐑲𐑓 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑥𐑱𐑒 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑰𐑟𐑽 𐑑 𐑣𐑸𐑝𐑦𐑕𐑑.

𐑢𐑲 𐑑𐑧𐑤 𐑞 𐑣𐑴𐑤? 𐑞 𐑚𐑤𐑴𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑚𐑱𐑕𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑥𐑼 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑛𐑱 𐑜𐑮𐑵 𐑥𐑹 𐑯 𐑥𐑹 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑢𐑰𐑯; 𐑯 𐑰𐑗 𐑚𐑤𐑴 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑛𐑱 𐑜𐑮𐑵 𐑓𐑱𐑯𐑑𐑼 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑞 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑; 𐑞 𐑢𐑲𐑓 𐑕𐑨𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑴𐑟𐑩𐑯 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑴, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑑𐑽𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑲𐑟, 𐑜𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑼𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑜𐑱𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑢𐑰𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑱𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑝 𐑣𐑻 𐑗𐑦𐑤𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑯; 𐑞 𐑚𐑧𐑤𐑴𐑟 𐑓𐑧𐑤; 𐑞 𐑓𐑹𐑡 𐑗𐑴𐑒𐑑 𐑳𐑐 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑕𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑟; 𐑞 𐑣𐑬𐑕 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑴𐑤𐑛; 𐑞 𐑥𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑛𐑲𐑝𐑛 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑗𐑻𐑗-𐑘𐑸𐑛 𐑜𐑮𐑭𐑕; 𐑣𐑻 𐑗𐑦𐑤𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑯 𐑑𐑢𐑲𐑕 𐑓𐑪𐑤𐑴𐑛 𐑣𐑻 𐑞𐑦𐑞𐑼; 𐑯 𐑞 𐑙𐑬𐑟𐑤𐑧𐑕, 𐑓𐑩𐑥𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑜𐑼𐑛 𐑪𐑓 𐑩 𐑝𐑨𐑜𐑩𐑚𐑪𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑒𐑮𐑱𐑐; 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑢𐑴 𐑳𐑯𐑮𐑧𐑝𐑼𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑑; 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑜𐑮𐑱 𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑩 𐑕𐑒𐑹𐑯 𐑑 𐑓𐑤𐑨𐑒𐑕𐑩𐑯 𐑒𐑻𐑤𐑟!

𐑛𐑧𐑔 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑟 𐑞 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑦𐑟𐑲𐑼𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑩𐑤 𐑓 𐑩 𐑒𐑼𐑽 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑞𐑦𐑕; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 ·𐑛𐑧𐑔 𐑦𐑟 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑩 𐑤𐑷𐑯𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑮𐑰𐑡𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡 ·𐑳𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑛; 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑨𐑤𐑿𐑑𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑑 𐑞 𐑐𐑪𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑦𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑕 ·𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑴𐑑, 𐑞 ·𐑢𐑲𐑤𐑛, 𐑞 ·𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼𐑦, 𐑞 ·𐑳𐑯𐑖𐑹𐑛; 𐑞𐑺𐑓𐑹, 𐑑 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑔-𐑤𐑪𐑙𐑦𐑙 𐑲𐑟 𐑝 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑥𐑧𐑯, 𐑣𐑵 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑤𐑧𐑓𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑽𐑽 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑳𐑙𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑵𐑦𐑕𐑲𐑛, 𐑛𐑳𐑟 𐑞 𐑷𐑤-𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑚𐑿𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑯 𐑷𐑤-𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑧𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑝 𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑩𐑤𐑫𐑼𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑛 𐑓𐑹𐑔 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑴𐑤 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑯 𐑝 𐑳𐑯𐑦𐑥𐑨𐑡𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤, 𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑑𐑧𐑮𐑼𐑟, 𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑓𐑩𐑤, 𐑯𐑿-𐑤𐑲𐑓 𐑩𐑛𐑝𐑧𐑯𐑗𐑼𐑟; 𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑣𐑸𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑦𐑯𐑓𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑑 ·𐑐𐑩𐑕𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑒𐑕, 𐑞 𐑔𐑬𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑥𐑻𐑥𐑱𐑛𐑟 𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑞𐑧𐑥—“𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑣𐑦𐑞𐑼, 𐑚𐑮𐑴𐑒𐑩𐑯-𐑣𐑸𐑑𐑩𐑛; 𐑣𐑽 𐑦𐑟 𐑩𐑯𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑤𐑲𐑓 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑 𐑞 𐑜𐑦𐑤𐑑 𐑝 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑥𐑰𐑛𐑾𐑑 𐑛𐑧𐑔; 𐑣𐑽 𐑸 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑟 𐑕𐑵𐑐𐑼𐑯𐑨𐑗𐑼𐑩𐑤, 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑 𐑛𐑲𐑦𐑙 𐑓 𐑞𐑧𐑥. 𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑣𐑦𐑞𐑼! 𐑚𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑞𐑲𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑤𐑲𐑓 𐑢𐑦𐑗, 𐑑 𐑘𐑹 𐑯𐑬 𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑩𐑚𐑣𐑹𐑛 𐑯 𐑩𐑚𐑣𐑹𐑦𐑙, 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛, 𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑹 𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑦𐑝𐑾𐑕 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑛𐑧𐑔. 𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑣𐑦𐑞𐑼! 𐑐𐑫𐑑 𐑳𐑐 𐑞𐑲 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑝𐑕𐑑𐑴𐑯, 𐑑𐑵, 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑗𐑻𐑗𐑘𐑸𐑛, 𐑯 𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑣𐑦𐑞𐑼, 𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑢𐑰 𐑥𐑨𐑮𐑦 𐑞𐑰!”

𐑣𐑸𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑝𐑶𐑕𐑩𐑟, ·𐑰𐑕𐑑 𐑯 ·𐑢𐑧𐑕𐑑, 𐑚𐑲 𐑻𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑳𐑯𐑮𐑲𐑟, 𐑯 𐑚𐑲 𐑓𐑷𐑤 𐑝 𐑰𐑝, 𐑞 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑒𐑕𐑥𐑦𐑔'𐑕 𐑕𐑴𐑤 𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑪𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛, ·𐑲, 𐑲 𐑒𐑳𐑥! 𐑯 𐑕𐑴 ·𐑐𐑻𐑔 𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑩-𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙.

·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 113. 𐑞 ·𐑓𐑹𐑡.

𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑥𐑨𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑽𐑛, 𐑯 𐑕𐑢𐑱𐑞𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑚𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑖𐑸𐑒-𐑕𐑒𐑦𐑯 𐑱𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑯, 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑥𐑦𐑛-𐑛𐑱, ·𐑐𐑻𐑔 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑢𐑰𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑹𐑡 𐑯 𐑨𐑯𐑝𐑦𐑤, 𐑞 𐑤𐑨𐑑𐑼 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕𐑑 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑩𐑯 𐑲𐑼𐑯-𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑤𐑪𐑜, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑐𐑲𐑒-𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑒𐑴𐑤𐑟, 𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑹𐑡'𐑩𐑟 𐑤𐑳𐑙𐑟, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑒𐑱𐑥 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑙, 𐑒𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑩 𐑕𐑥𐑷𐑤 𐑮𐑳𐑕𐑑𐑦-𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑤𐑧𐑞𐑼𐑯 𐑚𐑨𐑜. 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑩 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑓𐑹𐑡, 𐑥𐑵𐑛𐑦 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑐𐑷𐑟𐑛; 𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑, ·𐑐𐑻𐑔, 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑛𐑮𐑷𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑲𐑼𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑓𐑲𐑼, 𐑚𐑦𐑜𐑨𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑥𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑑 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑨𐑯𐑝𐑦𐑤—𐑞 𐑮𐑧𐑛 𐑥𐑨𐑕 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑪𐑓 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑸𐑒𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑔𐑦𐑒 𐑣𐑪𐑝𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑤𐑲𐑑𐑕, 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑝 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑓𐑤𐑵 𐑒𐑤𐑴𐑕 𐑑 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚.

“𐑸 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑞𐑲 ·𐑥𐑳𐑞𐑼 ·𐑒𐑺𐑦'𐑟 𐑗𐑦𐑒𐑦𐑯𐑟, ·𐑐𐑻𐑔? 𐑞𐑱 𐑸 𐑷𐑤𐑢𐑱𐑟 𐑓𐑤𐑲𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑲 𐑢𐑱𐑒; 𐑚𐑻𐑛𐑟 𐑝 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑴𐑥𐑩𐑯, 𐑑𐑵, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑑 𐑷𐑤;—𐑤𐑫𐑒 𐑣𐑽, 𐑞𐑱 𐑚𐑻𐑯; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞𐑬—𐑞𐑬 𐑤𐑦𐑝'𐑕𐑑 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑 𐑩 𐑕𐑒𐑹𐑗.”

“𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑪𐑟 𐑲 𐑨𐑥 𐑕𐑒𐑹𐑗𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑴𐑝𐑼, ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚,” 𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑼𐑛 ·𐑐𐑻𐑔, 𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑓 𐑩 𐑥𐑴𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑥𐑼; “𐑲 𐑨𐑥 𐑐𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑒𐑹𐑗𐑦𐑙; 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑰𐑟𐑦𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑨𐑯'𐑕𐑑 𐑞𐑬 𐑕𐑒𐑹𐑗 𐑩 𐑕𐑒𐑸.”

“𐑢𐑧𐑤, 𐑢𐑧𐑤; 𐑯𐑴 𐑥𐑹. 𐑞𐑲 𐑖𐑮𐑳𐑙𐑒 𐑝𐑶𐑕 𐑕𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑑𐑵 𐑒𐑭𐑥𐑤𐑦, 𐑕𐑱𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑢𐑴𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑑 𐑥𐑰. 𐑦𐑯 𐑯𐑴 ·𐑐𐑨𐑮𐑩𐑛𐑲𐑕 𐑥𐑲𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓, 𐑲 𐑨𐑥 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑷𐑤 𐑥𐑦𐑟𐑼𐑦 𐑦𐑯 𐑳𐑞𐑼𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑥𐑨𐑛. 𐑞𐑬 𐑖𐑵𐑛'𐑕𐑑 𐑜𐑴 𐑥𐑨𐑛, 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑒𐑕𐑥𐑦𐑔; 𐑕𐑱, 𐑢𐑲 𐑛𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑞𐑬 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑜𐑴 𐑥𐑨𐑛? 𐑣𐑬 𐑒𐑨𐑯'𐑕𐑑 𐑞𐑬 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑻 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑨𐑛? 𐑛𐑵 𐑞 𐑣𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑣𐑱𐑑 𐑞𐑰, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑬 𐑒𐑨𐑯'𐑕𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑜𐑴 𐑥𐑨𐑛?—𐑢𐑪𐑑 ·𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑑 𐑞𐑬 𐑥𐑱𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑺?”

“𐑢𐑧𐑤𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑯 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑐𐑲𐑒-𐑣𐑧𐑛, 𐑕𐑻; 𐑞𐑺 𐑢𐑻 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑟 𐑯 𐑛𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑦𐑑.”

“𐑯 𐑒𐑨𐑯'𐑕𐑑 𐑞𐑬 𐑥𐑱𐑒 𐑦𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑕𐑥𐑵𐑞 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯, 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑒𐑕𐑥𐑦𐑔, 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑣𐑸𐑛 𐑿𐑕𐑦𐑡 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑛?”

“𐑲 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒 𐑕𐑴, 𐑕𐑻.”

“𐑯 𐑲 𐑕𐑩𐑐𐑴𐑟 𐑞𐑬 𐑒𐑨𐑯'𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑥𐑵𐑞 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑟 𐑯 𐑛𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑕; 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑥𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑣𐑬 𐑣𐑸𐑛 𐑞 𐑥𐑧𐑑𐑩𐑤, 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑒𐑕𐑥𐑦𐑔?”

“𐑲, 𐑕𐑻, 𐑲 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒 𐑲 𐑒𐑨𐑯; 𐑷𐑤 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑟 𐑯 𐑛𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯.”

“𐑤𐑫𐑒 𐑘𐑰 𐑣𐑽, 𐑞𐑧𐑯,” 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚, 𐑐𐑨𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑩𐑛𐑝𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑙, 𐑯 𐑤𐑰𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑔 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑪𐑯 ·𐑐𐑻𐑔'𐑕 𐑖𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑼𐑟; “𐑤𐑫𐑒 𐑘𐑰 𐑣𐑽—𐑣𐑽—𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑘𐑰 𐑕𐑥𐑵𐑞 𐑬𐑑 𐑩 𐑕𐑰𐑥 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑞𐑦𐑕, 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑒𐑕𐑥𐑦𐑔,” 𐑕𐑢𐑰𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑩𐑒𐑮𐑪𐑕 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑮𐑦𐑚𐑛 𐑚𐑮𐑬; “𐑦𐑓 𐑞𐑬 𐑒𐑫𐑛'𐑕𐑑, 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑒𐑕𐑥𐑦𐑔, 𐑜𐑤𐑨𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑳𐑓 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑲 𐑤𐑱 𐑥𐑲 𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞𐑲 𐑨𐑯𐑝𐑦𐑤, 𐑯 𐑓𐑰𐑤 𐑞𐑲 𐑣𐑧𐑝𐑾𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑥𐑼 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑢𐑰𐑯 𐑥𐑲 𐑲𐑟. 𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑼! 𐑒𐑨𐑯'𐑕𐑑 𐑞𐑬 𐑕𐑥𐑵𐑞 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑕𐑰𐑥?”

“𐑴! 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑞 𐑢𐑳𐑯, 𐑕𐑻! 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑲 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑟 𐑯 𐑛𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯?”

“𐑲, 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑒𐑕𐑥𐑦𐑔, 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑞 𐑢𐑳𐑯; 𐑲, 𐑥𐑨𐑯, 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑳𐑯𐑕𐑥𐑵𐑞𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤; 𐑓 𐑞𐑴 𐑞𐑬 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑰'𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑣𐑽 𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑲 𐑓𐑤𐑧𐑖, 𐑦𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑢𐑻𐑒𐑑 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑯 𐑝 𐑥𐑲 𐑕𐑒𐑳𐑤—𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑷𐑤 𐑮𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑟! 𐑚𐑳𐑑, 𐑩𐑢𐑱 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑗𐑲𐑤𐑛'𐑟 𐑐𐑤𐑱; 𐑯𐑴 𐑥𐑹 𐑜𐑨𐑓𐑕 𐑯 𐑐𐑲𐑒𐑕 𐑑-𐑛𐑱. 𐑤𐑫𐑒 𐑘𐑰 𐑣𐑽!” 𐑡𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑤𐑧𐑞𐑼𐑯 𐑚𐑨𐑜, 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑓 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑻 𐑓𐑫𐑤 𐑝 𐑜𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑒𐑶𐑯𐑟. “𐑲, 𐑑𐑵, 𐑢𐑪𐑯𐑑 𐑩 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯 𐑥𐑱𐑛; 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑩 𐑔𐑬𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑘𐑴𐑒 𐑝 𐑓𐑰𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑐𐑸𐑑, ·𐑐𐑻𐑔; 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑴𐑯 𐑓𐑦𐑯-𐑚𐑴𐑯. 𐑞𐑺'𐑟 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑓,” 𐑓𐑤𐑦𐑙𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑐𐑬𐑗 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑨𐑯𐑝𐑦𐑤. “𐑤𐑫𐑒 𐑘𐑰, 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑒𐑕𐑥𐑦𐑔, 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑸 𐑞 𐑜𐑨𐑞𐑼𐑛 𐑯𐑱𐑤-𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑰𐑤 𐑖𐑵𐑟 𐑝 𐑮𐑱𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑹𐑕𐑩𐑟.”

“𐑣𐑹𐑕-𐑖𐑵 𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚𐑟, 𐑕𐑻? 𐑢𐑲, ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚, 𐑞𐑬 𐑣𐑨𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑽, 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑞 𐑚𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚𐑼𐑯𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑓 𐑢𐑰 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑒𐑕𐑥𐑦𐑔𐑕 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑢𐑻𐑒.”

“𐑲 𐑯𐑴 𐑦𐑑, 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑥𐑨𐑯; 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑢𐑧𐑤𐑛 𐑑𐑩𐑜𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑜𐑤𐑵 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑥𐑧𐑤𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑴𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑥𐑻𐑛𐑼𐑼𐑟. 𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑒! 𐑓𐑹𐑡 𐑥𐑰 𐑞 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯. 𐑯 𐑓𐑹𐑡 𐑥𐑰 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑, 𐑑𐑢𐑧𐑤𐑝 𐑮𐑪𐑛𐑟 𐑓 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑖𐑨𐑙𐑒; 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛, 𐑯 𐑑𐑢𐑦𐑕𐑑, 𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑥𐑼 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑑𐑢𐑧𐑤𐑝 𐑑𐑩𐑜𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑞 𐑘𐑸𐑯𐑟 𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑝 𐑩 𐑑𐑴-𐑤𐑲𐑯. 𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑒! 𐑲'𐑤 𐑚𐑤𐑴 𐑞 𐑓𐑲𐑼.”

𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑞 𐑑𐑢𐑧𐑤𐑝 𐑮𐑪𐑛𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑥𐑱𐑛, ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑛 𐑞𐑧𐑥, 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑚𐑲 𐑢𐑳𐑯, 𐑚𐑲 𐑕𐑐𐑲𐑮𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑧𐑥, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑴𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛, 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑩 𐑤𐑪𐑙, 𐑣𐑧𐑝𐑦 𐑲𐑼𐑯 𐑚𐑴𐑤𐑑. “𐑩 𐑓𐑤𐑷!” 𐑮𐑦𐑡𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯. “𐑢𐑻𐑒 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯, ·𐑐𐑻𐑔.”

𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑛𐑳𐑯, ·𐑐𐑻𐑔 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑜𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑧𐑤𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑑𐑢𐑧𐑤𐑝 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑢𐑳𐑯, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛, 𐑯 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑢𐑧𐑤𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑴𐑯 𐑲𐑼𐑯. 𐑨𐑟, 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑮𐑧𐑜𐑿𐑤𐑼, 𐑜𐑭𐑕𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑧𐑥𐑟, 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑥𐑼𐑛 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑨𐑯𐑝𐑦𐑤, ·𐑐𐑻𐑔 𐑐𐑭𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑞 𐑜𐑤𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑮𐑪𐑛𐑟, 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑞 𐑳𐑞𐑼, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑣𐑸𐑛 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑓𐑹𐑡 𐑖𐑵𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑳𐑐 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑕 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑓𐑤𐑱𐑥, 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑸𐑟𐑰 𐑐𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦, 𐑯 𐑚𐑬𐑦𐑙 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑑𐑩𐑢𐑹𐑛𐑟 𐑞 𐑓𐑲𐑼, 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑴𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑒𐑻𐑕 𐑹 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑚𐑤𐑧𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑑𐑶𐑤. 𐑚𐑳𐑑, 𐑨𐑟 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑑 𐑳𐑐, 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑤𐑦𐑛 𐑩𐑕𐑲𐑛.

“𐑢𐑪𐑑'𐑕 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑚𐑳𐑯𐑗 𐑝 𐑤𐑵𐑕𐑦𐑓𐑼𐑟 𐑛𐑪𐑡𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑓?” 𐑥𐑳𐑑𐑼𐑛 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚, 𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑪𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑓𐑴𐑒𐑕𐑩𐑤. “𐑞𐑨𐑑 ·𐑐𐑸𐑟𐑰 𐑕𐑥𐑧𐑤𐑟 𐑓𐑲𐑼 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑓𐑿𐑟𐑰; 𐑯 𐑕𐑥𐑧𐑤𐑟 𐑝 𐑦𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓, 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑣𐑪𐑑 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑒𐑩𐑑'𐑕 𐑐𐑬𐑛𐑼-𐑐𐑨𐑯.”

𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑞 𐑖𐑨𐑙𐑒, 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑰𐑑 𐑮𐑪𐑛, 𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑰𐑝𐑛 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑓𐑲𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑣𐑰𐑑; 𐑯 𐑨𐑟 ·𐑐𐑻𐑔, 𐑑 𐑑𐑧𐑥𐑐𐑼 𐑦𐑑, 𐑐𐑤𐑳𐑯𐑡𐑛 𐑦𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑣𐑦𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑒𐑭𐑕𐑒 𐑝 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼 𐑯𐑽 𐑚𐑲, 𐑞 𐑕𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑑𐑰𐑥 𐑖𐑪𐑑 𐑳𐑐 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚'𐑟 𐑚𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑓𐑱𐑕.

“𐑢𐑫𐑛'𐑕𐑑 𐑞𐑬 𐑚𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑥𐑰, ·𐑐𐑻𐑔?” 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑓 𐑩 𐑥𐑴𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑐𐑱𐑯; “𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑲 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑓𐑹𐑡𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑲 𐑴𐑯 𐑚𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙-𐑲𐑼𐑯, 𐑞𐑧𐑯?”

“𐑐𐑮𐑱 ·𐑜𐑪𐑛, 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑; 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑲 𐑓𐑽 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑔𐑦𐑙, ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚. 𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯 𐑓 𐑞 ·𐑢𐑲𐑑 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤?”

“𐑓 𐑞 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑓𐑰𐑯𐑛! 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑯𐑬 𐑓 𐑞 𐑚𐑸𐑚𐑟; 𐑞𐑬 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑥𐑱𐑒 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑞𐑲𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓, 𐑥𐑨𐑯. 𐑣𐑽 𐑸 𐑥𐑲 𐑮𐑱𐑟𐑼𐑟—𐑞 𐑚𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑝 𐑕𐑑𐑰𐑤; 𐑣𐑽, 𐑯 𐑥𐑱𐑒 𐑞 𐑚𐑸𐑚𐑟 𐑖𐑸𐑐 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑯𐑰𐑛𐑩𐑤-𐑕𐑤𐑰𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑲𐑕𐑦 ·𐑕𐑰.”

𐑓 𐑩 𐑥𐑴𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑, 𐑞 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑒𐑕𐑥𐑦𐑔 𐑲𐑛 𐑞 𐑮𐑱𐑟𐑼𐑟 𐑨𐑟 𐑞𐑴 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑓𐑱𐑯 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑿𐑟 𐑞𐑧𐑥.

“𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑞𐑧𐑥, 𐑥𐑨𐑯, 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑯𐑴 𐑯𐑰𐑛 𐑓 𐑞𐑧𐑥; 𐑓 𐑲 𐑯𐑬 𐑯𐑲𐑞𐑼 𐑖𐑱𐑝, 𐑕𐑳𐑐, 𐑯𐑹 𐑐𐑮𐑱 𐑑𐑦𐑤—𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑣𐑽—𐑑 𐑢𐑻𐑒!”

𐑓𐑨𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑩𐑯 𐑨𐑮𐑴𐑦 𐑖𐑱𐑐, 𐑯 𐑢𐑧𐑤𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑲 ·𐑐𐑻𐑔 𐑑 𐑞 𐑖𐑨𐑙𐑒, 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑰𐑤 𐑕𐑵𐑯 𐑐𐑶𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑞 𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑝 𐑞 𐑲𐑼𐑯; 𐑯 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑒𐑕𐑥𐑦𐑔 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑜𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑚𐑸𐑚𐑟 𐑞𐑺 𐑓𐑲𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑣𐑰𐑑, 𐑐𐑮𐑲𐑼 𐑑 𐑑𐑧𐑥𐑐𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑧𐑥, 𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 𐑑 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑑 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕 𐑞 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼-𐑒𐑭𐑕𐑒 𐑯𐑽.

“𐑯𐑴, 𐑯𐑴—𐑯𐑴 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼 𐑓 𐑞𐑨𐑑; 𐑲 𐑢𐑪𐑯𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑑𐑮𐑵 𐑛𐑧𐑔-𐑑𐑧𐑥𐑐𐑼. 𐑩𐑣𐑶, 𐑞𐑺! ·𐑑𐑨𐑖𐑑𐑱𐑜𐑴, ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜, ·𐑛𐑨𐑜𐑵! 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑱 𐑘𐑰, 𐑐𐑱𐑜𐑩𐑯𐑟! 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑘𐑰 𐑜𐑦𐑝 𐑥𐑰 𐑨𐑟 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑚𐑤𐑳𐑛 𐑨𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑒𐑳𐑝𐑼 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑚𐑸𐑚?” 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑑 𐑣𐑲 𐑳𐑐. 𐑩 𐑒𐑤𐑳𐑕𐑑𐑼 𐑝 𐑛𐑸𐑒 𐑯𐑪𐑛𐑟 𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑤𐑲𐑛, ·𐑘𐑧𐑕. 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑐𐑳𐑙𐑒𐑗𐑼𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑣𐑰𐑞𐑩𐑯 𐑓𐑤𐑧𐑖, 𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑢𐑲𐑑 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤'𐑟 𐑚𐑸𐑚𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑑𐑧𐑥𐑐𐑼𐑛.

“𐑰𐑜𐑴 𐑯𐑪𐑯 𐑚𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑲𐑟𐑴 𐑑𐑱 𐑦𐑯 𐑯𐑴𐑥𐑲𐑯 𐑐𐑨𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑕, 𐑕𐑦𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑯𐑴𐑥𐑲𐑯 𐑛𐑲𐑩𐑚𐑪𐑤𐑦!” 𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑽𐑾𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑣𐑬𐑤𐑛 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚, 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑥𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑜𐑯𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑲𐑼𐑯 𐑕𐑒𐑹𐑗𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑦𐑝𐑬𐑼𐑛 𐑞 𐑚𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑟𐑥𐑩𐑤 𐑚𐑤𐑳𐑛.

𐑯𐑬, 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑺 𐑐𐑴𐑤𐑟 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑴, 𐑯 𐑕𐑦𐑤𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑒𐑼𐑦, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑚𐑸𐑒 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑑, ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑓𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑞 𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑪𐑒𐑩𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑲𐑼𐑯. 𐑩 𐑒𐑶𐑤 𐑝 𐑯𐑿 𐑑𐑴-𐑤𐑲𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑳𐑯𐑢𐑬𐑯𐑛, 𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑓𐑨𐑞𐑩𐑥𐑟 𐑝 𐑦𐑑 𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑑 𐑞 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑤𐑩𐑕, 𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑧𐑗𐑑 𐑑 𐑩 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑯. 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑫𐑑 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑦𐑑, 𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑞 𐑮𐑴𐑐 𐑣𐑳𐑥𐑛 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑣𐑸𐑐-𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑙, 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑰𐑜𐑼𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑦𐑑, 𐑯 𐑕𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑯𐑴 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙𐑟, ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑒𐑤𐑱𐑥𐑛, “𐑜𐑫𐑛! 𐑯 𐑯𐑬 𐑓 𐑞 𐑕𐑰𐑟𐑦𐑙𐑟.”

𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑧𐑥𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑞 𐑮𐑴𐑐 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑳𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑧𐑐𐑼𐑩𐑑 𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑛 𐑘𐑸𐑯𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑷𐑤 𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑯 𐑢𐑴𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑞 𐑕𐑪𐑒𐑩𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯; 𐑞 𐑐𐑴𐑤 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑛𐑮𐑦𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑣𐑸𐑛 𐑳𐑐 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑕𐑪𐑒𐑩𐑑; 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑤𐑴𐑼 𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑞 𐑮𐑴𐑐 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑭𐑓-𐑢𐑱 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑞 𐑐𐑴𐑤'𐑟 𐑤𐑧𐑙𐑔, 𐑯 𐑓𐑻𐑥𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑛 𐑕𐑴, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑑𐑢𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑝 𐑑𐑢𐑲𐑯. 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑛𐑳𐑯, 𐑐𐑴𐑤, 𐑲𐑼𐑯, 𐑯 𐑮𐑴𐑐—𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑞 ·𐑔𐑮𐑰 ·𐑓𐑱𐑑𐑕—𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑱𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑧𐑐𐑼𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤, 𐑯 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑥𐑵𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑑𐑷𐑒𐑑 𐑩𐑢𐑱 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑢𐑧𐑐𐑩𐑯; 𐑞 𐑕𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑲𐑝𐑼𐑦 𐑤𐑧𐑜, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑝 𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑒𐑼𐑦 𐑐𐑴𐑤, 𐑚𐑴𐑔 𐑣𐑪𐑤𐑴𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑦𐑙𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑐𐑤𐑨𐑙𐑒. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑺 𐑣𐑰 𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑨𐑚𐑦𐑯, 𐑤𐑲𐑑, 𐑳𐑯𐑯𐑨𐑗𐑼𐑩𐑤, 𐑣𐑭𐑓-𐑚𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑦𐑙, 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑐𐑦𐑑𐑾𐑕 𐑕𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑣𐑻𐑛. 𐑴, ·𐑐𐑦𐑐! 𐑞𐑲 𐑮𐑧𐑗𐑩𐑛 𐑤𐑭𐑓, 𐑞𐑲 𐑲𐑛𐑩𐑤 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑳𐑯𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑲; 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑲 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡 𐑥𐑳𐑥𐑼𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑳𐑯𐑥𐑰𐑯𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑤𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑒 𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑡𐑩𐑛𐑦 𐑝 𐑞 𐑥𐑧𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑒𐑪𐑤𐑦 𐑖𐑦𐑐, 𐑯 𐑥𐑪𐑒𐑑 𐑦𐑑!

·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 114. 𐑞 ·𐑜𐑦𐑤𐑛𐑼.

𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑻𐑞𐑼 𐑯 𐑓𐑻𐑞𐑼 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑣𐑸𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑡𐑨𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑰𐑟 𐑒𐑮𐑵𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑜𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛, 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑵𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑩𐑕𐑑𐑻 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑼𐑦. 𐑪𐑓𐑩𐑯, 𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑲𐑤𐑛, 𐑐𐑤𐑧𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑢𐑧𐑞𐑼, 𐑓 𐑑𐑢𐑧𐑤𐑝, 𐑓𐑦𐑓𐑑𐑰𐑯, 𐑱𐑑𐑰𐑯, 𐑯 𐑑𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑦 𐑬𐑼𐑟 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑧𐑗, 𐑞𐑱 𐑢𐑻 𐑦𐑯𐑜𐑱𐑡𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕, 𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑫𐑤𐑦𐑙, 𐑹 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙, 𐑹 𐑐𐑨𐑛𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟, 𐑹 𐑓 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑤𐑵𐑛 𐑝 𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑦 𐑹 𐑕𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑦 𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑒𐑭𐑥𐑤𐑦 𐑩𐑢𐑱𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑺 𐑳𐑐𐑮𐑲𐑟𐑦𐑙; 𐑞𐑴 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑕𐑥𐑷𐑤 𐑕𐑩𐑒𐑕𐑧𐑕 𐑓 𐑞𐑺 𐑐𐑱𐑯𐑟.

𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟, 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑩𐑯 𐑩𐑚𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑕𐑳𐑯; 𐑩𐑓𐑤𐑴𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑛𐑱 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑕𐑥𐑵𐑞, 𐑕𐑤𐑴 𐑣𐑰𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑢𐑧𐑤𐑟; 𐑕𐑰𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑴𐑑, 𐑤𐑲𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑩 𐑚𐑻𐑗 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑵; 𐑯 𐑕𐑴 𐑕𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑥𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑕𐑪𐑓𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑝𐑟 𐑞𐑧𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑝𐑟, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑣𐑸𐑔-𐑕𐑑𐑴𐑯 𐑒𐑨𐑑𐑕 𐑞𐑱 𐑐𐑻 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑞 𐑜𐑳𐑯𐑩𐑤; 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑸 𐑞 𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑝 𐑛𐑮𐑰𐑥𐑦 𐑒𐑢𐑲𐑩𐑑𐑵𐑛, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑚𐑦𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑚𐑿𐑑𐑦 𐑯 𐑚𐑮𐑦𐑤𐑾𐑯𐑕𐑦 𐑝 𐑞 𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯'𐑟 𐑕𐑒𐑦𐑯, 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑓𐑼𐑜𐑧𐑑𐑕 𐑞 𐑑𐑲𐑜𐑼 𐑣𐑸𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑐𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑚𐑦𐑯𐑰𐑔 𐑦𐑑; 𐑯 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑧𐑥𐑚𐑼, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑝𐑧𐑤𐑝𐑩𐑑 𐑐𐑷 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑰𐑤𐑟 𐑩 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑹𐑕𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑓𐑨𐑙.

𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑸 𐑞 𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑱𐑤-𐑚𐑴𐑑 𐑞 𐑮𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑕𐑪𐑓𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑓𐑰𐑤𐑟 𐑩 𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑓𐑦𐑤𐑾𐑤, 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑓𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑑, 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛-𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑓𐑰𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑑𐑩𐑢𐑹𐑛𐑟 𐑞 𐑕𐑰; 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑮𐑦𐑜𐑸𐑛𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑕𐑴 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑓𐑤𐑬𐑼𐑦 𐑻𐑔; 𐑯 𐑞 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑮𐑦𐑝𐑰𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑞 𐑑𐑪𐑐𐑕 𐑝 𐑣𐑻 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑕, 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑜𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑹𐑢𐑼𐑛, 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑣𐑲 𐑮𐑴𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑱𐑝𐑟, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑞 𐑑𐑷𐑤 𐑜𐑮𐑭𐑕 𐑝 𐑩 𐑮𐑴𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑐𐑮𐑺𐑦: 𐑨𐑟 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑯 𐑧𐑥𐑦𐑜𐑮𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕' 𐑣𐑹𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑖𐑴 𐑞𐑺 𐑦𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑽𐑟, 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑞𐑺 𐑣𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑯 𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑲𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑢𐑱𐑛 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑞 𐑩𐑥𐑱𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑝𐑻𐑡𐑼.

𐑞 𐑤𐑪𐑙-𐑛𐑮𐑷𐑯 𐑝𐑻𐑡𐑦𐑯 𐑝𐑱𐑤𐑟; 𐑞 𐑥𐑲𐑤𐑛 𐑚𐑤𐑵 𐑣𐑦𐑤-𐑕𐑲𐑛𐑟; 𐑨𐑟 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑞𐑺 𐑕𐑑𐑰𐑤𐑟 𐑞 𐑣𐑳𐑖, 𐑞 𐑣𐑳𐑥; 𐑿 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑢𐑺 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑐𐑤𐑱-𐑢𐑽𐑦𐑛 𐑗𐑦𐑤𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑯 𐑤𐑲 𐑕𐑤𐑰𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑕𐑪𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑿𐑛𐑟, 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑜𐑤𐑨𐑛 𐑥𐑱-𐑑𐑲𐑥, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑤𐑬𐑼𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑫𐑛𐑟 𐑸 𐑐𐑤𐑳𐑒𐑑. 𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑥𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑘𐑹 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑥𐑵𐑛; 𐑕𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑓𐑨𐑒𐑑 𐑯 𐑓𐑨𐑯𐑕𐑦, 𐑣𐑭𐑓-𐑢𐑱 𐑥𐑰𐑑𐑦𐑙, 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑻𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑑, 𐑯 𐑓𐑹𐑥 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑣𐑴𐑤.

𐑯𐑹 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑕𐑵𐑞𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑰𐑯𐑟, 𐑣𐑬𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑑𐑧𐑥𐑐𐑼𐑼𐑦, 𐑓𐑱𐑤 𐑝 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑰𐑕𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑑𐑧𐑥𐑐𐑼𐑼𐑦 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑓𐑧𐑒𐑑 𐑪𐑯 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑓 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑕𐑰𐑒𐑮𐑩𐑑 𐑜𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑩𐑯 𐑒𐑰𐑟 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑕𐑰𐑥 𐑑 𐑴𐑐𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑴𐑯 𐑕𐑰𐑒𐑮𐑩𐑑 𐑜𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑩𐑯 𐑑𐑮𐑧𐑠𐑼𐑦𐑟, 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑮𐑧𐑔 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑐𐑮𐑵𐑝 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑑𐑸𐑯𐑦𐑖𐑦𐑙.

𐑴, 𐑜𐑮𐑭𐑕𐑦 𐑜𐑤𐑱𐑛𐑟! 𐑴, 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑝𐑻𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑕𐑒𐑱𐑐𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑴𐑤; 𐑦𐑯 𐑘𐑰,—𐑞𐑴 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑐𐑸𐑗𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑛 𐑛𐑮𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑻𐑔𐑦 𐑤𐑲𐑓,—𐑦𐑯 𐑘𐑰, 𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑥𐑱 𐑮𐑴𐑤, 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑘𐑳𐑙 𐑣𐑹𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑯𐑿 𐑥𐑹𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑒𐑤𐑴𐑝𐑼; 𐑯 𐑓 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑓𐑿 𐑓𐑤𐑰𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑴𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑕, 𐑓𐑰𐑤 𐑞 𐑒𐑵𐑤 𐑛𐑿 𐑝 𐑞 𐑤𐑲𐑓 𐑦𐑥𐑹𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑪𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑥. 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑑 ·𐑜𐑪𐑛 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑚𐑤𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑒𐑭𐑥𐑟 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞 𐑥𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑩𐑤𐑛, 𐑥𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑔𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑟 𐑝 𐑤𐑲𐑓 𐑸 𐑢𐑴𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑚𐑲 𐑢𐑹𐑐 𐑯 𐑢𐑵𐑓: 𐑒𐑭𐑥𐑟 𐑒𐑮𐑪𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑕𐑑𐑹𐑥𐑟, 𐑩 𐑕𐑑𐑹𐑥 𐑓 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑒𐑭𐑥. 𐑞𐑺 𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑴 𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑛𐑦 𐑳𐑯𐑮𐑰𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑐𐑮𐑴𐑜𐑮𐑧𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑤𐑲𐑓; 𐑢𐑰 𐑛𐑵 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑩𐑛𐑝𐑭𐑯𐑕 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑓𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑑 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑛𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟, 𐑯 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑐𐑷𐑟:—𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑦𐑯𐑓𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦'𐑟 𐑳𐑯𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑕 𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑤, 𐑚𐑶𐑣𐑫𐑛'𐑟 𐑔𐑷𐑑𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑓𐑱𐑔, 𐑨𐑛𐑩𐑤𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑕' 𐑛𐑬𐑑 (𐑞 𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑛𐑵𐑥), 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑕𐑒𐑧𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑕𐑦𐑟𐑩𐑥, 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑰𐑓, 𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑨𐑯𐑣𐑫𐑛'𐑟 𐑐𐑪𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑴𐑟 𐑝 𐑦𐑓. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑕 𐑜𐑪𐑯 𐑔𐑮𐑵, 𐑢𐑰 𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑕 𐑞 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯; 𐑯 𐑸 𐑦𐑯𐑓𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕, 𐑚𐑶𐑟, 𐑯 𐑥𐑧𐑯, 𐑯 ·𐑦𐑓𐑕 𐑦𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑩𐑤𐑦. 𐑢𐑺 𐑤𐑲𐑟 𐑞 𐑓𐑲𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑣𐑸𐑚𐑼, 𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑕 𐑢𐑰 𐑳𐑯𐑥𐑫𐑼 𐑯𐑴 𐑥𐑹? 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑮𐑨𐑐𐑑 𐑰𐑔𐑼 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑞 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛, 𐑝 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑞 𐑢𐑽𐑾𐑕𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑢𐑽𐑦? 𐑢𐑺 𐑦𐑟 𐑞 𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑤𐑦𐑙'𐑟 𐑓𐑭𐑞𐑼 𐑣𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑯? 𐑬𐑼 𐑕𐑴𐑤𐑟 𐑸 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑹𐑓𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑣𐑵𐑟 𐑳𐑯𐑢𐑧𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑥𐑳𐑞𐑼𐑟 𐑛𐑲 𐑦𐑯 𐑚𐑺𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑧𐑥: 𐑞 𐑕𐑰𐑒𐑮𐑩𐑑 𐑝 𐑬𐑼 𐑐𐑩𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑤𐑲𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑝, 𐑯 𐑢𐑰 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑑 𐑤𐑻𐑯 𐑦𐑑.

𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑛𐑱, 𐑑𐑵, 𐑜𐑱𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑸 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑴𐑑'𐑕 𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑜𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑩𐑯 𐑕𐑰, ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒 𐑤𐑴𐑤𐑦 𐑥𐑻𐑥𐑼𐑛:—

“𐑤𐑳𐑝𐑤𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑳𐑯𐑓𐑨𐑞𐑩𐑥𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤, 𐑨𐑟 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑤𐑳𐑝𐑼 𐑕𐑷 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑘𐑳𐑙 𐑚𐑮𐑲𐑛'𐑟 𐑲!—𐑑𐑧𐑤 𐑥𐑰 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑝 𐑞𐑲 𐑑𐑰𐑔-𐑑𐑽𐑛 𐑖𐑸𐑒𐑕, 𐑯 𐑞𐑲 𐑒𐑦𐑛𐑯𐑨𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑱𐑟. 𐑤𐑧𐑑 𐑓𐑱𐑔 𐑬𐑕𐑑 𐑓𐑨𐑒𐑑; 𐑤𐑧𐑑 𐑓𐑨𐑯𐑕𐑦 𐑬𐑕𐑑 𐑥𐑧𐑥𐑼𐑦; 𐑲 𐑤𐑫𐑒 𐑛𐑰𐑐 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑯 𐑛𐑵 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑰𐑝.”

𐑯 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚, 𐑓𐑦𐑖-𐑤𐑲𐑒, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑸𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑒𐑱𐑤𐑟, 𐑤𐑰𐑐𐑑 𐑳𐑐 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑜𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑩𐑯 𐑤𐑲𐑑:—

“𐑲 𐑨𐑥 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚, 𐑯 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑦; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑣𐑽 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚 𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑕 𐑴𐑞𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑷𐑤𐑢𐑱𐑟 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑡𐑪𐑤𐑦!”

·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 115. 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛 ·𐑥𐑰𐑑𐑕 𐑞 ·𐑚𐑨𐑗𐑩𐑤𐑼.

𐑯 𐑡𐑪𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑯𐑳𐑓 𐑢𐑻 𐑞 𐑕𐑲𐑑𐑕 𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑒𐑱𐑥 𐑚𐑺𐑦𐑙 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑞 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛, 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑓𐑿 𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑕 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚'𐑟 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑢𐑧𐑤𐑛𐑩𐑛.

𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩 ·𐑯𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑑 𐑖𐑦𐑐, 𐑞 ·𐑚𐑨𐑗𐑩𐑤𐑼, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑡𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑢𐑧𐑡𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑻 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑒𐑭𐑕𐑒 𐑝 𐑶𐑤, 𐑯 𐑚𐑴𐑤𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑣𐑻 𐑚𐑻𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑨𐑗𐑩𐑟; 𐑯 𐑯𐑬, 𐑦𐑯 𐑜𐑤𐑨𐑛 𐑣𐑪𐑤𐑦𐑛𐑱 𐑩𐑐𐑨𐑮𐑩𐑤, 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑡𐑶𐑩𐑕𐑤𐑦, 𐑞𐑴 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑝𐑱𐑯-𐑜𐑤𐑹𐑾𐑕𐑤𐑦, 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑞 𐑢𐑲𐑛𐑤𐑦-𐑕𐑧𐑐𐑼𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑕 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛, 𐑐𐑮𐑰𐑝𐑾𐑕 𐑑 𐑐𐑶𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑻 𐑐𐑮𐑬 𐑓 𐑣𐑴𐑥.

𐑞 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑻 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑-𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑢𐑹 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑰𐑥𐑼𐑟 𐑝 𐑯𐑼𐑴 𐑮𐑧𐑛 𐑚𐑳𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑣𐑨𐑑𐑕; 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑻𐑯, 𐑩 𐑢𐑱𐑤-𐑚𐑴𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑩𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛, 𐑚𐑪𐑑𐑩𐑥 𐑛𐑬𐑯; 𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑙𐑦𐑙 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑝 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑰𐑯 𐑞 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑤𐑴𐑼 𐑡𐑷 𐑝 𐑞 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑞𐑱 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑕𐑤𐑱𐑯. 𐑕𐑦𐑜𐑯𐑩𐑤𐑟, 𐑧𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑟, 𐑯 𐑡𐑨𐑒𐑕 𐑝 𐑷𐑤 𐑒𐑳𐑤𐑼𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑓𐑤𐑲𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑣𐑻 𐑮𐑦𐑜𐑦𐑙, 𐑪𐑯 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑕𐑲𐑛. 𐑕𐑲𐑛𐑢𐑱𐑟 𐑤𐑨𐑖𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑰𐑗 𐑝 𐑣𐑻 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑚𐑭𐑕𐑒𐑩𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑑𐑪𐑐𐑕 𐑢𐑻 𐑑𐑵 𐑚𐑨𐑮𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑝 𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥; 𐑩𐑚𐑳𐑝 𐑢𐑦𐑗, 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑻 𐑑𐑪𐑐-𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑒𐑮𐑪𐑕-𐑑𐑮𐑰𐑟, 𐑿 𐑕𐑷 𐑕𐑤𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑒𐑼𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑕 𐑓𐑤𐑵𐑦𐑛; 𐑯 𐑯𐑱𐑤𐑛 𐑑 𐑣𐑻 𐑥𐑱𐑯 𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑒 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩 𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑟𐑩𐑯 𐑤𐑨𐑥𐑐.

𐑨𐑟 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼𐑢𐑼𐑛𐑟 𐑤𐑻𐑯𐑛, 𐑞 ·𐑚𐑨𐑗𐑩𐑤𐑼 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑥𐑧𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑼𐑐𐑮𐑲𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑩𐑒𐑕𐑧𐑕; 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑥𐑹 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑓𐑩𐑤, 𐑓 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑒𐑮𐑵𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑕𐑰𐑟 𐑯𐑿𐑥𐑼𐑩𐑕 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑝𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑜𐑪𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑲𐑼 𐑥𐑳𐑯𐑔𐑕 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑 𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑕𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑩𐑤 𐑓𐑦𐑖. 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑨𐑮𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑓 𐑯 𐑚𐑮𐑧𐑛 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑜𐑦𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑩𐑢𐑱 𐑑 𐑥𐑱𐑒 𐑮𐑵𐑥 𐑓 𐑞 𐑓𐑸 𐑥𐑹 𐑝𐑨𐑤𐑿𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑩𐑛𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑳𐑐𐑤𐑦𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑒𐑭𐑕𐑒𐑕 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑚𐑸𐑑𐑼𐑛 𐑓, 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑕 𐑖𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑥𐑧𐑑; 𐑯 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑕𐑑𐑴𐑛 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑒, 𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯'𐑟 𐑯 𐑪𐑓𐑦𐑕𐑼𐑟' 𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑑-𐑮𐑵𐑥𐑟. 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑞 𐑒𐑨𐑚𐑦𐑯 𐑑𐑱𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑑𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑯𐑪𐑒𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑒𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙-𐑢𐑫𐑛; 𐑯 𐑞 𐑒𐑨𐑚𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑧𐑕 𐑛𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑪𐑓 𐑞 𐑚𐑮𐑷𐑛 𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑝 𐑩𐑯 𐑶𐑤-𐑚𐑳𐑑, 𐑤𐑨𐑖𐑑 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑑 𐑞 𐑓𐑤𐑹 𐑓 𐑩 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑐𐑰𐑕. 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑴𐑒𐑕𐑩𐑤, 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑼𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑨𐑒𐑗𐑵𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑷𐑒𐑑 𐑯 𐑐𐑦𐑗𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑗𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑕, 𐑯 𐑓𐑦𐑤𐑛 𐑞𐑧𐑥; 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑣𐑿𐑥𐑼𐑩𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑨𐑛𐑩𐑛, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑒𐑫𐑒 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑒𐑤𐑨𐑐𐑑 𐑩 𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑤𐑸𐑡𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑶𐑤𐑼, 𐑯 𐑓𐑦𐑤𐑛 𐑦𐑑; 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑿𐑼𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑐𐑤𐑳𐑜𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑐𐑺 𐑒𐑪𐑓𐑦-𐑐𐑪𐑑 𐑯 𐑓𐑦𐑤𐑛 𐑦𐑑; 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑽𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑞 𐑕𐑪𐑒𐑩𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑞𐑺 𐑲𐑼𐑯𐑟 𐑯 𐑓𐑦𐑤𐑛 𐑞𐑧𐑥; 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑰𐑛 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑓𐑦𐑤𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥, 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑧𐑐𐑑 𐑞 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯'𐑟 𐑐𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑵𐑯𐑟 𐑐𐑪𐑒𐑩𐑑𐑕, 𐑯 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑻𐑝𐑛 𐑑 𐑔𐑮𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵, 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓-𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑑𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑦 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑲𐑼 𐑕𐑨𐑑𐑦𐑕𐑓𐑨𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯.

𐑨𐑟 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑜𐑤𐑨𐑛 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑝 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑤𐑳𐑒 𐑚𐑹 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑥𐑵𐑛𐑦 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛, 𐑞 𐑚𐑸𐑚𐑼𐑾𐑯 𐑕𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑝 𐑦𐑯𐑹𐑥𐑩𐑕 𐑛𐑮𐑳𐑥𐑟 𐑒𐑱𐑥 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑣𐑻 𐑓𐑴𐑒𐑕𐑩𐑤; 𐑯 𐑛𐑮𐑷𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑯𐑽𐑼, 𐑩 𐑒𐑮𐑬𐑛 𐑝 𐑣𐑻 𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑢𐑻 𐑕𐑰𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑣𐑻 𐑣𐑿𐑡 𐑑𐑮𐑲-𐑐𐑪𐑑𐑕, 𐑢𐑦𐑗, 𐑒𐑳𐑝𐑼𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑐𐑸𐑗𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑-𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑐𐑴𐑒 𐑹 𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑥𐑩𐑒 𐑕𐑒𐑦𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑒 𐑓𐑦𐑖, 𐑜𐑱𐑝 𐑓𐑹𐑔 𐑩 𐑤𐑬𐑛 𐑮𐑹 𐑑 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑴𐑒 𐑝 𐑞 𐑒𐑤𐑧𐑯𐑗𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑵. 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑒𐑢𐑹𐑑𐑼-𐑛𐑧𐑒, 𐑞 𐑥𐑱𐑑𐑕 𐑯 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑽𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑛𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑪𐑤𐑦𐑝-𐑣𐑿𐑛 𐑜𐑻𐑤𐑟 𐑣𐑵 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑦𐑤𐑴𐑐𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑪𐑤𐑦𐑯𐑰𐑟𐑾𐑯 ·𐑲𐑤𐑟; 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑕𐑩𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑩𐑯 𐑹𐑯𐑩𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑴𐑑, 𐑓𐑻𐑥𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑛 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑓𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑢𐑰𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑹𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑯 𐑥𐑱𐑯𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑, 𐑔𐑮𐑰 ·𐑤𐑪𐑙 ·𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑯𐑰𐑜𐑮𐑴𐑟, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑜𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑤-𐑚𐑴𐑟 𐑝 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑲𐑝𐑼𐑦, 𐑢𐑻 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑲𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑤𐑺𐑾𐑕 𐑡𐑦𐑜. 𐑥𐑰𐑯𐑢𐑲𐑤, 𐑳𐑞𐑼𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐'𐑕 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑦 𐑢𐑻 𐑑𐑿𐑥𐑳𐑤𐑗𐑵𐑩𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑦𐑟𐑦 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑥𐑱𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑼𐑦 𐑝 𐑞 𐑑𐑮𐑲-𐑢𐑻𐑒𐑕, 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑞 𐑣𐑿𐑡 𐑐𐑪𐑑𐑕 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑵𐑝𐑛. 𐑿 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑔𐑷𐑑 𐑞𐑱 𐑢𐑻 𐑐𐑫𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑞 𐑒𐑻𐑕𐑑 ·𐑚𐑨𐑕𐑑𐑰𐑤, 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑢𐑲𐑤𐑛 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑟 𐑞𐑱 𐑮𐑱𐑟𐑛, 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑯𐑬 𐑿𐑕𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑚𐑮𐑦𐑒 𐑯 𐑥𐑹𐑑𐑼 𐑢𐑻 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑻𐑤𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑕𐑰.

𐑤𐑹𐑛 𐑯 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑼 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑕𐑰𐑯, 𐑞 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑫𐑛 𐑦𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑑 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐'𐑕 𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑝𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑒𐑢𐑹𐑑𐑼-𐑛𐑧𐑒, 𐑕𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑣𐑴𐑤 𐑮𐑦𐑡𐑶𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑛𐑮𐑭𐑥𐑩 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑓𐑫𐑤 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑯 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑥𐑽𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑝𐑛 𐑓 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑴𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑡𐑵𐑩𐑤 𐑛𐑲𐑝𐑻𐑖𐑩𐑯.

𐑯 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚, 𐑣𐑰 𐑑𐑵 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑢𐑹𐑑𐑼-𐑛𐑧𐑒, 𐑖𐑨𐑜𐑦 𐑯 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑒, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚𐑼𐑯 𐑜𐑤𐑵𐑥; 𐑯 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑑𐑵 𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑕 𐑒𐑮𐑪𐑕𐑑 𐑰𐑗 𐑳𐑞𐑼'𐑟 𐑢𐑱𐑒𐑕—𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑡𐑵𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑓 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑐𐑭𐑕𐑑, 𐑞 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑷𐑤 𐑓𐑹𐑚𐑴𐑛𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑨𐑟 𐑑 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑑 𐑒𐑳𐑥—𐑞𐑺 𐑑𐑵 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑝𐑟 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑻𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑞 𐑣𐑴𐑤 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑰𐑯.

“𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑩𐑚𐑹𐑛, 𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑩𐑚𐑹𐑛!” 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 𐑞 𐑜𐑱 ·𐑚𐑨𐑗𐑩𐑤𐑼'𐑟 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑭𐑯𐑛𐑼, 𐑤𐑦𐑓𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑜𐑤𐑭𐑕 𐑯 𐑩 𐑚𐑪𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑺.

“𐑣𐑨𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑢𐑲𐑑 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤?” 𐑜𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑛 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑦𐑯 𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑤𐑲.

“𐑯𐑴; 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑣𐑻𐑛 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑥; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑛𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑰𐑝 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑨𐑑 𐑷𐑤,” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑞 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑜𐑫𐑛-𐑣𐑿𐑥𐑼𐑩𐑛𐑤𐑦. “𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑩𐑚𐑹𐑛!”

“𐑞𐑬 𐑸𐑑 𐑑𐑵 𐑛𐑨𐑥𐑛 𐑡𐑪𐑤𐑦. 𐑕𐑱𐑤 𐑪𐑯. 𐑣𐑨𐑕𐑑 𐑤𐑪𐑕𐑑 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑥𐑧𐑯?”

“𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑳𐑓 𐑑 𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑒 𐑝—𐑑𐑵 𐑲𐑕𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑟, 𐑞𐑨𐑑'𐑕 𐑷𐑤;—𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑩𐑚𐑹𐑛, 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑣𐑸𐑑𐑦, 𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑙. 𐑲'𐑤 𐑕𐑵𐑯 𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑒 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑘𐑹 𐑚𐑮𐑬. 𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑙, 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑘𐑰 (𐑥𐑧𐑮𐑦'𐑟 𐑞 𐑐𐑤𐑱); 𐑩 𐑓𐑫𐑤 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑯 𐑣𐑴𐑥𐑢𐑼𐑛-𐑚𐑬𐑯𐑛.”

“𐑣𐑬 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑕 𐑓𐑩𐑥𐑦𐑤𐑽 𐑦𐑟 𐑩 𐑓𐑵𐑤!” 𐑥𐑳𐑑𐑼𐑛 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚; 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑩𐑤𐑬𐑛, “𐑞𐑬 𐑸𐑑 𐑩 𐑓𐑫𐑤 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑯 𐑣𐑴𐑥𐑢𐑼𐑛 𐑚𐑬𐑯𐑛, 𐑞𐑬 𐑕𐑱'𐑕𐑑; 𐑢𐑧𐑤, 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑒𐑷𐑤 𐑥𐑰 𐑩𐑯 𐑧𐑥𐑐𐑑𐑦 𐑖𐑦𐑐, 𐑯 𐑬𐑑𐑢𐑼𐑛-𐑚𐑬𐑯𐑛. 𐑕𐑴 𐑜𐑴 𐑞𐑲 𐑢𐑱𐑟, 𐑯 𐑲 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑥𐑲𐑯. 𐑓𐑹𐑢𐑼𐑛 𐑞𐑺! 𐑕𐑧𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑕𐑱𐑤, 𐑯 𐑒𐑰𐑐 𐑣𐑻 𐑑 𐑞 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛!”

𐑯 𐑞𐑳𐑕, 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑞 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑗𐑽𐑦𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑞 𐑚𐑮𐑰𐑟, 𐑞 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚𐑼𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑓𐑷𐑑 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑑; 𐑯 𐑕𐑴 𐑞 𐑑𐑵 𐑝𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑐𐑸𐑑𐑩𐑛; 𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑵 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛 𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑝, 𐑤𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑜𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑑𐑩𐑢𐑹𐑛𐑟 𐑞 𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑰𐑛𐑦𐑙 ·𐑚𐑨𐑗𐑩𐑤𐑼; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑚𐑨𐑗𐑩𐑤𐑼'𐑟 𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑣𐑰𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑺 𐑜𐑱𐑟 𐑓 𐑞 𐑤𐑲𐑝𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑮𐑦 𐑞𐑱 𐑢𐑻 𐑦𐑯. 𐑯 𐑨𐑟 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚, 𐑤𐑰𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑞 𐑑𐑨𐑓𐑮𐑱𐑤, 𐑲𐑛 𐑞 𐑣𐑴𐑥𐑢𐑼𐑛-𐑚𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑒𐑮𐑭𐑓𐑑, 𐑣𐑰 𐑑𐑫𐑒 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑪𐑒𐑩𐑑 𐑩 𐑕𐑥𐑷𐑤 𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑕𐑨𐑯𐑛, 𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑑 𐑞 𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑤, 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑞𐑺𐑚𐑲 𐑚𐑮𐑦𐑙𐑦𐑙 𐑑𐑵 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑴𐑑 𐑩𐑕𐑴𐑖𐑦𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑑𐑩𐑜𐑧𐑞𐑼, 𐑓 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑓𐑦𐑤𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 ·𐑯𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑑 𐑕𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙𐑟.

·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 116. 𐑞 ·𐑛𐑲𐑦𐑙 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤.

𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑛𐑩𐑥 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑤𐑲𐑓, 𐑢𐑧𐑯, 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑮𐑲𐑑 𐑕𐑲𐑛, 𐑓𐑹𐑗𐑵𐑯'𐑟 𐑓𐑱𐑝𐑼𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑕𐑱𐑤 𐑒𐑤𐑴𐑕 𐑚𐑲 𐑳𐑕, 𐑢𐑰, 𐑞𐑴 𐑷𐑤 𐑱𐑛𐑮𐑵𐑐 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹, 𐑒𐑨𐑗 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑮𐑳𐑖𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑮𐑰𐑟, 𐑯 𐑡𐑶𐑓𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑓𐑰𐑤 𐑬𐑼 𐑚𐑨𐑜𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑓𐑦𐑤 𐑬𐑑. 𐑕𐑴 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛. 𐑓 𐑯𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑 𐑛𐑱 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑜𐑱 ·𐑚𐑨𐑗𐑩𐑤𐑼, 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑕𐑰𐑯 𐑯 𐑓𐑹 𐑢𐑻 𐑕𐑤𐑱𐑯; 𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑚𐑲 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚.

𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑓𐑸 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑞 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼𐑯𐑵𐑯; 𐑯 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑽𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑟𐑩𐑯 𐑓𐑲𐑑 𐑢𐑻 𐑛𐑳𐑯: 𐑯 𐑓𐑤𐑴𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑤𐑳𐑝𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑳𐑯𐑕𐑧𐑑 𐑕𐑰 𐑯 𐑕𐑒𐑲, 𐑕𐑳𐑯 𐑯 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑚𐑴𐑔 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑲𐑛 𐑑𐑩𐑜𐑧𐑞𐑼; 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩 𐑕𐑢𐑰𐑑𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑝𐑯𐑩𐑕, 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑦𐑯𐑮𐑰𐑞𐑦𐑙 𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑒𐑻𐑤𐑛 𐑳𐑐 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑮𐑴𐑟𐑦 𐑺, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑓 𐑓𐑸 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑛𐑰𐑐 𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑯 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑝𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑝𐑨𐑤𐑦𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑤𐑩 𐑲𐑤𐑟, 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑐𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑖 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛-𐑚𐑮𐑰𐑟, 𐑢𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑛 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑼, 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑜𐑪𐑯 𐑑 𐑕𐑰, 𐑓𐑮𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑝𐑧𐑕𐑐𐑼 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑟.

𐑕𐑵𐑞𐑛 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑵𐑞𐑛 𐑑 𐑛𐑰𐑐𐑼 𐑜𐑤𐑵𐑥, ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚, 𐑣𐑵 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑕𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑛 𐑪𐑓 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑕𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑢𐑪𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑲𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑱𐑯𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑯𐑬 𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑚𐑴𐑑. 𐑓 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡 𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑩𐑚𐑟𐑻𐑝𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑛𐑲𐑦𐑙—𐑞 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑳𐑯𐑢𐑼𐑛𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑣𐑧𐑛, 𐑯 𐑕𐑴 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑲𐑼𐑦𐑙—𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡 𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑒𐑩𐑤, 𐑚𐑦𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑛 𐑝 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩 𐑐𐑤𐑨𐑕𐑦𐑛 𐑰𐑝𐑯𐑦𐑙, 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑣𐑬 𐑑 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑝𐑱𐑛 𐑩 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑕𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑳𐑯𐑯𐑴𐑯 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹.

“𐑣𐑰 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑟 𐑯 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑑 𐑦𐑑,—𐑣𐑬 𐑕𐑤𐑴𐑤𐑦, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑣𐑬 𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑛𐑓𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑤𐑦, 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑪𐑥𐑦𐑡-𐑮𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑴𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑮𐑬, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑛𐑲𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟. 𐑣𐑰 𐑑𐑵 𐑢𐑻𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑕 𐑓𐑲𐑼; 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑓𐑱𐑔𐑓𐑩𐑤, 𐑚𐑮𐑷𐑛, 𐑚𐑼𐑴𐑯𐑾𐑤 𐑝𐑨𐑕𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑯!—𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑑𐑵-𐑓𐑱𐑝𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑲𐑟 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑕𐑰 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑑𐑵-𐑓𐑱𐑝𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑲𐑑𐑕. 𐑤𐑫𐑒! 𐑣𐑽, 𐑓𐑸 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼-𐑤𐑪𐑒𐑑; 𐑚𐑦𐑘𐑪𐑯𐑛 𐑷𐑤 𐑣𐑳𐑥 𐑝 𐑣𐑿𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑰𐑤 𐑹 𐑢𐑴; 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑯 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑸𐑖𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑰𐑟; 𐑢𐑺 𐑑 𐑑𐑮𐑩𐑛𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑯𐑴 𐑮𐑪𐑒𐑕 𐑓𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑖 𐑑𐑨𐑚𐑤𐑩𐑑𐑕; 𐑢𐑺 𐑓 𐑤𐑪𐑙 ·𐑗𐑲𐑯𐑰𐑟 𐑱𐑡𐑩𐑟, 𐑞 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑴𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑮𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑪𐑯 𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑗𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑯 𐑳𐑯𐑕𐑐𐑴𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑑, 𐑨𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑖𐑲𐑯 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑯𐑰𐑠𐑺'𐑟 𐑳𐑯𐑯𐑴𐑯 𐑕𐑹𐑕; 𐑣𐑽, 𐑑𐑵, 𐑤𐑲𐑓 𐑛𐑲𐑟 𐑕𐑳𐑯𐑢𐑼𐑛𐑟 𐑓𐑫𐑤 𐑝 𐑓𐑱𐑔; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑕𐑰! 𐑯𐑴 𐑕𐑵𐑯𐑼 𐑛𐑧𐑛, 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑛𐑧𐑔 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑟 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑞 𐑒𐑹𐑐𐑕, 𐑯 𐑦𐑑 𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑟 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑢𐑱.

“𐑴, 𐑞𐑬 𐑛𐑸𐑒 ·𐑣𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑵 𐑣𐑭𐑓 𐑝 𐑯𐑱𐑗𐑼, 𐑣𐑵 𐑝 𐑛𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑚𐑴𐑯𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑞𐑲 𐑕𐑧𐑐𐑼𐑩𐑑 𐑔𐑮𐑴𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑢𐑺 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑣𐑸𐑑 𐑝 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑳𐑯𐑝𐑻𐑡𐑼𐑛 𐑕𐑰𐑟; 𐑞𐑬 𐑸𐑑 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑓𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑤, 𐑞𐑬 𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑯, 𐑯 𐑑𐑵 𐑑𐑮𐑵𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑑 𐑥𐑰 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑲𐑛-𐑕𐑤𐑷𐑑𐑼𐑦𐑙 ·𐑑𐑲𐑓𐑵𐑯, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑣𐑳𐑖𐑑 𐑚𐑧𐑮𐑾𐑤 𐑝 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑒𐑭𐑥. 𐑯𐑹 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑞𐑲 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑕𐑳𐑯𐑢𐑼𐑛𐑟 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑛𐑲𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑧𐑛, 𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑜𐑪𐑯 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯, 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑 𐑩 𐑤𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑯 𐑑 𐑥𐑰.

“𐑴, 𐑑𐑮𐑧𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑣𐑵𐑐𐑑 𐑯 𐑢𐑧𐑤𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑐 𐑝 𐑐𐑬𐑼! 𐑴, 𐑣𐑲 𐑩𐑕𐑐𐑲𐑼𐑦𐑙, 𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑚𐑴𐑛 𐑡𐑧𐑑!—𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑝𐑩𐑕𐑑, 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑡𐑧𐑑𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑝𐑱𐑯! 𐑦𐑯 𐑝𐑱𐑯, 𐑴 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑛𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑞𐑬 𐑕𐑰𐑒 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑕𐑰𐑛𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑘𐑪𐑯 𐑷𐑤-𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑳𐑯, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑟 𐑓𐑹𐑔 𐑤𐑲𐑓, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑜𐑦𐑝𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯. 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑛𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑞𐑬, 𐑛𐑸𐑒𐑼 𐑣𐑭𐑓, 𐑮𐑪𐑒 𐑥𐑰 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑐𐑮𐑬𐑛𐑼, 𐑦𐑓 𐑩 𐑛𐑸𐑒𐑼 𐑓𐑱𐑔. 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑲 𐑳𐑯𐑯𐑱𐑥𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑓𐑤𐑴𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑯𐑰𐑔 𐑥𐑰 𐑣𐑽; 𐑲 𐑨𐑥 𐑚𐑶𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑚𐑮𐑧𐑔𐑕 𐑝 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑕 𐑤𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑟, 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑣𐑱𐑤𐑛 𐑨𐑟 𐑺, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼 𐑯𐑬.

“𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑣𐑱𐑤, 𐑓 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑣𐑱𐑤, 𐑴 𐑕𐑰, 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑵𐑟 𐑦𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑑𐑪𐑕𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑞 𐑢𐑲𐑤𐑛 𐑓𐑬𐑤 𐑓𐑲𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑑. 𐑚𐑹𐑯 𐑝 𐑻𐑔, 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑕𐑰; 𐑞𐑴 𐑣𐑦𐑤 𐑯 𐑝𐑨𐑤𐑦 𐑥𐑳𐑞𐑼𐑛 𐑥𐑰, 𐑘𐑰 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑴𐑟 𐑸 𐑥𐑲 𐑓𐑪𐑕𐑑𐑼-𐑚𐑮𐑳𐑞𐑼𐑟!”

·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 117. 𐑞 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤 ·𐑢𐑪𐑗.

𐑞 𐑓𐑹 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑕𐑤𐑱𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑰𐑝𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑛𐑲𐑛 𐑢𐑲𐑛 𐑩𐑐𐑸𐑑; 𐑢𐑳𐑯, 𐑓𐑸 𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑢𐑼𐑛; 𐑢𐑳𐑯, 𐑤𐑧𐑕 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑, 𐑑 𐑤𐑰𐑢𐑼𐑛; 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑩𐑣𐑧𐑛; 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑩𐑕𐑑𐑻𐑯. 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑢𐑻 𐑚𐑮𐑷𐑑 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑙𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑺 𐑯𐑲𐑑𐑓𐑷𐑤; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑢𐑼𐑛 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑮𐑰𐑗𐑑 𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑥𐑹𐑯𐑦𐑙; 𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑒𐑦𐑤𐑛 𐑦𐑑 𐑤𐑱 𐑚𐑲 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑷𐑤 𐑯𐑲𐑑; 𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑚𐑴𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚'𐑟.

𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑓-𐑐𐑴𐑤 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑔𐑮𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑳𐑐𐑮𐑲𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑛 𐑢𐑱𐑤'𐑟 𐑕𐑐𐑬𐑑-𐑣𐑴𐑤; 𐑯 𐑞 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑙𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑑𐑪𐑐, 𐑒𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑩 𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑓𐑤𐑦𐑒𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑜𐑤𐑺 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑒, 𐑜𐑤𐑪𐑕𐑦 𐑚𐑨𐑒, 𐑯 𐑓𐑸 𐑬𐑑 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑥𐑦𐑛𐑯𐑲𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑝𐑟, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑗𐑱𐑓𐑑 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤'𐑟 𐑚𐑮𐑷𐑛 𐑓𐑤𐑨𐑙𐑒, 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑕𐑪𐑓𐑑 𐑕𐑻𐑓 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑩 𐑚𐑰𐑗.

𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑴𐑑'𐑕 𐑒𐑮𐑵 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑩𐑕𐑤𐑰𐑐 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑸𐑟𐑰; 𐑣𐑵 𐑒𐑮𐑬𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑬, 𐑕𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑖𐑸𐑒𐑕, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑮𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑛 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑯 𐑑𐑨𐑐𐑑 𐑞 𐑤𐑲𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑛𐑼 𐑐𐑤𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑕 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞𐑺 𐑑𐑱𐑤𐑟. 𐑩 𐑕𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑞 𐑥𐑴𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑴𐑝𐑼 ·𐑨𐑕𐑓𐑨𐑤𐑑𐑲𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑳𐑯𐑓𐑼𐑜𐑦𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑜𐑴𐑕𐑑𐑕 𐑝 ·𐑜𐑩𐑥𐑹𐑩, 𐑮𐑨𐑯 𐑖𐑳𐑛𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑞 𐑺.

𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑤𐑳𐑥𐑚𐑼𐑟, ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚, 𐑓𐑱𐑕 𐑑 𐑓𐑱𐑕, 𐑕𐑷 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑸𐑟𐑰; 𐑯 𐑣𐑵𐑐𐑑 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑜𐑤𐑵𐑥 𐑝 𐑞 𐑯𐑲𐑑 𐑞𐑱 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑞 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑓𐑤𐑳𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛. “𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑛𐑮𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑦𐑑 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯,” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑣𐑰.

“𐑝 𐑞 𐑣𐑻𐑕𐑩𐑟? 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑲 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑧𐑛, 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑥𐑨𐑯, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑯𐑲𐑞𐑼 𐑣𐑻𐑕 𐑯𐑹 𐑒𐑪𐑓𐑦𐑯 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑚𐑰 𐑞𐑲𐑯?”

“𐑯 𐑣𐑵 𐑸 𐑣𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑛𐑲 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑰?”

“𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑲 𐑕𐑧𐑛, 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑥𐑨𐑯, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑺 𐑞𐑬 𐑒𐑫𐑛𐑕𐑑 𐑛𐑲 𐑪𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑝𐑶𐑦𐑡, 𐑑𐑵 𐑣𐑻𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑰 𐑕𐑰𐑯 𐑚𐑲 𐑞𐑰 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑰; 𐑞 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑥𐑹𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟; 𐑯 𐑞 𐑝𐑦𐑟𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑝 𐑞 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑜𐑮𐑴𐑯 𐑦𐑯 ·𐑩𐑥𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑩.”

“𐑲, 𐑲! 𐑩 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡 𐑕𐑲𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑, ·𐑐𐑸𐑟𐑰:—𐑩 𐑣𐑻𐑕 𐑯 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑐𐑤𐑵𐑥𐑟 𐑓𐑤𐑴𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑞 𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑝𐑟 𐑓 𐑞 𐑐𐑷𐑤-𐑚𐑺𐑼𐑟. 𐑣𐑭! 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩 𐑕𐑲𐑑 𐑢𐑰 𐑖𐑨𐑤 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑵𐑯 𐑕𐑰.”

“𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑰𐑝 𐑦𐑑 𐑹 𐑯𐑪𐑑, 𐑞𐑬 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑛𐑲 𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑦𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑕𐑰𐑯, 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑥𐑨𐑯.”

“𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑱𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑞𐑲𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓?”

“𐑞𐑴 𐑦𐑑 𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑑 𐑞 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑, 𐑲 𐑖𐑨𐑤 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑜𐑴 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑞𐑰 𐑞𐑲 𐑐𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑑.”

“𐑯 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑞𐑬 𐑸𐑑 𐑕𐑴 𐑜𐑪𐑯 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹—𐑦𐑓 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑷𐑤—𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑺 𐑲 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑓𐑪𐑤𐑴, 𐑞𐑬 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑩𐑐𐑽 𐑑 𐑥𐑰, 𐑑 𐑐𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑑 𐑥𐑰 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤?—𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑴? 𐑢𐑧𐑤, 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑲 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑰𐑝 𐑷𐑤 𐑘𐑰 𐑕𐑱, 𐑴 𐑥𐑲 𐑐𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑑! 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑣𐑽 𐑑𐑵 𐑐𐑤𐑧𐑡𐑩𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑲 𐑖𐑨𐑤 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑕𐑤𐑱 ·𐑥𐑪𐑚𐑦 ·𐑛𐑦𐑒 𐑯 𐑕𐑼𐑝𐑲𐑝 𐑦𐑑.”

“𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑩𐑯𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑐𐑤𐑧𐑡, 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑥𐑨𐑯,” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑸𐑟𐑰, 𐑨𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑲𐑟 𐑤𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑳𐑐 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑓𐑲𐑼-𐑓𐑤𐑲𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑜𐑤𐑵𐑥—“𐑣𐑧𐑥𐑐 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑒𐑦𐑤 𐑞𐑰.”

“𐑞 𐑜𐑨𐑤𐑴𐑟, 𐑘𐑰 𐑥𐑰𐑯.—𐑲 𐑨𐑥 𐑦𐑥𐑹𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑪𐑯 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑯 𐑪𐑯 𐑕𐑰,” 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑤𐑭𐑓 𐑝 𐑛𐑦𐑮𐑦𐑠𐑩𐑯;—“𐑦𐑥𐑹𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑪𐑯 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑯 𐑪𐑯 𐑕𐑰!”

𐑚𐑴𐑔 𐑢𐑻 𐑕𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯, 𐑨𐑟 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑥𐑨𐑯. 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑱 𐑛𐑷𐑯 𐑒𐑱𐑥 𐑪𐑯, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑤𐑳𐑥𐑚𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑒𐑮𐑵 𐑼𐑴𐑟 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑'𐑕 𐑚𐑪𐑑𐑩𐑥, 𐑯 𐑺 𐑯𐑵𐑯 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑛 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑚𐑮𐑷𐑑 𐑑 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐.

·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 118. 𐑞 ·𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑯𐑑.

𐑞 𐑕𐑰𐑟𐑩𐑯 𐑓 𐑞 ·𐑤𐑲𐑯 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑧𐑙𐑔 𐑛𐑮𐑵 𐑯𐑽; 𐑯 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑛𐑱 𐑢𐑧𐑯 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚, 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑨𐑚𐑦𐑯, 𐑒𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑲𐑟 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑓𐑑, 𐑞 𐑝𐑦𐑡𐑦𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑥𐑟𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑪𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑤 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑐𐑴𐑒𐑕, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑰𐑜𐑼 𐑥𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑯𐑼𐑟 𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑳𐑯 𐑑 𐑞 𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑕𐑩𐑟, 𐑯 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑞𐑺 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑺 𐑲𐑟 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑓𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑑 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑯𐑱𐑤𐑛 𐑛𐑳𐑚𐑤𐑵𐑯; 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑓 𐑞 𐑹𐑛𐑼 𐑑 𐑐𐑶𐑯𐑑 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐'𐑕 𐑐𐑮𐑬 𐑓 𐑞 𐑦𐑒𐑢𐑱𐑑𐑼. 𐑦𐑯 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑞 𐑹𐑛𐑼 𐑒𐑱𐑥. 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑣𐑸𐑛 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑲 𐑯𐑵𐑯; 𐑯 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚, 𐑕𐑰𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑬𐑟 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑲-𐑣𐑶𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑴𐑑, 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑴𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑛𐑱𐑤𐑦 𐑪𐑚𐑟𐑼𐑝𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑯 𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑑𐑻𐑥𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑤𐑨𐑑𐑦𐑑𐑿𐑛.

𐑯𐑬, 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 ·𐑡𐑨𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑰𐑟 𐑕𐑰, 𐑞 𐑛𐑱𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑼 𐑸 𐑨𐑟 𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑦𐑓𐑳𐑤𐑡𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟. 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑳𐑯𐑚𐑤𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑝𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑛 ·𐑡𐑨𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑰𐑟 𐑕𐑳𐑯 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑟 𐑞 𐑚𐑤𐑱𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑴𐑒𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑜𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑦 𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯'𐑟 𐑦𐑥𐑧𐑠𐑼𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑚𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑙-𐑜𐑤𐑭𐑕. 𐑞 𐑕𐑒𐑲 𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑕 𐑤𐑨𐑒𐑼𐑛; 𐑒𐑤𐑬𐑛𐑟 𐑞𐑺 𐑸 𐑯𐑳𐑯; 𐑞 𐑣𐑼𐑲𐑟𐑩𐑯 𐑓𐑤𐑴𐑑𐑕; 𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑯𐑱𐑒𐑩𐑛𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑳𐑯𐑮𐑦𐑤𐑰𐑝𐑛 𐑮𐑱𐑛𐑾𐑯𐑕 𐑦𐑟 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑳𐑓𐑼𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑐𐑤𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑟 𐑝 ·𐑜𐑪𐑛'𐑟 𐑔𐑮𐑴𐑯. 𐑢𐑧𐑤 𐑞𐑨𐑑 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚'𐑟 𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑓𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑖𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑒𐑳𐑤𐑼𐑛 𐑜𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑩𐑟, 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑑 𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑕𐑲𐑑 𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑴𐑤𐑼 𐑓𐑲𐑼. 𐑕𐑴, 𐑕𐑢𐑦𐑙𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑰𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑓𐑹𐑥 𐑑 𐑞 𐑮𐑴𐑤 𐑝 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐, 𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑨𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑡𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤-𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑩𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕𐑑 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑲, 𐑣𐑰 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑱𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑐𐑪𐑕𐑗𐑼 𐑓 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑥𐑴𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑑 𐑒𐑨𐑗 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑲𐑕 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑯 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑜𐑱𐑯 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑲𐑕 𐑥𐑼𐑦𐑛𐑾𐑯. 𐑥𐑰𐑯𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑴𐑤 𐑩𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩𐑚𐑕𐑹𐑚𐑛, 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑸𐑟𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑰𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑦𐑯𐑰𐑔 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐'𐑕 𐑛𐑧𐑒, 𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑓𐑱𐑕 𐑔𐑮𐑴𐑯 𐑳𐑐 𐑤𐑲𐑒 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚'𐑟, 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑲𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑕𐑳𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑥; 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑞 𐑤𐑦𐑛𐑟 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑲𐑟 𐑣𐑭𐑓 𐑣𐑫𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑞𐑺 𐑹𐑚𐑟, 𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑲𐑤𐑛 𐑓𐑱𐑕 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑛𐑿𐑛 𐑑 𐑩𐑯 𐑻𐑔𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑭𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑩𐑕𐑯𐑩𐑕. 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑧𐑙𐑔 𐑞 𐑛𐑦𐑟𐑲𐑼𐑛 𐑪𐑚𐑟𐑼𐑝𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑩𐑯; 𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑤 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑲𐑝𐑼𐑦 𐑤𐑧𐑜, ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑕𐑵𐑯 𐑒𐑨𐑤𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑤𐑨𐑑𐑦𐑑𐑿𐑛 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑲𐑕 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑. 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑓𐑷𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑩 𐑥𐑴𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑'𐑕 𐑮𐑧𐑝𐑼𐑦, 𐑣𐑰 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯 𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑑 𐑳𐑐 𐑑𐑩𐑢𐑹𐑛𐑟 𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑯 𐑯 𐑥𐑻𐑥𐑼𐑛 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓: “𐑞𐑬 𐑕𐑰-𐑥𐑸𐑒! 𐑞𐑬 𐑣𐑲 𐑯 𐑥𐑲𐑑𐑦 ·𐑐𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑑! 𐑞𐑬 𐑑𐑧𐑤𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑥𐑰 𐑑𐑮𐑵𐑤𐑦 𐑢𐑺 𐑲 𐑨𐑥—𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑞𐑬 𐑒𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑞 𐑤𐑰𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑯𐑑 𐑢𐑺 𐑲 𐑖𐑨𐑤 𐑚𐑰? 𐑹 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑞𐑬 𐑑𐑧𐑤 𐑢𐑺 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑦𐑕𐑲𐑛𐑟 𐑥𐑰 𐑦𐑟 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑥𐑴𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑤𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑙? 𐑢𐑺 𐑦𐑟 ·𐑥𐑪𐑚𐑦 ·𐑛𐑦𐑒? 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑞𐑬 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑲𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑥. 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑲𐑟 𐑝 𐑥𐑲𐑯 𐑤𐑫𐑒 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑲 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑯𐑬 𐑚𐑦𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑥; 𐑲, 𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑲 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑯𐑬 𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑦𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑪𐑚𐑡𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑕 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑳𐑯𐑯𐑴𐑯, 𐑞𐑦𐑞𐑼 𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑝 𐑞𐑰, 𐑞𐑬 𐑕𐑳𐑯!”

𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑜𐑱𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑯𐑑, 𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙, 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑞 𐑳𐑞𐑼, 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑯𐑿𐑥𐑼𐑩𐑕 𐑒𐑩𐑚𐑨𐑤𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑝𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟, 𐑣𐑰 𐑐𐑪𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑛 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯, 𐑯 𐑥𐑳𐑑𐑼𐑛: “𐑓𐑵𐑤𐑦𐑖 𐑑𐑶! 𐑚𐑱𐑚𐑦𐑟' 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑣𐑷𐑑𐑦 ·𐑨𐑛𐑥𐑼𐑩𐑤𐑟, 𐑯 ·𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑛𐑹𐑟, 𐑯 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑟; 𐑞 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛 𐑚𐑮𐑨𐑜𐑟 𐑝 𐑞𐑰, 𐑝 𐑞𐑲 𐑒𐑳𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑯 𐑥𐑲𐑑; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑷𐑤 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑞𐑬 𐑛𐑵, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑑𐑧𐑤 𐑞 𐑐𐑫𐑼, 𐑐𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑐𐑶𐑯𐑑, 𐑢𐑺 𐑞𐑬 𐑞𐑲𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑪𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑲𐑛 𐑐𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑩𐑑, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑟 𐑞𐑰: 𐑯𐑴! 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑡𐑪𐑑 𐑥𐑹! 𐑞𐑬 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑑𐑧𐑤 𐑢𐑺 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑛𐑮𐑪𐑐 𐑝 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼 𐑹 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑯 𐑝 𐑕𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑚𐑰 𐑑-𐑥𐑪𐑮𐑴 𐑯𐑵𐑯; 𐑯 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞𐑲 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑞𐑬 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑳𐑤𐑑𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑯! 𐑕𐑲𐑩𐑯𐑕! 𐑒𐑻𐑕 𐑞𐑰, 𐑞𐑬 𐑝𐑱𐑯 𐑑𐑶; 𐑯 𐑒𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑒𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑥𐑨𐑯'𐑟 𐑲𐑟 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑓𐑑 𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑯, 𐑣𐑵𐑟 𐑤𐑲𐑝 𐑝𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑛𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑕𐑒𐑹𐑗𐑩𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑨𐑟 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑲𐑟 𐑸 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑯𐑬 𐑕𐑒𐑹𐑗𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞𐑲 𐑤𐑲𐑑, 𐑴 𐑕𐑳𐑯! 𐑤𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑤 𐑚𐑲 𐑯𐑱𐑗𐑼 𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑻𐑔'𐑕 𐑣𐑼𐑲𐑟𐑩𐑯 𐑸 𐑞 𐑜𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑝 𐑥𐑨𐑯'𐑟 𐑲𐑟; 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑖𐑪𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑬𐑯 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑧𐑛, 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑓 ·𐑜𐑪𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑑 𐑜𐑱𐑟 𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑻𐑥𐑩𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑. 𐑒𐑻𐑕 𐑞𐑰, 𐑞𐑬 𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑯𐑑!” 𐑛𐑨𐑖𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑑 𐑑 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑒, “𐑯𐑴 𐑤𐑪𐑙𐑜𐑼 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑲 𐑜𐑲𐑛 𐑥𐑲 𐑻𐑔𐑤𐑦 𐑢𐑱 𐑚𐑲 𐑞𐑰; 𐑞 𐑤𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑤 𐑖𐑦𐑐'𐑕 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑕, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑤𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑤 𐑛𐑧𐑛-𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑙, 𐑚𐑲 𐑤𐑪𐑜 𐑯 𐑚𐑲 𐑤𐑲𐑯; 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑖𐑨𐑤 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑛𐑳𐑒𐑑 𐑥𐑰, 𐑯 𐑖𐑴 𐑥𐑰 𐑥𐑲 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑰. 𐑲,” 𐑤𐑲𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑 𐑑 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑒, “𐑞𐑳𐑕 𐑲 𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑤 𐑪𐑯 𐑞𐑰, 𐑞𐑬 𐑐𐑷𐑤𐑑𐑮𐑦 𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑓𐑰𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑶𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑲; 𐑞𐑳𐑕 𐑲 𐑕𐑐𐑤𐑦𐑑 𐑯 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑶 𐑞𐑰!”

𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑓𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑞𐑳𐑕 𐑕𐑐𐑴𐑒 𐑯 𐑞𐑳𐑕 𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑤𐑲𐑝 𐑯 𐑛𐑧𐑛 𐑓𐑰𐑑, 𐑩 𐑕𐑯𐑽𐑦𐑙 𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑳𐑥𐑓 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑓 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚, 𐑯 𐑩 𐑓𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑺 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑓 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓—𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑐𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑞 𐑥𐑿𐑑, 𐑥𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑩𐑕 ·𐑐𐑸𐑟𐑰'𐑟 𐑓𐑱𐑕. 𐑳𐑯𐑩𐑚𐑟𐑻𐑝𐑛 𐑣𐑰 𐑮𐑴𐑟 𐑯 𐑜𐑤𐑲𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑩𐑢𐑱; 𐑢𐑲𐑤, 𐑷𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑒 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑨𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑 𐑝 𐑞𐑺 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑭𐑯𐑛𐑼, 𐑞 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑒𐑤𐑳𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑛 𐑑𐑩𐑜𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑴𐑒𐑕𐑩𐑤, 𐑑𐑦𐑤 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚, 𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑩𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑱𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑒, 𐑖𐑬𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑬𐑑—“𐑑 𐑞 𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑕𐑩𐑟! 𐑳𐑐 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑥!—𐑕𐑒𐑢𐑺 𐑦𐑯!”

𐑦𐑯 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑞 𐑘𐑸𐑛𐑟 𐑕𐑢𐑳𐑙 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛; 𐑯 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑣𐑭𐑓-𐑢𐑰𐑤𐑛 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑻 𐑣𐑰𐑤, 𐑣𐑻 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑓𐑻𐑥-𐑕𐑰𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑕𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑕 𐑦𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑶𐑟𐑛 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑻 𐑤𐑪𐑙, 𐑮𐑦𐑚𐑛 𐑣𐑳𐑤, 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑔𐑮𐑰 ·𐑣𐑪𐑮𐑱𐑑𐑦 𐑐𐑦𐑮𐑵𐑧𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑪𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑕𐑩𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑰𐑛.

𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑢𐑰𐑯 𐑞 𐑯𐑲𐑑-𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑟, ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒 𐑢𐑪𐑗𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛'𐑟 𐑑𐑿𐑥𐑳𐑤𐑗𐑵𐑩𐑕 𐑢𐑱, 𐑯 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚'𐑟 𐑷𐑤𐑕𐑴, 𐑨𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑤𐑻𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑒.

“𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑕𐑨𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑯𐑕 𐑒𐑴𐑤 𐑓𐑲𐑼 𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑗𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑩𐑜𐑤𐑴, 𐑓𐑫𐑤 𐑝 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑑𐑹𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑓𐑤𐑱𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑤𐑲𐑓; 𐑯 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑕𐑰𐑯 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑯 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑, 𐑛𐑬𐑯, 𐑛𐑬𐑯, 𐑑 𐑛𐑳𐑥𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑛𐑳𐑕𐑑. 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑝 𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟! 𐑝 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑓𐑲𐑼𐑦 𐑤𐑲𐑓 𐑝 𐑞𐑲𐑯, 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑧𐑙𐑔 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑱𐑯 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑣𐑰𐑐 𐑝 𐑨𐑖𐑩𐑟!”

“𐑲,” 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚, “𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑕𐑰-𐑒𐑴𐑤 𐑨𐑖𐑩𐑟—𐑥𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑘𐑰 𐑞𐑨𐑑, ·𐑥𐑼 ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒—𐑕𐑰-𐑒𐑴𐑤, 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑘𐑹 𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑗𐑸𐑒𐑴𐑤. 𐑢𐑧𐑤, 𐑢𐑧𐑤; 𐑲 𐑣𐑻𐑛 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑥𐑳𐑑𐑼, '·𐑣𐑽 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑔𐑮𐑳𐑕𐑑𐑕 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑒𐑸𐑛𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑝 𐑥𐑲𐑯; 𐑕𐑢𐑺𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑲 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑐𐑤𐑱 𐑞𐑧𐑥, 𐑯 𐑯𐑴 𐑳𐑞𐑼𐑟.' 𐑯 𐑛𐑨𐑥 𐑥𐑰, ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞𐑬 𐑨𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑮𐑲𐑑; 𐑤𐑦𐑝 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑜𐑱𐑥, 𐑯 𐑛𐑲 𐑦𐑯 𐑦𐑑!”

·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 119. 𐑞 ·𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑤𐑟.

𐑢𐑹𐑥𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑒𐑤𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑯𐑻𐑕 𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑵𐑩𐑤𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑓𐑨𐑙𐑟: 𐑞 𐑑𐑲𐑜𐑼 𐑝 ·𐑚𐑧𐑯𐑜𐑨𐑤 𐑒𐑮𐑬𐑗𐑩𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑐𐑲𐑕𐑑 𐑜𐑮𐑴𐑝𐑟 𐑝 𐑕𐑰𐑕𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑝𐑻𐑡𐑼. 𐑕𐑒𐑲𐑟 𐑞 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑓𐑳𐑤𐑡𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑚𐑭𐑕𐑒𐑩𐑑 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑛𐑤𐑾𐑕𐑑 𐑔𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑟: 𐑜𐑹𐑡𐑩𐑕 ·𐑒𐑿𐑚𐑩 𐑯𐑴𐑟 𐑑𐑹𐑯𐑱𐑛𐑴𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑕𐑢𐑧𐑐𐑑 𐑑𐑱𐑥 𐑯𐑹𐑞𐑼𐑯 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟. 𐑕𐑴, 𐑑𐑵, 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑤𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑑 ·𐑡𐑨𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑰𐑟 𐑕𐑰𐑟 𐑞 𐑥𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑯𐑼 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑟 𐑞 𐑛𐑲𐑼𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑝 𐑷𐑤 𐑕𐑑𐑹𐑥𐑟, 𐑞 ·𐑑𐑲𐑓𐑵𐑯. 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑚𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑬𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑒𐑤𐑬𐑛𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑕𐑒𐑲, 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑤𐑴𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑪𐑥 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑩 𐑛𐑱𐑟𐑛 𐑯 𐑕𐑤𐑰𐑐𐑦 𐑑𐑬𐑯.

𐑑𐑩𐑢𐑹𐑛𐑟 𐑰𐑝𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑛𐑱, 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑑𐑹𐑯 𐑝 𐑣𐑻 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑝𐑩𐑕, 𐑯 𐑚𐑺-𐑐𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑤𐑧𐑓𐑑 𐑑 𐑓𐑲𐑑 𐑩 ·𐑑𐑲𐑓𐑵𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑒 𐑣𐑻 𐑛𐑦𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑩𐑣𐑧𐑛. 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑛𐑸𐑒𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑒𐑱𐑥 𐑪𐑯, 𐑕𐑒𐑲 𐑯 𐑕𐑰 𐑮𐑹𐑛 𐑯 𐑕𐑐𐑤𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑔𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼, 𐑯 𐑚𐑤𐑱𐑟𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑤𐑲𐑑𐑯𐑦𐑙, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑖𐑴𐑛 𐑞 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑱𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑕 𐑓𐑤𐑳𐑑𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑽 𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑮𐑨𐑜𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑞 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑓𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑦 𐑝 𐑞 𐑑𐑧𐑥𐑐𐑦𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑤𐑧𐑓𐑑 𐑓 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑕𐑐𐑹𐑑.

𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑲 𐑩 𐑖𐑮𐑬𐑛, ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑒𐑢𐑹𐑑𐑼-𐑛𐑧𐑒; 𐑨𐑑 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑓𐑤𐑨𐑖 𐑝 𐑞 𐑤𐑲𐑑𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑜𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑓𐑑, 𐑑 𐑕𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑩𐑛𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑛𐑦𐑟𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑼 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑷𐑤𐑩𐑯 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑥𐑐𐑼 𐑞𐑺; 𐑢𐑲𐑤 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚 𐑯 ·𐑓𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑒 𐑢𐑻 𐑛𐑦𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑣𐑲𐑼 𐑣𐑶𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑯 𐑓𐑻𐑥𐑼 𐑤𐑨𐑖𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑺 𐑐𐑱𐑯𐑟 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑯𐑷𐑑. 𐑞𐑴 𐑤𐑦𐑓𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑑 𐑞 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑑𐑪𐑐 𐑝 𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑟, 𐑞 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑢𐑼𐑛 𐑒𐑢𐑹𐑑𐑼 𐑚𐑴𐑑 (·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚'𐑟) 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑱𐑐. 𐑩 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑮𐑴𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑰, 𐑛𐑨𐑖𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑲 𐑳𐑐 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑞 𐑮𐑰𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑖𐑦𐑐'𐑕 𐑣𐑲 𐑑𐑰𐑑𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑲𐑛, 𐑕𐑑𐑴𐑝 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑'𐑕 𐑚𐑪𐑑𐑩𐑥 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑻𐑯, 𐑯 𐑤𐑧𐑓𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯, 𐑷𐑤 𐑛𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑕𐑦𐑝.

“𐑚𐑨𐑛 𐑢𐑻𐑒, 𐑚𐑨𐑛 𐑢𐑻𐑒! ·𐑥𐑼 ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒,” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚, 𐑮𐑦𐑜𐑸𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑮𐑧𐑒, “𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑰 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑢𐑱. 𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚, 𐑓 𐑢𐑳𐑯, 𐑒𐑭𐑯𐑑 𐑓𐑲𐑑 𐑦𐑑. 𐑿 𐑕𐑰, ·𐑥𐑼 ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒, 𐑩 𐑢𐑱𐑝 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑦𐑑 𐑤𐑰𐑐𐑕, 𐑷𐑤 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑞 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛 𐑦𐑑 𐑮𐑳𐑯𐑟, 𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑟 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑙! 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑓 𐑥𐑰, 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑑 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑓 𐑑 𐑥𐑰𐑑 𐑦𐑑, 𐑦𐑟 𐑡𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑩𐑒𐑮𐑪𐑕 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑒 𐑣𐑽. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑥𐑲𐑯𐑛; 𐑦𐑑'𐑕 𐑷𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑓𐑳𐑯: 𐑕𐑴 𐑞 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑕𐑪𐑙 𐑕𐑧𐑟;”—(𐑕𐑦𐑙𐑟.)

“𐑩𐑝𐑭𐑕𐑑 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚,” 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒, “𐑤𐑧𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑑𐑲𐑓𐑵𐑯 𐑕𐑦𐑙, 𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑒 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑸𐑐 𐑣𐑽 𐑦𐑯 𐑬𐑼 𐑮𐑦𐑜𐑦𐑙; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑓 𐑞𐑬 𐑸𐑑 𐑩 𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑝 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑞𐑬 𐑢𐑦𐑤𐑑 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑞𐑲 𐑐𐑰𐑕.”

“𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑲 𐑨𐑥 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑩 𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑝 𐑥𐑨𐑯; 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑲 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩 𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑝 𐑥𐑨𐑯; 𐑲 𐑨𐑥 𐑩 𐑒𐑬𐑼𐑛; 𐑯 𐑲 𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑒𐑰𐑐 𐑳𐑐 𐑥𐑲 𐑕𐑐𐑦𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑕. 𐑯 𐑲 𐑑𐑧𐑤 𐑿 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟, ·𐑥𐑼 ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒, 𐑞𐑺'𐑟 𐑯𐑴 𐑢𐑱 𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑪𐑐 𐑥𐑲 𐑕𐑦𐑙𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑑 𐑒𐑳𐑑 𐑥𐑲 𐑔𐑮𐑴𐑑. 𐑯 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑'𐑕 𐑛𐑳𐑯, 𐑑𐑧𐑯 𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑲 𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑘𐑰 𐑞 𐑛𐑪𐑒𐑕𐑪𐑤𐑩𐑡𐑦 𐑓 𐑩 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛-𐑳𐑐.”

“𐑥𐑨𐑛𐑥𐑩𐑯! 𐑤𐑫𐑒 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑥𐑲 𐑲𐑟 𐑦𐑓 𐑞𐑬 𐑣𐑨𐑕𐑑 𐑯𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑞𐑲𐑯 𐑴𐑯.”

“𐑢𐑪𐑑! 𐑣𐑬 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑿 𐑕𐑰 𐑚𐑧𐑑𐑼 𐑝 𐑩 𐑛𐑸𐑒 𐑯𐑲𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑧𐑯𐑦𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦 𐑧𐑤𐑕, 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑥𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑣𐑬 𐑓𐑵𐑤𐑦𐑖?”

“𐑣𐑽!” 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒, 𐑕𐑰𐑟𐑦𐑙 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑖𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑼, 𐑯 𐑐𐑶𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑑𐑩𐑢𐑹𐑛𐑟 𐑞 𐑢𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑚𐑬, “𐑥𐑸𐑒𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑞𐑬 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑜𐑱𐑤 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑟 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑰𐑕𐑑𐑢𐑼𐑛, 𐑞 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑒𐑹𐑕 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑦𐑟 𐑑 𐑮𐑳𐑯 𐑓 ·𐑥𐑪𐑚𐑦 ·𐑛𐑦𐑒? 𐑞 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑒𐑹𐑕 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑢𐑳𐑙 𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑛𐑱 𐑯𐑵𐑯? 𐑯𐑬 𐑥𐑸𐑒 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑴𐑑 𐑞𐑺; 𐑢𐑺 𐑦𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑴𐑝? 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑻𐑯-𐑖𐑰𐑑𐑕, 𐑥𐑨𐑯; 𐑢𐑺 𐑣𐑰 𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛—𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛-𐑐𐑶𐑯𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑴𐑝, 𐑥𐑨𐑯! 𐑯𐑬 𐑡𐑳𐑥𐑐 𐑴𐑝𐑼𐑚𐑹𐑛, 𐑯 𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑢𐑱, 𐑦𐑓 𐑞𐑬 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑!

“𐑲 𐑛𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑣𐑭𐑓 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑘𐑰: 𐑢𐑪𐑑'𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛?”

“𐑘𐑧𐑕, 𐑘𐑧𐑕, 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑞 ·𐑒𐑱𐑐 𐑝 𐑜𐑫𐑛 ·𐑣𐑴𐑐 𐑦𐑟 𐑞 𐑖𐑹𐑑𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑢𐑱 𐑑 ·𐑯𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑑,” 𐑕𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑤𐑩𐑒𐑢𐑲𐑟𐑛 ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒 𐑕𐑳𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑦, 𐑣𐑰𐑛𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑝 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚'𐑟 𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑕𐑗𐑩𐑯. “𐑞 𐑜𐑱𐑤 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑯𐑬 𐑣𐑨𐑥𐑼𐑟 𐑨𐑑 𐑳𐑕 𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑝 𐑳𐑕, 𐑢𐑰 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑑𐑻𐑯 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑩 𐑓𐑺 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑛𐑮𐑲𐑝 𐑳𐑕 𐑑𐑩𐑢𐑹𐑛𐑟 𐑣𐑴𐑥. 𐑘𐑪𐑯𐑛𐑼, 𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑢𐑼𐑛, 𐑷𐑤 𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑒𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑛𐑵𐑥; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑑 𐑤𐑰𐑢𐑼𐑛, 𐑣𐑴𐑥𐑢𐑼𐑛—𐑲 𐑕𐑰 𐑦𐑑 𐑤𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑳𐑐 𐑞𐑺; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑤𐑲𐑑𐑯𐑦𐑙.”

𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑴𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑝 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑛𐑸𐑒𐑯𐑩𐑕, 𐑓𐑪𐑤𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑓𐑤𐑨𐑖𐑩𐑟, 𐑩 𐑝𐑶𐑕 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑣𐑻𐑛 𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑲𐑛; 𐑯 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑩 𐑝𐑪𐑤𐑦 𐑝 𐑔𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑐𐑰𐑤𐑟 𐑮𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑴𐑝𐑼𐑣𐑧𐑛.

“𐑣𐑵'𐑟 𐑞𐑺?”

“𐑴𐑤𐑛 ·𐑔𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼!” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚, 𐑜𐑮𐑴𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑱 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑞 𐑚𐑫𐑤𐑢𐑼𐑒𐑕 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑦𐑝𐑩𐑑-𐑣𐑴𐑤; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑓𐑲𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑭𐑔 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑯 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑚𐑲 𐑧𐑤𐑚𐑴𐑛 𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑝 𐑓𐑲𐑼.

𐑯𐑬, 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑤𐑲𐑑𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑮𐑪𐑛 𐑑 𐑩 𐑕𐑐𐑲𐑼 𐑪𐑯 𐑖𐑹 𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑑 𐑒𐑨𐑮𐑦 𐑪𐑓 𐑞 𐑐𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑓𐑤𐑵𐑦𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑕𐑶𐑤; 𐑕𐑴 𐑞 𐑒𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑛 𐑮𐑪𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑰 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑕 𐑒𐑨𐑮𐑦 𐑑 𐑰𐑗 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑, 𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑑 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑛𐑳𐑒𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑛𐑳𐑒𐑑𐑼 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑑 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑼𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑛𐑧𐑐𐑔, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑥𐑱 𐑩𐑝𐑶𐑛 𐑷𐑤 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑨𐑒𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑣𐑳𐑤; 𐑯 𐑨𐑟 𐑥𐑹𐑴𐑝𐑼, 𐑦𐑓 𐑒𐑧𐑐𐑑 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑑𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑺, 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑚𐑰 𐑤𐑲𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑑 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑕, 𐑚𐑦𐑕𐑲𐑛𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑓𐑽𐑦𐑙 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑩 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑝 𐑞 𐑮𐑦𐑜𐑦𐑙, 𐑯 𐑥𐑹 𐑹 𐑤𐑧𐑕 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑰𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑝𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑤'𐑟 𐑢𐑱 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼; 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑪𐑟 𐑝 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑦𐑕, 𐑞 𐑤𐑴𐑼 𐑐𐑸𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑩 𐑖𐑦𐑐'𐑕 𐑤𐑲𐑑𐑯𐑦𐑙-𐑮𐑪𐑛𐑟 𐑸 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑷𐑤𐑢𐑱𐑟 𐑴𐑝𐑼𐑚𐑹𐑛; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑸 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑕𐑤𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑤𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑕, 𐑕𐑴 𐑨𐑟 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑞 𐑥𐑹 𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑦 𐑣𐑷𐑤𐑛 𐑳𐑐 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑗𐑱𐑯𐑟 𐑬𐑑𐑕𐑲𐑛, 𐑹 𐑔𐑮𐑴𐑯 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑕𐑰, 𐑨𐑟 𐑩𐑒𐑱𐑠𐑩𐑯 𐑥𐑱 𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑢𐑲𐑼.

“𐑞 𐑮𐑪𐑛𐑟! 𐑞 𐑮𐑪𐑛𐑟!” 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒 𐑑 𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑵, 𐑕𐑳𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑨𐑛𐑥𐑪𐑯𐑦𐑖𐑑 𐑑 𐑝𐑦𐑡𐑦𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑝𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑛 𐑤𐑲𐑑𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑡𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑛𐑸𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑤𐑨𐑥𐑚𐑴𐑟, 𐑑 𐑤𐑲𐑑 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑴𐑕𐑑. “𐑸 𐑞𐑱 𐑴𐑝𐑼𐑚𐑹𐑛? 𐑛𐑮𐑪𐑐 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑴𐑝𐑼, 𐑓𐑹 𐑯 𐑭𐑓𐑑. 𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑒!”

“𐑩𐑝𐑭𐑕𐑑!” 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚; “𐑤𐑧𐑑'𐑕 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑓𐑺 𐑐𐑤𐑱 𐑣𐑽, 𐑞𐑴 𐑢𐑰 𐑚𐑰 𐑞 𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑼 𐑕𐑲𐑛. 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑲'𐑤 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑚𐑿𐑑 𐑑 𐑮𐑱𐑟 𐑮𐑪𐑛𐑟 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑙𐑦𐑥𐑩𐑤𐑱𐑟 𐑯 ·𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑰𐑟, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛 𐑥𐑱 𐑚𐑰 𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑛; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑬𐑑 𐑪𐑯 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑡𐑩𐑟! 𐑤𐑧𐑑 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑚𐑰, 𐑕𐑻.”

“𐑤𐑫𐑒 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑓𐑑!” 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒. “𐑞 𐑒𐑹𐑐𐑩𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕! 𐑞 𐑒𐑹𐑐𐑩𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕!”

𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑘𐑸𐑛-𐑸𐑥𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑑𐑦𐑐𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑐𐑨𐑤𐑦𐑛 𐑓𐑲𐑼; 𐑯 𐑑𐑳𐑗𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑰𐑗 𐑑𐑮𐑲-𐑐𐑶𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑤𐑲𐑑𐑯𐑦𐑙-𐑮𐑪𐑛-𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑑𐑱𐑐𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑓𐑤𐑱𐑥𐑟, 𐑰𐑗 𐑝 𐑞 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑑𐑷𐑤 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑕 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑤𐑓𐑼𐑩𐑕 𐑺, 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑡𐑲𐑜𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑢𐑨𐑒𐑕 𐑑𐑱𐑐𐑼𐑟 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑩𐑯 𐑷𐑤𐑑𐑼.

“𐑚𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑! 𐑤𐑧𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑜𐑴!” 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚 𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑, 𐑨𐑟 𐑩 𐑕𐑢𐑭𐑖𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑰 𐑣𐑰𐑝𐑛 𐑳𐑐 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑴𐑯 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑒𐑮𐑭𐑓𐑑, 𐑕𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑜𐑳𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑡𐑨𐑥𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛, 𐑨𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑐𐑭𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑤𐑨𐑖𐑦𐑙. “𐑚𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑑!”—𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑕𐑤𐑦𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑨𐑒𐑢𐑼𐑛 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑒, 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑳𐑐𐑤𐑦𐑓𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑲𐑟 𐑒𐑷𐑑 𐑞 𐑓𐑤𐑱𐑥𐑟; 𐑯 𐑦𐑥𐑰𐑛𐑾𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑖𐑦𐑓𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑑𐑴𐑯 𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛—“𐑞 𐑒𐑹𐑐𐑩𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑥𐑻𐑕𐑦 𐑪𐑯 𐑳𐑕 𐑷𐑤!”

𐑑 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑼𐑟, 𐑴𐑞𐑟 𐑸 𐑣𐑬𐑕𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑢𐑻𐑛𐑟; 𐑞𐑱 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑕𐑢𐑺 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑑𐑮𐑭𐑯𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑒𐑭𐑥, 𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑑𐑰𐑔 𐑝 𐑞 𐑑𐑧𐑥𐑐𐑦𐑕𐑑; 𐑞𐑱 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑱𐑑 𐑒𐑻𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑑𐑪𐑐𐑕𐑱𐑤-𐑘𐑸𐑛-𐑸𐑥𐑟, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑞𐑱 𐑑𐑰𐑑𐑼 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑑 𐑩 𐑕𐑰𐑞𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑰; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑥𐑲 𐑝𐑶𐑦𐑡𐑦𐑙𐑟, 𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑛𐑩𐑥 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑲 𐑣𐑻𐑛 𐑩 𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑴𐑔 𐑢𐑧𐑯 ·𐑜𐑪𐑛'𐑟 𐑚𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑼 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑤𐑱𐑛 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐; 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 “𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑧, ·𐑥𐑰𐑯𐑦, ·𐑑𐑧𐑒𐑩𐑤 ·𐑿𐑓𐑸𐑟𐑦𐑯” 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑢𐑴𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑖𐑮𐑬𐑛𐑟 𐑯 𐑞 𐑒𐑹𐑛𐑦𐑡.

𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑐𐑨𐑤𐑦𐑛𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑚𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑓𐑑, 𐑓𐑿 𐑢𐑻𐑛𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑣𐑻𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑗𐑭𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑒𐑮𐑵; 𐑣𐑵 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑔𐑦𐑒 𐑒𐑤𐑳𐑕𐑑𐑼 𐑕𐑑𐑫𐑛 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑴𐑒𐑕𐑩𐑤, 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑺 𐑲𐑟 𐑜𐑤𐑰𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑐𐑱𐑤 𐑓𐑪𐑕𐑓𐑼𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑕, 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑓𐑸 𐑩𐑢𐑱 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑟. 𐑮𐑦𐑤𐑰𐑝𐑛 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑞 𐑜𐑴𐑕𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑤𐑲𐑑, 𐑞 𐑡𐑲𐑜𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑡𐑧𐑑 𐑯𐑰𐑜𐑮𐑴, ·𐑛𐑨𐑜𐑵, 𐑤𐑵𐑥𐑛 𐑳𐑐 𐑑 𐑔𐑮𐑲𐑕 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑮𐑾𐑤 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑗𐑼, 𐑯 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑞 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑒 𐑒𐑤𐑬𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑞 𐑔𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑒𐑳𐑥. 𐑞 𐑐𐑸𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑥𐑬𐑔 𐑝 ·𐑑𐑨𐑖𐑑𐑱𐑜𐑴 𐑮𐑦𐑝𐑰𐑤𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑖𐑸𐑒-𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑑𐑰𐑔, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑤𐑦 𐑜𐑤𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑓 𐑞𐑱 𐑑𐑵 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑑𐑦𐑐𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑒𐑹𐑐𐑩𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕; 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑤𐑦𐑑 𐑳𐑐 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑰𐑑𐑼𐑯𐑨𐑗𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑤𐑲𐑑, ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜'𐑟 𐑑𐑩𐑑𐑵𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑻𐑯𐑛 𐑤𐑲𐑒 ·𐑕𐑩𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑒 𐑚𐑤𐑵 𐑓𐑤𐑱𐑥𐑟 𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦.

𐑞 𐑑𐑨𐑚𐑤𐑴 𐑷𐑤 𐑢𐑱𐑯𐑛 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑐𐑨𐑤𐑦𐑛𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑓𐑑; 𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑕 𐑥𐑹 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛 𐑯 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑕𐑴𐑤 𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑻 𐑛𐑧𐑒𐑕 𐑢𐑻 𐑮𐑨𐑐𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑐𐑷𐑤. 𐑩 𐑥𐑴𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑹 𐑑𐑵 𐑐𐑭𐑕𐑑, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒, 𐑜𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑹𐑢𐑼𐑛, 𐑐𐑫𐑖𐑑 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑢𐑳𐑯. 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚. “𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑞𐑬 𐑯𐑬, 𐑥𐑨𐑯; 𐑲 𐑣𐑻𐑛 𐑞𐑲 𐑒𐑮𐑲; 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑪𐑙.”

“𐑯𐑴, 𐑯𐑴, 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑑; 𐑲 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑞 𐑒𐑹𐑐𐑩𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑥𐑻𐑕𐑦 𐑪𐑯 𐑳𐑕 𐑷𐑤; 𐑯 𐑲 𐑣𐑴𐑐 𐑞𐑱 𐑢𐑦𐑤, 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑛𐑵 𐑞𐑱 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑥𐑻𐑕𐑦 𐑪𐑯 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑓𐑱𐑕𐑩𐑟?—𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑞𐑱 𐑯𐑴 𐑚𐑬𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑓 𐑩 𐑤𐑭𐑓? 𐑯 𐑤𐑫𐑒 𐑘𐑰, ·𐑥𐑼 ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒—𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑑'𐑕 𐑑𐑵 𐑛𐑸𐑒 𐑑 𐑤𐑫𐑒. 𐑣𐑽 𐑥𐑰, 𐑞𐑧𐑯: 𐑲 𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑-𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑓𐑤𐑱𐑥 𐑢𐑰 𐑕𐑷 𐑓 𐑩 𐑕𐑲𐑯 𐑝 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑤𐑳𐑒; 𐑓 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑕 𐑸 𐑮𐑵𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑜𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑗𐑪𐑒 𐑩' 𐑚𐑤𐑪𐑒 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥-𐑶𐑤, 𐑛'𐑘𐑰 𐑕𐑰; 𐑯 𐑕𐑴, 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑢𐑻𐑒 𐑳𐑐 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑕, 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑕𐑨𐑐 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑑𐑮𐑰. 𐑘𐑧𐑕, 𐑬𐑼 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑕 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑨𐑟 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥𐑩𐑕𐑧𐑑𐑦 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑤𐑟—𐑞𐑨𐑑'𐑕 𐑞 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑥𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑰 𐑕𐑷.”

𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑴𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑 ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒 𐑒𐑷𐑑 𐑕𐑲𐑑 𐑝 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚'𐑟 𐑓𐑱𐑕 𐑕𐑤𐑴𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑦𐑜𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑜𐑤𐑦𐑥𐑼 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑕𐑲𐑑. 𐑜𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑳𐑐𐑢𐑼𐑛𐑟, 𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛: “𐑕𐑰! 𐑕𐑰!” 𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑕 𐑥𐑹 𐑞 𐑣𐑲 𐑑𐑱𐑐𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑤𐑱𐑥𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑚𐑦𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑮𐑦𐑛𐑳𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑕𐑵𐑐𐑼𐑯𐑨𐑗𐑼𐑩𐑤𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑐𐑨𐑤𐑼.

“𐑞 𐑒𐑹𐑐𐑩𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑥𐑻𐑕𐑦 𐑪𐑯 𐑳𐑕 𐑷𐑤,” 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚, 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯.

𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑚𐑱𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑥𐑱𐑯𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑, 𐑓𐑫𐑤 𐑚𐑦𐑯𐑰𐑔 𐑞 𐑛𐑳𐑚𐑤𐑵𐑯 𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑤𐑱𐑥, 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑸𐑟𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑰𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚'𐑟 𐑓𐑮𐑳𐑯𐑑, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑚𐑬𐑛 𐑩𐑢𐑱 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑣𐑦𐑥; 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑯𐑽 𐑚𐑲, 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑸𐑗𐑑 𐑯 𐑴𐑝𐑼𐑣𐑨𐑙𐑦𐑙 𐑮𐑦𐑜𐑦𐑙, 𐑢𐑺 𐑞𐑱 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑡𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑜𐑱𐑡𐑛 𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑕𐑐𐑸, 𐑩 𐑯𐑳𐑥𐑚𐑼 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑧𐑯, 𐑼𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑜𐑤𐑺, 𐑯𐑬 𐑒𐑴𐑣𐑽𐑛 𐑑𐑩𐑜𐑧𐑞𐑼, 𐑯 𐑣𐑳𐑙 𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑡𐑩𐑤𐑩𐑕, 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑝 𐑯𐑳𐑥𐑛 𐑢𐑪𐑕𐑐𐑕 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑩 𐑛𐑮𐑵𐑐𐑦𐑙, 𐑹𐑗𐑼𐑛 𐑑𐑢𐑦𐑜. 𐑦𐑯 𐑝𐑺𐑾𐑕 𐑦𐑯𐑗𐑭𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑨𐑑𐑦𐑑𐑿𐑛𐑟, 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙, 𐑹 𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑐𐑦𐑙, 𐑹 𐑮𐑳𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑒𐑧𐑤𐑩𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑦𐑯 ·𐑣𐑼𐑒𐑘𐑩𐑤𐑱𐑯𐑾𐑥, 𐑳𐑞𐑼𐑟 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑱𐑯𐑛 𐑮𐑵𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑑 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑒; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑺 𐑲𐑟 𐑳𐑐𐑒𐑭𐑕𐑑.

“𐑲, 𐑲, 𐑥𐑧𐑯!” 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚. “𐑤𐑫𐑒 𐑳𐑐 𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑑; 𐑥𐑸𐑒 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑧𐑤; 𐑞 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑓𐑤𐑱𐑥 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑤𐑲𐑑𐑕 𐑞 𐑢𐑱 𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑢𐑲𐑑 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤! 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑥𐑰 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑥𐑱𐑯𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑤𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑕 𐑞𐑺; 𐑲 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑓𐑱𐑯 𐑓𐑰𐑤 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑐𐑳𐑤𐑕, 𐑯 𐑤𐑧𐑑 𐑥𐑲𐑯 𐑚𐑰𐑑 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑑; 𐑚𐑤𐑳𐑛 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑓𐑲𐑼! 𐑕𐑴.”

𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑙—𐑞 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑤𐑦𐑙𐑒 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑛 𐑓𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑤𐑧𐑓𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛, 𐑣𐑰 𐑐𐑫𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑫𐑑 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑸𐑟𐑰; 𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑓𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑑 𐑳𐑐𐑢𐑼𐑛 𐑲, 𐑯 𐑣𐑲-𐑓𐑤𐑳𐑙 𐑮𐑲𐑑 𐑸𐑥, 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑑𐑫𐑛 𐑦𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑞 𐑤𐑪𐑓𐑑𐑦 𐑑𐑮𐑲-𐑐𐑶𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑝 𐑓𐑤𐑱𐑥𐑟.

“𐑴! 𐑞𐑬 𐑒𐑤𐑽 𐑕𐑐𐑦𐑮𐑦𐑑 𐑝 𐑒𐑤𐑽 𐑓𐑲𐑼, 𐑣𐑵𐑥 𐑪𐑯 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑕𐑰𐑟 𐑲 𐑨𐑟 ·𐑐𐑻𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑕 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑢𐑻𐑖𐑦𐑐, 𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑨𐑒𐑮𐑩𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑨𐑒𐑑 𐑕𐑴 𐑚𐑻𐑯𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑞𐑰, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑬𐑼 𐑲 𐑚𐑺 𐑞 𐑕𐑒𐑸; 𐑲 𐑯𐑬 𐑯𐑴 𐑞𐑰, 𐑞𐑬 𐑒𐑤𐑽 𐑕𐑐𐑦𐑮𐑦𐑑, 𐑯 𐑲 𐑯𐑬 𐑯𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑲 𐑮𐑲𐑑 𐑢𐑻𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑦𐑟 𐑛𐑦𐑓𐑲𐑩𐑯𐑕. 𐑑 𐑯𐑲𐑞𐑼 𐑤𐑳𐑝 𐑯𐑹 𐑮𐑧𐑝𐑼𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑢𐑦𐑤𐑑 𐑞𐑬 𐑚𐑰 𐑒𐑲𐑯𐑛; 𐑯 𐑰'𐑩𐑯 𐑓 𐑣𐑱𐑑 𐑞𐑬 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑒𐑦𐑤; 𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑸 𐑒𐑦𐑤𐑛. 𐑯𐑴 𐑓𐑽𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑓𐑵𐑤 𐑯𐑬 𐑓𐑮𐑳𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑞𐑰. 𐑲 𐑴𐑯 𐑞𐑲 𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑗𐑤𐑩𐑕, 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑐𐑬𐑼; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑑 𐑞 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑜𐑭𐑕𐑐 𐑝 𐑥𐑲 𐑻𐑔𐑒𐑢𐑱𐑒 𐑤𐑲𐑓 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑿𐑑 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑳𐑯𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑤, 𐑳𐑯𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑜𐑮𐑩𐑤 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑦 𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑰. 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑥𐑦𐑛𐑕𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑐𐑼𐑕𐑪𐑯𐑦𐑓𐑲𐑛 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑻𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑤, 𐑩 𐑐𐑻𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑨𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑣𐑽. 𐑞𐑴 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑩 𐑐𐑶𐑯𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑚𐑧𐑕𐑑; 𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑟𐑴'𐑼 𐑲 𐑒𐑱𐑥; 𐑢𐑺𐑕𐑴𐑺 𐑲 𐑜𐑴; 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑲 𐑻𐑔𐑤𐑦 𐑤𐑲𐑝, 𐑞 𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑻𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑨𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑤𐑦𐑝𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑰, 𐑯 𐑓𐑰𐑤𐑟 𐑣𐑻 𐑮𐑶𐑩𐑤 𐑮𐑲𐑑𐑕. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑹 𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑱𐑯, 𐑯 𐑣𐑱𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑴. 𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑲 𐑤𐑴𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑓𐑹𐑥 𐑝 𐑤𐑳𐑝, 𐑯 𐑲 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑯𐑰𐑤 𐑯 𐑒𐑦𐑕 𐑞𐑰; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑲 𐑣𐑲𐑩𐑕𐑑, 𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑨𐑟 𐑥𐑽 𐑕𐑵𐑐𐑻𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑐𐑬𐑼; 𐑯 𐑞𐑴 𐑞𐑬 𐑤𐑷𐑯𐑗𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑯𐑱𐑝𐑦𐑟 𐑝 𐑓𐑫𐑤-𐑓𐑮𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛𐑟, 𐑞𐑺'𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑽 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑱𐑯𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑓𐑼𐑩𐑯𐑑. 𐑴, 𐑞𐑬 𐑒𐑤𐑽 𐑕𐑐𐑦𐑮𐑦𐑑, 𐑝 𐑞𐑲 𐑓𐑲𐑼 𐑞𐑬 𐑥𐑱𐑛𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑥𐑰, 𐑯 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑑𐑮𐑵 𐑗𐑲𐑤𐑛 𐑝 𐑓𐑲𐑼, 𐑲 𐑚𐑮𐑰𐑞 𐑦𐑑 𐑚𐑨𐑒 𐑑 𐑞𐑰.”

[𐑕𐑳𐑛𐑩𐑯, 𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑰𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑓𐑤𐑨𐑖𐑩𐑟 𐑝 𐑤𐑲𐑑𐑯𐑦𐑙; 𐑞 𐑯𐑲𐑯 𐑓𐑤𐑱𐑥𐑟 𐑤𐑰𐑐 𐑤𐑧𐑙𐑔𐑢𐑲𐑟 𐑑 𐑔𐑮𐑲𐑕 𐑞𐑺 𐑐𐑮𐑰𐑝𐑾𐑕 𐑣𐑲𐑑; ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑑, 𐑒𐑤𐑴𐑟𐑩𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑲𐑟, 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑮𐑲𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑸𐑛 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑥.]

“𐑲 𐑴𐑯 𐑞𐑲 𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑗𐑤𐑩𐑕, 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑐𐑬𐑼; 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑲 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑴? 𐑯𐑹 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑮𐑳𐑙 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑥𐑰; 𐑯𐑹 𐑛𐑵 𐑲 𐑯𐑬 𐑛𐑮𐑪𐑐 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑤𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑕. 𐑞𐑬 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑤𐑲𐑯𐑛; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑲 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑜𐑮𐑴𐑐. 𐑞𐑬 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑿𐑥; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑲 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑚𐑰 𐑨𐑖𐑩𐑟. 𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑞 𐑣𐑪𐑥𐑦𐑡 𐑝 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑐𐑫𐑼 𐑲𐑟, 𐑯 𐑖𐑳𐑑𐑼-𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟. 𐑲 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑦𐑑. 𐑞 𐑤𐑲𐑑𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑤𐑨𐑖𐑩𐑟 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑥𐑲 𐑕𐑒𐑳𐑤; 𐑥𐑲𐑯 𐑲-𐑚𐑷𐑤𐑟 𐑱𐑒 𐑯 𐑱𐑒; 𐑥𐑲 𐑣𐑴𐑤 𐑚𐑰𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑯 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑟 𐑨𐑟 𐑚𐑦𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑩𐑛, 𐑯 𐑮𐑴𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑪𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑜𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛. 𐑴, 𐑴! 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑚𐑤𐑲𐑯𐑛𐑓𐑴𐑤𐑛, 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑲 𐑑𐑷𐑒 𐑑 𐑞𐑰. 𐑤𐑲𐑑 𐑞𐑴 𐑞𐑬 𐑚𐑰, 𐑞𐑬 𐑤𐑰𐑐𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑛𐑸𐑒𐑯𐑩𐑕; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑲 𐑨𐑥 𐑛𐑸𐑒𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑤𐑰𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑤𐑲𐑑, 𐑤𐑰𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑞𐑰! 𐑞 𐑡𐑨𐑝𐑤𐑦𐑯𐑟 𐑕𐑰𐑕; 𐑴𐑐𐑩𐑯 𐑲𐑟; 𐑕𐑰, 𐑹 𐑯𐑪𐑑? 𐑞𐑺 𐑚𐑻𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑤𐑱𐑥𐑟! 𐑴, 𐑞𐑬 𐑥𐑨𐑜𐑯𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑥𐑩𐑕! 𐑯𐑬 𐑲 𐑛𐑵 𐑜𐑤𐑹𐑦 𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑲 𐑡𐑰𐑯𐑦𐑨𐑤𐑩𐑡𐑦. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞𐑬 𐑸𐑑 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑥𐑲 𐑓𐑲𐑼𐑦 𐑓𐑭𐑞𐑼; 𐑥𐑲 𐑕𐑢𐑰𐑑 𐑥𐑳𐑞𐑼, 𐑲 𐑯𐑴 𐑯𐑪𐑑. 𐑴, 𐑒𐑮𐑵𐑩𐑤! 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑕𐑑 𐑞𐑬 𐑛𐑳𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑻? 𐑞𐑺 𐑤𐑲𐑟 𐑥𐑲 𐑐𐑳𐑟𐑩𐑤; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞𐑲𐑯 𐑦𐑟 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑𐑼. 𐑞𐑬 𐑯𐑴𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑣𐑬 𐑒𐑱𐑥 𐑘𐑰, 𐑣𐑧𐑯𐑕 𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑞𐑲𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑳𐑯𐑚𐑦𐑜𐑪𐑑𐑩𐑯; 𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑯𐑴𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑞𐑲 𐑚𐑦𐑜𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑙, 𐑣𐑧𐑯𐑕 𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑞𐑲𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑳𐑯𐑚𐑦𐑜𐑳𐑯. 𐑲 𐑯𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑝 𐑥𐑰, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑞𐑬 𐑯𐑴𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑝 𐑞𐑲𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓, 𐑴, 𐑞𐑬 𐑪𐑥𐑯𐑦𐑐𐑩𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑. 𐑞𐑺 𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑳𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑓𐑿𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑦𐑘𐑪𐑯𐑛 𐑞𐑰, 𐑞𐑬 𐑒𐑤𐑽 𐑕𐑐𐑦𐑮𐑦𐑑, 𐑑 𐑣𐑵𐑥 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑲 𐑦𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑑𐑲𐑥, 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑲 𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑱𐑑𐑦𐑝𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑥𐑦𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤. 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑞𐑰, 𐑞𐑲 𐑓𐑤𐑱𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓, 𐑥𐑲 𐑕𐑒𐑹𐑗𐑑 𐑲𐑟 𐑛𐑵 𐑛𐑦𐑥𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑰 𐑦𐑑. 𐑴, 𐑞𐑬 𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑲𐑼, 𐑞𐑬 𐑣𐑻𐑥𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑥𐑩𐑥𐑹𐑾𐑤, 𐑞𐑬 𐑑𐑵 𐑣𐑨𐑕𐑑 𐑞𐑲 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑿𐑯𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑮𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑤, 𐑞𐑲 𐑳𐑯𐑐𐑸𐑑𐑦𐑕𐑦𐑐𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑓. 𐑣𐑽 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑷𐑑𐑦 𐑨𐑜𐑩𐑯𐑦, 𐑲 𐑮𐑰𐑛 𐑥𐑲 𐑕𐑲𐑼. 𐑤𐑰𐑐! 𐑤𐑰𐑐 𐑳𐑐, 𐑯 𐑤𐑦𐑒 𐑞 𐑕𐑒𐑲! 𐑲 𐑤𐑰𐑐 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞𐑰; 𐑲 𐑚𐑻𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞𐑰; 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑓𐑱𐑯 𐑚𐑰 𐑢𐑧𐑤𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞𐑰; 𐑛𐑦𐑓𐑲𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑲 𐑢𐑻𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑞𐑰!”

“𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑! 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑!” 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒, “𐑤𐑫𐑒 𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑲 𐑚𐑴𐑑, 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑥𐑨𐑯!”

𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚'𐑟 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯, 𐑞 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑓𐑹𐑡𐑛 𐑨𐑑 ·𐑐𐑻𐑔'𐑕 𐑓𐑲𐑼, 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑱𐑯𐑛 𐑓𐑻𐑥𐑤𐑦 𐑤𐑨𐑖𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑩𐑕 𐑒𐑮𐑪𐑗, 𐑕𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑡𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑦𐑘𐑪𐑯𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑱𐑤-𐑚𐑴𐑑'𐑕 𐑚𐑬; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑰 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑕𐑑𐑴𐑝 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑚𐑪𐑑𐑩𐑥 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑒𐑷𐑟𐑛 𐑞 𐑤𐑵𐑕 𐑤𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑖𐑰𐑔 𐑑 𐑛𐑮𐑪𐑐 𐑪𐑓; 𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑒𐑰𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑰𐑤 𐑚𐑸𐑚 𐑞𐑺 𐑯𐑬 𐑒𐑱𐑥 𐑩 𐑤𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑓𐑤𐑱𐑥 𐑝 𐑐𐑱𐑤, 𐑓𐑹𐑒𐑑 𐑓𐑲𐑼. 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑕𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯 𐑚𐑻𐑯𐑛 𐑞𐑺 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑕𐑻𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑑'𐑕 𐑑𐑳𐑙, ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒 𐑜𐑮𐑭𐑕𐑐𐑑 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑸𐑥—“𐑜𐑪𐑛, ·𐑜𐑪𐑛 𐑦𐑟 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑞𐑰, 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑥𐑨𐑯; 𐑓𐑹𐑚𐑺! '𐑑𐑦𐑟 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑤 𐑝𐑶𐑦𐑡! 𐑦𐑤 𐑚𐑦𐑜𐑳𐑯, 𐑦𐑤 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑿𐑛; 𐑤𐑧𐑑 𐑥𐑰 𐑕𐑒𐑢𐑺 𐑞 𐑘𐑸𐑛𐑟, 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑢𐑰 𐑥𐑱, 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑥𐑨𐑯, 𐑯 𐑥𐑱𐑒 𐑩 𐑓𐑺 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛 𐑝 𐑦𐑑 𐑣𐑴𐑥𐑢𐑼𐑛𐑟, 𐑑 𐑜𐑴 𐑪𐑯 𐑩 𐑚𐑧𐑑𐑼 𐑝𐑶𐑦𐑡 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕.”

𐑴𐑝𐑼𐑣𐑽𐑦𐑙 ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒, 𐑞 𐑐𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑒-𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑒𐑮𐑵 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑨𐑯 𐑑 𐑞 𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑕𐑩𐑟—𐑞𐑴 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑩 𐑕𐑱𐑤 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑤𐑧𐑓𐑑 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑓𐑑. 𐑓 𐑞 𐑥𐑴𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑩𐑜𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑥𐑱𐑑'𐑕 𐑔𐑷𐑑𐑕 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑞𐑺𐑟; 𐑞𐑱 𐑮𐑱𐑟𐑛 𐑩 𐑣𐑭𐑓 𐑥𐑿𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑒𐑮𐑲. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑛𐑨𐑖𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑮𐑨𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑤𐑲𐑑𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑤𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑕 𐑑 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑒, 𐑯 𐑕𐑯𐑨𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑚𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯, ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑢𐑱𐑝𐑛 𐑦𐑑 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑑𐑹𐑗 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑞𐑧𐑥; 𐑕𐑢𐑺𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑕𐑓𐑦𐑒𐑕 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑦𐑑 𐑞 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑼 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑒𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑤𐑵𐑕 𐑩 𐑮𐑴𐑐'𐑕 𐑧𐑯𐑛. 𐑐𐑧𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑓𐑲𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑨𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑, 𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑥𐑹 𐑖𐑮𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑓𐑲𐑼𐑦 𐑛𐑸𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑛, 𐑞 𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑓𐑧𐑤 𐑚𐑨𐑒 𐑦𐑯 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑥𐑱, 𐑯 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯 𐑕𐑐𐑴𐑒:—

“𐑷𐑤 𐑘𐑹 𐑴𐑞𐑟 𐑑 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑢𐑲𐑑 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑸 𐑨𐑟 𐑚𐑲𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑨𐑟 𐑥𐑲𐑯; 𐑯 𐑣𐑸𐑑, 𐑕𐑴𐑤, 𐑯 𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦, 𐑤𐑳𐑙𐑟 𐑯 𐑤𐑲𐑓, 𐑴𐑤𐑛 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑬𐑯𐑛. 𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑘𐑰 𐑥𐑱 𐑯𐑴 𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑑𐑿𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑣𐑸𐑑 𐑚𐑰𐑑𐑕; 𐑤𐑫𐑒 𐑘𐑰 𐑣𐑽; 𐑞𐑳𐑕 𐑲 𐑚𐑤𐑴 𐑬𐑑 𐑞 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑓𐑽!” 𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑚𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑮𐑧𐑔 𐑣𐑰 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑢𐑦𐑖𐑑 𐑞 𐑓𐑤𐑱𐑥.

𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑣𐑳𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑱𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑢𐑰𐑐𐑕 𐑞 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑯, 𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑓𐑤𐑲 𐑞 𐑯𐑱𐑚𐑼𐑣𐑫𐑛 𐑝 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑤𐑴𐑯, 𐑡𐑲𐑜𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑧𐑤𐑥, 𐑣𐑵𐑟 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑣𐑲𐑑 𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑧𐑙𐑔 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑮𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑴 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑞 𐑥𐑹 𐑳𐑯𐑕𐑱𐑓, 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑴 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑞 𐑥𐑹 𐑩 𐑥𐑸𐑒 𐑓 𐑔𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑚𐑴𐑤𐑑𐑕; 𐑕𐑴 𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑢𐑻𐑛𐑟 𐑝 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚'𐑟 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑝 𐑞 𐑥𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑯𐑼𐑟 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑮𐑳𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑑𐑧𐑮𐑼 𐑝 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑥𐑱.

·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 121. 𐑥𐑦𐑛𐑯𐑲𐑑.—𐑞 ·𐑓𐑴𐑒𐑕𐑩𐑤 ·𐑚𐑫𐑤𐑢𐑼𐑒𐑕.

𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚 𐑯 ·𐑓𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑒 𐑥𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑪𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑥, 𐑯 𐑐𐑭𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑛𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑤𐑨𐑖𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑞 𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑼𐑟 𐑞𐑺 𐑣𐑨𐑙𐑦𐑙.

“𐑯𐑴, ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚; 𐑿 𐑥𐑱 𐑐𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑨𐑟 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑨𐑟 𐑿 𐑐𐑤𐑰𐑟, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑿 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑐𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑥𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑿 𐑢𐑻 𐑡𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑯𐑬 𐑕𐑱𐑦𐑙. 𐑯 𐑣𐑬 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑩𐑜𐑴 𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑦𐑯𐑕 𐑿 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑞 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑺𐑦? 𐑛𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑿 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑕 𐑕𐑱 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑑𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑖𐑦𐑐 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑦𐑯, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑐𐑱 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑩 𐑪𐑯 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑦𐑯𐑖𐑫𐑼𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑐𐑪𐑤𐑩𐑕𐑦, 𐑡𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑞𐑴 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑻 𐑤𐑴𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑐𐑬𐑛𐑼 𐑚𐑨𐑮𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑭𐑓𐑑 𐑯 𐑚𐑪𐑒𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑝 𐑤𐑵𐑕𐑦𐑓𐑼𐑟 𐑓𐑹𐑢𐑼𐑛? 𐑕𐑑𐑪𐑐, 𐑯𐑬; 𐑛𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑿 𐑕𐑱 𐑕𐑴?”

“𐑢𐑧𐑤, 𐑕𐑩𐑐𐑴𐑟 𐑲 𐑛𐑦𐑛? 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑞𐑧𐑯? 𐑲'𐑝 𐑐𐑸𐑑 𐑗𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑛 𐑥𐑲 𐑓𐑤𐑧𐑖 𐑕𐑦𐑯𐑕 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑑𐑲𐑥, 𐑢𐑲 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑥𐑲 𐑥𐑲𐑯𐑛? 𐑚𐑦𐑕𐑲𐑛𐑟, 𐑕𐑩𐑐𐑴𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑰 𐑸 𐑤𐑴𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑐𐑬𐑛𐑼 𐑚𐑨𐑮𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑭𐑓𐑑 𐑯 𐑤𐑵𐑕𐑦𐑓𐑼𐑟 𐑓𐑹𐑢𐑼𐑛; 𐑣𐑬 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑤 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑞 𐑤𐑵𐑕𐑦𐑓𐑼𐑟 𐑜𐑧𐑑 𐑩𐑓𐑲𐑼 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑛𐑮𐑧𐑯𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑱 𐑣𐑽? 𐑢𐑲, 𐑥𐑲 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑥𐑨𐑯, 𐑿 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑮𐑧𐑛 𐑣𐑺, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑿 𐑒𐑫𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑜𐑧𐑑 𐑩𐑓𐑲𐑼 𐑯𐑬. 𐑖𐑱𐑒 𐑘𐑹𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓; 𐑿'𐑼 ·𐑩𐑒𐑢𐑺𐑾𐑕, 𐑹 𐑞 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼-𐑚𐑺𐑼, ·𐑓𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑒; 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑓𐑦𐑤 𐑐𐑦𐑗𐑼𐑟 𐑨𐑑 𐑘𐑹 𐑒𐑴𐑑 𐑒𐑪𐑤𐑼. 𐑛𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑿 𐑕𐑰, 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑓 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑩 𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑕 𐑞 ·𐑥𐑼𐑰𐑯 ·𐑦𐑯𐑖𐑫𐑼𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑩 𐑜𐑨𐑮𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑰𐑟? 𐑣𐑽 𐑸 𐑣𐑲𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕, ·𐑓𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑒. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑣𐑸𐑒, 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯, 𐑯 𐑲'𐑤 𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑼 𐑘𐑰 𐑞 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑔𐑦𐑙. 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑘𐑹 𐑤𐑧𐑜 𐑪𐑓 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑬𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑼 𐑣𐑽, 𐑞𐑴, 𐑕𐑴 𐑲 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑐𐑭𐑕 𐑞 𐑮𐑴𐑐; 𐑯𐑬 𐑤𐑦𐑕𐑩𐑯. 𐑢𐑪𐑑'𐑕 𐑞 𐑥𐑲𐑑𐑦 𐑛𐑦𐑓𐑼𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑢𐑰𐑯 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑'𐑕 𐑤𐑲𐑑𐑯𐑦𐑙-𐑮𐑪𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑹𐑥, 𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑒𐑤𐑴𐑕 𐑚𐑲 𐑩 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑜𐑪𐑑 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑤𐑲𐑑𐑯𐑦𐑙-𐑮𐑪𐑛 𐑨𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑕𐑑𐑹𐑥? 𐑛𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑿 𐑕𐑰, 𐑿 𐑑𐑦𐑥𐑚𐑼-𐑣𐑧𐑛, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑯𐑴 𐑣𐑸𐑥 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑑 𐑞 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑼 𐑝 𐑞 𐑮𐑪𐑛, 𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑧𐑕 𐑞 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑒? 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑸 𐑿 𐑑𐑷𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑, 𐑞𐑧𐑯? 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑛 𐑒𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑟 𐑮𐑪𐑛𐑟, 𐑯 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚,—𐑲, 𐑥𐑨𐑯, 𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑝 𐑳𐑕,—𐑢𐑻 𐑦𐑯 𐑯𐑴 𐑥𐑹 𐑛𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑼 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑲 𐑐𐑫𐑼 𐑩𐑐𐑦𐑯𐑘𐑩𐑯, 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑵𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑑𐑧𐑯 𐑔𐑬𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑕 𐑯𐑬 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑕𐑰𐑟. 𐑢𐑲, 𐑿 ·𐑒𐑦𐑙-·𐑐𐑴𐑕𐑑, 𐑿, 𐑲 𐑕𐑩𐑐𐑴𐑟 𐑿 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛 𐑜𐑴 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑕𐑥𐑷𐑤 𐑤𐑲𐑑𐑯𐑦𐑙-𐑮𐑪𐑛 𐑮𐑳𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑳𐑐 𐑞 𐑒𐑹𐑯𐑼 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑑, 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑥𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑖𐑩 𐑪𐑓𐑦𐑕𐑼'𐑟 𐑕𐑒𐑿𐑼𐑛 𐑓𐑧𐑞𐑼, 𐑯 𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑦𐑣𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑨𐑖. 𐑢𐑲 𐑛𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑘𐑰 𐑚𐑰 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤, ·𐑓𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑒? 𐑦𐑑'𐑕 𐑰𐑟𐑦 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤; 𐑢𐑲 𐑛𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑘𐑰, 𐑞𐑧𐑯? 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑭𐑓 𐑩𐑯 𐑲 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑚𐑰 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤.”

“𐑲 𐑛𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑯𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑, ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚. 𐑿 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑓𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑑 𐑮𐑭𐑞𐑼 𐑣𐑸𐑛.”

“𐑘𐑧𐑕, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑩 𐑓𐑧𐑤𐑴'𐑟 𐑕𐑴𐑒𐑑 𐑔𐑮𐑵, 𐑦𐑑'𐑕 𐑣𐑸𐑛 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤, 𐑞𐑨𐑑'𐑕 𐑩 𐑓𐑨𐑒𐑑. 𐑯 𐑲 𐑨𐑥 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑛𐑮𐑧𐑯𐑗𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑱. 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑥𐑲𐑯𐑛; 𐑒𐑨𐑗 𐑞 𐑑𐑻𐑯 𐑞𐑺, 𐑯 𐑐𐑭𐑕 𐑦𐑑. 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑟 𐑑 𐑥𐑰 𐑢𐑰 𐑸 𐑤𐑨𐑖𐑦𐑙 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑼𐑟 𐑯𐑬 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑓 𐑞𐑱 𐑢𐑻 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑜𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑿𐑟𐑛 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯. 𐑑𐑲𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑑𐑵 𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑼𐑟 𐑣𐑽, ·𐑓𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑒, 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑟 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑑𐑲𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑥𐑨𐑯'𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑚𐑦𐑣𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥. 𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑜 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑕 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑞𐑱 𐑸, 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑖𐑫𐑼. 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑸 𐑘𐑹 𐑲𐑼𐑯 𐑓𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑕, 𐑣𐑱? 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑩 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑞𐑱 𐑣𐑨𐑝, 𐑑𐑵! 𐑲 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼, ·𐑓𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑒, 𐑢𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑞 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛 𐑦𐑟 𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑼𐑛 𐑧𐑯𐑦𐑢𐑺; 𐑦𐑓 𐑖𐑰 𐑦𐑟, 𐑖𐑰 𐑕𐑢𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩𐑯 𐑳𐑯𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑒𐑱𐑚𐑩𐑤, 𐑞𐑴. 𐑞𐑺, 𐑣𐑨𐑥𐑼 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑛𐑬𐑯, 𐑯 𐑢𐑰'𐑝 𐑛𐑳𐑯. 𐑕𐑴; 𐑯𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑 𐑑 𐑑𐑳𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛, 𐑤𐑲𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑪𐑯 𐑛𐑧𐑒 𐑦𐑟 𐑞 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑨𐑑𐑦𐑕𐑓𐑨𐑒𐑑𐑼𐑦. 𐑲 𐑕𐑱, 𐑡𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑙 𐑬𐑑 𐑥𐑲 𐑡𐑨𐑒𐑩𐑑 𐑕𐑒𐑻𐑑𐑕, 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑘𐑰? 𐑔𐑨𐑙𐑒 𐑘𐑰. 𐑞𐑱 𐑤𐑭𐑓 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑪𐑙-𐑑𐑪𐑜𐑟 𐑕𐑴, ·𐑓𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑒; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑟 𐑑 𐑥𐑰, 𐑩 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑑𐑱𐑤𐑛 𐑒𐑴𐑑 𐑷𐑑 𐑷𐑤𐑢𐑱𐑟 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑢𐑹𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑕𐑑𐑹𐑥𐑟 𐑩𐑓𐑤𐑴𐑑. 𐑞 𐑑𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑑𐑱𐑐𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑱, 𐑕𐑻𐑝 𐑑 𐑒𐑨𐑮𐑦 𐑪𐑓 𐑞 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼, 𐑛'𐑘𐑰 𐑕𐑰. 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑒𐑪𐑒𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑑𐑕; 𐑞 𐑒𐑪𐑒𐑕 𐑓𐑹𐑥 𐑜𐑱𐑚𐑩𐑤-𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑰𐑝-𐑑𐑮𐑪𐑓𐑕, ·𐑓𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑒. 𐑯𐑴 𐑥𐑹 𐑥𐑳𐑙𐑒𐑦-𐑡𐑨𐑒𐑩𐑑𐑕 𐑯 𐑑𐑸𐑐𐑷𐑤𐑦𐑯𐑟 𐑓 𐑥𐑰; 𐑲 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑥𐑬𐑯𐑑 𐑩 𐑕𐑢𐑪𐑤𐑴-𐑑𐑱𐑤, 𐑯 𐑛𐑮𐑲𐑝 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑩 𐑚𐑰𐑝𐑼; 𐑕𐑴. 𐑣𐑩𐑤𐑴! 𐑓𐑿! 𐑞𐑺 𐑜𐑴𐑟 𐑥𐑲 𐑑𐑸𐑐𐑷𐑤𐑦𐑯 𐑴𐑝𐑼𐑚𐑹𐑛; ·𐑤𐑹𐑛, ·𐑤𐑹𐑛, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑣𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑚𐑰 𐑕𐑴 𐑳𐑯𐑥𐑨𐑯𐑼𐑤𐑦! 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑦𐑟 𐑩 𐑯𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑦 𐑯𐑲𐑑, 𐑤𐑨𐑛.”

·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 123. 𐑞 ·𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑒𐑩𐑑.

𐑛𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑖𐑪𐑒𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑑𐑲𐑓𐑵𐑯, 𐑞 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛'𐑟 𐑡𐑷-𐑚𐑴𐑯 𐑑𐑦𐑤𐑼 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑕𐑧𐑝𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑮𐑰𐑤𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑣𐑻𐑤𐑛 𐑑 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑒 𐑚𐑲 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑕𐑐𐑨𐑟𐑥𐑪𐑛𐑦𐑒 𐑥𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟, 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑞𐑴 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑝𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑼 𐑑𐑨𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑩𐑑𐑨𐑗𐑑 𐑑 𐑦𐑑—𐑓 𐑞𐑱 𐑢𐑻 𐑕𐑤𐑨𐑒—𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑐𐑤𐑱 𐑑 𐑞 𐑑𐑦𐑤𐑼 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤.

𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑕𐑦𐑝𐑽 𐑜𐑱𐑤 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑞𐑦𐑕, 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑩 𐑑𐑪𐑕𐑑 𐑖𐑳𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑒𐑪𐑒 𐑑 𐑞 𐑚𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑, 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑲 𐑯𐑴 𐑥𐑰𐑯𐑟 𐑳𐑯𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑑 𐑕𐑰 𐑞 𐑯𐑰𐑛𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑕𐑩𐑟, 𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑟, 𐑜𐑴 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑯 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛. 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞𐑳𐑕 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛'𐑟; 𐑨𐑑 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑖𐑪𐑒 𐑞 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑥𐑟𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑓𐑱𐑤𐑛 𐑑 𐑯𐑴𐑑𐑦𐑕 𐑞 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑝𐑦𐑤𐑪𐑕𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑞𐑱 𐑮𐑦𐑝𐑪𐑤𐑝𐑛 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑒𐑸𐑛𐑟; 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑩 𐑕𐑲𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑸𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑧𐑯𐑦𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑚𐑦𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑕𐑹𐑑 𐑝 𐑳𐑯𐑢𐑴𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑥𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯.

𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑬𐑼𐑟 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑥𐑦𐑛𐑯𐑲𐑑, 𐑞 ·𐑑𐑲𐑓𐑵𐑯 𐑩𐑚𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑕𐑴 𐑥𐑳𐑗, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑧𐑯𐑿𐑩𐑕 𐑦𐑜𐑟𐑻𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑝 ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒 𐑯 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚—𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑜𐑱𐑡𐑛 𐑓𐑹𐑢𐑼𐑛 𐑯 𐑞 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑭𐑓𐑑—𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑝𐑼𐑛 𐑮𐑧𐑥𐑯𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑡𐑦𐑚 𐑯 𐑓𐑹 𐑯 𐑥𐑱𐑯-𐑑𐑪𐑐-𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑒𐑳𐑑 𐑩𐑛𐑮𐑦𐑓𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑸𐑟, 𐑯 𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑧𐑛𐑦𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑢𐑱 𐑑 𐑤𐑰𐑢𐑼𐑛, 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑞 𐑓𐑧𐑞𐑼𐑟 𐑝 𐑩𐑯 𐑨𐑤𐑚𐑩𐑑𐑮𐑪𐑕, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑸 𐑒𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑑 𐑞 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑹𐑥-𐑑𐑪𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑻𐑛 𐑦𐑟 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑦𐑙.

𐑞 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑒𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑪𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑯𐑿 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑯𐑬 𐑚𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑯 𐑮𐑰𐑓𐑑, 𐑯 𐑩 𐑕𐑑𐑹𐑥-𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑕𐑱𐑤 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑧𐑑 𐑓𐑻𐑞𐑼 𐑭𐑓𐑑; 𐑕𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑕𐑵𐑯 𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑞 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑦𐑠𐑩𐑯 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯; 𐑯 𐑞 𐑒𐑹𐑕—𐑓 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑑, ·𐑰𐑕𐑑-𐑕𐑬𐑔-𐑰𐑕𐑑—𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑽, 𐑦𐑓 𐑐𐑮𐑨𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤, 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑕 𐑥𐑹 𐑜𐑦𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑑 𐑞 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑥𐑟𐑥𐑩𐑯. 𐑓 𐑛𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑜𐑱𐑤, 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑑𐑽𐑛 𐑩𐑒𐑹𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑝𐑦𐑕𐑦𐑕𐑦𐑑𐑿𐑛𐑟. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑬 𐑚𐑮𐑦𐑙𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑨𐑟 𐑯𐑽 𐑣𐑻 𐑒𐑹𐑕 𐑨𐑟 𐑐𐑪𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤, 𐑢𐑪𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑕 𐑥𐑰𐑯𐑢𐑲𐑤, 𐑤𐑴! 𐑩 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑕𐑲𐑯! 𐑞 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑩𐑕𐑑𐑻𐑯; 𐑲, 𐑞 𐑓𐑬𐑤 𐑚𐑮𐑰𐑟 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑱𐑥 𐑓𐑺!

𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑞 𐑘𐑸𐑛𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑕𐑒𐑢𐑺𐑛, 𐑑 𐑞 𐑤𐑲𐑝𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑪𐑙 𐑝 “𐑣𐑴! 𐑞 𐑓𐑺 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛! 𐑴-𐑘𐑰-𐑣𐑴, 𐑗𐑽𐑤𐑦 𐑥𐑧𐑯!” 𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑵 𐑕𐑦𐑙𐑦𐑙 𐑓 𐑡𐑶, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑴 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑝𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑕𐑴 𐑕𐑵𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑓𐑷𐑤𐑕𐑦𐑓𐑲𐑛 𐑞 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑤 𐑐𐑹𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑰𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑑.

𐑦𐑯 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑲𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑹𐑛𐑼 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑭𐑯𐑛𐑼—𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑹𐑑 𐑦𐑥𐑰𐑛𐑾𐑑𐑤𐑦, 𐑯 𐑨𐑑 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑑𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑦-𐑓𐑹 𐑬𐑼𐑟, 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑲𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑗𐑱𐑯𐑡 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑩𐑓𐑺𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑒,—·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑯𐑴 𐑕𐑵𐑯𐑼 𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑛 𐑞 𐑘𐑸𐑛𐑟 𐑑 𐑞 𐑚𐑮𐑰𐑟—𐑣𐑬𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑮𐑦𐑤𐑳𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑯 𐑜𐑤𐑵𐑥𐑦𐑤𐑦,—𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑣𐑰 𐑥𐑦𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑦 𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑴 𐑑 𐑩𐑐𐑮𐑲𐑟 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑻𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑕.

𐑺 𐑯𐑪𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑑-𐑮𐑵𐑥, 𐑣𐑰 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑪𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑺𐑦𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑷𐑟𐑛 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑦𐑑 𐑩 𐑥𐑴𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑. 𐑞 𐑒𐑨𐑚𐑦𐑯 𐑤𐑨𐑥𐑐—𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑕𐑢𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑱 𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑—𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑚𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑦𐑑𐑓𐑩𐑤𐑦, 𐑯 𐑒𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑦𐑑𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑖𐑨𐑛𐑴𐑟 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑥𐑨𐑯'𐑟 𐑚𐑴𐑤𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑛𐑹,—𐑩 𐑔𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑓𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑤𐑲𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑛, 𐑦𐑯 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕 𐑝 𐑳𐑐𐑼 𐑐𐑨𐑯𐑩𐑤𐑟. 𐑞 𐑲𐑕𐑩𐑤𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑕𐑳𐑚𐑑𐑼𐑱𐑯𐑾𐑕𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑒𐑨𐑚𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑩 𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑣𐑳𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑑 𐑮𐑱𐑯 𐑞𐑺, 𐑞𐑴 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑣𐑵𐑐𐑑 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑮𐑹 𐑝 𐑞 𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕. 𐑞 𐑤𐑴𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑒𐑩𐑑𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑮𐑨𐑒 𐑢𐑻 𐑖𐑲𐑯𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑦𐑝𐑰𐑤𐑛, 𐑨𐑟 𐑞𐑱 𐑕𐑑𐑫𐑛 𐑳𐑐𐑮𐑲𐑑 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑞 𐑓𐑹𐑢𐑼𐑛 𐑚𐑳𐑤𐑒𐑣𐑧𐑛. 𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩𐑯 𐑪𐑯𐑩𐑕𐑑, 𐑳𐑐𐑮𐑲𐑑 𐑥𐑨𐑯; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒'𐑕 𐑣𐑸𐑑, 𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑷 𐑞 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑒𐑩𐑑𐑕, 𐑞𐑺 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑝𐑪𐑤𐑝𐑛 𐑩𐑯 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑤 𐑔𐑷𐑑; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑕𐑴 𐑚𐑤𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑯𐑿𐑑𐑮𐑩𐑤 𐑹 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑩𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑓 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑸𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑯𐑿 𐑦𐑑 𐑓 𐑦𐑑𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓.

“𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑖𐑪𐑑 𐑥𐑰 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑕,” 𐑣𐑰 𐑥𐑻𐑥𐑼𐑛, “𐑘𐑧𐑕, 𐑞𐑺'𐑟 𐑞 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑒𐑩𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑐𐑶𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑰;—𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑕𐑑𐑪𐑒; 𐑤𐑧𐑑 𐑥𐑰 𐑑𐑳𐑗 𐑦𐑑—𐑤𐑦𐑓𐑑 𐑦𐑑. 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑲, 𐑣𐑵 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑕𐑴 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑛𐑧𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟, 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑲 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑖𐑱𐑒 𐑕𐑴 𐑯𐑬. 𐑤𐑴𐑛𐑩𐑛? 𐑲 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑰. 𐑲, 𐑲; 𐑯 𐑐𐑬𐑛𐑼 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑐𐑨𐑯;—𐑞𐑨𐑑'𐑕 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑜𐑫𐑛. 𐑚𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑐𐑦𐑤 𐑦𐑑?—𐑢𐑱𐑑. 𐑲'𐑤 𐑒𐑘𐑫𐑼 𐑥𐑲𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑝 𐑞𐑦𐑕. 𐑲'𐑤 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑞 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑒𐑩𐑑 𐑚𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑲 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒.—𐑲 𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑹𐑑 𐑩 𐑓𐑺 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑣𐑬 𐑓𐑺? 𐑓𐑺 𐑓 𐑛𐑧𐑔 𐑯 𐑛𐑵𐑥,—𐑞𐑨𐑑'𐑕 𐑓𐑺 𐑓 ·𐑥𐑪𐑚𐑦 ·𐑛𐑦𐑒. 𐑦𐑑'𐑕 𐑩 𐑓𐑺 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑'𐑕 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑓𐑺 𐑓 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑩𐑒𐑻𐑕𐑩𐑛 𐑓𐑦𐑖.—𐑞 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑑𐑿𐑚 𐑣𐑰 𐑐𐑶𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑰!—𐑞 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑢𐑳𐑯; 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑳𐑯—𐑲 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑦𐑑 𐑣𐑽; 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑒𐑦𐑤𐑛 𐑥𐑰 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑤 𐑯𐑬.—𐑲 𐑯 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑓𐑱𐑯 𐑒𐑦𐑤 𐑷𐑤 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑮𐑵. 𐑛𐑳𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑱 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑒 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑐𐑸𐑟 𐑑 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑜𐑱𐑤? 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑛𐑨𐑖𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑯𐑑? 𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑐𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑕𐑰𐑟, 𐑜𐑮𐑴𐑐𐑕 𐑣𐑰 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑱 𐑚𐑲 𐑥𐑽 𐑛𐑧𐑛 𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑞 𐑻𐑼-𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑤𐑪𐑜? 𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 ·𐑑𐑲𐑓𐑵𐑯, 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑣𐑰 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑢𐑺 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑯𐑴 𐑤𐑲𐑑𐑯𐑦𐑙-𐑮𐑪𐑛𐑟? 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑖𐑨𐑤 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑒𐑮𐑱𐑟𐑛 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑚𐑰 𐑑𐑱𐑥𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑳𐑓𐑼𐑛 𐑑 𐑛𐑮𐑨𐑜 𐑩 𐑣𐑴𐑤 𐑖𐑦𐑐'𐑕 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑦 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑑 𐑛𐑵𐑥 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑥?—𐑘𐑧𐑕, 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑥𐑱𐑒 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑞 𐑢𐑦𐑤𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑥𐑻𐑛𐑼𐑼 𐑝 𐑔𐑻𐑑𐑦 𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑯 𐑥𐑹, 𐑦𐑓 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑑 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑛𐑧𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑣𐑸𐑥; 𐑯 𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑑 𐑛𐑧𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑣𐑸𐑥, 𐑥𐑲 𐑕𐑴𐑤 𐑕𐑢𐑺𐑟 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑢𐑦𐑤, 𐑦𐑓 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑱. 𐑦𐑓, 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑻 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑—𐑐𐑫𐑑 𐑩𐑕𐑲𐑛, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑥 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑣𐑦𐑟. 𐑣𐑭! 𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑥𐑳𐑑𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑤𐑰𐑐? 𐑘𐑧𐑕, 𐑡𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑞𐑺,—𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑺, 𐑣𐑰'𐑟 𐑕𐑤𐑰𐑐𐑦𐑙. 𐑕𐑤𐑰𐑐𐑦𐑙? 𐑲, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑩𐑤𐑲𐑝, 𐑯 𐑕𐑵𐑯 𐑩𐑢𐑱𐑒 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯. 𐑲 𐑒𐑭𐑯𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑞𐑰, 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑥𐑨𐑯. 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑮𐑰𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑙; 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑩𐑯𐑕; 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑰𐑑𐑦 𐑢𐑦𐑤𐑑 𐑞𐑬 𐑣𐑸𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑑; 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑞𐑬 𐑕𐑒𐑹𐑯𐑩𐑕𐑑. 𐑓𐑤𐑨𐑑 𐑴𐑚𐑰𐑛𐑾𐑯𐑕 𐑑 𐑞𐑲 𐑴𐑯 𐑓𐑤𐑨𐑑 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑭𐑯𐑛𐑟, 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑦𐑟 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑬 𐑚𐑮𐑰𐑞𐑩𐑕𐑑. 𐑲, 𐑯 𐑕𐑱'𐑕𐑑 𐑞 𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑝𐑬'𐑛 𐑞𐑲 𐑝𐑬; 𐑕𐑱'𐑕𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑝 𐑳𐑕 𐑸 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚𐑟. 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 ·𐑜𐑪𐑛 𐑓𐑼𐑚𐑦𐑛!—𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑞𐑺 𐑯𐑴 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑢𐑱? 𐑯𐑴 𐑤𐑷𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑱?—𐑥𐑱𐑒 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑩 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑼 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑣𐑴𐑥? 𐑢𐑪𐑑! 𐑣𐑴𐑐 𐑑 𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑥𐑨𐑯'𐑟 𐑤𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑐𐑬𐑼 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑴𐑯 𐑤𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟? 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑩 𐑓𐑵𐑤 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑑𐑮𐑲 𐑦𐑑. 𐑕𐑱 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑻 𐑐𐑦𐑯𐑘𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯; 𐑯𐑪𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑷𐑤 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑮𐑴𐑐𐑕 𐑯 𐑣𐑷𐑟𐑼𐑟; 𐑗𐑱𐑯𐑛 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑙-𐑚𐑴𐑤𐑑𐑕 𐑪𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑒𐑨𐑚𐑦𐑯 𐑓𐑤𐑹; 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑚𐑰 𐑥𐑹 𐑣𐑦𐑛𐑾𐑕 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑩 𐑒𐑱𐑡𐑛 𐑑𐑲𐑜𐑼, 𐑞𐑧𐑯. 𐑲 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑻 𐑞 𐑕𐑲𐑑; 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑐𐑪𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑓𐑤𐑲 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑬𐑤𐑦𐑙𐑟; 𐑷𐑤 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑓𐑼𐑑, 𐑕𐑤𐑰𐑐 𐑦𐑑𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓, 𐑦𐑯𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑥𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑮𐑰𐑟𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑤𐑰𐑝 𐑥𐑰 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑪𐑤𐑼𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑝𐑶𐑦𐑡. 𐑢𐑪𐑑, 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑱𐑯𐑟? 𐑞 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑛𐑟 𐑝 𐑤𐑰𐑜𐑟 𐑩𐑢𐑱, 𐑯 𐑤𐑪𐑒𐑑 ·𐑡𐑩𐑐𐑨𐑯 𐑞 𐑯𐑽𐑩𐑕𐑑. 𐑲 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑩𐑤𐑴𐑯 𐑣𐑽 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑩𐑯 𐑴𐑐𐑩𐑯 𐑕𐑰, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑑𐑵 𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑯 𐑩 𐑣𐑴𐑤 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑢𐑰𐑯 𐑥𐑰 𐑯 𐑤𐑷.—𐑲, 𐑲, '𐑑𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑴.—𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑩 𐑥𐑻𐑛𐑼𐑼 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑤𐑲𐑑𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑒𐑕 𐑩 𐑢𐑫𐑛-𐑚𐑰 𐑥𐑻𐑛𐑼𐑼 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑧𐑛, 𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑖𐑰𐑑𐑕 𐑯 𐑕𐑒𐑦𐑯 𐑑𐑩𐑜𐑧𐑞𐑼?—𐑯 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑲 𐑚𐑰 𐑩 𐑥𐑻𐑛𐑼𐑼, 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑦𐑓”—𐑯 𐑕𐑤𐑴𐑤𐑦, 𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑤𐑔𐑦𐑤𐑦, 𐑯 𐑣𐑭𐑓 𐑕𐑲𐑛𐑢𐑱𐑟 𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑦𐑙, 𐑣𐑰 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕𐑑 𐑞 𐑤𐑴𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑒𐑩𐑑'𐑕 𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑞 𐑛𐑹.

“𐑪𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑤𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑤, ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚'𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑥𐑩𐑒 𐑕𐑢𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑦𐑯; 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑱. 𐑩 𐑑𐑳𐑗, 𐑯 ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒 𐑥𐑱 𐑕𐑼𐑝𐑲𐑝 𐑑 𐑣𐑳𐑜 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑲𐑓 𐑯 𐑗𐑲𐑤𐑛 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯.—𐑴 ·𐑥𐑺𐑦! 𐑥𐑺𐑦!—𐑚𐑶! 𐑚𐑶! 𐑚𐑶!—𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑓 𐑲 𐑢𐑱𐑒 𐑞𐑰 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑑 𐑛𐑧𐑔, 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑥𐑨𐑯, 𐑣𐑵 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑑𐑧𐑤 𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑳𐑯𐑕𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑛𐑰𐑐𐑕 ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒'𐑕 𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑛𐑱 𐑢𐑰𐑒 𐑥𐑱 𐑕𐑦𐑙𐑒, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑵! 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 ·𐑜𐑪𐑛, 𐑢𐑺 𐑸𐑑 ·𐑞𐑬? 𐑖𐑨𐑤 𐑲? 𐑖𐑨𐑤 𐑲?—𐑞 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑜𐑪𐑯 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑯 𐑖𐑦𐑓𐑑𐑩𐑛, 𐑕𐑻; 𐑞 𐑓𐑹 𐑯 𐑥𐑱𐑯 𐑑𐑪𐑐𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑸 𐑮𐑰𐑓𐑑 𐑯 𐑕𐑧𐑑; 𐑖𐑰 𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑟 𐑣𐑻 𐑒𐑹𐑕.”

“𐑕𐑑𐑻𐑯 𐑷𐑤! 𐑴 ·𐑥𐑪𐑚𐑦 ·𐑛𐑦𐑒, 𐑲 𐑒𐑤𐑳𐑗 𐑞𐑲 𐑣𐑸𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑!”

𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑢𐑻 𐑞 𐑕𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑯𐑬 𐑒𐑱𐑥 𐑣𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑬𐑑 𐑞 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑥𐑨𐑯'𐑟 𐑑𐑹𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑕𐑤𐑰𐑐, 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑓 ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒'𐑕 𐑝𐑶𐑕 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑒𐑷𐑟𐑛 𐑞 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑛𐑳𐑥 𐑛𐑮𐑰𐑥 𐑑 𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑒.

𐑞 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑤𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑒𐑩𐑑 𐑖𐑫𐑒 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑛𐑮𐑳𐑯𐑒𐑼𐑛'𐑟 𐑸𐑥 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑞 𐑐𐑨𐑯𐑩𐑤; ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩𐑯 𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑩𐑤; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑛𐑹, 𐑣𐑰 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕𐑑 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑔-𐑑𐑿𐑚 𐑦𐑯 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑮𐑨𐑒, 𐑯 𐑤𐑧𐑓𐑑 𐑞 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕.

“𐑣𐑰'𐑟 𐑑𐑵 𐑕𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑩𐑕𐑤𐑰𐑐, ·𐑥𐑼 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚; 𐑜𐑴 𐑞𐑬 𐑛𐑬𐑯, 𐑯 𐑢𐑱𐑒 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑯 𐑑𐑧𐑤 𐑣𐑦𐑥. 𐑲 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑰 𐑑 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑒 𐑣𐑽. 𐑞𐑬 𐑯𐑴'𐑕𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑑 𐑕𐑱.”

·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 124. 𐑞 ·𐑯𐑰𐑛𐑩𐑤.

𐑯𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑 𐑥𐑹𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑯𐑪𐑑-𐑘𐑧𐑑-𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑕𐑲𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑕𐑰 𐑮𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑕𐑤𐑴 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑴𐑟 𐑝 𐑥𐑲𐑑𐑦 𐑚𐑳𐑤𐑒, 𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛'𐑟 𐑜𐑻𐑜𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑒, 𐑐𐑫𐑖𐑑 𐑣𐑻 𐑪𐑯 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑡𐑲𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕' 𐑐𐑭𐑥𐑟 𐑬𐑑𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑛. 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑪𐑙, 𐑳𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑜𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑮𐑰𐑟 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑕𐑴, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑒𐑲 𐑯 𐑺 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑝𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑬𐑑𐑚𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑟; 𐑞 𐑣𐑴𐑤 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛 𐑚𐑵𐑥𐑛 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑞 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛. 𐑥𐑳𐑓𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑫𐑤 𐑥𐑹𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑤𐑲𐑑, 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑦𐑟𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑳𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑯𐑴𐑯 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕; 𐑢𐑺 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑱𐑩𐑯𐑧𐑑 𐑮𐑱𐑟 𐑥𐑵𐑝𐑛 𐑪𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑒𐑕. 𐑦𐑥𐑚𐑤𐑱𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑙𐑟, 𐑨𐑟 𐑝 𐑒𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 ·𐑚𐑨𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑴𐑯𐑾𐑯 𐑒𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑯 𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑯𐑟, 𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑛 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦𐑔𐑦𐑙. 𐑞 𐑕𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑨𐑟 𐑩 𐑒𐑮𐑵𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑥𐑴𐑤𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑜𐑴𐑤𐑛, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑚𐑳𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑤𐑰𐑐𐑕 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑤𐑲𐑑 𐑯 𐑣𐑰𐑑.

𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑥𐑱𐑯𐑑𐑱𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑗𐑭𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑕𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑕, ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑕𐑑𐑫𐑛 𐑩𐑐𐑸𐑑; 𐑯 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑞 ·𐑑𐑰𐑑𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑤𐑴𐑼𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑦𐑗𐑑 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑣𐑻 𐑚𐑴𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑑, 𐑣𐑰 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑛 𐑑 𐑲 𐑞 𐑚𐑮𐑲𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑯'𐑟 𐑮𐑱𐑟 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑛𐑿𐑕𐑑 𐑩𐑣𐑧𐑛; 𐑯 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑖𐑰 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑧𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑻𐑯, 𐑣𐑰 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑛 𐑚𐑦𐑣𐑲𐑯𐑛, 𐑯 𐑕𐑷 𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑯'𐑟 𐑮𐑽𐑢𐑼𐑛 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕, 𐑯 𐑣𐑬 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑘𐑧𐑤𐑴 𐑮𐑱𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑚𐑤𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑰𐑝𐑦𐑱𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑱𐑒.

“𐑣𐑭, 𐑣𐑭, 𐑥𐑲 𐑖𐑦𐑐! 𐑞𐑬 𐑥𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑢𐑧𐑤 𐑚𐑰 𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑯𐑬 𐑓 𐑞 𐑕𐑰-𐑗𐑨𐑮𐑾𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑯. 𐑣𐑴, 𐑣𐑴! 𐑷𐑤 𐑘𐑰 𐑯𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑥𐑲 𐑐𐑮𐑬, 𐑲 𐑚𐑮𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑯 𐑑 𐑘𐑰! 𐑘𐑴𐑒 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑻𐑞𐑼 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑴𐑟; 𐑣𐑩𐑤𐑴! 𐑩 𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑥, 𐑲 𐑛𐑮𐑲𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑰!”

𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑛 𐑚𐑨𐑒 𐑚𐑲 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑼 𐑔𐑷𐑑, 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑳𐑮𐑦𐑛 𐑑𐑩𐑢𐑹𐑛𐑟 𐑞 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑥, 𐑣𐑳𐑕𐑒𐑦𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑦𐑥𐑭𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑬 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑦𐑙.

“𐑰𐑕𐑑-𐑕𐑵-𐑰𐑕𐑑, 𐑕𐑻,” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑞 𐑓𐑮𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑕𐑑𐑽𐑟𐑥𐑩𐑯.

“𐑞𐑬 𐑤𐑲𐑩𐑕𐑑!” 𐑕𐑥𐑲𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑤𐑧𐑯𐑗𐑑 𐑓𐑦𐑕𐑑. “𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑦𐑙 ·𐑰𐑕𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑬𐑼 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑥𐑹𐑯𐑦𐑙, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑯 𐑩𐑕𐑑𐑻𐑯?”

𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑕𐑴𐑤 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛; 𐑓 𐑞 𐑓𐑦𐑯𐑪𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑪𐑯 𐑡𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑩𐑚𐑟𐑻𐑝𐑛 𐑚𐑲 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑳𐑯𐑩𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑱𐑐𐑑 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑧𐑤𐑕; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑚𐑤𐑲𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑐𐑨𐑤𐑐𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑞 𐑒𐑷𐑟.

𐑔𐑮𐑳𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑣𐑭𐑓 𐑢𐑱 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑚𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑒𐑩𐑤, ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑒𐑷𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑜𐑤𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑕𐑩𐑟; 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑳𐑐𐑤𐑦𐑓𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑸𐑥 𐑕𐑤𐑴𐑤𐑦 𐑓𐑧𐑤; 𐑓 𐑩 𐑥𐑴𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑜𐑼. 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑦𐑣𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥 ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒 𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑑, 𐑯 𐑤𐑴! 𐑞 𐑑𐑵 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑐𐑶𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 ·𐑰𐑕𐑑, 𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑓𐑨𐑤𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑜𐑴𐑦𐑙 ·𐑢𐑧𐑕𐑑.

𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑺 𐑞 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑢𐑲𐑤𐑛 𐑩𐑤𐑸𐑥 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑜𐑧𐑑 𐑬𐑑 𐑩𐑚𐑮𐑷𐑛 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑵, 𐑞 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑮𐑦𐑡𐑦𐑛 𐑤𐑭𐑓 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑒𐑤𐑱𐑥𐑛, “𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑦𐑑! 𐑦𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹. ·𐑥𐑼 ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒, 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑯𐑲𐑑'𐑕 𐑔𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑛 𐑬𐑼 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑕𐑩𐑟—𐑞𐑨𐑑'𐑕 𐑷𐑤. 𐑞𐑬 𐑣𐑨𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑯𐑬 𐑣𐑻𐑛 𐑝 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩 𐑔𐑦𐑙, 𐑲 𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑦𐑑.”

“𐑲; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑑 𐑥𐑰, 𐑕𐑻,” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑞 𐑐𐑱𐑤 𐑥𐑱𐑑, 𐑜𐑤𐑵𐑥𐑦𐑤𐑦.

𐑣𐑽, 𐑦𐑑 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑯𐑰𐑛𐑟 𐑚𐑰 𐑕𐑧𐑛, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑨𐑒𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑹 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑒𐑱𐑕 𐑩𐑒𐑻𐑛 𐑑 𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑹𐑥𐑟. 𐑞 𐑥𐑨𐑜𐑯𐑧𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑧𐑯𐑼𐑡𐑦, 𐑨𐑟 𐑛𐑦𐑝𐑧𐑤𐑩𐑐𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑥𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑯𐑼'𐑟 𐑯𐑰𐑛𐑩𐑤, 𐑦𐑟, 𐑨𐑟 𐑷𐑤 𐑯𐑴, 𐑦𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑦𐑤𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑚𐑦𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑯; 𐑣𐑧𐑯𐑕 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑥𐑸𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑨𐑑, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑚𐑰. 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑢𐑺 𐑞 𐑤𐑲𐑑𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑨𐑒𐑗𐑵𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑒 𐑞 𐑝𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑤, 𐑕𐑴 𐑨𐑟 𐑑 𐑕𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑸𐑟 𐑯 𐑮𐑦𐑜𐑦𐑙, 𐑞 𐑦𐑓𐑧𐑒𐑑 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑯𐑰𐑛𐑩𐑤 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑨𐑑 𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑥𐑹 𐑓𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑤; 𐑷𐑤 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑤𐑴𐑛𐑕𐑑𐑴𐑯 𐑝𐑻𐑗𐑵 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑯𐑲𐑩𐑤𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛, 𐑕𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑥𐑨𐑜𐑯𐑧𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑕𐑑𐑰𐑤 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑝 𐑯𐑴 𐑥𐑹 𐑿𐑕 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑩𐑯 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑢𐑲𐑓'𐑕 𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑯𐑰𐑛𐑩𐑤. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑲𐑞𐑼 𐑒𐑱𐑕, 𐑞 𐑯𐑰𐑛𐑩𐑤 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯, 𐑝 𐑦𐑑𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓, 𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑳𐑝𐑼𐑟 𐑞 𐑼𐑦𐑡𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑝𐑻𐑗𐑵 𐑞𐑳𐑕 𐑥𐑸𐑛 𐑹 𐑤𐑪𐑕𐑑; 𐑯 𐑦𐑓 𐑞 𐑚𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑚𐑰 𐑩𐑓𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑛, 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑓𐑱𐑑 𐑮𐑰𐑗𐑩𐑟 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑳𐑞𐑼𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑱 𐑚𐑰 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐; 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑻 𐑞 𐑤𐑴𐑼𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑒𐑧𐑤𐑕𐑩𐑯.

𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑚𐑼𐑩𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑞 𐑚𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑒𐑩𐑤, 𐑯 𐑲𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑟𐑐𐑶𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑕𐑩𐑟, 𐑞 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑥𐑨𐑯, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑖𐑸𐑐 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛, 𐑯𐑬 𐑑𐑫𐑒 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑲𐑕 𐑚𐑺𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑯, 𐑯 𐑕𐑨𐑑𐑦𐑕𐑓𐑲𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑯𐑰𐑛𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑦𐑜𐑟𐑨𐑒𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑛, 𐑖𐑬𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑬𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑹𐑛𐑼𐑟 𐑓 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐'𐑕 𐑒𐑹𐑕 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑗𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑛 𐑩𐑒𐑹𐑛𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦. 𐑞 𐑘𐑸𐑛𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑣𐑸𐑛 𐑳𐑐; 𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑕 𐑥𐑹 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛 𐑔𐑮𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑻 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑷𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑬𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑩𐑐𐑴𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛, 𐑓 𐑞 𐑕𐑩𐑐𐑴𐑟𐑛 𐑓𐑺 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑡𐑳𐑜𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑻.

𐑥𐑰𐑯𐑢𐑲𐑤, 𐑢𐑪𐑑𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑢𐑻 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑴𐑯 𐑕𐑰𐑒𐑮𐑩𐑑 𐑔𐑷𐑑𐑕, ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑯𐑳𐑔𐑦𐑙, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑒𐑢𐑲𐑩𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑣𐑰 𐑦𐑖𐑿𐑛 𐑷𐑤 𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑟𐑦𐑑 𐑹𐑛𐑼𐑟; 𐑢𐑲𐑤 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚 𐑯 ·𐑓𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑒—𐑣𐑵 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑕𐑥𐑷𐑤 𐑛𐑦𐑜𐑮𐑰 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑖𐑺𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑰𐑤𐑦𐑙𐑟—𐑤𐑲𐑒𐑢𐑲𐑟 𐑳𐑯𐑥𐑻𐑥𐑼𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑨𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑧𐑕𐑑. 𐑨𐑟 𐑓 𐑞 𐑥𐑧𐑯, 𐑞𐑴 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑝 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑤𐑴𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑳𐑥𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑛, 𐑞𐑺 𐑓𐑽 𐑝 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑𐑼 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑓𐑽 𐑝 ·𐑓𐑱𐑑. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹, 𐑞 𐑐𐑱𐑜𐑩𐑯 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑽𐑟 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑱𐑯𐑛 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑦 𐑳𐑯𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑑; 𐑹 𐑦𐑓 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑑, 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑥𐑨𐑜𐑯𐑩𐑑𐑦𐑟𐑩𐑥 𐑖𐑪𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞𐑺 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑡𐑰𐑯𐑾𐑤 𐑣𐑸𐑑𐑕 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑦𐑯𐑓𐑤𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚'𐑟.

𐑓 𐑩 𐑕𐑐𐑱𐑕 𐑞 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑢𐑷𐑒𐑑 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑒 𐑦𐑯 𐑮𐑴𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑮𐑧𐑝𐑼𐑦𐑟. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑗𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑕𐑤𐑦𐑐 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑲𐑝𐑼𐑦 𐑣𐑰𐑤, 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑷 𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑳𐑖𐑑 𐑒𐑪𐑐𐑼 𐑕𐑲𐑑-𐑑𐑿𐑚𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑞 𐑛𐑱 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑛𐑨𐑖𐑑 𐑑 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑒.

“𐑞𐑬 𐑐𐑫𐑼, 𐑐𐑮𐑬𐑛 𐑣𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑯-𐑜𐑱𐑟𐑼 𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑯'𐑟 𐑐𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑑! 𐑘𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑛𐑱 𐑲 𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑑 𐑞𐑰, 𐑯 𐑑-𐑛𐑱 𐑞 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑓𐑱𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑑 𐑥𐑰. 𐑕𐑴, 𐑕𐑴. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑦𐑟 𐑤𐑹𐑛 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑞 𐑤𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑤 𐑤𐑴𐑛𐑕𐑑𐑴𐑯 𐑘𐑧𐑑. ·𐑥𐑼 ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒—𐑩 𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑕 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑 𐑩 𐑐𐑴𐑤; 𐑩 𐑑𐑪𐑐-𐑥𐑷𐑤, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑥𐑷𐑤𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑤-𐑥𐑱𐑒𐑼'𐑟 𐑯𐑰𐑛𐑩𐑤𐑟. 𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑒!”

𐑩𐑒𐑕𐑧𐑕𐑼𐑦, 𐑐𐑼𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑕, 𐑑 𐑞 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑳𐑤𐑕 𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑑𐑱𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑬 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑑 𐑛𐑵, 𐑢𐑻 𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑐𐑮𐑵𐑛𐑧𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑤 𐑥𐑴𐑑𐑦𐑝𐑟, 𐑣𐑵𐑟 𐑪𐑚𐑡𐑧𐑒𐑑 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑝𐑲𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑦𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑮𐑵 𐑚𐑲 𐑩 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑴𐑒 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑳𐑚𐑑𐑲𐑤 𐑕𐑒𐑦𐑤, 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑥𐑨𐑑𐑼 𐑕𐑴 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑕 𐑨𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑕𐑩𐑟. 𐑚𐑦𐑕𐑲𐑛𐑟, 𐑞 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑢𐑧𐑤 𐑯𐑿 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑽 𐑚𐑲 𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑟𐑐𐑶𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑯𐑰𐑛𐑩𐑤𐑟, 𐑞𐑴 𐑒𐑤𐑳𐑥𐑟𐑦𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑮𐑨𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤, 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑩 𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑐𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑚𐑲 𐑕𐑵𐑐𐑼𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑕 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑼𐑟, 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑖𐑳𐑛𐑼𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑯 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑤 𐑐𐑹𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑕.

“𐑥𐑧𐑯,” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑣𐑰, 𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑦 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑵, 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑥𐑱𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑞 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑛𐑦𐑥𐑭𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛, “𐑥𐑲 𐑥𐑧𐑯, 𐑞 𐑔𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑛 𐑴𐑤𐑛 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚'𐑟 𐑯𐑰𐑛𐑩𐑤𐑟; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑚𐑦𐑑 𐑝 𐑕𐑑𐑰𐑤 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑥𐑱𐑒 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑴𐑯, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑐𐑶𐑯𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑑𐑮𐑵 𐑨𐑟 𐑧𐑯𐑦.”

𐑩𐑚𐑨𐑖𐑑 𐑜𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑝 𐑕𐑻𐑝𐑲𐑤 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑢𐑻 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑗𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑼𐑟, 𐑨𐑟 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑧𐑛; 𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑓𐑨𐑕𐑦𐑯𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑲𐑟 𐑞𐑱 𐑩𐑢𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑪𐑑𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑥𐑨𐑡𐑦𐑒 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑓𐑪𐑤𐑴. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒 𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑑 𐑩𐑢𐑱.

𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑚𐑤𐑴 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑑𐑪𐑐-𐑥𐑷𐑤 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑯𐑪𐑒𐑑 𐑪𐑓 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑰𐑤 𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑝 𐑞 𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑕, 𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑞 𐑥𐑱𐑑 𐑞 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑲𐑼𐑯 𐑮𐑪𐑛 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑱𐑯𐑦𐑙, 𐑚𐑨𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑦𐑑 𐑳𐑐𐑮𐑲𐑑, 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑑𐑳𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑒. 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑥𐑷𐑤, 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑰𐑑𐑩𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑥𐑲𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑳𐑐𐑼 𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑝 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑲𐑼𐑯 𐑮𐑪𐑛, 𐑣𐑰 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕𐑑 𐑞 𐑚𐑤𐑳𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑯𐑰𐑛𐑩𐑤 𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑢𐑲𐑟 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑑𐑪𐑐 𐑝 𐑦𐑑, 𐑯 𐑤𐑧𐑕 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑪𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑣𐑨𐑥𐑼𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑, 𐑕𐑧𐑝𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟, 𐑞 𐑥𐑱𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑮𐑪𐑛 𐑨𐑟 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹. 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑜𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑕𐑥𐑷𐑤 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡 𐑥𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑦𐑑—𐑢𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑑 𐑞 𐑥𐑨𐑜𐑯𐑩𐑑𐑲𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑰𐑤, 𐑹 𐑥𐑽𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑑 𐑷𐑜𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑞 𐑷 𐑝 𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑵, 𐑦𐑟 𐑳𐑯𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑯—𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑛 𐑓 𐑤𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑯 𐑔𐑮𐑧𐑛; 𐑯 𐑥𐑵𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑞 𐑚𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑒𐑩𐑤, 𐑕𐑤𐑦𐑐𐑑 𐑬𐑑 𐑞 𐑑𐑵 𐑮𐑦𐑝𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑯𐑰𐑛𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑞𐑺, 𐑯 𐑣𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑩𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑤-𐑯𐑰𐑛𐑩𐑤 𐑚𐑲 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑥𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑤, 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑕-𐑒𐑸𐑛𐑟. 𐑨𐑑 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑, 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑰𐑤 𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑯 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛, 𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑝𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑯 𐑝𐑲𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑨𐑑 𐑲𐑞𐑼 𐑧𐑯𐑛; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑧𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑑 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚, 𐑣𐑵 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑢𐑪𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑓 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑳𐑤𐑑, 𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑐𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑨𐑒 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑚𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑒𐑩𐑤, 𐑯 𐑐𐑶𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑧𐑗𐑑 𐑸𐑥 𐑑𐑩𐑢𐑹𐑛𐑟 𐑦𐑑, 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑒𐑤𐑱𐑥𐑛,—“𐑤𐑫𐑒 𐑘𐑰, 𐑓 𐑘𐑹𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑝𐑟, 𐑦𐑓 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑚𐑰 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑤𐑹𐑛 𐑝 𐑞 𐑤𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑤 𐑤𐑴𐑛𐑕𐑑𐑴𐑯! 𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑯 𐑦𐑟 ·𐑰𐑕𐑑, 𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑕 𐑕𐑢𐑺𐑟 𐑦𐑑!”

𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑩𐑯𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑞𐑱 𐑐𐑽𐑛 𐑦𐑯, 𐑓 𐑯𐑳𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑴𐑯 𐑲𐑟 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑐𐑼𐑕𐑢𐑱𐑛 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑦𐑜𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑨𐑟 𐑞𐑺𐑟, 𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑩𐑯𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑞𐑱 𐑕𐑤𐑳𐑙𐑒 𐑩𐑢𐑱.

𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑲𐑼𐑦 𐑲𐑟 𐑝 𐑕𐑒𐑹𐑯 𐑯 𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑳𐑥𐑓, 𐑿 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑕𐑷 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑦𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑐𐑮𐑲𐑛.

·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 125. 𐑞 ·𐑤𐑪𐑜 𐑯 ·𐑤𐑲𐑯.

𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑯𐑬 𐑞 𐑓𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑕𐑴 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑩𐑓𐑤𐑴𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑝𐑶𐑦𐑡, 𐑞 𐑤𐑪𐑜 𐑯 𐑤𐑲𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑛𐑩𐑥 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑿𐑕. 𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑩 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑓𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑤𐑲𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑥𐑰𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑛𐑦𐑑𐑻𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑝𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑤'𐑟 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕, 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑥𐑻𐑗𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑥𐑧𐑯, 𐑯 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑥𐑧𐑯, 𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑒𐑮𐑵𐑟𐑦𐑙, 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑦 𐑯𐑦𐑜𐑤𐑧𐑒𐑑 𐑑 𐑣𐑰𐑝 𐑞 𐑤𐑪𐑜; 𐑞𐑴 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑑𐑲𐑥, 𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑥𐑹 𐑓 𐑓𐑹𐑥'𐑟 𐑕𐑱𐑒 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑧𐑯𐑦𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑧𐑤𐑕, 𐑮𐑧𐑜𐑿𐑤𐑼𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑫𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑒𐑳𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑥𐑼𐑦 𐑕𐑤𐑱𐑑 𐑞 𐑒𐑹𐑕 𐑕𐑑𐑽𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐, 𐑨𐑟 𐑢𐑧𐑤 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑿𐑥𐑛 𐑨𐑝𐑼𐑦𐑡 𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑝 𐑐𐑮𐑴𐑜𐑮𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑬𐑼. 𐑦𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑞𐑳𐑕 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛. 𐑞 𐑢𐑫𐑛𐑩𐑯 𐑮𐑰𐑤 𐑯 𐑨𐑙𐑜𐑿𐑤𐑼 𐑤𐑪𐑜 𐑩𐑑𐑨𐑗𐑑 𐑣𐑳𐑙, 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑳𐑯𐑑𐑳𐑗𐑑, 𐑡𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑯𐑰𐑔 𐑞 𐑮𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑞 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑚𐑫𐑤𐑢𐑼𐑒𐑕. 𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑟 𐑯 𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑱 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑛𐑨𐑥𐑐𐑑 𐑦𐑑; 𐑕𐑳𐑯 𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑢𐑹𐑐𐑑 𐑦𐑑; 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑚𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑑 𐑮𐑪𐑑 𐑩 𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑳𐑙 𐑕𐑴 𐑲𐑛𐑤𐑦. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑣𐑰𐑛𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑦𐑕, 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑵𐑛 𐑕𐑰𐑟𐑛 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚, 𐑨𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑑 𐑜𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑕 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑮𐑰𐑤, 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑬𐑼𐑟 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑞 𐑥𐑨𐑜𐑯𐑩𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑯, 𐑯 𐑣𐑰 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑧𐑥𐑚𐑼𐑛 𐑣𐑬 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑴 𐑥𐑹, 𐑯 𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑴𐑔 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑞 𐑤𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑤 𐑤𐑪𐑜 𐑯 𐑤𐑲𐑯. 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑐𐑤𐑳𐑯𐑡𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦; 𐑩𐑕𐑑𐑻𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑴𐑟 𐑮𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑮𐑲𐑩𐑑𐑕.

“𐑓𐑹𐑢𐑼𐑛, 𐑞𐑺! 𐑣𐑰𐑝 𐑞 𐑤𐑪𐑜!”

𐑑𐑵 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑒𐑱𐑥. 𐑞 𐑜𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑩𐑯-𐑣𐑿𐑛 ·𐑑𐑭𐑣𐑰𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑯 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑤𐑦 ·𐑥𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑕𐑥𐑩𐑯. “𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑞 𐑮𐑰𐑤, 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑘𐑰, 𐑲'𐑤 𐑣𐑰𐑝.”

𐑞𐑱 𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑑𐑩𐑢𐑹𐑛𐑟 𐑞 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑰𐑥 𐑕𐑑𐑻𐑯, 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐'𐑕 𐑤𐑰 𐑕𐑲𐑛, 𐑢𐑺 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑒, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑴𐑚𐑤𐑰𐑒 𐑧𐑯𐑼𐑡𐑦 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛, 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑬 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑰𐑥𐑦, 𐑕𐑲𐑛𐑤𐑪𐑙-𐑮𐑳𐑖𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑰.

𐑞 ·𐑥𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑕𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑑𐑫𐑒 𐑞 𐑮𐑰𐑤, 𐑯 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑑 𐑣𐑲 𐑳𐑐, 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑡𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑤-𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑤, 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑵𐑤 𐑝 𐑤𐑲𐑯 𐑮𐑦𐑝𐑪𐑤𐑝𐑛, 𐑕𐑴 𐑕𐑑𐑫𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑨𐑙𐑜𐑿𐑤𐑼 𐑤𐑪𐑜 𐑣𐑨𐑙𐑦𐑙 𐑛𐑬𐑯𐑢𐑼𐑛𐑟, 𐑑𐑦𐑤 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑩𐑛𐑝𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥.

𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑕𐑑𐑫𐑛 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑤𐑲𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑳𐑯𐑢𐑲𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑔𐑻𐑑𐑦 𐑹 𐑓𐑹𐑑𐑦 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑟 𐑑 𐑓𐑹𐑥 𐑩 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑼𐑦 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛-𐑒𐑶𐑤 𐑑 𐑑𐑪𐑕 𐑴𐑝𐑼𐑚𐑹𐑛, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑞 𐑴𐑤𐑛 ·𐑥𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑕𐑥𐑩𐑯, 𐑣𐑵 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑲𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑴𐑔 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑯 𐑞 𐑤𐑲𐑯, 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑚𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑑 𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑒.

“𐑕𐑻, 𐑲 𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑑; 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑤𐑲𐑯 𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑕 𐑓𐑸 𐑜𐑪𐑯, 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑣𐑰𐑑 𐑯 𐑢𐑧𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑕𐑐𐑶𐑤𐑛 𐑦𐑑.”

“'𐑑𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛, 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑥𐑩𐑯. 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑣𐑰𐑑 𐑯 𐑢𐑧𐑑, 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑞𐑱 𐑕𐑐𐑶𐑤𐑛 𐑞𐑰? 𐑞𐑬 𐑕𐑰𐑥'𐑕𐑑 𐑑 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛. 𐑹, 𐑑𐑮𐑵𐑼 𐑐𐑼𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑕, 𐑤𐑲𐑓 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑟 𐑞𐑰; 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑞𐑬 𐑦𐑑.”

“𐑲 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑵𐑤, 𐑕𐑻. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑡𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑥𐑲 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑧𐑟. 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑜𐑮𐑱 𐑣𐑺𐑟 𐑝 𐑥𐑲𐑯 '𐑑𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑢𐑻𐑔 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑿𐑑𐑦𐑙, '𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑕𐑵𐑐𐑽𐑽, 𐑣𐑵'𐑤 𐑯𐑺 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑓𐑧𐑕.”

“𐑢𐑪𐑑'𐑕 𐑞𐑨𐑑? 𐑞𐑺 𐑯𐑬'𐑟 𐑩 𐑐𐑨𐑗𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑓𐑧𐑕𐑼 𐑦𐑯 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑯 ·𐑯𐑱𐑗𐑼'𐑟 𐑜𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑑-𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 ·𐑒𐑪𐑤𐑦𐑡; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑥𐑦𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑕 𐑣𐑰'𐑟 𐑑𐑵 𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑕𐑻𐑝𐑾𐑯𐑑. 𐑢𐑺 ·𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑑 𐑞𐑬 𐑚𐑹𐑯?”

“𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑮𐑪𐑒𐑦 ·𐑲𐑤 𐑝 ·𐑥𐑨𐑯, 𐑕𐑻.”

“𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑩𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑑! 𐑞𐑬'𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑑 𐑞 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑞𐑨𐑑.”

“𐑲 𐑯𐑴 𐑯𐑪𐑑, 𐑕𐑻, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑲 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑚𐑹𐑯 𐑞𐑺.”

“𐑦𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑲𐑤 𐑝 ·𐑥𐑨𐑯, 𐑣𐑱? 𐑢𐑧𐑤, 𐑞 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑢𐑱, 𐑦𐑑'𐑕 𐑜𐑫𐑛. 𐑣𐑽'𐑟 𐑩 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 ·𐑥𐑨𐑯; 𐑩 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑚𐑹𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑕 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑑 ·𐑥𐑨𐑯, 𐑯 𐑯𐑬 𐑳𐑯𐑥𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑝 ·𐑥𐑨𐑯; 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑳𐑒𐑑 𐑦𐑯—𐑚𐑲 𐑢𐑪𐑑? 𐑳𐑐 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑮𐑰𐑤! 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑛, 𐑚𐑤𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑢𐑷𐑤 𐑚𐑳𐑑𐑕 𐑷𐑤 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑢𐑲𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑟 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑. 𐑳𐑐 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑦𐑑! 𐑕𐑴.”

𐑞 𐑤𐑪𐑜 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑣𐑰𐑝𐑛. 𐑞 𐑤𐑵𐑕 𐑒𐑶𐑤𐑟 𐑮𐑨𐑐𐑦𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑬𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑛𐑮𐑨𐑜𐑦𐑙 𐑤𐑲𐑯 𐑩𐑕𐑑𐑻𐑯, 𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦, 𐑞 𐑮𐑰𐑤 𐑚𐑦𐑜𐑨𐑯 𐑑 𐑢𐑻𐑤. 𐑦𐑯 𐑑𐑻𐑯, 𐑡𐑻𐑒𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑱𐑟𐑛 𐑯 𐑤𐑴𐑼𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑮𐑴𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑴𐑟, 𐑞 𐑑𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑤𐑪𐑜 𐑒𐑷𐑟𐑛 𐑞 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑮𐑰𐑤𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑜𐑼 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑤𐑦.

“𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑣𐑸𐑛!”

𐑕𐑯𐑨𐑐! 𐑞 𐑴𐑝𐑼𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑛 𐑤𐑲𐑯 𐑕𐑨𐑜𐑛 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑓𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑵𐑯; 𐑞 𐑑𐑳𐑜𐑦𐑙 𐑤𐑪𐑜 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑜𐑪𐑯.

“𐑲 𐑒𐑮𐑳𐑖 𐑞 𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑯𐑑, 𐑞 𐑔𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑟 𐑞 𐑯𐑰𐑛𐑩𐑤𐑟, 𐑯 𐑯𐑬 𐑞 𐑥𐑨𐑛 𐑕𐑰 𐑐𐑸𐑑𐑕 𐑞 𐑤𐑪𐑜-𐑤𐑲𐑯. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑷𐑤. 𐑣𐑷𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑽, ·𐑑𐑭𐑣𐑰𐑖𐑩𐑯; 𐑮𐑰𐑤 𐑳𐑐, ·𐑥𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑕𐑥𐑩𐑯. 𐑯 𐑤𐑫𐑒 𐑘𐑰, 𐑤𐑧𐑑 𐑞 𐑒𐑸𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑼 𐑥𐑱𐑒 𐑩𐑯𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑤𐑪𐑜, 𐑯 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑞𐑬 𐑞 𐑤𐑲𐑯. 𐑕𐑰 𐑑 𐑦𐑑.”

“𐑞𐑺 𐑣𐑰 𐑜𐑴𐑟 𐑯𐑬; 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑯𐑳𐑔𐑦𐑙'𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑛; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑑 𐑥𐑰, 𐑞 𐑕𐑒𐑿𐑼 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑟 𐑤𐑵𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑥𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛. 𐑣𐑷𐑤 𐑦𐑯, 𐑣𐑷𐑤 𐑦𐑯, ·𐑑𐑭𐑣𐑰𐑖𐑩𐑯! 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑤𐑲𐑯𐑟 𐑮𐑳𐑯 𐑣𐑴𐑤, 𐑯 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑬𐑑: 𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑦𐑯 𐑚𐑮𐑴𐑒𐑩𐑯, 𐑯 𐑛𐑮𐑨𐑜𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑤𐑴. 𐑣𐑭, ·𐑐𐑦𐑐? 𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑑 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑐; 𐑱, ·𐑐𐑦𐑐?”

“𐑐𐑦𐑐? 𐑣𐑵𐑥 𐑒𐑷𐑤 𐑘𐑰 ·𐑐𐑦𐑐? 𐑐𐑦𐑐 𐑡𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤-𐑚𐑴𐑑. 𐑐𐑦𐑐'𐑕 𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑦𐑙. 𐑤𐑧𐑑'𐑕 𐑕𐑰 𐑯𐑬 𐑦𐑓 𐑘𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑝𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑳𐑐 𐑣𐑽, 𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑼𐑥𐑩𐑯. 𐑦𐑑 𐑛𐑮𐑨𐑜𐑟 𐑣𐑸𐑛; 𐑲 𐑜𐑧𐑕 𐑣𐑰'𐑟 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑪𐑯. 𐑡𐑻𐑒 𐑣𐑦𐑥, ·𐑑𐑭𐑣𐑰𐑑𐑦! 𐑡𐑻𐑒 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑪𐑓; 𐑢𐑰 𐑣𐑷𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑯𐑴 𐑒𐑬𐑼𐑛𐑟 𐑣𐑽. 𐑣𐑴! 𐑞𐑺'𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑸𐑥 𐑡𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼. 𐑩 𐑣𐑨𐑗𐑩𐑑! 𐑩 𐑣𐑨𐑗𐑩𐑑! 𐑒𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑪𐑓—𐑢𐑰 𐑣𐑷𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑯𐑴 𐑒𐑬𐑼𐑛𐑟 𐑣𐑽. 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚! 𐑕𐑻, 𐑕𐑻! 𐑣𐑽'𐑟 ·𐑐𐑦𐑐, 𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑜𐑧𐑑 𐑪𐑯 𐑚𐑹𐑛 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯.”

“𐑐𐑰𐑕, 𐑞𐑬 𐑒𐑮𐑱𐑟𐑦 𐑤𐑵𐑯,” 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 𐑞 ·𐑥𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑕𐑥𐑩𐑯, 𐑕𐑰𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑸𐑥. “𐑩𐑢𐑱 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑒𐑢𐑹𐑑𐑼-𐑛𐑧𐑒!”

“𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑𐑼 𐑦𐑛𐑾𐑑 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑕𐑒𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑟 𐑞 𐑤𐑧𐑕𐑼,” 𐑥𐑳𐑑𐑼𐑛 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚, 𐑩𐑛𐑝𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑙. “𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑪𐑓 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑕! 𐑢𐑺 𐑕𐑱𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑞𐑬 ·𐑐𐑦𐑐 𐑢𐑪𐑟, 𐑚𐑶?

“𐑩𐑕𐑑𐑻𐑯 𐑞𐑺, 𐑕𐑻, 𐑩𐑕𐑑𐑻𐑯! 𐑤𐑴! 𐑤𐑴!”

“𐑯 𐑣𐑵 𐑸𐑑 𐑞𐑬, 𐑚𐑶? 𐑲 𐑕𐑰 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑥𐑲 𐑮𐑦𐑓𐑤𐑧𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑝𐑱𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑐𐑿𐑐𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑝 𐑞𐑲 𐑲𐑟. 𐑴 ·𐑜𐑪𐑛! 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑚𐑰 𐑩 𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑓 𐑦𐑥𐑹𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑴𐑤𐑟 𐑑 𐑕𐑦𐑝 𐑔𐑮𐑵! 𐑣𐑵 𐑸𐑑 𐑞𐑬, 𐑚𐑶?”

“𐑚𐑧𐑤-𐑚𐑶, 𐑕𐑻; 𐑖𐑦𐑐'𐑕-𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑼; 𐑛𐑦𐑙, 𐑛𐑪𐑙, 𐑛𐑦𐑙! 𐑐𐑦𐑐! 𐑐𐑦𐑐! 𐑐𐑦𐑐! 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑛 𐑐𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑝 𐑒𐑤𐑱 𐑮𐑦𐑢𐑹𐑛 𐑓 ·𐑐𐑦𐑐; 𐑓𐑲𐑝 𐑓𐑰𐑑 𐑣𐑲—𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑕 𐑒𐑬𐑼𐑛𐑤𐑦—𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑯𐑴𐑯 𐑚𐑲 𐑞𐑨𐑑! 𐑛𐑦𐑙, 𐑛𐑪𐑙, 𐑛𐑦𐑙! 𐑣𐑵'𐑟 𐑕𐑰𐑯 ·𐑐𐑦𐑐 𐑞 𐑒𐑬𐑼𐑛?”

“𐑞𐑺 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑚𐑰 𐑯𐑴 𐑣𐑸𐑑𐑕 𐑩𐑚𐑳𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑯𐑴-𐑤𐑲𐑯. 𐑴, 𐑘𐑰 𐑓𐑮𐑴𐑟𐑩𐑯 𐑣𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑯𐑟! 𐑤𐑫𐑒 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑣𐑽. 𐑘𐑰 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑚𐑦𐑜𐑧𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑤𐑳𐑒𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑗𐑲𐑤𐑛, 𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑩𐑚𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑘𐑰 𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑱𐑑𐑦𐑝 𐑤𐑦𐑚𐑼𐑑𐑰𐑯𐑟. 𐑣𐑽, 𐑚𐑶; ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚'𐑟 𐑒𐑨𐑚𐑦𐑯 𐑖𐑨𐑤 𐑚𐑰 ·𐑐𐑦𐑐'𐑕 𐑣𐑴𐑥 𐑣𐑧𐑯𐑕𐑓𐑹𐑔, 𐑢𐑲𐑤 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑤𐑦𐑝𐑟. 𐑞𐑬 ·𐑑𐑬𐑗𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑥𐑲 𐑦𐑯𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑼, 𐑚𐑶; 𐑞𐑬 𐑸𐑑 𐑑𐑲𐑛 𐑑 𐑥𐑰 𐑚𐑲 𐑒𐑹𐑛𐑟 𐑢𐑴𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑥𐑲 𐑣𐑸𐑑-𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑙𐑟. 𐑒𐑳𐑥, 𐑤𐑧𐑑'𐑕 𐑛𐑬𐑯.”

“𐑢𐑪𐑑'𐑕 𐑞𐑦𐑕? 𐑣𐑽'𐑟 𐑝𐑧𐑤𐑝𐑩𐑑 𐑖𐑸𐑒-𐑕𐑒𐑦𐑯,” 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑜𐑱𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑨𐑑 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚'𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛, 𐑯 𐑓𐑰𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑑. “𐑭, 𐑯𐑬, 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑐𐑫𐑼 ·𐑐𐑦𐑐 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑓𐑧𐑤𐑑 𐑕𐑴 𐑒𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑩 𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑨𐑟 𐑞𐑦𐑕, 𐑐𐑼𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑕 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑯𐑺 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑤𐑪𐑕𐑑! 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑟 𐑑 𐑥𐑰, 𐑕𐑻, 𐑨𐑟 𐑩 𐑥𐑨𐑯-𐑮𐑴𐑐; 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑰𐑒 𐑕𐑴𐑤𐑟 𐑥𐑱 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑚𐑲. 𐑴, 𐑕𐑻, 𐑤𐑧𐑑 𐑴𐑤𐑛 ·𐑐𐑻𐑔 𐑯𐑬 𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑯 𐑮𐑦𐑝𐑩𐑑 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑑𐑵 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑑𐑩𐑜𐑧𐑞𐑼; 𐑞 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑒 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑢𐑲𐑑, 𐑓 𐑲 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑤𐑧𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑜𐑴.”

“𐑴, 𐑚𐑶, 𐑯𐑹 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑲 𐑞𐑰, 𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑧𐑕 𐑲 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑞𐑺𐑚𐑲 𐑛𐑮𐑨𐑜 𐑞𐑰 𐑑 𐑢𐑻𐑕 𐑣𐑪𐑮𐑼𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑸 𐑣𐑽. 𐑒𐑳𐑥, 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑑 𐑥𐑲 𐑒𐑨𐑚𐑦𐑯. 𐑤𐑴! 𐑘𐑰 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑰𐑝𐑼𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑜𐑪𐑛𐑟 𐑷𐑤 𐑜𐑫𐑛𐑯𐑩𐑕, 𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑦𐑤, 𐑤𐑴 𐑿! 𐑕𐑰 𐑞 𐑪𐑥𐑯𐑦𐑕𐑾𐑯𐑑 𐑜𐑪𐑛𐑟 𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑦𐑝𐑾𐑕 𐑝 𐑕𐑳𐑓𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑨𐑯; 𐑯 𐑥𐑨𐑯, 𐑞𐑴 𐑦𐑛𐑦𐑪𐑑𐑦𐑒, 𐑯 𐑯𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑛𐑳𐑟, 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑓𐑫𐑤 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑢𐑰𐑑 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑝 𐑤𐑳𐑝 𐑯 𐑜𐑮𐑨𐑑𐑦𐑑𐑿𐑛. 𐑒𐑳𐑥! 𐑲 𐑓𐑰𐑤 𐑐𐑮𐑬𐑛𐑼 𐑤𐑰𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑰 𐑚𐑲 𐑞𐑲 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑒 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛, 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑞𐑴 𐑲 𐑜𐑮𐑭𐑕𐑐𐑑 𐑩𐑯 ·𐑧𐑥𐑐𐑼𐑼'𐑟!”

“𐑞𐑺 𐑜𐑴 𐑑𐑵 𐑛𐑭𐑓𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑟 𐑯𐑬,” 𐑥𐑳𐑑𐑼𐑛 𐑞 𐑴𐑤𐑛 ·𐑥𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑕𐑥𐑩𐑯. “𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑛𐑭𐑓𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑧𐑙𐑔, 𐑞 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑛𐑭𐑓𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑯𐑩𐑕. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑣𐑽'𐑟 𐑞 𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑝 𐑞 𐑮𐑪𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑤𐑲𐑯—𐑷𐑤 𐑛𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑦𐑙, 𐑑𐑵. 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑑, 𐑱? 𐑲 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒 𐑢𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑩 𐑯𐑿 𐑤𐑲𐑯 𐑷𐑤𐑑𐑩𐑜𐑧𐑞𐑼. 𐑲'𐑤 𐑕𐑰 ·𐑥𐑼 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑦𐑑.”

·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 126. 𐑞 ·𐑤𐑲𐑓-·𐑚𐑶.

𐑕𐑑𐑽𐑦𐑙 𐑯𐑬 𐑕𐑬𐑔-𐑰𐑕𐑑𐑢𐑼𐑛 𐑚𐑲 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚'𐑟 𐑤𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑕𐑑𐑰𐑤, 𐑯 𐑣𐑻 𐑐𐑮𐑴𐑜𐑮𐑧𐑕 𐑕𐑴𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑦𐑑𐑻𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑛 𐑚𐑲 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚'𐑟 𐑤𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑤 𐑤𐑪𐑜 𐑯 𐑤𐑲𐑯; 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑛 𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑻 𐑐𐑭𐑔 𐑑𐑩𐑢𐑹𐑛𐑟 𐑞 ·𐑦𐑒𐑢𐑱𐑑𐑼. 𐑥𐑱𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑴 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑩 𐑐𐑨𐑕𐑦𐑡 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑳𐑯𐑓𐑮𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼𐑟, 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑦𐑙 𐑯𐑴 𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑕, 𐑯 𐑺 𐑤𐑪𐑙, 𐑕𐑲𐑛𐑢𐑱𐑟 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑧𐑤𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑳𐑯𐑝𐑺𐑦𐑦𐑙 𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑟, 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑢𐑱𐑝𐑟 𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑪𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑥𐑲𐑤𐑛; 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡 𐑒𐑭𐑥 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑤𐑿𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑮𐑲𐑩𐑑𐑩𐑕 𐑯 𐑛𐑧𐑕𐑐𐑼𐑩𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑯.

𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑛𐑮𐑵 𐑯𐑽 𐑑 𐑞 𐑬𐑑𐑕𐑒𐑻𐑑𐑕, 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑻, 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑧𐑒𐑢𐑩𐑑𐑹𐑾𐑤 𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑦𐑙-𐑜𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛, 𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑛𐑰𐑐 𐑛𐑸𐑒𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑜𐑴𐑟 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑞 𐑛𐑷𐑯, 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑲 𐑩 𐑒𐑤𐑳𐑕𐑑𐑼 𐑝 𐑮𐑪𐑒𐑦 𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑑𐑕; 𐑞 𐑢𐑪𐑗—𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑲 ·𐑓𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑒—𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑩 𐑒𐑮𐑲 𐑕𐑴 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑝𐑤𐑦 𐑢𐑲𐑤𐑛 𐑯 𐑳𐑯𐑻𐑔𐑤𐑦—𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑣𐑭𐑓-𐑸𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑜𐑴𐑕𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑷𐑤 ·𐑣𐑧𐑮𐑩𐑛'𐑟 𐑥𐑻𐑛𐑼𐑛 ·𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕—𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑯 𐑷𐑤, 𐑞𐑱 𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞𐑺 𐑮𐑧𐑝𐑼𐑦𐑟, 𐑯 𐑓 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑱𐑕 𐑝 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑥𐑴𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑕𐑑𐑫𐑛, 𐑹 𐑕𐑨𐑑, 𐑹 𐑤𐑰𐑯𐑛 𐑷𐑤 𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑕𐑓𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑩𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑤𐑦𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑙, 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑞 𐑒𐑸𐑝𐑛 ·𐑮𐑴𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑕𐑤𐑱𐑝, 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑲𐑤𐑛 𐑒𐑮𐑲 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑱𐑯𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑽𐑦𐑙. 𐑞 ·𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑗𐑩𐑯 𐑹 𐑕𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑤𐑲𐑟𐑛 𐑐𐑸𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑵 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑥𐑻𐑥𐑱𐑛𐑟, 𐑯 𐑖𐑳𐑛𐑼𐑛; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞 𐑐𐑱𐑜𐑩𐑯 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑽𐑟 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑱𐑯𐑛 𐑳𐑯𐑩𐑐𐑷𐑤𐑛. 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑱 ·𐑥𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑕𐑥𐑩𐑯—𐑞 𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑥𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑯𐑼 𐑝 𐑷𐑤—𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑺𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑢𐑲𐑤𐑛 𐑔𐑮𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑻 𐑣𐑻𐑛, 𐑢𐑻 𐑞 𐑝𐑶𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑝 𐑯𐑿𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑰.

𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑴 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑥𐑩𐑒, ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑣𐑽 𐑝 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑜𐑮𐑱 𐑛𐑷𐑯, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑱𐑥 𐑑 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑒; 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑚𐑲 ·𐑓𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑒, 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑳𐑯𐑩𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑛𐑸𐑒 𐑥𐑰𐑯𐑦𐑙𐑟. 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑪𐑤𐑴𐑤𐑦 𐑤𐑭𐑓𐑑, 𐑯 𐑞𐑳𐑕 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑯𐑛 𐑞 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼.

𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑮𐑪𐑒𐑦 𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑐𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑢𐑻 𐑞 𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑹𐑑 𐑝 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑯𐑳𐑥𐑚𐑼𐑟 𐑝 𐑕𐑰𐑤𐑟, 𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑘𐑳𐑙 𐑕𐑰𐑤𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑤𐑪𐑕𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑛𐑨𐑥𐑟, 𐑹 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑛𐑨𐑥𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑤𐑪𐑕𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑒𐑳𐑚𐑟, 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑩𐑯 𐑯𐑲 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑯 𐑒𐑧𐑐𐑑 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑦 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑻, 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑦𐑙 𐑯 𐑕𐑪𐑚𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞𐑺 𐑣𐑿𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑕𐑹𐑑 𐑝 𐑢𐑱𐑤. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑞 𐑥𐑹 𐑩𐑓𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑝 𐑞𐑧𐑥, 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑪𐑟 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑥𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑯𐑼𐑟 𐑗𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑖 𐑩 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑕𐑵𐑐𐑼𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑕 𐑓𐑰𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑤𐑟, 𐑼𐑲𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞𐑺 𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑽 𐑑𐑴𐑯𐑟 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑧𐑕, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑷𐑤𐑕𐑴 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑣𐑿𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑤𐑫𐑒 𐑝 𐑞𐑺 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑟 𐑯 𐑕𐑧𐑥𐑦-𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑡𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑓𐑱𐑕𐑩𐑟, 𐑕𐑰𐑯 𐑐𐑽𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑳𐑐𐑮𐑲𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑙𐑕𐑲𐑛. 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑰, 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑕𐑻𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟, 𐑕𐑰𐑤𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑥𐑹 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑕 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑓 𐑥𐑧𐑯.

𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑛𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑵 𐑢𐑻 𐑛𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑛 𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑰𐑝 𐑩 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑐𐑤𐑷𐑟𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑓𐑼𐑥𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑱𐑑 𐑝 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑞𐑺 𐑯𐑳𐑥𐑚𐑼 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑹𐑯𐑦𐑙. 𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑯-𐑮𐑲𐑟 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑥𐑩𐑒 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑-𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑓𐑹; 𐑯 𐑢𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑣𐑭𐑓 𐑢𐑱𐑒𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑤𐑰𐑐 (𐑓 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑼𐑟 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑜𐑴 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑓𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑟𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑑), 𐑢𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞𐑳𐑕 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑥𐑨𐑯, 𐑞𐑺 𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑬 𐑯𐑴 𐑑𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑙; 𐑚𐑳𐑑, 𐑚𐑰 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑥𐑱, 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑻𐑗, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑩 𐑒𐑮𐑲 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑣𐑻𐑛—𐑩 𐑒𐑮𐑲 𐑯 𐑩 𐑮𐑳𐑖𐑦𐑙—𐑯 𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑳𐑐, 𐑞𐑱 𐑕𐑷 𐑩 𐑓𐑷𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑥 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑺; 𐑯 𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑛𐑬𐑯, 𐑩 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑑𐑪𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑰𐑐 𐑝 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑚𐑳𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑤𐑵 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑰.

𐑞 𐑤𐑲𐑓-𐑚𐑶—𐑩 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑕𐑤𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑒𐑭𐑕𐑒—𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑛𐑮𐑪𐑐𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑻𐑯, 𐑢𐑺 𐑦𐑑 𐑷𐑤𐑢𐑱𐑟 𐑣𐑳𐑙 𐑴𐑚𐑰𐑛𐑾𐑯𐑑 𐑑 𐑩 𐑒𐑳𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑙; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑯𐑴 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑮𐑴𐑟 𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑟 𐑦𐑑, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑚𐑰𐑑 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑒𐑭𐑕𐑒 𐑦𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑖𐑮𐑳𐑙𐑒𐑩𐑯, 𐑕𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑤𐑴𐑤𐑦 𐑓𐑦𐑤𐑛, 𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑐𐑸𐑗𐑑 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑷𐑤𐑕𐑴 𐑓𐑦𐑤𐑛 𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑐𐑹; 𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑲𐑼𐑯-𐑚𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑒𐑭𐑕𐑒 𐑓𐑪𐑤𐑴𐑛 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑼 𐑑 𐑞 𐑚𐑪𐑑𐑩𐑥, 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑓 𐑑 𐑘𐑰𐑤𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑦𐑤𐑴, 𐑞𐑴 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑵𐑔 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑩 𐑣𐑸𐑛 𐑢𐑳𐑯.

𐑯 𐑞𐑳𐑕 𐑞 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑞 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑑 𐑤𐑫𐑒 𐑬𐑑 𐑓 𐑞 ·𐑢𐑲𐑑 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑢𐑲𐑑 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤'𐑟 𐑴𐑯 𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑽 𐑜𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛; 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑢𐑪𐑤𐑴𐑛 𐑳𐑐 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑛𐑰𐑐. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑓𐑿, 𐑐𐑼𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑕, 𐑔𐑷𐑑 𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑑𐑲𐑥. 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑰𐑛, 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑕𐑹𐑑, 𐑞𐑱 𐑢𐑻 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑝𐑛 𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑦𐑝𐑧𐑯𐑑, 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑰𐑕𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑩 𐑐𐑹𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑑; 𐑓 𐑞𐑱 𐑮𐑦𐑜𐑸𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑑, 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑩 𐑓𐑹𐑖𐑨𐑛𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑿𐑗𐑼, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑓𐑫𐑤𐑓𐑦𐑤𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑩𐑯 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑤 𐑷𐑤𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑦 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑱𐑡𐑛. 𐑞𐑱 𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑺𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑯𐑬 𐑞𐑱 𐑯𐑿 𐑞 𐑮𐑰𐑟𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑢𐑲𐑤𐑛 𐑖𐑮𐑰𐑒𐑕 𐑞𐑱 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑣𐑻𐑛 𐑞 𐑯𐑲𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯 𐑞 𐑴𐑤𐑛 ·𐑥𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑕𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑯𐑱.

𐑞 𐑤𐑪𐑕𐑑 𐑤𐑲𐑓-𐑚𐑶 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑬 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕𐑑; ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑛𐑦𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑑 𐑕𐑰 𐑑 𐑦𐑑; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑯𐑴 𐑒𐑭𐑕𐑒 𐑝 𐑕𐑩𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑤𐑲𐑑𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑚𐑰 𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛, 𐑯 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑰𐑝𐑼𐑦𐑖 𐑰𐑜𐑼𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑞 𐑩𐑐𐑮𐑴𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑕𐑦𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑝𐑶𐑦𐑡, 𐑷𐑤 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑑𐑶𐑤 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑛𐑦𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑓𐑲𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑧𐑯𐑛, 𐑢𐑪𐑑𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑵𐑝 𐑑 𐑚𐑰; 𐑞𐑺𐑓𐑹, 𐑞𐑱 𐑢𐑻 𐑜𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑤𐑰𐑝 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐'𐑕 𐑕𐑑𐑻𐑯 𐑳𐑯𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑝𐑲𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑚𐑶, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑚𐑲 𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡 𐑕𐑲𐑯𐑟 𐑯 𐑲𐑯𐑿𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑳𐑟 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜 𐑣𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑩 𐑣𐑦𐑯𐑑 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑪𐑓𐑦𐑯.

“𐑩 𐑤𐑲𐑓-𐑚𐑶 𐑝 𐑩 𐑒𐑪𐑓𐑦𐑯!” 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒, 𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑑𐑦𐑙.

“𐑮𐑭𐑞𐑼 𐑒𐑢𐑽, 𐑞𐑨𐑑, 𐑲 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑕𐑱,” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚.

“𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑥𐑱𐑒 𐑩 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑳𐑓 𐑢𐑳𐑯,” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 ·𐑓𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑒, “𐑞 𐑒𐑸𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑼 𐑣𐑽 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑼𐑱𐑯𐑡 𐑦𐑑 𐑰𐑟𐑦𐑤𐑦.”

“𐑚𐑮𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑑 𐑳𐑐; 𐑞𐑺'𐑟 𐑯𐑳𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑧𐑤𐑕 𐑓 𐑦𐑑,” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒, 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑩 𐑥𐑧𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑒𐑪𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑷𐑟. “𐑮𐑦𐑜 𐑦𐑑, 𐑒𐑸𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑼; 𐑛𐑵 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑤𐑫𐑒 𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑰 𐑕𐑴—𐑞 𐑒𐑪𐑓𐑦𐑯, 𐑲 𐑥𐑰𐑯. 𐑛𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑞𐑬 𐑣𐑽 𐑥𐑰? 𐑮𐑦𐑜 𐑦𐑑.”

“𐑯 𐑖𐑨𐑤 𐑲 𐑯𐑱𐑤 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑞 𐑤𐑦𐑛, 𐑕𐑻?” 𐑥𐑵𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑨𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑣𐑨𐑥𐑼.

“𐑲.”

“𐑯 𐑖𐑨𐑤 𐑲 𐑒𐑷𐑒 𐑞 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑟, 𐑕𐑻?” 𐑥𐑵𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑨𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑒𐑷𐑒𐑦𐑙-𐑲𐑼𐑯.

“𐑲.”

“𐑯 𐑖𐑨𐑤 𐑲 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑐𐑱 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑐𐑦𐑗, 𐑕𐑻?” 𐑥𐑵𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑨𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑐𐑦𐑗-𐑐𐑪𐑑.

“𐑩𐑢𐑱! 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑐𐑩𐑟𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑞𐑰 𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕? 𐑥𐑱𐑒 𐑩 𐑤𐑲𐑓-𐑚𐑶 𐑝 𐑞 𐑒𐑪𐑓𐑦𐑯, 𐑯 𐑯𐑴 𐑥𐑹.—·𐑥𐑼 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚, ·𐑥𐑼 ·𐑓𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑒, 𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑓𐑹𐑢𐑼𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑥𐑰.”

“𐑣𐑰 𐑜𐑴𐑟 𐑪𐑓 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑣𐑳𐑓. 𐑞 𐑣𐑴𐑤 𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑻; 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑐𐑸𐑑𐑕 𐑣𐑰 𐑚𐑷𐑒𐑕. 𐑯𐑬 𐑲 𐑛𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑞𐑦𐑕. 𐑲 𐑥𐑱𐑒 𐑩 𐑤𐑧𐑜 𐑓 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚, 𐑯 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑺𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑥𐑩𐑯; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑲 𐑥𐑱𐑒 𐑩 𐑚𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑚𐑪𐑒𐑕 𐑓 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜, 𐑯 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑐𐑫𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑦𐑑. 𐑸 𐑷𐑤 𐑥𐑲 𐑐𐑱𐑯𐑟 𐑑 𐑜𐑴 𐑓 𐑯𐑳𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑒𐑪𐑓𐑦𐑯? 𐑯 𐑯𐑬 𐑲'𐑥 𐑹𐑛𐑼𐑛 𐑑 𐑥𐑱𐑒 𐑩 𐑤𐑲𐑓-𐑚𐑶 𐑝 𐑦𐑑. 𐑦𐑑'𐑕 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑯 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑒𐑴𐑑; 𐑜𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑚𐑮𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑓𐑤𐑧𐑖 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑯𐑬. 𐑲 𐑛𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑒𐑪𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑹𐑑 𐑝 𐑚𐑦𐑟𐑯𐑩𐑕—𐑲 𐑛𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑦𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑷𐑤; 𐑦𐑑'𐑕 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑜𐑯𐑦𐑓𐑲𐑛; 𐑦𐑑'𐑕 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑥𐑲 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕. 𐑤𐑧𐑑 𐑑𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑼𐑟' 𐑚𐑮𐑨𐑑𐑕 𐑛𐑵 𐑑𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑼𐑦𐑙𐑟; 𐑢𐑰 𐑸 𐑞𐑺 𐑚𐑧𐑑𐑼𐑟. 𐑲 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑑 𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑯𐑳𐑯 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑒𐑤𐑰𐑯, 𐑝𐑻𐑡𐑦𐑯, 𐑓𐑺-𐑯-𐑕𐑒𐑢𐑺 𐑥𐑨𐑔𐑩𐑥𐑨𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑡𐑪𐑚𐑟, 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑮𐑧𐑜𐑿𐑤𐑼𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑦𐑜𐑦𐑯𐑟 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑚𐑦𐑜𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑙, 𐑯 𐑦𐑟 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑥𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑥𐑦𐑛𐑢𐑱, 𐑯 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑟 𐑑 𐑩𐑯 𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑒𐑤𐑵𐑠𐑩𐑯; 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑩 𐑒𐑪𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑼'𐑟 𐑡𐑪𐑚, 𐑞𐑨𐑑'𐑕 𐑨𐑑 𐑩𐑯 𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑥𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑤, 𐑯 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑚𐑦𐑜𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑧𐑯𐑛. 𐑦𐑑'𐑕 𐑞 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑢𐑫𐑥𐑩𐑯'𐑟 𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑕 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑜𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑒𐑪𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑡𐑪𐑚𐑟. 𐑤𐑹𐑛! 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑩𐑯 𐑩𐑓𐑧𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑓 𐑑𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑼𐑟. 𐑲 𐑯𐑴 𐑩𐑯 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑢𐑫𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑦-𐑓𐑲𐑝 𐑣𐑵 𐑮𐑨𐑯 𐑩𐑢𐑱 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑚𐑷𐑤𐑛-𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑘𐑳𐑙 𐑑𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑼 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑕. 𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑'𐑕 𐑞 𐑮𐑰𐑟𐑩𐑯 𐑲 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑢𐑻𐑒 𐑓 𐑤𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑢𐑦𐑛𐑴 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑯 𐑩𐑖𐑹, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑲 𐑒𐑧𐑐𐑑 𐑥𐑲 𐑡𐑪𐑚-𐑖𐑪𐑐 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑝𐑦𐑯𐑘𐑼𐑛; 𐑞𐑱 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞𐑺 𐑤𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑟 𐑑 𐑮𐑳𐑯 𐑪𐑓 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑥𐑰. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 ·𐑣𐑱-𐑣𐑴! 𐑞𐑺 𐑸 𐑯𐑴 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑕 𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑰 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑕𐑯𐑴-𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑕. 𐑤𐑧𐑑 𐑥𐑰 𐑕𐑰. 𐑯𐑱𐑤 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑞 𐑤𐑦𐑛; 𐑒𐑷𐑒 𐑞 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑟; 𐑐𐑱 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑐𐑦𐑗; 𐑚𐑨𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑑𐑲𐑑, 𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑙 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑕𐑯𐑨𐑐-𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑙 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐'𐑕 𐑕𐑑𐑻𐑯. 𐑢𐑻 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑛𐑳𐑯 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑒𐑪𐑓𐑦𐑯? 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑕𐑵𐑐𐑼𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑕 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑒𐑸𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑟, 𐑯𐑬, 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑚𐑰 𐑑𐑲𐑛 𐑳𐑐 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑮𐑦𐑜𐑦𐑙, 𐑺 𐑞𐑱 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑛𐑵 𐑞 𐑡𐑪𐑚. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑲'𐑥 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑝 𐑯𐑪𐑑𐑦 ·𐑩𐑮𐑵𐑕𐑑𐑫𐑒 𐑣𐑧𐑥𐑤𐑪𐑒; 𐑲 𐑛𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑚𐑳𐑡. 𐑒𐑮𐑳𐑐𐑼𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑒𐑪𐑓𐑦𐑯! 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑝-𐑘𐑸𐑛 𐑑𐑮𐑱! 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑥𐑲𐑯𐑛. 𐑢𐑰 𐑢𐑻𐑒𐑼𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑫𐑛𐑟 𐑥𐑱𐑒 𐑚𐑮𐑲𐑛𐑩𐑤-𐑚𐑧𐑛𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑛𐑟 𐑯 𐑒𐑸𐑛-𐑑𐑱𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑟, 𐑨𐑟 𐑢𐑧𐑤 𐑨𐑟 𐑒𐑪𐑓𐑦𐑯𐑟 𐑯 𐑣𐑻𐑕𐑩𐑟. 𐑢𐑰 𐑢𐑻𐑒 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑥𐑳𐑯𐑔, 𐑹 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑡𐑪𐑚, 𐑹 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑓𐑦𐑑; 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑓 𐑳𐑕 𐑑 𐑭𐑕𐑒 𐑞 𐑢𐑲 𐑯 𐑢𐑺𐑓𐑹 𐑝 𐑬𐑼 𐑢𐑻𐑒, 𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑧𐑕 𐑦𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑑𐑵 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑒𐑪𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙, 𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑢𐑰 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑖 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑓 𐑢𐑰 𐑒𐑨𐑯. 𐑣𐑧𐑥! 𐑲'𐑤 𐑛𐑵 𐑞 𐑡𐑪𐑚, 𐑯𐑬, 𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑤𐑦. 𐑲'𐑤 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑥𐑰—𐑤𐑧𐑑'𐑕 𐑕𐑰—𐑣𐑬 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐'𐑕 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑦, 𐑷𐑤 𐑑𐑴𐑤𐑛? 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑲'𐑝 𐑓𐑼𐑜𐑪𐑑𐑩𐑯. 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑢𐑱, 𐑲'𐑤 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑥𐑰 𐑔𐑻𐑑𐑦 𐑕𐑧𐑐𐑼𐑩𐑑, ·𐑑𐑻𐑒'𐑕-𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑤𐑲𐑓-𐑤𐑲𐑯𐑟, 𐑰𐑗 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑓𐑰𐑑 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑣𐑨𐑙𐑦𐑙 𐑷𐑤 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑑 𐑞 𐑒𐑪𐑓𐑦𐑯. 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑦𐑓 𐑞 𐑣𐑳𐑤 𐑜𐑴 𐑛𐑬𐑯, 𐑞𐑺'𐑤 𐑚𐑰 𐑔𐑻𐑑𐑦 𐑤𐑲𐑝𐑤𐑦 𐑓𐑧𐑤𐑴𐑟 𐑷𐑤 𐑓𐑲𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑓 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑒𐑪𐑓𐑦𐑯, 𐑩 𐑕𐑲𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑯 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑪𐑓𐑩𐑯 𐑚𐑦𐑯𐑰𐑔 𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑯! 𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑣𐑨𐑥𐑼, 𐑒𐑷𐑒𐑦𐑙-𐑲𐑼𐑯, 𐑐𐑦𐑗-𐑐𐑪𐑑, 𐑯 𐑥𐑸𐑤𐑦𐑙-𐑕𐑐𐑲𐑒! 𐑤𐑧𐑑'𐑕 𐑑 𐑦𐑑.”

·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 127. 𐑞 ·𐑛𐑧𐑒.

𐑞 𐑒𐑪𐑓𐑦𐑯 𐑤𐑱𐑛 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑑𐑵 𐑤𐑲𐑯-𐑑𐑳𐑚𐑟, 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑢𐑰𐑯 𐑞 𐑝𐑲𐑕-𐑚𐑧𐑯𐑗 𐑯 𐑞 𐑴𐑐𐑩𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑗𐑢𐑱; 𐑞 ·𐑒𐑸𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑼 𐑒𐑷𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑟; 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑑𐑢𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑴𐑒𐑩𐑥 𐑕𐑤𐑴𐑤𐑦 𐑳𐑯𐑢𐑲𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑩 𐑤𐑸𐑡 𐑮𐑴𐑤 𐑝 𐑦𐑑 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑫𐑟𐑩𐑥 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑒.—𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑟 𐑕𐑤𐑴𐑤𐑦 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑒𐑨𐑚𐑦𐑯-𐑜𐑨𐑙𐑢𐑱, 𐑯 𐑣𐑽𐑟 ·𐑐𐑦𐑐 𐑓𐑪𐑤𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑥.

“𐑚𐑨𐑒, 𐑤𐑨𐑛; 𐑲 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑚𐑰 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑘𐑰 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦. 𐑣𐑰 𐑜𐑴𐑟! 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑲𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑥𐑲 𐑣𐑿𐑥𐑼 𐑥𐑹 𐑡𐑰𐑯𐑾𐑤𐑦 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑚𐑶.—𐑥𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑤 𐑲𐑤 𐑝 𐑩 𐑗𐑻𐑗! 𐑢𐑪𐑑'𐑕 𐑣𐑽?”

“𐑤𐑲𐑓-𐑚𐑶, 𐑕𐑻. ·𐑥𐑼 ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒'𐑕 𐑹𐑛𐑼𐑟. 𐑴, 𐑤𐑫𐑒, 𐑕𐑻! 𐑚𐑦𐑢𐑺 𐑞 𐑣𐑨𐑗𐑢𐑱!”

“𐑔𐑨𐑙𐑒 𐑘𐑰, 𐑥𐑨𐑯. 𐑞𐑲 𐑒𐑪𐑓𐑦𐑯 𐑤𐑲𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑦 𐑑 𐑞 𐑝𐑷𐑤𐑑.”

“𐑕𐑻? 𐑞 𐑣𐑨𐑗𐑢𐑱? 𐑴! 𐑕𐑴 𐑦𐑑 𐑛𐑳𐑟, 𐑕𐑻, 𐑕𐑴 𐑦𐑑 𐑛𐑳𐑟.”

“𐑸𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑞𐑬 𐑞 𐑤𐑧𐑜-𐑥𐑱𐑒𐑼? 𐑤𐑫𐑒, 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑥𐑐 𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞𐑲 𐑖𐑪𐑐?”

“𐑲 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑰𐑝 𐑦𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑛, 𐑕𐑻; 𐑛𐑳𐑟 𐑞 𐑓𐑧𐑮𐑵𐑤 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛, 𐑕𐑻?”

“𐑢𐑧𐑤 𐑦𐑯𐑳𐑓. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑸𐑑 𐑞𐑬 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑷𐑤𐑕𐑴 𐑞 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑼?”

“𐑲, 𐑕𐑻; 𐑲 𐑐𐑨𐑗𐑑 𐑳𐑐 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑽 𐑨𐑟 𐑩 𐑒𐑪𐑓𐑦𐑯 𐑓 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞𐑱'𐑝 𐑕𐑧𐑑 𐑥𐑰 𐑯𐑬 𐑑 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑧𐑤𐑕.”

“𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑑𐑧𐑤 𐑥𐑰; 𐑸𐑑 𐑞𐑬 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑩𐑯 𐑨𐑮𐑩𐑯𐑑, 𐑷𐑤-𐑜𐑮𐑭𐑕𐑐𐑦𐑙, 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑥𐑧𐑛𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙, 𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑪𐑐𐑩𐑤𐑲𐑟𐑦𐑙, 𐑣𐑰𐑞𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑖 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑕𐑒𐑨𐑥𐑐, 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑛𐑱 𐑥𐑱𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑤𐑧𐑜𐑟, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑯𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑 𐑛𐑱 𐑒𐑪𐑓𐑦𐑯𐑟 𐑑 𐑒𐑤𐑨𐑐 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑦𐑯, 𐑯 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯 𐑤𐑲𐑓-𐑚𐑶𐑟 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑒𐑪𐑓𐑦𐑯𐑟? 𐑞𐑬 𐑸𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑳𐑯𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑐𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑜𐑪𐑛𐑟, 𐑯 𐑨𐑟 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑝 𐑩 𐑡𐑨𐑒-𐑝-𐑷𐑤-𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑛𐑟.”

“𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑲 𐑛𐑵 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑥𐑰𐑯 𐑧𐑯𐑦𐑔𐑦𐑙, 𐑕𐑻. 𐑲 𐑛𐑵 𐑨𐑟 𐑲 𐑛𐑵.”

“𐑞 𐑜𐑪𐑛𐑟 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯. 𐑣𐑸𐑒 𐑘𐑰, 𐑛𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑞𐑬 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑻𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑩 𐑒𐑪𐑓𐑦𐑯? 𐑞 ·𐑑𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑟, 𐑞𐑱 𐑕𐑱, 𐑣𐑳𐑥𐑛 𐑕𐑯𐑨𐑗𐑩𐑟 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑗𐑦𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑬𐑑 𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑱𐑑𐑼𐑟 𐑓 𐑝𐑪𐑤𐑒𐑱𐑯𐑴𐑟; 𐑯 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑝-𐑛𐑦𐑜𐑼 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑐𐑤𐑱 𐑕𐑦𐑙𐑟, 𐑕𐑐𐑱𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛. 𐑛𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑞𐑬 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼?”

“𐑕𐑦𐑙, 𐑕𐑻? 𐑛𐑵 𐑲 𐑕𐑦𐑙? 𐑴, 𐑲'𐑥 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑓𐑼𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑳𐑓, 𐑕𐑻, 𐑓 𐑞𐑨𐑑; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞 𐑮𐑰𐑟𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑲 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑝-𐑛𐑦𐑜𐑼 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑥𐑿𐑟𐑦𐑒 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑪𐑟 𐑞𐑺 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑳𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑐𐑱𐑛, 𐑕𐑻. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞 𐑒𐑷𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑨𐑤𐑩𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑫𐑤 𐑝 𐑦𐑑. 𐑣𐑸𐑒 𐑑 𐑦𐑑.”

“𐑲, 𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑'𐑕 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑪𐑟 𐑞 𐑤𐑦𐑛 𐑞𐑺'𐑟 𐑩 𐑕𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙-𐑚𐑹𐑛; 𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑥𐑱𐑒𐑕 𐑞 𐑕𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙-𐑚𐑹𐑛 𐑦𐑟 𐑞𐑦𐑕—𐑞𐑺'𐑟 𐑯𐑷𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑯𐑰𐑔. 𐑯 𐑘𐑧𐑑, 𐑩 𐑒𐑪𐑓𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦 𐑦𐑯 𐑦𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥, ·𐑒𐑸𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑼. 𐑣𐑨𐑕𐑑 𐑞𐑬 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑐𐑑 𐑒𐑨𐑮𐑦 𐑩 𐑚𐑽, 𐑯 𐑣𐑻𐑛 𐑞 𐑒𐑪𐑓𐑦𐑯 𐑯𐑪𐑒 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑞 𐑗𐑻𐑗𐑘𐑸𐑛 𐑜𐑱𐑑, 𐑜𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯?

“𐑓𐑱𐑔, 𐑕𐑻, 𐑲'𐑝——”

“𐑓𐑱𐑔? 𐑢𐑪𐑑'𐑕 𐑞𐑨𐑑?”

“𐑢𐑲, 𐑓𐑱𐑔, 𐑕𐑻, 𐑦𐑑'𐑕 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑩 𐑕𐑹𐑑 𐑝 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑒𐑤𐑩𐑥𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯-𐑤𐑲𐑒—𐑞𐑨𐑑'𐑕 𐑷𐑤, 𐑕𐑻.”

“𐑳𐑥, 𐑳𐑥; 𐑜𐑴 𐑪𐑯.”

“𐑲 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑑 𐑕𐑱, 𐑕𐑻, 𐑞𐑨𐑑——”

“𐑸𐑑 𐑞𐑬 𐑩 𐑕𐑦𐑤𐑒-𐑢𐑻𐑥? 𐑛𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑞𐑬 𐑕𐑐𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑲 𐑴𐑯 𐑖𐑮𐑬𐑛 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑞𐑲𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓? 𐑤𐑫𐑒 𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑲 𐑚𐑫𐑟𐑩𐑥! 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑨𐑗! 𐑯 𐑜𐑧𐑑 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑐𐑕 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑕𐑲𐑑.”

“𐑣𐑰 𐑜𐑴𐑟 𐑭𐑓𐑑. 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑳𐑛𐑩𐑯, 𐑯𐑬; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑕𐑒𐑢𐑷𐑤𐑟 𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑕𐑳𐑛𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑪𐑑 𐑤𐑨𐑑𐑦𐑑𐑿𐑛𐑟. 𐑲'𐑝 𐑣𐑻𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑲𐑤 𐑝 ·𐑨𐑤𐑚𐑩𐑥𐑸𐑤, 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑜𐑨𐑤𐑲𐑐𐑩𐑜𐑴𐑟, 𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑳𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 ·𐑦𐑒𐑢𐑱𐑑𐑼 𐑮𐑲𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑥𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑤. 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑟 𐑑 𐑥𐑰 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑕𐑹𐑑 𐑝 ·𐑦𐑒𐑢𐑱𐑑𐑼 𐑒𐑳𐑑𐑕 𐑘𐑪𐑯 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑥𐑨𐑯, 𐑑𐑵, 𐑮𐑲𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑤. 𐑣𐑰'𐑟 𐑷𐑤𐑢𐑱𐑟 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑞 ·𐑤𐑲𐑯—𐑓𐑲𐑼𐑦 𐑣𐑪𐑑, 𐑲 𐑑𐑧𐑤 𐑘𐑰! 𐑣𐑰'𐑟 𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑱—𐑒𐑳𐑥, 𐑴𐑒𐑩𐑥; 𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑒. 𐑣𐑽 𐑢𐑰 𐑜𐑴 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯. 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑫𐑛𐑩𐑯 𐑥𐑨𐑤𐑩𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑞 𐑒𐑹𐑒, 𐑯 𐑲'𐑥 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑓𐑧𐑕𐑼 𐑝 𐑥𐑿𐑟𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑜𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑩𐑟—𐑑𐑨𐑐, 𐑑𐑨𐑐!”

(𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓.)

“𐑞𐑺'𐑟 𐑩 𐑕𐑲𐑑! 𐑞𐑺'𐑟 𐑩 𐑕𐑬𐑯𐑛! 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑫𐑛𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑼 𐑑𐑨𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑣𐑪𐑤𐑴 𐑑𐑮𐑰! 𐑚𐑤𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑯 𐑛𐑳𐑥 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑢𐑧𐑤 𐑚𐑰 𐑧𐑯𐑝𐑦𐑛 𐑯𐑬. 𐑕𐑰! 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑕 𐑪𐑯 𐑑𐑵 𐑤𐑲𐑯-𐑑𐑳𐑚𐑟, 𐑓𐑫𐑤 𐑝 𐑑𐑴-𐑤𐑲𐑯𐑟. 𐑩 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑥𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑕 𐑢𐑨𐑜, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑓𐑧𐑤𐑴. 𐑮𐑨𐑑-𐑑𐑨𐑑! 𐑕𐑴 𐑥𐑨𐑯'𐑟 𐑕𐑧𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑑𐑦𐑒! 𐑴! 𐑣𐑬 𐑦𐑥𐑩𐑑𐑽𐑾𐑤 𐑸 𐑷𐑤 𐑥𐑩𐑑𐑽𐑾𐑤𐑟! 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑮𐑾𐑤 𐑸 𐑞𐑺, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑪𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑔𐑷𐑑𐑕? 𐑣𐑽 𐑯𐑬'𐑟 𐑞 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑛𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑕𐑦𐑥𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑜𐑮𐑦𐑥 𐑛𐑧𐑔, 𐑚𐑲 𐑩 𐑥𐑽 𐑣𐑨𐑐, 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑞 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑦𐑝 𐑕𐑲𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑐 𐑯 𐑣𐑴𐑐 𐑝 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑼𐑛 𐑤𐑲𐑓. 𐑩 𐑤𐑲𐑓-𐑚𐑶 𐑝 𐑩 𐑒𐑪𐑓𐑦𐑯! 𐑛𐑳𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑜𐑴 𐑓𐑻𐑞𐑼? 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑦𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑕𐑐𐑦𐑮𐑦𐑗𐑵𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑕 𐑞 𐑒𐑪𐑓𐑦𐑯 𐑦𐑟, 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑷𐑤, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑥𐑹𐑑𐑨𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑦-𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑻𐑝𐑼! 𐑲'𐑤 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒 𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑯𐑴. 𐑕𐑴 𐑓𐑸 𐑜𐑪𐑯 𐑨𐑥 𐑲 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑛𐑸𐑒 𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑝 𐑻𐑔, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑕𐑲𐑛, 𐑞 𐑔𐑽𐑧𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑚𐑮𐑲𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯, 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑟 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑳𐑯𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑑𐑢𐑲𐑤𐑲𐑑 𐑑 𐑥𐑰. 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑘𐑰 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑛𐑳𐑯, ·𐑒𐑸𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑼, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑩𐑒𐑻𐑕𐑩𐑛 𐑕𐑬𐑯𐑛? 𐑲 𐑜𐑴 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑴; 𐑤𐑧𐑑 𐑥𐑰 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑰 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑽 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑲 𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑻𐑯 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯. 𐑯𐑬, 𐑞𐑧𐑯, ·𐑐𐑦𐑐, 𐑢𐑰'𐑤 𐑑𐑷𐑒 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑴𐑝𐑼; 𐑲 𐑛𐑵 𐑕𐑳𐑒 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑕 𐑓𐑦𐑤𐑪𐑕𐑩𐑓𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞𐑰! 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑳𐑯𐑯𐑴𐑯 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑛𐑿𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑳𐑯𐑯𐑴𐑯 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛𐑟 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑧𐑥𐑐𐑑𐑦 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞𐑰!”

·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 128. 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛 ·𐑥𐑰𐑑𐑕 𐑞 ·𐑮𐑱𐑗𐑩𐑤.

𐑯𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑 𐑛𐑱, 𐑩 𐑤𐑸𐑡 𐑖𐑦𐑐, 𐑞 ·𐑮𐑱𐑗𐑩𐑤, 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛, 𐑚𐑺𐑦𐑙 𐑛𐑦𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛, 𐑷𐑤 𐑣𐑻 𐑕𐑐𐑸𐑟 𐑔𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑤𐑳𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑥𐑧𐑯. 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑥𐑱𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑛 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑞 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑚𐑮𐑷𐑛-𐑢𐑦𐑙𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑢𐑼𐑛 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑼 𐑖𐑪𐑑 𐑯𐑲 𐑑 𐑣𐑻, 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑕𐑑𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑷𐑤 𐑓𐑧𐑤 𐑑𐑩𐑜𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑨𐑟 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑙𐑒 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑛𐑼𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑸 𐑚𐑻𐑕𐑑, 𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑤𐑲𐑓 𐑓𐑤𐑧𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑕𐑥𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑣𐑳𐑤.

“𐑚𐑨𐑛 𐑯𐑿𐑟; 𐑖𐑰 𐑚𐑮𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑚𐑨𐑛 𐑯𐑿𐑟,” 𐑥𐑳𐑑𐑼𐑛 𐑞 𐑴𐑤𐑛 ·𐑥𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑕𐑥𐑩𐑯. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑺 𐑣𐑻 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑭𐑯𐑛𐑼, 𐑣𐑵, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑑 𐑑 𐑥𐑬𐑞, 𐑕𐑑𐑫𐑛 𐑳𐑐 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑴𐑑; 𐑺 𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑣𐑴𐑐𐑓𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑣𐑱𐑤, ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚'𐑟 𐑝𐑶𐑕 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑣𐑻𐑛.

“𐑣𐑨𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑢𐑲𐑑 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤?”

“𐑲, 𐑘𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑛𐑱. 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑘𐑰 𐑕𐑰𐑯 𐑩 𐑢𐑱𐑤-𐑚𐑴𐑑 𐑩𐑛𐑮𐑦𐑓𐑑?”

𐑔𐑮𐑪𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑡𐑶, ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑯𐑧𐑜𐑩𐑑𐑦𐑝𐑤𐑦 𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑼𐑛 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑳𐑯𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑕𐑗𐑩𐑯; 𐑯 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑓𐑱𐑯 𐑚𐑹𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑼, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑼 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓, 𐑣𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑑𐑪𐑐𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑝𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑤'𐑟 𐑢𐑱, 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑰𐑯 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑻 𐑕𐑲𐑛. 𐑩 𐑓𐑿 𐑒𐑰𐑯 𐑐𐑫𐑤𐑟, 𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑴𐑑-𐑣𐑫𐑒 𐑕𐑵𐑯 𐑒𐑤𐑦𐑯𐑗𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛'𐑟 𐑥𐑱𐑯-𐑗𐑱𐑯𐑟, 𐑯 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑨𐑙 𐑑 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑒. 𐑦𐑥𐑰𐑛𐑾𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑩𐑜𐑯𐑲𐑟𐑛 𐑚𐑲 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑓 𐑩 ·𐑯𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑑𐑼 𐑣𐑰 𐑯𐑿. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑯𐑴 𐑓𐑹𐑥𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑨𐑤𐑿𐑑𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑗𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑛.

“𐑢𐑺 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑣𐑰?—𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑒𐑦𐑤𐑛!—𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑒𐑦𐑤𐑛!” 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚, 𐑒𐑤𐑴𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑩𐑛𐑝𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑙. “𐑣𐑬 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑦𐑑?”

𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑤𐑱𐑑 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼𐑯𐑵𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑛𐑱 𐑐𐑮𐑰𐑝𐑾𐑕, 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑼'𐑟 𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕 𐑢𐑻 𐑦𐑯𐑜𐑱𐑡𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑖𐑴𐑤 𐑝 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑤𐑧𐑛 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑓𐑹 𐑹 𐑓𐑲𐑝 𐑥𐑲𐑤𐑟 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐; 𐑯 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑞𐑱 𐑢𐑻 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑢𐑦𐑓𐑑 𐑗𐑱𐑕 𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑢𐑼𐑛, 𐑞 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑣𐑳𐑥𐑐 𐑯 𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑝 ·𐑥𐑪𐑚𐑦 ·𐑛𐑦𐑒 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑕𐑳𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑤𐑵𐑥𐑛 𐑳𐑐 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼, 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑓𐑸 𐑑 𐑤𐑰𐑢𐑼𐑛; 𐑢𐑺𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯, 𐑞 𐑓𐑹𐑔 𐑮𐑦𐑜𐑛 𐑚𐑴𐑑—𐑩 𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑻𐑝𐑛 𐑢𐑳𐑯—𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑤𐑴𐑼𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑗𐑱𐑕. 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑩 𐑒𐑰𐑯 𐑕𐑱𐑤 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑞 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛, 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑓𐑹𐑔 𐑚𐑴𐑑—𐑞 𐑕𐑢𐑦𐑓𐑑𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑒𐑰𐑤𐑛 𐑝 𐑷𐑤—𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑕𐑩𐑒𐑕𐑰𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑓𐑭𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑙—𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑰𐑕𐑑, 𐑨𐑟 𐑢𐑧𐑤 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑-𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑑𐑧𐑤 𐑧𐑯𐑦𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑦𐑑. 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑷 𐑞 𐑛𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑖𐑑 𐑛𐑪𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑴𐑑; 𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑩 𐑕𐑢𐑦𐑓𐑑 𐑜𐑤𐑰𐑥 𐑝 𐑚𐑳𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼; 𐑯 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑯𐑳𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑹; 𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑕 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑒𐑤𐑵𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑧𐑓𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑳𐑯 𐑩𐑢𐑱 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑼𐑕𐑿𐑼𐑟, 𐑨𐑟 𐑪𐑓𐑩𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑟. 𐑞𐑺 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑨𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑣𐑧𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑯, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑯𐑴 𐑐𐑪𐑟𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑝 𐑩𐑤𐑸𐑥, 𐑨𐑟 𐑘𐑧𐑑. 𐑞 𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑷𐑤 𐑕𐑦𐑜𐑯𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑮𐑦𐑜𐑦𐑙; 𐑛𐑸𐑒𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑒𐑱𐑥 𐑪𐑯; 𐑯 𐑓𐑹𐑕𐑑 𐑑 𐑐𐑦𐑒 𐑳𐑐 𐑣𐑻 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑓𐑸 𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑢𐑼𐑛 𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕—𐑺 𐑜𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑓𐑹𐑔 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑲𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑪𐑐𐑩𐑟𐑦𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯—𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑯𐑦𐑕𐑧𐑕𐑦𐑑𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑑 𐑤𐑰𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑚𐑴𐑑 𐑑 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑓𐑱𐑑 𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑯𐑽 𐑥𐑦𐑛𐑯𐑲𐑑, 𐑚𐑳𐑑, 𐑓 𐑞 𐑑𐑲𐑥, 𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑮𐑰𐑕 𐑣𐑻 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑦𐑑. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞 𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑝 𐑣𐑻 𐑒𐑮𐑵 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑱𐑓 𐑩𐑚𐑹𐑛, 𐑖𐑰 𐑒𐑮𐑬𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑷𐑤 𐑕𐑱𐑤—𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑯𐑕𐑱𐑤 𐑪𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑯𐑕𐑱𐑤—𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑞 𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑴𐑑; 𐑒𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑓𐑲𐑼 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑻 𐑑𐑮𐑲-𐑐𐑪𐑑𐑕 𐑓 𐑩 𐑚𐑰𐑒𐑩𐑯; 𐑯 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑓𐑑 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑤𐑫𐑒-𐑬𐑑. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞𐑴 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑖𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑞𐑳𐑕 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑛 𐑩 𐑕𐑩𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑑 𐑜𐑱𐑯 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑿𐑥𐑛 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑨𐑚𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑟 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑯; 𐑞𐑴 𐑖𐑰 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑐𐑷𐑟𐑛 𐑑 𐑤𐑴𐑼 𐑣𐑻 𐑕𐑐𐑺 𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕 𐑑 𐑐𐑫𐑤 𐑷𐑤 𐑼𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑣𐑻; 𐑯 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑓𐑲𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑧𐑯𐑦𐑔𐑦𐑙, 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯 𐑛𐑨𐑖𐑑 𐑪𐑯; 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯 𐑐𐑷𐑟𐑛, 𐑯 𐑤𐑴𐑼𐑛 𐑣𐑻 𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕; 𐑯 𐑞𐑴 𐑖𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑞𐑳𐑕 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑿𐑛 𐑛𐑵𐑦𐑙 𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑛𐑱𐑤𐑲𐑑; 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑞 𐑤𐑰𐑕𐑑 𐑜𐑤𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑒𐑰𐑤 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑕𐑰𐑯.

𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑹𐑦 𐑑𐑴𐑤𐑛, 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑼 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 𐑦𐑥𐑰𐑛𐑾𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑪𐑯 𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑝𐑰𐑤 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑪𐑚𐑡𐑧𐑒𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑚𐑹𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛. 𐑣𐑰 𐑛𐑦𐑟𐑲𐑼𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑑 𐑿𐑯𐑲𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑴𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑻𐑗; 𐑚𐑲 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑞 𐑕𐑰 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑓𐑹 𐑹 𐑓𐑲𐑝 𐑥𐑲𐑤𐑟 𐑩𐑐𐑸𐑑, 𐑪𐑯 𐑐𐑨𐑮𐑩𐑤𐑧𐑤 𐑤𐑲𐑯𐑟, 𐑯 𐑕𐑴 𐑕𐑢𐑰𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑛𐑳𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑣𐑼𐑲𐑟𐑩𐑯, 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑻.

“𐑲 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑢𐑱𐑡𐑼 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑯𐑬,” 𐑢𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑼𐑛 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚 𐑑 ·𐑓𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑒, “𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑴𐑑 𐑢𐑹 𐑪𐑓 𐑞𐑨𐑑 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯'𐑟 𐑚𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑒𐑴𐑑; 𐑥𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑐, 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑪𐑗—𐑣𐑰'𐑟 𐑕𐑴 𐑒𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑕 𐑑 𐑜𐑧𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑚𐑨𐑒. 𐑣𐑵 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑣𐑻𐑛 𐑝 𐑑𐑵 𐑐𐑲𐑩𐑕 𐑢𐑱𐑤-𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑕 𐑒𐑮𐑵𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑱𐑤-𐑚𐑴𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑣𐑲𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑰𐑟𐑩𐑯? 𐑕𐑰, ·𐑓𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑒, 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑰 𐑣𐑬 𐑐𐑱𐑤 𐑣𐑰 𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑕—𐑐𐑱𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑚𐑳𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑲𐑟—𐑤𐑫𐑒—𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑞 𐑒𐑴𐑑—𐑦𐑑 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑞—”

“𐑥𐑲 𐑚𐑶, 𐑥𐑲 𐑴𐑯 𐑚𐑶 𐑦𐑟 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑞𐑧𐑥. 𐑓 ·𐑜𐑪𐑛'𐑟 𐑕𐑱𐑒—𐑲 𐑚𐑧𐑜, 𐑲 𐑒𐑳𐑯𐑡𐑼”—𐑣𐑽 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑒𐑤𐑱𐑥𐑛 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑼 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 𐑑 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚, 𐑣𐑵 𐑞𐑳𐑕 𐑓𐑸 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑲𐑕𐑦𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑰𐑝𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑩𐑑𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯. “𐑓 𐑱𐑑-𐑯-𐑓𐑹𐑑𐑦 𐑬𐑼𐑟 𐑤𐑧𐑑 𐑥𐑰 𐑗𐑸𐑑𐑼 𐑘𐑹 𐑖𐑦𐑐—𐑲 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑜𐑤𐑨𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑱 𐑓 𐑦𐑑, 𐑯 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑱 𐑓 𐑦𐑑—𐑦𐑓 𐑞𐑺 𐑚𐑰 𐑯𐑴 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑢𐑱—𐑓 𐑱𐑑-𐑯-𐑓𐑹𐑑𐑦 𐑬𐑼𐑟 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦—𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑞𐑨𐑑—𐑿 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑, 𐑴, 𐑿 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑, 𐑯 𐑿 𐑖𐑨𐑤 𐑛𐑵 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑔𐑦𐑙.”

“𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑳𐑯!” 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚, “𐑴, 𐑦𐑑'𐑕 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑳𐑯 𐑣𐑰'𐑟 𐑤𐑪𐑕𐑑! 𐑲 𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑚𐑨𐑒 𐑞 𐑒𐑴𐑑 𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑗—𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑧𐑟 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚? 𐑢𐑰 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑱𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑚𐑶.”

“𐑣𐑰'𐑟 𐑛𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑪𐑯 '𐑩𐑥, 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑯𐑲𐑑,” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑞 𐑴𐑤𐑛 ·𐑥𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑕 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑼 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑦𐑣𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑞𐑧𐑥; “𐑲 𐑣𐑻𐑛; 𐑷𐑤 𐑝 𐑘𐑰 𐑣𐑻𐑛 𐑞𐑺 𐑕𐑐𐑦𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑕.”

𐑯𐑬, 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑖𐑹𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑛 𐑬𐑑, 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑮𐑱𐑗𐑩𐑤'𐑟 𐑞 𐑥𐑹 𐑥𐑧𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑒𐑪𐑤𐑦, 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞 𐑕𐑻𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑕, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯'𐑟 𐑕𐑳𐑯𐑟 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑞 𐑯𐑳𐑥𐑚𐑼 𐑝 𐑞 𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑴𐑑'𐑕 𐑒𐑮𐑵; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑞 𐑯𐑳𐑥𐑚𐑼 𐑝 𐑞 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑚𐑴𐑑'𐑕 𐑒𐑮𐑵𐑟, 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑑𐑲𐑥, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛, 𐑕𐑧𐑐𐑼𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑛𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑛𐑸𐑒 𐑝𐑦𐑕𐑦𐑕𐑦𐑑𐑿𐑛𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑗𐑱𐑕, 𐑞𐑺 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑩𐑯𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑕𐑳𐑯; 𐑨𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑓 𐑩 𐑑𐑲𐑥, 𐑞 𐑮𐑧𐑗𐑩𐑛 𐑓𐑭𐑞𐑼 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑐𐑤𐑳𐑯𐑡𐑛 𐑑 𐑞 𐑚𐑪𐑑𐑩𐑥 𐑝 𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑵𐑩𐑤𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑐𐑼𐑐𐑤𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑦𐑑𐑦; 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑪𐑤𐑝𐑛 𐑓 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑚𐑲 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑗𐑰𐑓 𐑥𐑱𐑑'𐑕 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑝𐑤𐑦 𐑩𐑛𐑪𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑹𐑛𐑦𐑯𐑼𐑦 𐑐𐑮𐑴𐑕𐑰𐑡𐑼 𐑝 𐑩 𐑢𐑱𐑤-𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑦𐑥𐑻𐑡𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑟, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑟, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑢𐑰𐑯 𐑡𐑧𐑐𐑼𐑛𐑲𐑟𐑛 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑝𐑲𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕, 𐑷𐑤𐑢𐑱𐑟 𐑑 𐑐𐑦𐑒 𐑳𐑐 𐑞 𐑥𐑩𐑡𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯, 𐑓 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑳𐑯𐑯𐑴𐑯 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑑𐑿𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑮𐑰𐑟𐑩𐑯, 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑮𐑦𐑓𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑦𐑕, 𐑯 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑓𐑹𐑕𐑑 𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑚𐑲 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚'𐑟 𐑲𐑕𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑣𐑰 𐑩𐑤𐑵𐑛 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑶; 𐑩 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑤𐑨𐑛, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑑𐑢𐑧𐑤𐑝 𐑘𐑽𐑟 𐑴𐑤𐑛, 𐑣𐑵𐑟 𐑓𐑭𐑞𐑼 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑻𐑯𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑳𐑯𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑜𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑸𐑛𐑦𐑣𐑫𐑛 𐑝 𐑩 ·𐑯𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑑𐑼'𐑟 𐑐𐑩𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑤𐑳𐑝, 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑞𐑳𐑕 𐑻𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑷𐑑 𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑖𐑦𐑱𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑐𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑤𐑟 𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑟 𐑝 𐑩 𐑝𐑴𐑒𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑥𐑩𐑥𐑹𐑾𐑤𐑦 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑦 𐑝 𐑷𐑤 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑮𐑱𐑕. 𐑯𐑹 𐑛𐑳𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑳𐑯𐑓𐑮𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑩𐑒𐑻, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 ·𐑯𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑑 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑩 𐑕𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑱𐑡 𐑩𐑢𐑱 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞𐑧𐑥, 𐑓 𐑩 𐑐𐑮𐑴𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑹 𐑓𐑹 𐑘𐑽𐑟' 𐑝𐑶𐑦𐑡 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑴𐑯; 𐑕𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑤𐑦𐑡 𐑝 𐑩 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑥𐑩𐑯'𐑟 𐑒𐑼𐑽 𐑖𐑨𐑤 𐑚𐑰 𐑳𐑯𐑧𐑯𐑼𐑝𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑗𐑭𐑯𐑕 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑤𐑱 𐑝 𐑩 𐑓𐑭𐑞𐑼'𐑟 𐑯𐑨𐑗𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑳𐑯𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑸𐑖𐑦𐑨𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑦, 𐑹 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑿 𐑨𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑣𐑧𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑝𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑯 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑻𐑯.

𐑥𐑰𐑯𐑑𐑲𐑥, 𐑯𐑬 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑼 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑚𐑦𐑕𐑰𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑫𐑼 𐑚𐑵𐑯 𐑝 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚; 𐑯 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑕𐑑𐑫𐑛 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩𐑯 𐑨𐑯𐑝𐑦𐑤, 𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑰𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑖𐑪𐑒, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑 𐑞 𐑤𐑰𐑕𐑑 𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑝𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑴𐑯.

“𐑲 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑜𐑴,” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑼, “𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑿 𐑕𐑱 𐑲 𐑑 𐑥𐑰. 𐑛𐑵 𐑑 𐑥𐑰 𐑨𐑟 𐑿 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑥𐑰 𐑛𐑵 𐑑 𐑿 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑒𐑱𐑕. 𐑓 𐑿 𐑑𐑵 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑩 𐑚𐑶, ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚—𐑞𐑴 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑩 𐑗𐑲𐑤𐑛, 𐑯 𐑯𐑧𐑕𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑱𐑓𐑤𐑦 𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑴𐑥 𐑯𐑬—𐑩 𐑗𐑲𐑤𐑛 𐑝 𐑘𐑹 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑱𐑡 𐑑𐑵—·𐑘𐑧𐑕, 𐑘𐑧𐑕, 𐑿 𐑮𐑦𐑤𐑧𐑯𐑑; 𐑲 𐑕𐑰 𐑦𐑑—𐑮𐑳𐑯, 𐑮𐑳𐑯, 𐑥𐑧𐑯, 𐑯𐑬, 𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑑 𐑕𐑒𐑢𐑺 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑘𐑸𐑛𐑟.”

“𐑩𐑝𐑭𐑕𐑑,” 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚—“𐑑𐑳𐑗 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑩 𐑮𐑴𐑐-𐑘𐑸𐑯”; 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑝𐑶𐑕 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑴𐑤𐑪𐑙𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑥𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑢𐑻𐑛—“𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 ·𐑜𐑸𐑛𐑯𐑼, 𐑲 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑛𐑵 𐑦𐑑. 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑯𐑬 𐑲 𐑤𐑵𐑟 𐑑𐑲𐑥. 𐑜𐑫𐑛-𐑚𐑲, 𐑜𐑫𐑛-𐑚𐑲. 𐑜𐑪𐑛 𐑚𐑤𐑧𐑕 𐑘𐑰, 𐑥𐑨𐑯, 𐑯 𐑥𐑱 𐑲 𐑓𐑼𐑜𐑦𐑝 𐑥𐑲𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑲 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑜𐑴. ·𐑥𐑼 ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒, 𐑤𐑫𐑒 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑚𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑪𐑗, 𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑢𐑹𐑯 𐑪𐑓 𐑷𐑤 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑼𐑟: 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑕 𐑓𐑹𐑢𐑼𐑛 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯, 𐑯 𐑤𐑧𐑑 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑕𐑱𐑤 𐑨𐑟 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹.”

𐑣𐑳𐑮𐑦𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑙, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩𐑝𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑓𐑱𐑕, 𐑣𐑰 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑨𐑚𐑦𐑯, 𐑤𐑰𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑕𐑓𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑳𐑯𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑯 𐑳𐑑𐑼 𐑮𐑦𐑡𐑧𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑴 𐑻𐑯𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑵𐑑. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑗𐑭𐑯𐑑𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑, ·𐑜𐑸𐑛𐑯𐑼 𐑕𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑣𐑳𐑮𐑦𐑛 𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑲𐑛; 𐑥𐑹 𐑓𐑧𐑤 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑐𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑴𐑑, 𐑯 𐑮𐑩𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑛 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑖𐑦𐑐.

𐑕𐑵𐑯 𐑞 𐑑𐑵 𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑕 𐑛𐑲𐑝𐑻𐑡𐑛 𐑞𐑺 𐑢𐑱𐑒𐑕; 𐑯 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡 𐑝𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑝𐑿, 𐑖𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑰𐑯 𐑑 𐑘𐑷 𐑣𐑦𐑞𐑼 𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑞𐑼 𐑨𐑑 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑛𐑸𐑒 𐑕𐑐𐑪𐑑, 𐑣𐑬𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑕𐑥𐑷𐑤, 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑰. 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑱 𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑻 𐑘𐑸𐑛𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑕𐑢𐑳𐑙 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛; 𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑼𐑛 𐑯 𐑤𐑸𐑚𐑼𐑛, 𐑖𐑰 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑿𐑛 𐑑 𐑑𐑨𐑒; 𐑯𐑬 𐑖𐑰 𐑚𐑰𐑑 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑩 𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑕𐑰; 𐑯 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯 𐑦𐑑 𐑐𐑫𐑖𐑑 𐑣𐑻 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑦𐑑; 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑢𐑲𐑤, 𐑣𐑻 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑕 𐑯 𐑘𐑸𐑛𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑔𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑤𐑳𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑥𐑧𐑯, 𐑨𐑟 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑑𐑷𐑤 𐑗𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑑𐑮𐑰𐑟, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑶𐑟 𐑸 𐑗𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑞 𐑚𐑬𐑟.

𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑣𐑻 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑣𐑷𐑤𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑒𐑹𐑕 𐑯 𐑢𐑲𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙, 𐑢𐑴𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑱, 𐑿 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑷 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑴 𐑢𐑧𐑐𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑱, 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑱𐑯𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑓𐑼𐑑. 𐑖𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 ·𐑮𐑱𐑗𐑩𐑤, 𐑢𐑰𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑓 𐑣𐑻 𐑗𐑦𐑤𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑯, 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑪𐑟 𐑞𐑱 𐑢𐑻 𐑯𐑪𐑑.

·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 129. 𐑞 ·𐑒𐑨𐑚𐑦𐑯.

(𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑥𐑵𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑜𐑴 𐑪𐑯 𐑛𐑧𐑒; ·𐑐𐑦𐑐 𐑒𐑨𐑗𐑩𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑑 𐑓𐑪𐑤𐑴.)

“𐑤𐑨𐑛, 𐑤𐑨𐑛, 𐑲 𐑑𐑧𐑤 𐑞𐑰 𐑞𐑬 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑓𐑪𐑤𐑴 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑯𐑬. 𐑞 𐑬𐑼 𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑧𐑯 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑒𐑺 𐑞𐑰 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑞𐑰 𐑚𐑲 𐑣𐑦𐑥. 𐑞𐑺 𐑦𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑰, 𐑐𐑫𐑼 𐑤𐑨𐑛, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑲 𐑓𐑰𐑤 𐑑𐑵 𐑒𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑥𐑲 𐑥𐑨𐑤𐑩𐑛𐑦. 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑒𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑟 𐑤𐑲𐑒; 𐑯 𐑓 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑑, 𐑥𐑲 𐑥𐑨𐑤𐑩𐑛𐑦 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑟 𐑥𐑲 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑟𐑲𐑼𐑛 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑔. 𐑛𐑵 𐑞𐑬 𐑩𐑚𐑲𐑛 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑴 𐑣𐑽, 𐑢𐑺 𐑞𐑱 𐑖𐑨𐑤 𐑕𐑻𐑝 𐑞𐑰, 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑓 𐑞𐑬 ·𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑑 𐑞 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯. 𐑲, 𐑤𐑨𐑛, 𐑞𐑬 𐑖𐑨𐑤𐑑 𐑕𐑦𐑑 𐑣𐑽 𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑲 𐑴𐑯 𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑵𐑛 𐑗𐑺; 𐑩𐑯𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑵 𐑑 𐑦𐑑, 𐑞𐑬 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑰.”

“𐑯𐑴, 𐑯𐑴, 𐑯𐑴! 𐑘𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑩 𐑣𐑴𐑤 𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦, 𐑕𐑻; 𐑛𐑵 𐑘𐑰 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑿𐑟 𐑐𐑫𐑼 𐑥𐑰 𐑓 𐑘𐑹 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑤𐑪𐑕𐑑 𐑤𐑧𐑜; 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑑𐑮𐑧𐑛 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑥𐑰, 𐑕𐑻; 𐑲 𐑭𐑕𐑒 𐑯𐑴 𐑥𐑹, 𐑕𐑴 𐑲 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑱𐑯 𐑩 𐑐𐑸𐑑 𐑝 𐑘𐑰.”

“𐑴! 𐑕𐑐𐑲𐑑 𐑝 𐑥𐑦𐑤𐑾𐑯 𐑝𐑦𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑟, 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑥𐑱𐑒𐑕 𐑥𐑰 𐑩 𐑚𐑦𐑜𐑩𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑱𐑛𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑓𐑦𐑛𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑝 𐑥𐑨𐑯!—𐑯 𐑩 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑒! 𐑯 𐑒𐑮𐑱𐑟𐑦!—𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑥𐑦𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑕 𐑤𐑲𐑒-𐑒𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑟-𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩𐑐𐑤𐑲𐑟 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑑𐑵; 𐑣𐑰 𐑜𐑮𐑴𐑟 𐑕𐑴 𐑕𐑱𐑯 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯.”

“𐑞𐑱 𐑑𐑧𐑤 𐑥𐑰, 𐑕𐑻, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑕 𐑛𐑧𐑟𐑼𐑑 𐑐𐑫𐑼 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 ·𐑐𐑦𐑐, 𐑣𐑵𐑟 𐑛𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑚𐑴𐑯𐑟 𐑯𐑬 𐑖𐑴 𐑢𐑲𐑑, 𐑓 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑒𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑤𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑒𐑦𐑯. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑲 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑛𐑦𐑟𐑻𐑑 𐑘𐑰, 𐑕𐑻, 𐑨𐑟 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥. 𐑕𐑻, 𐑲 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑜𐑴 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑘𐑰.”

“𐑦𐑓 𐑞𐑬 𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑞𐑳𐑕 𐑑 𐑥𐑰 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑥𐑹, ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚'𐑟 𐑐𐑻𐑐𐑩𐑕 𐑒𐑰𐑤𐑟 𐑳𐑐 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥. 𐑲 𐑑𐑧𐑤 𐑞𐑰 𐑯𐑴; 𐑦𐑑 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑚𐑰.”

“𐑴 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑼, 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑼, 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑼!

“𐑢𐑰𐑐 𐑕𐑴, 𐑯 𐑲 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑥𐑻𐑛𐑼 𐑞𐑰! 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑩 𐑒𐑺, 𐑓 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑑𐑵 𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑨𐑛. 𐑤𐑦𐑕𐑩𐑯, 𐑯 𐑞𐑬 𐑢𐑦𐑤𐑑 𐑪𐑓𐑩𐑯 𐑣𐑽 𐑥𐑲 𐑲𐑝𐑼𐑦 𐑓𐑫𐑑 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑒, 𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑯𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑲 𐑨𐑥 𐑞𐑺. 𐑯 𐑯𐑬 𐑲 𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑑 𐑞𐑰. 𐑞𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛!—𐑥𐑧𐑑! 𐑑𐑮𐑵 𐑸𐑑 𐑞𐑬, 𐑤𐑨𐑛, 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑕𐑼𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑓𐑼𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑑 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑼. 𐑕𐑴: 𐑜𐑪𐑛 𐑓 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑚𐑤𐑧𐑕 𐑞𐑰; 𐑯 𐑦𐑓 𐑦𐑑 𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑,—·𐑜𐑪𐑛 𐑓 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑕𐑱𐑝 𐑞𐑰, 𐑤𐑧𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑷𐑤.”

(𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑜𐑴𐑟; ·𐑐𐑦𐑐 𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑐𐑕 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑐 𐑓𐑹𐑢𐑼𐑛.)

“𐑣𐑽 𐑣𐑰 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑫𐑛; 𐑲 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑺,—𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑲'𐑥 𐑩𐑤𐑴𐑯. 𐑯𐑬 𐑢𐑻 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑐𐑫𐑼 ·𐑐𐑦𐑐 𐑣𐑽 𐑲 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑻 𐑦𐑑, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑣𐑰'𐑟 𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑦𐑙. 𐑐𐑦𐑐! 𐑐𐑦𐑐! 𐑛𐑦𐑙, 𐑛𐑪𐑙, 𐑛𐑦𐑙! 𐑣𐑵'𐑟 𐑕𐑰𐑯 ·𐑐𐑦𐑐? 𐑣𐑰 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑳𐑐 𐑣𐑽; 𐑤𐑧𐑑'𐑕 𐑑𐑮𐑲 𐑞 𐑛𐑹. 𐑢𐑪𐑑? 𐑯𐑲𐑞𐑼 𐑤𐑪𐑒, 𐑯𐑹 𐑚𐑴𐑤𐑑, 𐑯𐑹 𐑚𐑸; 𐑯 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑞𐑺'𐑟 𐑯𐑴 𐑴𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑑. 𐑦𐑑 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑤; 𐑣𐑰 𐑑𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑥𐑰 𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑱 𐑣𐑽: 𐑲, 𐑯 𐑑𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑥𐑰 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑵𐑛 𐑗𐑺 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑥𐑲𐑯. 𐑣𐑽, 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑲'𐑤 𐑕𐑰𐑑 𐑥𐑰, 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑞 𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑥, 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐'𐑕 𐑓𐑫𐑤 𐑥𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑤, 𐑷𐑤 𐑣𐑻 𐑒𐑰𐑤 𐑯 𐑣𐑻 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑕 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑥𐑰. 𐑣𐑽, 𐑬𐑼 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑼𐑟 𐑕𐑱, 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑒 𐑕𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑦-𐑓𐑹𐑟 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑨𐑛𐑥𐑼𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑕𐑦𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑑𐑱𐑚𐑩𐑤, 𐑯 𐑤𐑹𐑛 𐑦𐑑 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑮𐑴𐑟 𐑝 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑟 𐑯 𐑤𐑧𐑓𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕. 𐑣𐑭! 𐑢𐑪𐑑'𐑕 𐑞𐑦𐑕? 𐑧𐑐𐑩𐑤𐑧𐑑𐑕! 𐑧𐑐𐑩𐑤𐑧𐑑𐑕! 𐑞 𐑧𐑐𐑩𐑤𐑧𐑑𐑕 𐑷𐑤 𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑒𐑮𐑬𐑛𐑦𐑙! 𐑐𐑭𐑕 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑞 𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑟; 𐑜𐑤𐑨𐑛 𐑑 𐑕𐑰 𐑘𐑰; 𐑓𐑦𐑤 𐑳𐑐, 𐑥𐑩𐑕𐑘𐑻𐑟! 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑩𐑯 𐑪𐑛 𐑓𐑰𐑤𐑦𐑙, 𐑯𐑬, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑩 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑒 𐑚𐑶'𐑟 𐑣𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑑 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑜𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑤𐑱𐑕 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑒𐑴𐑑𐑕!—𐑥𐑩𐑕𐑘𐑻𐑟, 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑘𐑰 𐑕𐑰𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯 ·𐑐𐑦𐑐?—𐑩 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑯𐑰𐑜𐑮𐑴 𐑤𐑨𐑛, 𐑓𐑲𐑝 𐑓𐑰𐑑 𐑣𐑲, 𐑣𐑨𐑙-𐑛𐑪𐑜 𐑤𐑫𐑒, 𐑯 𐑒𐑬𐑼𐑛𐑤𐑦! 𐑡𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑩 𐑢𐑱𐑤-𐑚𐑴𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑕;—𐑕𐑰𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥? 𐑯𐑴! 𐑢𐑧𐑤 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑓𐑦𐑤 𐑳𐑐 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯, 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑟, 𐑯 𐑤𐑧𐑑'𐑕 𐑛𐑮𐑦𐑙𐑒 𐑖𐑱𐑥 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑒𐑬𐑼𐑛𐑟! 𐑲 𐑯𐑱𐑥 𐑯𐑴 𐑯𐑱𐑥𐑟. 𐑖𐑱𐑥 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑥! 𐑐𐑫𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑓𐑫𐑑 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑑𐑱𐑚𐑩𐑤. 𐑖𐑱𐑥 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑒𐑬𐑼𐑛𐑟.—𐑣𐑦𐑕𐑑! 𐑩𐑚𐑳𐑝 𐑞𐑺, 𐑲 𐑣𐑽 𐑲𐑝𐑼𐑦—𐑴, 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑼! 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑼! 𐑲 𐑨𐑥 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑰𐑛 𐑛𐑬𐑯-𐑣𐑸𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑿 𐑢𐑷𐑒 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑥𐑰. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑣𐑽 𐑲'𐑤 𐑕𐑑𐑱, 𐑞𐑴 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑕𐑑𐑻𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑒𐑕 𐑮𐑪𐑒𐑕; 𐑯 𐑞𐑱 𐑚𐑳𐑤𐑡 𐑔𐑮𐑵; 𐑯 𐑶𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑟 𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑑 𐑡𐑶𐑯 𐑥𐑰.”

·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 130. 𐑞 ·𐑣𐑨𐑑.

𐑯 𐑯𐑬 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑐𐑼 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑯 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕, 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑕𐑴 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑯 𐑢𐑲𐑛 𐑩 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑼𐑦 𐑒𐑮𐑵𐑟, ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚,—𐑷𐑤 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼𐑟 𐑕𐑢𐑧𐑐𐑑—𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑗𐑱𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑴 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑩𐑯 𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯-𐑓𐑴𐑤𐑛, 𐑑 𐑕𐑤𐑱 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑞 𐑥𐑹 𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑤𐑦 𐑞𐑺; 𐑯𐑬, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑣𐑸𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑤𐑨𐑑𐑦𐑑𐑿𐑛 𐑯 𐑤𐑪𐑯𐑜𐑦𐑑𐑿𐑛 𐑢𐑺 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑑𐑹𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑵𐑯𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑓𐑤𐑦𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑛; 𐑯𐑬 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑩 𐑝𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑤 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑕𐑐𐑴𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑛𐑱 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑰𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑨𐑒𐑗𐑵𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑛 ·𐑥𐑪𐑚𐑦 ·𐑛𐑦𐑒;—𐑯 𐑯𐑬 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑩𐑒𐑕𐑧𐑕𐑦𐑝 𐑥𐑰𐑑𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑝𐑺𐑾𐑕 𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑕 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑒𐑻𐑛 𐑑 𐑖𐑴 𐑞 𐑛𐑦𐑥𐑴𐑯𐑦𐑨𐑒 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑓𐑼𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑞 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑑𐑹 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑟, 𐑢𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑕𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑹 𐑕𐑦𐑯𐑛 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑕𐑑; 𐑯𐑬 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑤𐑻𐑒𐑑 𐑩 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑥𐑨𐑯'𐑟 𐑲𐑟, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑣𐑸𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑳𐑓𐑼𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑓 𐑓𐑰𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑴𐑤𐑟 𐑑 𐑕𐑰. 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑳𐑯𐑕𐑧𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑐𐑴𐑤𐑼 𐑕𐑑𐑸, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑞 𐑤𐑦𐑝𐑤𐑪𐑙, 𐑸𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑒, 𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑕 𐑥𐑳𐑯𐑔𐑕' 𐑯𐑲𐑑 𐑕𐑩𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑯𐑟 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑐𐑽𐑕𐑦𐑙, 𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑛𐑦, 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑩𐑤 𐑜𐑱𐑟; 𐑕𐑴 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚'𐑟 𐑐𐑻𐑐𐑩𐑕 𐑯𐑬 𐑓𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑩𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑜𐑤𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑥𐑦𐑛𐑯𐑲𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑜𐑤𐑵𐑥𐑦 𐑒𐑮𐑵. 𐑦𐑑 𐑛𐑪𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑽𐑛 𐑩𐑚𐑳𐑝 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑕𐑴, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑺 𐑚𐑴𐑛𐑦𐑙𐑟, 𐑛𐑬𐑑𐑕, 𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑜𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑙𐑟, 𐑓𐑽𐑟, 𐑢𐑻 𐑓𐑱𐑯 𐑑 𐑣𐑲𐑛 𐑚𐑦𐑯𐑰𐑔 𐑞𐑺 𐑕𐑴𐑤𐑟, 𐑯 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑬𐑑 𐑓𐑹𐑔 𐑩 𐑕𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑐𐑽 𐑹 𐑤𐑰𐑓.

𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑓𐑹𐑖𐑨𐑛𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑝𐑩𐑤 𐑑𐑵, 𐑷𐑤 𐑣𐑿𐑥𐑼, 𐑓𐑹𐑕𐑑 𐑹 𐑯𐑨𐑗𐑼𐑩𐑤, 𐑝𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑖𐑑. 𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚 𐑯𐑴 𐑥𐑹 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑴𐑝 𐑑 𐑮𐑱𐑟 𐑩 𐑕𐑥𐑲𐑤; ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒 𐑯𐑴 𐑥𐑹 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑴𐑝 𐑑 𐑗𐑧𐑒 𐑢𐑳𐑯. 𐑩𐑤𐑲𐑒, 𐑡𐑶 𐑯 𐑕𐑪𐑮𐑴, 𐑣𐑴𐑐 𐑯 𐑓𐑽, 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑜𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑑 𐑓𐑲𐑯𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑛𐑳𐑕𐑑, 𐑯 𐑐𐑬𐑛𐑼𐑛, 𐑓 𐑞 𐑑𐑲𐑥, 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑒𐑤𐑨𐑥𐑐𐑑 𐑥𐑹𐑑𐑼 𐑝 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚'𐑟 𐑲𐑼𐑯 𐑕𐑴𐑤. 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑥𐑩𐑖𐑰𐑯𐑟, 𐑞𐑱 𐑛𐑳𐑥𐑤𐑦 𐑥𐑵𐑝𐑛 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑒, 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑕 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑥𐑨𐑯'𐑟 𐑛𐑧𐑕𐑐𐑪𐑑 𐑲 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑪𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑥.

𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑿 𐑛𐑰𐑐𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑹 𐑕𐑰𐑒𐑮𐑩𐑑 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑓𐑦𐑛𐑧𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑤 𐑬𐑼𐑟; 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑣𐑰 𐑔𐑷𐑑 𐑯𐑴 𐑜𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑕 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥; 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑿 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑕𐑰𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑨𐑟 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚'𐑟 𐑲𐑟 𐑕𐑴 𐑷𐑛 𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑵'𐑟, 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑵𐑑𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 ·𐑐𐑸𐑟𐑰'𐑟 𐑜𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑕 𐑷𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟; 𐑹 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑣𐑬, 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑰𐑕𐑑, 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑢𐑲𐑤𐑛 𐑢𐑱, 𐑨𐑑 𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑩𐑓𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑑. 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩𐑯 𐑨𐑛𐑩𐑛, 𐑜𐑤𐑲𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑚𐑦𐑜𐑨𐑯 𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑞 𐑔𐑦𐑯 ·𐑓𐑧𐑛𐑩𐑤𐑩 𐑯𐑬; 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑕𐑰𐑕𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑖𐑳𐑛𐑼𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑖𐑫𐑒 𐑣𐑦𐑥; 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑑 𐑛𐑿𐑚𐑾𐑕 𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥; 𐑣𐑭𐑓 𐑳𐑯𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑯, 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛, 𐑢𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑰𐑛 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑻 𐑩 𐑥𐑹𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑳𐑚𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕, 𐑹 𐑧𐑤𐑕 𐑩 𐑑𐑮𐑧𐑥𐑿𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑖𐑨𐑛𐑴 𐑒𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑒 𐑚𐑲 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑳𐑯𐑕𐑰𐑯 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙'𐑟 𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦. 𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑖𐑨𐑛𐑴 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑷𐑤𐑢𐑱𐑟 𐑣𐑪𐑝𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑺. 𐑓 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑯𐑲𐑑, 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯, 𐑣𐑨𐑛 ·𐑓𐑧𐑛𐑩𐑤𐑩 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑯𐑴𐑯 𐑑 𐑕𐑤𐑳𐑥𐑚𐑼, 𐑹 𐑜𐑴 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑴. 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑓 𐑬𐑼𐑟: 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑕𐑨𐑑 𐑹 𐑤𐑰𐑯𐑛; 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑪𐑯 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑕 𐑲𐑟 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑱—𐑢𐑰 𐑑𐑵 𐑢𐑪𐑗𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑑.

𐑯𐑹, 𐑨𐑑 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑑𐑲𐑥, 𐑚𐑲 𐑯𐑲𐑑 𐑹 𐑛𐑱 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑞 𐑥𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑯𐑼𐑟 𐑯𐑬 𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑐 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑒, 𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑧𐑕 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑞𐑧𐑥; 𐑲𐑞𐑼 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑦𐑝𐑩𐑑-𐑣𐑴𐑤, 𐑹 𐑦𐑜𐑟𐑨𐑒𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑱𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑐𐑤𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑕 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑢𐑰𐑯 𐑑𐑵 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑰𐑝𐑦𐑱𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑤𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑑𐑕,—𐑞 𐑥𐑱𐑯-𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑯 𐑞 𐑥𐑦𐑟𐑩𐑯; 𐑹 𐑧𐑤𐑕 𐑞𐑱 𐑕𐑷 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑒𐑨𐑚𐑦𐑯-𐑕𐑒𐑳𐑑𐑩𐑤,—𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑤𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑫𐑑 𐑩𐑛𐑝𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑒, 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑓 𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑐; 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑤𐑬𐑗𐑑 𐑣𐑧𐑝𐑦𐑤𐑦 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑲𐑟; 𐑕𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑬𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑥𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑑𐑫𐑛, 𐑣𐑬𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑞 𐑛𐑱𐑟 𐑯 𐑯𐑲𐑑𐑕 𐑢𐑻 𐑨𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑪𐑯, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑢𐑳𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑥𐑩𐑒; 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑯 𐑚𐑦𐑯𐑰𐑔 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑤𐑬𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑨𐑑, 𐑞𐑱 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑑𐑧𐑤 𐑳𐑯𐑻𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑢𐑧𐑞𐑼, 𐑓 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑦𐑕, 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑲𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑮𐑾𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑤𐑴𐑟𐑛 𐑨𐑑 𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟; 𐑹 𐑢𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑧𐑥; 𐑯𐑴 𐑥𐑨𐑑𐑼, 𐑞𐑴 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑑𐑫𐑛 𐑕𐑴 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑒𐑳𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑓 𐑩 𐑣𐑴𐑤 𐑬𐑼 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑧𐑗, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑳𐑯𐑣𐑰𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑯𐑲𐑑-𐑛𐑨𐑥𐑐 𐑜𐑨𐑞𐑼𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑚𐑰𐑛𐑟 𐑝 𐑛𐑿 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑴𐑯-𐑒𐑸𐑝𐑛 𐑒𐑴𐑑 𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑑. 𐑞 𐑒𐑤𐑴𐑞𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑯𐑲𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑢𐑧𐑑, 𐑞 𐑯𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑 𐑛𐑱'𐑟 𐑕𐑳𐑯𐑖𐑲𐑯 𐑛𐑮𐑲𐑛 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥; 𐑯 𐑕𐑴, 𐑛𐑱 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑛𐑱, 𐑯 𐑯𐑲𐑑 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑯𐑲𐑑; 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑯𐑴 𐑥𐑹 𐑚𐑦𐑯𐑰𐑔 𐑞 𐑐𐑤𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑕; 𐑢𐑪𐑑𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑒𐑨𐑚𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑓.

𐑣𐑰 𐑱𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑴𐑐𐑩𐑯 𐑺; 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑟, 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑑𐑵 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑥𐑰𐑤𐑟,—𐑚𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑓𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑯 𐑛𐑦𐑯𐑼: 𐑕𐑳𐑐𐑼 𐑣𐑰 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑑𐑳𐑗𐑑; 𐑯𐑹 𐑮𐑰𐑐𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑽𐑛; 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑛𐑸𐑒𐑤𐑦 𐑜𐑮𐑵 𐑷𐑤 𐑯𐑸𐑤𐑛, 𐑨𐑟 𐑳𐑯𐑻𐑔𐑑 𐑮𐑵𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑑𐑮𐑰𐑟 𐑚𐑤𐑴𐑯 𐑴𐑝𐑼, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑜𐑮𐑴 𐑲𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑪𐑯 𐑨𐑑 𐑯𐑱𐑒𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑱𐑕, 𐑞𐑴 𐑐𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑖𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑳𐑐𐑼 𐑝𐑻𐑡𐑼. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞𐑴 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑴𐑤 𐑤𐑲𐑓 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑬 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑗 𐑪𐑯 𐑛𐑧𐑒; 𐑯 𐑞𐑴 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑸𐑟𐑰'𐑟 𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑢𐑪𐑗 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑥𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑨𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑴𐑯; 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑑𐑵 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑑 𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑒—𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑑 𐑞 𐑳𐑞𐑼—𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑧𐑕 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑐𐑭𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑳𐑯𐑥𐑴𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑕 𐑥𐑨𐑑𐑼 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑦𐑑 𐑯𐑧𐑕𐑦𐑕𐑺𐑦. 𐑞𐑴 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩 𐑐𐑴𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑤 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑕𐑰𐑒𐑮𐑩𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑑 𐑡𐑶𐑯 𐑞 𐑑𐑢𐑱𐑯; 𐑴𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑦, 𐑯 𐑑 𐑞 𐑷-𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑒 𐑒𐑮𐑵, 𐑞𐑱 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑐𐑴𐑤-𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩𐑕𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼. 𐑦𐑓 𐑚𐑲 𐑛𐑱 𐑞𐑱 𐑗𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑑 𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑒 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑢𐑻𐑛; 𐑚𐑲 𐑯𐑲𐑑, 𐑛𐑳𐑥 𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑢𐑻 𐑚𐑴𐑔, 𐑕𐑴 𐑓𐑸 𐑨𐑟 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑻𐑯𐑛 𐑞 𐑕𐑤𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑝𐑻𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑗𐑱𐑯𐑡. 𐑨𐑑 𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟, 𐑓 𐑤𐑪𐑙𐑜𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑬𐑼𐑟, 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑 𐑩 𐑕𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑩𐑤 𐑣𐑱𐑤, 𐑞𐑱 𐑕𐑑𐑫𐑛 𐑓𐑸 𐑐𐑸𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑤𐑲𐑑; ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑒𐑳𐑑𐑩𐑤, 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑸𐑟𐑰 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑥𐑱𐑯𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑓𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑩𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑜𐑱𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑰𐑗 𐑳𐑞𐑼; 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑓 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑸𐑟𐑰 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑕𐑷 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑹𐑔𐑮𐑴𐑯 𐑖𐑨𐑛𐑴, 𐑦𐑯 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑸𐑟𐑰 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑩𐑚𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑕𐑳𐑚𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕.

𐑯 𐑘𐑧𐑑, 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑣𐑬, 𐑛𐑦𐑛 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚—𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑴𐑯 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑐𐑼 𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓, 𐑨𐑟 𐑛𐑱𐑤𐑦, 𐑬𐑼𐑤𐑦, 𐑯 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑, 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑭𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑦𐑝𐑰𐑤𐑛 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑹𐑛𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑑𐑕,—·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑤𐑹𐑛; 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑸𐑟𐑰 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑤𐑱𐑝. 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯 𐑚𐑴𐑔 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑘𐑴𐑒𐑑 𐑑𐑩𐑜𐑧𐑞𐑼, 𐑯 𐑩𐑯 𐑳𐑯𐑕𐑰𐑯 𐑑𐑲𐑮𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑛𐑮𐑲𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑧𐑥; 𐑞 𐑤𐑰𐑯 𐑖𐑱𐑛 𐑕𐑲𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑕𐑪𐑤𐑦𐑛 𐑮𐑦𐑚. 𐑓 𐑚𐑰 𐑞𐑦𐑕 ·𐑐𐑸𐑟𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑥𐑱, 𐑷𐑤 𐑮𐑦𐑚 𐑯 𐑒𐑰𐑤 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑪𐑤𐑦𐑛 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚.

𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑓𐑱𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑜𐑤𐑦𐑥𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑞 𐑛𐑷𐑯, 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑲𐑼𐑯 𐑝𐑶𐑕 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑣𐑻𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑭𐑓𐑑,—“𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑞 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑-𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑟!”—𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑞 𐑛𐑱, 𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑕𐑳𐑯𐑕𐑧𐑑 𐑯 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑑𐑢𐑲𐑤𐑲𐑑, 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑝𐑶𐑕 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑬𐑼, 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑞 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑥𐑟𐑥𐑩𐑯'𐑟 𐑚𐑧𐑤, 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑣𐑻𐑛—“𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑛'𐑘𐑰 𐑕𐑰?—𐑖𐑸𐑐! 𐑖𐑸𐑐!”

𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑹 𐑓𐑹 𐑛𐑱𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑕𐑤𐑲𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑲, 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑥𐑰𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑗𐑦𐑤𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑯-𐑕𐑰𐑒𐑦𐑙 ·𐑮𐑱𐑗𐑩𐑤; 𐑯 𐑯𐑴 𐑕𐑐𐑬𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑕𐑰𐑯; 𐑞 𐑥𐑪𐑯𐑩𐑥𐑱𐑯𐑦𐑨𐑒 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑕𐑑𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑮𐑵'𐑟 𐑓𐑦𐑛𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑦; 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑰𐑕𐑑, 𐑝 𐑯𐑽𐑤𐑦 𐑷𐑤 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑧𐑐𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑱𐑜𐑩𐑯 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑽𐑟; 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑑 𐑛𐑬𐑑, 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯, 𐑢𐑧𐑞𐑼 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚 𐑯 ·𐑓𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑒 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑴𐑝𐑼𐑤𐑫𐑒 𐑞 𐑕𐑲𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑷𐑑. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑓 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑕𐑩𐑕𐑐𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑮𐑾𐑤𐑦 𐑣𐑦𐑟, 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑦𐑓𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑝𐑻𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑧𐑥, 𐑣𐑬𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑨𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑥 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑯𐑑 𐑞𐑧𐑥.

“𐑲 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑞 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑲𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑥𐑲𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓,”—𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑧𐑛. “𐑲! 𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑞 𐑛𐑳𐑚𐑤𐑵𐑯!” 𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑴𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑮𐑦𐑜𐑛 𐑩 𐑯𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑝 𐑚𐑭𐑕𐑒𐑩𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑴𐑤𐑦𐑯𐑟; 𐑯 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑓𐑑, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑕𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑩𐑤 𐑖𐑰𐑝𐑛 𐑚𐑤𐑪𐑒, 𐑑 𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑘𐑫𐑼 𐑑 𐑞 𐑥𐑱𐑯-𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑧𐑛, 𐑣𐑰 𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑰𐑝𐑛 𐑞 𐑑𐑵 𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑛𐑬𐑯𐑢𐑼𐑛-𐑮𐑰𐑝𐑛 𐑮𐑴𐑐; 𐑯 𐑩𐑑𐑨𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑭𐑕𐑒𐑩𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑺𐑛 𐑩 𐑐𐑦𐑯 𐑓 𐑞 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑧𐑯𐑛, 𐑦𐑯 𐑹𐑛𐑼 𐑑 𐑓𐑭𐑕𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑮𐑱𐑤. 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑛𐑳𐑯, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑦𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑞 𐑐𐑦𐑯, 𐑣𐑰 𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑑 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑮𐑵, 𐑕𐑢𐑰𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑑 𐑞 𐑳𐑞𐑼; 𐑐𐑷𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑜𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑕 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 ·𐑛𐑨𐑜𐑵, ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜, ·𐑑𐑨𐑖𐑑𐑱𐑜𐑴; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑖𐑳𐑯𐑦𐑙 ·𐑓𐑧𐑛𐑩𐑤𐑩; 𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑕𐑧𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑻𐑥 𐑮𐑦𐑤𐑲𐑦𐑙 𐑲 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑗𐑰𐑓 𐑥𐑱𐑑, 𐑕𐑧𐑛,—“𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑞 𐑮𐑴𐑐, 𐑕𐑻—𐑲 𐑜𐑦𐑝 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟, ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒.” 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑼𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑻𐑕𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑭𐑕𐑒𐑩𐑑, 𐑣𐑰 𐑜𐑱𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑻𐑛 𐑓 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑑 𐑣𐑶𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑻𐑗, ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑣𐑵 𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑛 𐑞 𐑮𐑴𐑐 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑; 𐑯 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼𐑢𐑼𐑛𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑫𐑛 𐑯𐑽 𐑦𐑑. 𐑯 𐑞𐑳𐑕, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑒𐑤𐑦𐑙𐑦𐑙 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑞 𐑮𐑶𐑩𐑤 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑, ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑜𐑱𐑟𐑛 𐑩𐑚𐑮𐑷𐑛 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑰 𐑓 𐑥𐑲𐑤𐑟 𐑯 𐑥𐑲𐑤𐑟,—𐑩𐑣𐑧𐑛, 𐑩𐑕𐑑𐑻𐑯, 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑕𐑲𐑛, 𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑,—𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑲𐑛 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑕𐑻𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑭𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑴 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑩 𐑣𐑲𐑑.

𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑻𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑤𐑪𐑓𐑑𐑦 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑲𐑕𐑩𐑤𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑮𐑦𐑜𐑦𐑙, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑗𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑑 𐑩𐑓𐑹𐑛 𐑯𐑴 𐑓𐑫𐑑𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛, 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑼 𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑰 𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑶𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑳𐑐 𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑐𐑪𐑑, 𐑯 𐑕𐑩𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑯𐑛 𐑞𐑺 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑮𐑴𐑐; 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑕𐑻𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟, 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑓𐑭𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑪𐑯 𐑛𐑧𐑒 𐑦𐑟 𐑷𐑤𐑢𐑱𐑟 𐑜𐑦𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑑 𐑗𐑸𐑡 𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑣𐑵 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑪𐑗 𐑝 𐑦𐑑. 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑪𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩 𐑢𐑦𐑤𐑛𐑼𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑮𐑳𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑮𐑦𐑜𐑦𐑙, 𐑣𐑵𐑟 𐑝𐑺𐑾𐑕 𐑛𐑦𐑓𐑼𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑤𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑓𐑑 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑷𐑤𐑢𐑱𐑟 𐑚𐑰 𐑦𐑯𐑓𐑨𐑤𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑻𐑯𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑰𐑯 𐑝 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑒; 𐑯 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑒-𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑝 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑮𐑴𐑐𐑕 𐑸 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑓𐑿 𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑒𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑓𐑭𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑙𐑟, 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑚𐑰 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑩 𐑯𐑨𐑗𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑓𐑩𐑑𐑨𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑦, 𐑦𐑓, 𐑳𐑯𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑝𐑲𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑗𐑥𐑩𐑯, 𐑞 𐑣𐑶𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑼 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑒𐑺𐑤𐑩𐑕𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑵 𐑚𐑰 𐑒𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑩𐑛𐑮𐑦𐑓𐑑 𐑯 𐑓𐑷𐑤 𐑷𐑤 𐑕𐑢𐑵𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑰. 𐑕𐑴 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚'𐑟 𐑐𐑮𐑴𐑕𐑰𐑛𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑥𐑨𐑑𐑼 𐑢𐑻 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑳𐑯𐑿𐑠𐑵𐑩𐑤; 𐑞 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡 𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑑 𐑚𐑰, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒, 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑞 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑣𐑵 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑝𐑧𐑯𐑗𐑼𐑛 𐑑 𐑩𐑐𐑴𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑧𐑯𐑦𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑤𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑜𐑮𐑰 𐑩𐑐𐑮𐑴𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑦𐑠𐑩𐑯—𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑑𐑵, 𐑣𐑵𐑟 𐑓𐑱𐑔𐑓𐑩𐑤𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑤𐑫𐑒-𐑬𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑑 𐑛𐑬𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑢𐑪𐑑;—𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑣𐑰 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑕𐑦𐑤𐑧𐑒𐑑 𐑓 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑪𐑗𐑥𐑩𐑯; 𐑓𐑮𐑰𐑤𐑦 𐑜𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑴𐑤 𐑤𐑲𐑓 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩𐑯 𐑳𐑞𐑼𐑢𐑲𐑟 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑐𐑻𐑕𐑩𐑯'𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟.

𐑯𐑬, 𐑞 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑑𐑲𐑥 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑐𐑻𐑗𐑑 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑓𐑑; 𐑺 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑑𐑧𐑯 𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑕; 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑮𐑧𐑛-𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑛 𐑕𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑡 𐑕𐑰-𐑣𐑷𐑒𐑕 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑕𐑴 𐑪𐑓𐑩𐑯 𐑓𐑤𐑲 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑴𐑛𐑾𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑤𐑴𐑕 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑞 𐑥𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑-𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑟 𐑝 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑤𐑨𐑑𐑦𐑑𐑿𐑛𐑟; 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑚𐑻𐑛𐑟 𐑒𐑱𐑥 𐑢𐑰𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑯 𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑰𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑥𐑱𐑟 𐑝 𐑳𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑒𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑢𐑦𐑓𐑑 𐑕𐑻𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙𐑟. 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑦𐑑 𐑛𐑸𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑩 𐑔𐑬𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑓𐑰𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑳𐑐 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑺; 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑕𐑐𐑲𐑮𐑩𐑤𐑲𐑟𐑛 𐑛𐑬𐑯𐑢𐑼𐑛𐑟, 𐑯 𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑧𐑛𐑦𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑧𐑛.

𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑜𐑱𐑟 𐑓𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑑 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑛𐑦𐑥 𐑯 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑣𐑼𐑲𐑟𐑩𐑯, ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑑 𐑥𐑸𐑒 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑲𐑤𐑛 𐑚𐑻𐑛; 𐑯𐑹, 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑰𐑛, 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑧𐑤𐑕 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑥𐑸𐑒𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑥𐑳𐑗, 𐑦𐑑 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑯𐑴 𐑳𐑯𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑕𐑻𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑕; 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑯𐑬 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑞 𐑤𐑰𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑰𐑛𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑲 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑑 𐑕𐑰 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑕𐑹𐑑 𐑝 𐑒𐑳𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑰𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑕𐑲𐑑.

“𐑘𐑹 𐑣𐑨𐑑, 𐑘𐑹 𐑣𐑨𐑑, 𐑕𐑻!” 𐑕𐑳𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑦𐑕𐑦𐑤𐑾𐑯 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑩𐑯, 𐑣𐑵 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑐𐑴𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑥𐑦𐑟𐑩𐑯-𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑-𐑣𐑧𐑛, 𐑕𐑑𐑫𐑛 𐑛𐑦𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑦𐑣𐑲𐑯𐑛 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚, 𐑞𐑴 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑤𐑴𐑼 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑤𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑤, 𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑛𐑰𐑐 𐑜𐑳𐑤𐑓 𐑝 𐑺 𐑛𐑦𐑝𐑲𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑧𐑥.

𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑷𐑤𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑦 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑞 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑥𐑨𐑯'𐑟 𐑲𐑟; 𐑞 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑣𐑫𐑒𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑤 𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑧𐑛: 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑰𐑥, 𐑞 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑒 𐑣𐑷𐑒 𐑛𐑸𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑩𐑢𐑱 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑮𐑲𐑟.

𐑩𐑯 𐑰𐑜𐑩𐑤 𐑓𐑤𐑵 𐑔𐑮𐑲𐑕 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 ·𐑑𐑸𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑯'𐑟 𐑣𐑧𐑛, 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑵𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑨𐑐 𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕 𐑦𐑑, 𐑯 𐑞𐑺𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 ·𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑨𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑤, 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑲𐑓, 𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑺𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 ·𐑑𐑸𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑚𐑰 𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑝 ·𐑮𐑴𐑥. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑞 𐑒𐑨𐑐 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑴𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑩𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑜𐑫𐑛. 𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚'𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑹𐑛; 𐑞 𐑢𐑲𐑤𐑛 𐑣𐑷𐑒 𐑓𐑤𐑵 𐑪𐑯 𐑯 𐑪𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑦𐑑; 𐑓𐑸 𐑦𐑯 𐑩𐑛𐑝𐑭𐑯𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑬: 𐑯 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑩𐑐𐑽𐑛; 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑐𐑶𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑩𐑐𐑽𐑩𐑯𐑕, 𐑩 𐑥𐑲𐑯𐑿𐑑 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑒 𐑕𐑐𐑪𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑛𐑦𐑥𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑻𐑯𐑛, 𐑓𐑷𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑝𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑲𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑕𐑰.

·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 131. 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛 ·𐑥𐑰𐑑𐑕 𐑞 ·𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑲𐑑.

𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑕 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑛 𐑪𐑯; 𐑞 𐑮𐑴𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑱𐑝𐑟 𐑯 𐑛𐑱𐑟 𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑚𐑲; 𐑞 𐑤𐑲𐑓-𐑚𐑶-𐑒𐑪𐑓𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑤𐑲𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑢𐑳𐑙; 𐑯 𐑩𐑯𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑖𐑦𐑐, 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑥𐑦𐑟𐑼𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑯𐑱𐑥𐑛 𐑞 ·𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑲𐑑, 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛. 𐑨𐑟 𐑖𐑰 𐑛𐑮𐑵 𐑯𐑲, 𐑷𐑤 𐑲𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑓𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑑 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑻 𐑚𐑮𐑷𐑛 𐑚𐑰𐑥𐑟, 𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑛 𐑖𐑽𐑟, 𐑢𐑦𐑗, 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙-𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑕, 𐑒𐑮𐑪𐑕 𐑞 𐑒𐑢𐑹𐑑𐑼-𐑛𐑧𐑒 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑣𐑲𐑑 𐑝 𐑱𐑑 𐑹 𐑯𐑲𐑯 𐑓𐑰𐑑; 𐑕𐑻𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑒𐑨𐑮𐑦 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑺, 𐑳𐑯𐑮𐑦𐑜𐑛, 𐑹 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑱𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕.

𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑼'𐑟 𐑖𐑽𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑚𐑦𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑛 𐑞 𐑖𐑨𐑑𐑼𐑛, 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑚𐑟, 𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑓𐑿 𐑕𐑐𐑤𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑛 𐑐𐑤𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑕, 𐑝 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑕 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑩 𐑢𐑱𐑤-𐑚𐑴𐑑; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑿 𐑯𐑬 𐑕𐑷 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑮𐑧𐑒, 𐑨𐑟 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑨𐑟 𐑿 𐑕𐑰 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑞 𐑐𐑰𐑤𐑛, 𐑣𐑭𐑓-𐑳𐑯𐑣𐑦𐑯𐑡𐑛, 𐑯 𐑚𐑤𐑰𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑒𐑧𐑤𐑩𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑩 𐑣𐑹𐑕.

“𐑣𐑨𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑢𐑲𐑑 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤?”

“𐑤𐑫𐑒!” 𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑤𐑲𐑛 𐑞 𐑣𐑪𐑤𐑴-𐑗𐑰𐑒𐑑 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑑𐑨𐑓𐑮𐑱𐑤; 𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑐𐑶𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑑 𐑞 𐑮𐑧𐑒.

“𐑣𐑨𐑕𐑑 𐑒𐑦𐑤𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥?”

“𐑞 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯 𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑓𐑹𐑡𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑛𐑵 𐑞𐑨𐑑,” 𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑼𐑛 𐑞 𐑳𐑞𐑼, 𐑕𐑨𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑜𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑩 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑥𐑩𐑒 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑒, 𐑣𐑵𐑟 𐑜𐑨𐑞𐑼𐑛 𐑕𐑲𐑛𐑟 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑯𐑶𐑟𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑼𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑚𐑦𐑟𐑦 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑑𐑩𐑜𐑧𐑞𐑼.

“𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑓𐑹𐑡𐑛!” 𐑯 𐑕𐑯𐑨𐑗𐑦𐑙 ·𐑐𐑻𐑔'𐑕 𐑤𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑲𐑼𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑪𐑗, ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑛 𐑦𐑑 𐑬𐑑, 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑒𐑤𐑱𐑥𐑦𐑙—“𐑤𐑫𐑒 𐑘𐑰, ·𐑯𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑑𐑼; 𐑣𐑽 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑲 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑛𐑧𐑔! 𐑑𐑧𐑥𐑐𐑼𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑚𐑤𐑳𐑛, 𐑯 𐑑𐑧𐑥𐑐𐑼𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑤𐑲𐑑𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑸 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑚𐑸𐑚𐑟; 𐑯 𐑲 𐑕𐑢𐑺 𐑑 𐑑𐑧𐑥𐑐𐑼 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑪𐑑 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕 𐑚𐑦𐑣𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑞 𐑓𐑦𐑯, 𐑢𐑺 𐑞 ·𐑢𐑲𐑑 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑓𐑰𐑤𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑩𐑒𐑻𐑕𐑩𐑛 𐑤𐑲𐑓!”

“𐑞𐑧𐑯 ·𐑜𐑪𐑛 𐑒𐑰𐑐 𐑞𐑰, 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑥𐑨𐑯—𐑕𐑰'𐑕𐑑 𐑞𐑬 𐑞𐑨𐑑”—𐑐𐑶𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑞 𐑣𐑨𐑥𐑩𐑒—“𐑲 𐑚𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑓𐑲𐑝 𐑕𐑑𐑬𐑑 𐑥𐑧𐑯, 𐑣𐑵 𐑢𐑻 𐑩𐑤𐑲𐑝 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑘𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑛𐑱; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑻 𐑛𐑧𐑛 𐑺 𐑯𐑲𐑑. 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑲 𐑚𐑧𐑮𐑦; 𐑞 𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑢𐑻 𐑚𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑛 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑞𐑱 𐑛𐑲𐑛; 𐑿 𐑕𐑱𐑤 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑑𐑵𐑥.” 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑮𐑵—“𐑸 𐑘𐑰 𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑦 𐑞𐑺? 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕 𐑞 𐑐𐑤𐑨𐑙𐑒 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑮𐑱𐑤, 𐑯 𐑤𐑦𐑓𐑑 𐑞 𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦; 𐑕𐑴, 𐑞𐑧𐑯—𐑴! 𐑜𐑪𐑛”—𐑩𐑛𐑝𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑑𐑩𐑢𐑹𐑛𐑟 𐑞 𐑣𐑨𐑥𐑩𐑒 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑳𐑐𐑤𐑦𐑓𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟—“𐑥𐑱 𐑞 𐑮𐑧𐑟𐑼𐑧𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑯 𐑞 𐑤𐑲𐑓——”

“𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑕 𐑓𐑹𐑢𐑼𐑛! 𐑳𐑐 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑥!” 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑤𐑲𐑑𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑧𐑯.

𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑑𐑩𐑛 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑒 𐑦𐑯𐑳𐑓 𐑑 𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑱𐑐 𐑞 𐑕𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑤𐑨𐑖 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑒𐑹𐑐𐑕 𐑕𐑵𐑯 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑒 𐑞 𐑕𐑰; 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑴 𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑒, 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑰𐑛, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑝 𐑞 𐑓𐑤𐑲𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑳𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑣𐑻 𐑣𐑳𐑤 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞𐑺 𐑜𐑴𐑕𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑟𐑩𐑥.

𐑨𐑟 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑯𐑬 𐑜𐑤𐑲𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑛𐑦𐑡𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑛 ·𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑲𐑑, 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡 𐑤𐑲𐑓-𐑚𐑶 𐑣𐑨𐑙𐑦𐑙 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛'𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑻𐑯 𐑒𐑱𐑥 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑩𐑕 𐑮𐑦𐑤𐑰𐑓.

“𐑣𐑭! 𐑘𐑪𐑯𐑛𐑼! 𐑤𐑫𐑒 𐑘𐑪𐑯𐑛𐑼, 𐑥𐑧𐑯!” 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 𐑩 𐑓𐑹𐑚𐑴𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑝𐑶𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑻 𐑢𐑱𐑒. “𐑦𐑯 𐑝𐑱𐑯, 𐑴, 𐑘𐑰 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑼𐑟, 𐑘𐑰 𐑓𐑤𐑲 𐑬𐑼 𐑕𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑧𐑮𐑾𐑤; 𐑘𐑰 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑑𐑻𐑯 𐑳𐑕 𐑘𐑹 𐑑𐑨𐑓𐑮𐑱𐑤 𐑑 𐑖𐑴 𐑳𐑕 𐑘𐑹 𐑒𐑪𐑓𐑦𐑯!”

·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 132. 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑦𐑥𐑓𐑩𐑯𐑦.

𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩 𐑒𐑤𐑽 𐑕𐑑𐑰𐑤-𐑚𐑤𐑵 𐑛𐑱. 𐑞 𐑓𐑻𐑥𐑩𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑺 𐑯 𐑕𐑰 𐑢𐑻 𐑣𐑸𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑧𐑐𐑼𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑷𐑤-𐑐𐑼𐑝𐑱𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑨𐑠𐑼; 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦, 𐑞 𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑝 𐑺 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑕𐑐𐑨𐑮𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑘𐑫𐑼 𐑯 𐑕𐑪𐑓𐑑, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑢𐑫𐑥𐑩𐑯'𐑟 𐑤𐑫𐑒, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑮𐑴𐑚𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑯 𐑥𐑨𐑯-𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑕𐑰 𐑣𐑰𐑝𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑤𐑪𐑙, 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑪𐑙, 𐑤𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑢𐑧𐑤𐑟, 𐑨𐑟 ·𐑕𐑨𐑥𐑕𐑩𐑯'𐑟 𐑗𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑤𐑰𐑐.

𐑣𐑦𐑞𐑼, 𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑞𐑼, 𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑲, 𐑜𐑤𐑲𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑞 𐑕𐑯𐑴-𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑝 𐑕𐑥𐑷𐑤, 𐑳𐑯𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑚𐑻𐑛𐑟; 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑞 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑔𐑷𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑓𐑧𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑯 𐑺; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑑 𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑴 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑛𐑰𐑐𐑕, 𐑓𐑸 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑪𐑑𐑩𐑥𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑚𐑤𐑵, 𐑮𐑳𐑖𐑑 𐑥𐑲𐑑𐑦 𐑤𐑩𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑔𐑩𐑯𐑟, 𐑕𐑹𐑛-𐑓𐑦𐑖, 𐑯 𐑖𐑸𐑒𐑕; 𐑯 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑪𐑙, 𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑛, 𐑥𐑻𐑛𐑼𐑩𐑕 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑥𐑨𐑕𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑰.

𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞𐑴 𐑞𐑳𐑕 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑦𐑯, 𐑞 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑯 𐑖𐑱𐑛𐑟 𐑯 𐑖𐑨𐑛𐑴𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑; 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑑𐑵 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑢𐑳𐑯; 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑞 𐑕𐑧𐑒𐑕, 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑻, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑢𐑦𐑖𐑑 𐑞𐑧𐑥.

𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑓𐑑, 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑮𐑶𐑩𐑤 𐑑𐑕𐑸 𐑯 𐑒𐑦𐑙, 𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑯 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑜𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑺 𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑚𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑯 𐑮𐑴𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑰; 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑨𐑟 𐑚𐑮𐑲𐑛 𐑑 𐑜𐑮𐑵𐑥. 𐑯 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑜𐑻𐑛𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑤𐑲𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑣𐑼𐑲𐑟𐑩𐑯, 𐑩 𐑕𐑪𐑓𐑑 𐑯 𐑑𐑮𐑧𐑥𐑿𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑥𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯—𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑯 𐑣𐑽 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑦𐑒𐑢𐑱𐑑𐑼—𐑛𐑦𐑯𐑴𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑞 𐑓𐑪𐑯𐑛, 𐑔𐑮𐑪𐑚𐑦𐑙 𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑕𐑑, 𐑞 𐑤𐑳𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑤𐑸𐑥𐑟, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑞 𐑐𐑫𐑼 𐑚𐑮𐑲𐑛 𐑜𐑱𐑝 𐑣𐑻 𐑚𐑫𐑟𐑩𐑥 𐑩𐑢𐑱.

𐑑𐑲𐑛 𐑳𐑐 𐑯 𐑑𐑢𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛; 𐑯𐑸𐑤𐑛 𐑯 𐑯𐑪𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑮𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑟; 𐑣𐑨𐑜𐑼𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑓𐑻𐑥 𐑯 𐑳𐑯𐑘𐑰𐑤𐑛𐑦𐑙; 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑲𐑟 𐑜𐑤𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑒𐑴𐑤𐑟, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑜𐑤𐑴 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑨𐑖𐑩𐑟 𐑝 𐑮𐑵𐑦𐑯; 𐑳𐑯𐑑𐑪𐑑𐑼𐑦𐑙 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑕𐑑𐑫𐑛 𐑓𐑹𐑔 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑒𐑤𐑽𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑥𐑹𐑯; 𐑤𐑦𐑓𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑐𐑤𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑛 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑥𐑩𐑑 𐑝 𐑩 𐑚𐑮𐑬 𐑑 𐑞 𐑓𐑺 𐑜𐑻𐑤'𐑟 𐑓𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑛 𐑝 𐑣𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑯.

𐑴, 𐑦𐑥𐑹𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑯𐑓𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦, 𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦 𐑝 𐑞 𐑨𐑠𐑼! 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑦𐑟𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑦𐑙𐑛 𐑒𐑮𐑰𐑗𐑼𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑤𐑦𐑒 𐑷𐑤 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑳𐑕! 𐑕𐑢𐑰𐑑 𐑗𐑲𐑤𐑛𐑣𐑫𐑛 𐑝 𐑺 𐑯 𐑕𐑒𐑲! 𐑣𐑬 𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑦𐑝𐑾𐑕 𐑢𐑻 𐑘𐑰 𐑝 𐑴𐑤𐑛 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚'𐑟 𐑒𐑤𐑴𐑕-𐑒𐑶𐑤𐑛 𐑢𐑴! 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑕𐑴 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑲 𐑕𐑰𐑯 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 ·𐑥𐑦𐑮𐑾𐑥 𐑯 ·𐑥𐑸𐑔𐑩, 𐑤𐑭𐑓𐑦𐑙-𐑲𐑛 𐑧𐑤𐑝𐑟, 𐑣𐑰𐑛𐑤𐑩𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑜𐑨𐑥𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑼𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑞𐑺 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑕𐑲𐑼; 𐑕𐑐𐑹𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑕𐑻𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑕𐑦𐑯𐑡𐑛 𐑤𐑪𐑒𐑕 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑜𐑮𐑵 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑥𐑸𐑡 𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑚𐑻𐑯𐑑-𐑬𐑑 𐑒𐑮𐑱𐑑𐑼 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑯.

𐑕𐑤𐑴𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑮𐑪𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑒 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑕𐑒𐑳𐑑𐑩𐑤, ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑤𐑰𐑯𐑛 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑞 𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑗𐑑 𐑣𐑬 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑖𐑨𐑛𐑴 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼 𐑕𐑨𐑙𐑒 𐑯 𐑕𐑨𐑙𐑒 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑜𐑱𐑟, 𐑞 𐑥𐑹 𐑯 𐑞 𐑥𐑹 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑴𐑝 𐑑 𐑐𐑽𐑕 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑓𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑑𐑦. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞 𐑤𐑳𐑝𐑤𐑦 𐑼𐑴𐑥𐑩𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑗𐑭𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑺 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑥 𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑤, 𐑓 𐑩 𐑥𐑴𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑, 𐑞 𐑒𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑼𐑩𐑕 𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑴𐑤. 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑜𐑤𐑨𐑛, 𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑦 𐑺, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑥 𐑕𐑒𐑲, 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑴𐑒 𐑯 𐑒𐑼𐑧𐑕 𐑣𐑦𐑥; 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑐-𐑥𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛, 𐑕𐑴 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑒𐑮𐑵𐑩𐑤—𐑓𐑼𐑚𐑦𐑛𐑦𐑙—𐑯𐑬 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑩𐑓𐑧𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑑 𐑸𐑥𐑟 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚𐑼𐑯 𐑯𐑧𐑒, 𐑯 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑕𐑰𐑥 𐑑 𐑡𐑶𐑩𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑪𐑚 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑓 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑢𐑳𐑯, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑬𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑢𐑦𐑤𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑯 𐑻𐑦𐑙, 𐑖𐑰 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑓𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑻 𐑣𐑸𐑑 𐑑 𐑕𐑱𐑝 𐑯 𐑑 𐑚𐑤𐑧𐑕. 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑚𐑦𐑯𐑰𐑔 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑤𐑬𐑗𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑑 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑛𐑮𐑪𐑐𐑑 𐑩 𐑑𐑽 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑕𐑰; 𐑯𐑹 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑩𐑕𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑒 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑱𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑢𐑧𐑤𐑔 𐑨𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑢𐑰 𐑛𐑮𐑪𐑐.

𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒 𐑕𐑷 𐑞 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑥𐑨𐑯; 𐑕𐑷 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑣𐑬 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑧𐑝𐑦𐑤𐑦 𐑤𐑰𐑯𐑛 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑞 𐑕𐑲𐑛; 𐑯 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑑 𐑣𐑽 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑴𐑯 𐑑𐑮𐑵 𐑣𐑸𐑑 𐑞 𐑥𐑧𐑠𐑼𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑕𐑪𐑚𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑴𐑤 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑼 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑼𐑧𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑼𐑬𐑯𐑛. 𐑒𐑺𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑑 𐑑𐑳𐑗 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑹 𐑚𐑰 𐑯𐑴𐑑𐑦𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑣𐑰 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑛𐑮𐑵 𐑯𐑽 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑫𐑛 𐑞𐑺.

𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑛.

“𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒!”

“𐑕𐑻.”

“𐑴, ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒! 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑩 𐑥𐑲𐑤𐑛, 𐑥𐑲𐑤𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛, 𐑯 𐑩 𐑥𐑲𐑤𐑛 𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑒𐑲. 𐑪𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩 𐑛𐑱—𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩 𐑕𐑢𐑰𐑑𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑨𐑟 𐑞𐑦𐑕—𐑲 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑒 𐑥𐑲 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑤—𐑩 𐑚𐑶-𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑽 𐑝 𐑱𐑑𐑰𐑯! 𐑓𐑹𐑑𐑦—𐑓𐑹𐑑𐑦—𐑓𐑹𐑑𐑦 𐑘𐑽𐑟 𐑩𐑜𐑴!—𐑩𐑜𐑴! 𐑓𐑹𐑑𐑦 𐑘𐑽𐑟 𐑝 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑿𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙! 𐑓𐑹𐑑𐑦 𐑘𐑽𐑟 𐑝 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑝𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯, 𐑯 𐑐𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑤, 𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑹𐑥-𐑑𐑲𐑥! 𐑓𐑹𐑑𐑦 𐑘𐑽𐑟 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑐𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑕𐑰! 𐑓 𐑓𐑹𐑑𐑦 𐑘𐑽𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑟 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑓𐑼𐑕𐑱𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑞 𐑐𐑰𐑕𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛, 𐑓 𐑓𐑹𐑑𐑦 𐑘𐑽𐑟 𐑑 𐑥𐑱𐑒 𐑢𐑹 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑣𐑪𐑮𐑼𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑛𐑰𐑐! 𐑲 𐑯 𐑘𐑧𐑕, ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒, 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑓𐑹𐑑𐑦 𐑘𐑽𐑟 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑩𐑖𐑹. 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑲 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒 𐑝 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑤𐑲𐑓 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑤𐑧𐑛; 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑤𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑕𐑪𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑿𐑛 𐑦𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑚𐑰𐑯; 𐑞 𐑥𐑱𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑛, 𐑢𐑷𐑤𐑛-𐑑𐑬𐑯 𐑝 𐑩 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯'𐑟 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑒𐑤𐑵𐑕𐑦𐑝𐑯𐑩𐑕, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑩𐑛𐑥𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑕𐑥𐑷𐑤 𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑑 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑕𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑔𐑦 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑯 𐑒𐑳𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑦 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑—𐑴, 𐑢𐑽𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑕! 𐑣𐑧𐑝𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑕! 𐑜𐑦𐑯𐑦-𐑒𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑤𐑱𐑝𐑼𐑦 𐑝 𐑕𐑪𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑼𐑦 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑭𐑯𐑛!—𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑲 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒 𐑝 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑦𐑕; 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑣𐑭𐑓-𐑕𐑩𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑛, 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑴 𐑒𐑰𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑯𐑴𐑯 𐑑 𐑥𐑰 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹—𐑯 𐑣𐑬 𐑓 𐑓𐑹𐑑𐑦 𐑘𐑽𐑟 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑓𐑧𐑛 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑛𐑮𐑲 𐑕𐑷𐑤𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑓𐑺—𐑓𐑦𐑑 𐑧𐑥𐑚𐑤𐑩𐑥 𐑝 𐑞 𐑛𐑮𐑲 𐑯𐑳𐑮𐑦𐑖𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑥𐑲 𐑕𐑶𐑤!—𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑞 𐑐𐑫𐑼𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑖 𐑓𐑮𐑵𐑑 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑛𐑱𐑤𐑦 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛, 𐑯 𐑚𐑮𐑴𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛'𐑟 𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑖 𐑚𐑮𐑧𐑛 𐑑 𐑥𐑲 𐑥𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑦 𐑒𐑮𐑳𐑕𐑑𐑕—𐑩𐑢𐑱, 𐑣𐑴𐑤 𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑩𐑢𐑱, 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑘𐑳𐑙 𐑜𐑻𐑤-𐑢𐑲𐑓 𐑲 𐑢𐑧𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑐𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑓𐑦𐑓𐑑𐑦, 𐑯 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑛 𐑓 ·𐑒𐑱𐑐 ·𐑣𐑹𐑯 𐑞 𐑯𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑 𐑛𐑱, 𐑤𐑰𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑛𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑲 𐑥𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑡 𐑐𐑦𐑤𐑴—𐑢𐑲𐑓? 𐑢𐑲𐑓?—𐑮𐑭𐑞𐑼 𐑩 𐑢𐑦𐑛𐑴 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑻 𐑣𐑳𐑟𐑚𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑩𐑤𐑲𐑝! 𐑲, 𐑲 𐑢𐑦𐑛𐑴𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑐𐑫𐑼 𐑜𐑻𐑤 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑲 𐑥𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑛 𐑣𐑻, ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒; 𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑞 𐑥𐑨𐑛𐑯𐑩𐑕, 𐑞 𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑯𐑟𐑦, 𐑞 𐑚𐑶𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑤𐑳𐑛 𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑥𐑴𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑮𐑬, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑢𐑦𐑗, 𐑓 𐑩 𐑔𐑬𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑤𐑴𐑼𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑴𐑤𐑛 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑓𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑾𐑕𐑤𐑦, 𐑓𐑴𐑥𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑗𐑱𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑮𐑱—𐑥𐑹 𐑩 𐑛𐑰𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑩 𐑥𐑨𐑯!—𐑲, 𐑲! 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑩 𐑓𐑹𐑑𐑦 𐑘𐑽𐑟' 𐑓𐑵𐑤—𐑓𐑵𐑤—𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑓𐑵𐑤, 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑴𐑤𐑛 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑚𐑰𐑯! 𐑢𐑲 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑓 𐑝 𐑞 𐑗𐑱𐑕? 𐑢𐑲 𐑢𐑽𐑦, 𐑯 𐑐𐑷𐑤𐑟𐑦 𐑞 𐑸𐑥 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑹, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑲𐑼𐑯, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑕? 𐑣𐑬 𐑞 𐑮𐑦𐑗𐑼 𐑹 𐑚𐑧𐑑𐑼 𐑦𐑟 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑯𐑬? 𐑚𐑦𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛. 𐑴, ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒! 𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑣𐑸𐑛, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑽𐑦 𐑤𐑴𐑛 𐑲 𐑚𐑺, 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑐𐑫𐑼 𐑤𐑧𐑜 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑕𐑯𐑨𐑗𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑥𐑰? 𐑣𐑽, 𐑚𐑮𐑳𐑖 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑣𐑺 𐑩𐑕𐑲𐑛; 𐑦𐑑 𐑚𐑤𐑲𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑥𐑰, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑲 𐑕𐑰𐑥 𐑑 𐑢𐑰𐑐. 𐑤𐑪𐑒𐑕 𐑕𐑴 𐑜𐑮𐑱 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑜𐑮𐑴 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑬𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑨𐑖𐑩𐑟! 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑛𐑵 𐑲 𐑤𐑫𐑒 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑴𐑤𐑛, 𐑕𐑴 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦, 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑴𐑤𐑛, ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒? 𐑲 𐑓𐑰𐑤 𐑛𐑧𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑓𐑱𐑯𐑑, 𐑚𐑬𐑛, 𐑯 𐑣𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑑, 𐑨𐑟 𐑞𐑴 𐑲 𐑢𐑻 ·𐑨𐑛𐑩𐑥, 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑜𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑦𐑯𐑰𐑔 𐑞 𐑐𐑲𐑤𐑛 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑗𐑼𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑦𐑯𐑕 ·𐑐𐑨𐑮𐑩𐑛𐑲𐑕. 𐑜𐑪𐑛! 𐑜𐑪𐑛! 𐑜𐑪𐑛!—𐑒𐑮𐑨𐑒 𐑥𐑲 𐑣𐑸𐑑!—𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑝 𐑥𐑲 𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑯!—𐑥𐑪𐑒𐑼𐑦! 𐑥𐑪𐑒𐑼𐑦! 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑼, 𐑚𐑲𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑪𐑒𐑼𐑦 𐑝 𐑜𐑮𐑱 𐑣𐑺𐑟, 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑲 𐑤𐑦𐑝𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑳𐑓 𐑡𐑶 𐑑 𐑢𐑺 𐑘𐑰; 𐑯 𐑕𐑰𐑥 𐑯 𐑓𐑰𐑤 𐑞𐑳𐑕 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑪𐑤𐑼𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑴𐑤𐑛? 𐑒𐑤𐑴𐑕! 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑒𐑤𐑴𐑕 𐑑 𐑥𐑰, ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒; 𐑤𐑧𐑑 𐑥𐑰 𐑤𐑫𐑒 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑩 𐑣𐑿𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑲; 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑧𐑑𐑼 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑑 𐑜𐑱𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑕𐑰 𐑹 𐑕𐑒𐑲; 𐑚𐑧𐑑𐑼 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑑 𐑜𐑱𐑟 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 ·𐑜𐑪𐑛. 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑯 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛; 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑚𐑮𐑲𐑑 𐑣𐑸𐑔-𐑕𐑑𐑴𐑯! 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑦𐑟 𐑞 𐑥𐑨𐑡𐑦𐑒 𐑜𐑤𐑭𐑕, 𐑥𐑨𐑯; 𐑲 𐑕𐑰 𐑥𐑲 𐑢𐑲𐑓 𐑯 𐑥𐑲 𐑗𐑲𐑤𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑲𐑯 𐑲. 𐑯𐑴, 𐑯𐑴; 𐑕𐑑𐑱 𐑪𐑯 𐑚𐑹𐑛, 𐑪𐑯 𐑚𐑹𐑛!—𐑤𐑴𐑼 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑲 𐑛𐑵; 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑚𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑜𐑦𐑝𐑟 𐑗𐑱𐑕 𐑑 ·𐑥𐑪𐑚𐑦 ·𐑛𐑦𐑒. 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑟𐑼𐑛 𐑖𐑨𐑤 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑞𐑲𐑯. 𐑯𐑴, 𐑯𐑴! 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑓𐑸 𐑩𐑢𐑱 𐑣𐑴𐑥 𐑲 𐑕𐑰 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑲!”

“𐑴, 𐑥𐑲 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯! 𐑥𐑲 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯! 𐑯𐑴𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑴𐑤! 𐑜𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑣𐑸𐑑, 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑷𐑤! 𐑢𐑲 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑜𐑦𐑝 𐑗𐑱𐑕 𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑓𐑦𐑖! 𐑩𐑢𐑱 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑥𐑰! 𐑤𐑧𐑑 𐑳𐑕 𐑓𐑤𐑲 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑛𐑧𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼𐑟! 𐑤𐑧𐑑 𐑳𐑕 𐑣𐑴𐑥! 𐑢𐑲𐑓 𐑯 𐑗𐑲𐑤𐑛, 𐑑𐑵, 𐑸 ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒'𐑕—𐑢𐑲𐑓 𐑯 𐑗𐑲𐑤𐑛 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑮𐑳𐑞𐑼𐑤𐑦, 𐑕𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑤𐑦, 𐑐𐑤𐑱-𐑓𐑧𐑤𐑴 𐑿𐑔; 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑨𐑟 𐑞𐑲𐑯, 𐑕𐑻, 𐑸 𐑞 𐑢𐑲𐑓 𐑯 𐑗𐑲𐑤𐑛 𐑝 𐑞𐑲 𐑤𐑳𐑝𐑦𐑙, 𐑤𐑪𐑙𐑦𐑙, 𐑐𐑩𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑱𐑡! 𐑩𐑢𐑱! 𐑤𐑧𐑑 𐑳𐑕 𐑩𐑢𐑱!—𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑤𐑧𐑑 𐑥𐑰 𐑷𐑤𐑑𐑼 𐑞 𐑒𐑹𐑕! 𐑣𐑬 𐑗𐑽𐑦𐑤𐑦, 𐑣𐑬 𐑣𐑦𐑤𐑺𐑾𐑕𐑤𐑦, 𐑴 𐑥𐑲 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯, 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑢𐑰 𐑚𐑴𐑤 𐑪𐑯 𐑬𐑼 𐑢𐑱 𐑑 𐑕𐑰 𐑴𐑤𐑛 ·𐑯𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑑 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯! 𐑲 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒, 𐑕𐑻, 𐑞𐑱 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑥𐑲𐑤𐑛 𐑚𐑤𐑵 𐑛𐑱𐑟, 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑨𐑟 𐑞𐑦𐑕, 𐑦𐑯 ·𐑯𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑑.”

“𐑞𐑱 𐑣𐑨𐑝, 𐑞𐑱 𐑣𐑨𐑝. 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑕𐑰𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑥—𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑼 𐑛𐑱𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑥𐑹𐑯𐑦𐑙. 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑑𐑲𐑥—𐑘𐑧𐑕, 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑵𐑯 𐑯𐑨𐑐 𐑯𐑬—𐑞 𐑚𐑶 𐑝𐑦𐑝𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑢𐑱𐑒𐑕; 𐑕𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑳𐑐 𐑦𐑯 𐑚𐑧𐑛; 𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑑𐑧𐑤𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑝 𐑥𐑰, 𐑝 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑥𐑰; 𐑣𐑬 𐑲 𐑨𐑥 𐑩𐑚𐑮𐑷𐑛 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑛𐑰𐑐, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑚𐑨𐑒 𐑑 𐑛𐑭𐑯𐑕 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯.”

“'𐑑𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑲 ·𐑥𐑺𐑦, 𐑥𐑲 ·𐑥𐑺𐑦 𐑣𐑻𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓! 𐑖𐑰 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑲 𐑚𐑶, 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑥𐑹𐑯𐑦𐑙, 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑚𐑰 𐑒𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑛 𐑑 𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑤 𐑑 𐑒𐑨𐑗 𐑞 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑜𐑤𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑕 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑭𐑞𐑼'𐑟 𐑕𐑱𐑤! 𐑘𐑧𐑕, 𐑘𐑧𐑕! 𐑯𐑴 𐑥𐑹! 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑛𐑳𐑯! 𐑢𐑰 𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑓 ·𐑯𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑑! 𐑒𐑳𐑥, 𐑥𐑲 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯, 𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑛𐑦 𐑬𐑑 𐑞 𐑒𐑹𐑕, 𐑯 𐑤𐑧𐑑 𐑳𐑕 𐑩𐑢𐑱! 𐑕𐑰, 𐑕𐑰! 𐑞 𐑚𐑶'𐑟 𐑓𐑱𐑕 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑴! 𐑞 𐑚𐑶'𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑤!”

𐑚𐑳𐑑 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚'𐑟 𐑜𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑕 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩𐑝𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑛; 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑚𐑤𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑵𐑑 𐑑𐑮𐑰 𐑣𐑰 𐑖𐑫𐑒, 𐑯 𐑒𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑, 𐑕𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑛 𐑨𐑐𐑩𐑤 𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑶𐑤.

“𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑑, 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑯𐑱𐑥𐑤𐑩𐑕, 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑵𐑑𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤, 𐑳𐑯𐑻𐑔𐑤𐑦 𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑑; 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑒𐑳𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑙, 𐑣𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑯 𐑤𐑹𐑛 𐑯 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑼, 𐑯 𐑒𐑮𐑵𐑩𐑤, 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑹𐑕𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑧𐑥𐑐𐑼𐑼 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑭𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑥𐑰; 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑯𐑨𐑗𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑤𐑳𐑝𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑯 𐑤𐑪𐑙𐑦𐑙𐑟, 𐑲 𐑕𐑴 𐑒𐑰𐑐 𐑐𐑫𐑖𐑦𐑙, 𐑯 𐑒𐑮𐑬𐑛𐑦𐑙, 𐑯 𐑡𐑨𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑲𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑪𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑑𐑲𐑥; 𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑤𐑩𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑥𐑱𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑰 𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑦 𐑑 𐑛𐑵 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑲 𐑴𐑯 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑐𐑼, 𐑯𐑨𐑗𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑣𐑸𐑑, 𐑲 ·𐑛𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑴 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑨𐑟 𐑛𐑺? 𐑦𐑟 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚, ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚? 𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑲, ·𐑜𐑪𐑛, 𐑹 𐑣𐑵, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑦𐑓𐑑𐑕 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑸𐑥? 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑓 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑯 𐑥𐑵𐑝 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑨𐑟 𐑩𐑯 𐑧𐑮𐑩𐑯𐑛-𐑚𐑶 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑯; 𐑯𐑹 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑕𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑑𐑸 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑮𐑦𐑝𐑪𐑤𐑝, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑦𐑟𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑐𐑬𐑼; 𐑣𐑬 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑕𐑥𐑷𐑤 𐑣𐑸𐑑 𐑚𐑰𐑑; 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑕𐑥𐑷𐑤 𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑯 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒 𐑔𐑷𐑑𐑕; 𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑧𐑕 ·𐑜𐑪𐑛 𐑛𐑳𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑚𐑰𐑑𐑦𐑙, 𐑛𐑳𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑦𐑙, 𐑛𐑳𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑙, 𐑯 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑲. 𐑚𐑲 𐑣𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑯, 𐑥𐑨𐑯, 𐑢𐑰 𐑸 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑛 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑯 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛, 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑘𐑪𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑤𐑩𐑕, 𐑯 ·𐑓𐑱𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑞 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑕𐑐𐑲𐑒. 𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑑𐑲𐑥, 𐑤𐑴! 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑥𐑲𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑒𐑲, 𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑳𐑯𐑕𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑕𐑰! 𐑤𐑫𐑒! 𐑕𐑰 𐑘𐑪𐑯 ·𐑨𐑤𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑹! 𐑣𐑵 𐑐𐑫𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑑 𐑗𐑱𐑕 𐑯 𐑓𐑨𐑙 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑓𐑤𐑲𐑦𐑙-𐑓𐑦𐑖? 𐑢𐑺 𐑛𐑵 𐑥𐑻𐑛𐑼𐑼𐑟 𐑜𐑴, 𐑥𐑨𐑯! 𐑣𐑵'𐑟 𐑑 𐑛𐑵𐑥, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑞 𐑡𐑳𐑡 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑦𐑟 𐑛𐑮𐑨𐑜𐑛 𐑑 𐑞 𐑚𐑸? 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑩 𐑥𐑲𐑤𐑛, 𐑥𐑲𐑤𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛, 𐑯 𐑩 𐑥𐑲𐑤𐑛 𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑒𐑲; 𐑯 𐑞 𐑺 𐑕𐑥𐑧𐑤𐑟 𐑯𐑬, 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑓 𐑦𐑑 𐑚𐑤𐑵 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑩 𐑓𐑸-𐑩𐑢𐑱 𐑥𐑧𐑛𐑴; 𐑞𐑱 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑥𐑱𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑱 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑢𐑺 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑞 𐑕𐑤𐑴𐑐𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑰𐑟, ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑥𐑴𐑼𐑟 𐑸 𐑕𐑤𐑰𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑞 𐑯𐑿-𐑥𐑴𐑯 𐑣𐑱. 𐑕𐑤𐑰𐑐𐑦𐑙? 𐑲, 𐑑𐑶𐑤 𐑢𐑰 𐑣𐑬 𐑢𐑰 𐑥𐑱, 𐑢𐑰 𐑷𐑤 𐑕𐑤𐑰𐑐 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑰𐑤𐑛. 𐑕𐑤𐑰𐑐? 𐑲, 𐑯 𐑮𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑩𐑥𐑦𐑛 𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑯𐑯𐑩𐑕; 𐑨𐑟 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑘𐑽'𐑟 𐑕𐑲𐑞𐑟 𐑓𐑤𐑳𐑙 𐑛𐑬𐑯, 𐑯 𐑤𐑧𐑓𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑣𐑭𐑓-𐑒𐑳𐑑 𐑕𐑢𐑭𐑔𐑕—·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒!”

𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑚𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑗𐑑 𐑑 𐑩 𐑒𐑹𐑐𐑕'𐑩𐑟 𐑣𐑿 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑺, 𐑞 ·𐑥𐑱𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑕𐑑𐑴𐑤𐑩𐑯 𐑩𐑢𐑱.

𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑒𐑮𐑪𐑕𐑑 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑒 𐑑 𐑜𐑱𐑟 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑕𐑲𐑛; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑨𐑑 𐑑𐑵 𐑮𐑦𐑓𐑤𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑛, 𐑓𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑑 𐑲𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼 𐑞𐑺. 𐑓𐑧𐑛𐑩𐑤𐑩 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑥𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑩𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑤𐑰𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑮𐑱𐑤.

·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 133. 𐑞 ·𐑗𐑱𐑕—𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑛𐑱.

𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑯𐑲𐑑, 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑥𐑦𐑛-𐑢𐑪𐑗, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑞 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑥𐑨𐑯—𐑨𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑴𐑯𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑟—𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑐𐑑 𐑓𐑹𐑔 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑕𐑒𐑳𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑣𐑰 𐑤𐑰𐑯𐑛, 𐑯 𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑦𐑝𐑩𐑑-𐑣𐑴𐑤, 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑳𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑔𐑮𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑬𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑱𐑕 𐑓𐑽𐑕𐑤𐑦, 𐑕𐑯𐑳𐑓𐑦𐑙 𐑳𐑐 𐑞 𐑕𐑰 𐑺 𐑨𐑟 𐑩 𐑕𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑕 𐑖𐑦𐑐'𐑕 𐑛𐑪𐑜 𐑢𐑦𐑤, 𐑦𐑯 𐑛𐑮𐑷𐑦𐑙 𐑯𐑲 𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑚𐑸𐑚𐑼𐑩𐑕 𐑲𐑤. 𐑣𐑰 𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑺𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑩 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑯𐑽. 𐑕𐑵𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑽 𐑴𐑛𐑼, 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑑 𐑩 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑜𐑦𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑓𐑹𐑔 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑤𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑐𐑨𐑤𐑐𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑢𐑪𐑗; 𐑯𐑹 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑥𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑯𐑼 𐑕𐑼𐑐𐑮𐑲𐑟𐑛 𐑢𐑧𐑯, 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑕, 𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑞 𐑛𐑪𐑜-𐑝𐑱𐑯, 𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑨𐑕𐑼𐑑𐑱𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑲𐑕 𐑚𐑺𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑞 𐑴𐑛𐑼 𐑨𐑟 𐑯𐑽𐑤𐑦 𐑨𐑟 𐑐𐑪𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤, ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑮𐑨𐑐𐑦𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑹𐑛𐑼𐑛 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐'𐑕 𐑒𐑹𐑕 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑕𐑤𐑲𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑷𐑤𐑑𐑼𐑛, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑤 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑖𐑹𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑛.

𐑞 𐑩𐑒𐑿𐑑 𐑐𐑪𐑤𐑩𐑕𐑦 𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑑𐑱𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑥𐑵𐑝𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑩𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑝𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑨𐑑 𐑛𐑱𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑒, 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑕𐑲𐑑 𐑝 𐑩 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑕𐑤𐑰𐑒 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑰 𐑛𐑦𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑯 𐑤𐑧𐑙𐑔𐑢𐑲𐑟 𐑩𐑣𐑧𐑛, 𐑕𐑥𐑵𐑞 𐑨𐑟 𐑶𐑤, 𐑯 𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑧𐑥𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑐𐑤𐑰𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼𐑦 𐑮𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑚𐑹𐑛𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑑, 𐑞 𐑐𐑪𐑤𐑦𐑖𐑑 𐑥𐑦𐑑𐑨𐑤𐑦𐑒-𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑥𐑸𐑒𐑕 𐑝 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑕𐑢𐑦𐑓𐑑 𐑑𐑲𐑛-𐑮𐑦𐑐, 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑥𐑬𐑔 𐑝 𐑩 𐑛𐑰𐑐, 𐑮𐑨𐑐𐑦𐑛 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑰𐑥.

“𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑞 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑-𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑟! 𐑒𐑷𐑤 𐑷𐑤 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟!”

𐑔𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑚𐑳𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑒𐑤𐑳𐑚𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑕𐑐𐑲𐑒𐑕 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑴𐑒𐑕𐑩𐑤 𐑛𐑧𐑒, ·𐑛𐑨𐑜𐑵 𐑮𐑬𐑟𐑛 𐑞 𐑕𐑤𐑰𐑐𐑼𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑡𐑳𐑡𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑒𐑤𐑨𐑐𐑕 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑱 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑑 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑣𐑱𐑤 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑕𐑒𐑳𐑑𐑩𐑤, 𐑕𐑴 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑱𐑯𐑾𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑞𐑱 𐑩𐑐𐑽 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞𐑺 𐑒𐑤𐑴𐑞𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟.

“𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑛'𐑘𐑰 𐑕𐑰?” 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚, 𐑓𐑤𐑨𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑱𐑕 𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑒𐑲.

“𐑯𐑳𐑔𐑦𐑙, 𐑯𐑳𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑻!” 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞 𐑕𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑣𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑤𐑲.

“·𐑑'𐑜𐑨𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑟!—𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑯𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑟! 𐑱𐑤𐑴 𐑯 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑓𐑑, 𐑯 𐑪𐑯 𐑚𐑴𐑔 𐑕𐑲𐑛𐑟!”

𐑷𐑤 𐑕𐑱𐑤 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑧𐑑, 𐑣𐑰 𐑯𐑬 𐑒𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑤𐑵𐑕 𐑞 𐑤𐑲𐑓-𐑤𐑲𐑯, 𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑻𐑝𐑛 𐑓 𐑕𐑢𐑱𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑑 𐑞 𐑥𐑱𐑯 𐑮𐑶𐑩𐑤-𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑧𐑛; 𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑓𐑿 𐑥𐑴𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑞𐑱 𐑢𐑻 𐑣𐑶𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑞𐑦𐑞𐑼, 𐑢𐑧𐑯, 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑑𐑵 𐑔𐑻𐑛𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑱 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑓𐑑, 𐑯 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑐𐑽𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑞 𐑣𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑝𐑱𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑢𐑰𐑯 𐑞 𐑥𐑱𐑯-𐑑𐑪𐑐-𐑕𐑱𐑤 𐑯 𐑑𐑪𐑐-𐑜𐑨𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑑-𐑕𐑱𐑤, 𐑣𐑰 𐑮𐑱𐑟𐑛 𐑩 𐑜𐑳𐑤-𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑒𐑮𐑲 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑺. “𐑞𐑺 𐑖𐑰 𐑚𐑤𐑴𐑟!—𐑞𐑺 𐑖𐑰 𐑚𐑤𐑴𐑟! 𐑩 𐑣𐑳𐑥𐑐 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑕𐑯𐑴-𐑣𐑦𐑤! 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 ·𐑥𐑪𐑚𐑦 ·𐑛𐑦𐑒!”

𐑓𐑲𐑼𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑲 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑕𐑦𐑥𐑩𐑤𐑑𐑱𐑯𐑾𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑳𐑐 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑤𐑫𐑒-𐑬𐑑𐑕, 𐑞 𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑪𐑯 𐑛𐑧𐑒 𐑮𐑳𐑖𐑑 𐑑 𐑞 𐑮𐑦𐑜𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑞 𐑓𐑱𐑥𐑩𐑕 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑞𐑱 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑕𐑴 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑐𐑼𐑕𐑿𐑦𐑙. 𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑯𐑬 𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑲𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑐𐑻𐑗, 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑓𐑰𐑑 𐑩𐑚𐑳𐑝 𐑞 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑤𐑫𐑒-𐑬𐑑𐑕, ·𐑑𐑨𐑖𐑑𐑱𐑜𐑴 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑡𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑯𐑰𐑔 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑒𐑨𐑐 𐑝 𐑞 𐑑𐑪𐑐-𐑜𐑨𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑑-𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑, 𐑕𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑾𐑯'𐑟 𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑪𐑯 𐑩 𐑤𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑦𐑞 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚'𐑟 𐑣𐑰𐑤. 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑣𐑲𐑑 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑬 𐑕𐑰𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑥𐑲𐑤 𐑹 𐑕𐑴 𐑩𐑣𐑧𐑛, 𐑨𐑑 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑮𐑴𐑤 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑰 𐑮𐑦𐑝𐑰𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑲 𐑕𐑐𐑸𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑳𐑥𐑐, 𐑯 𐑮𐑧𐑜𐑿𐑤𐑼𐑤𐑦 𐑡𐑧𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑕𐑐𐑬𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑺. 𐑑 𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑧𐑡𐑵𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑥𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑯𐑼𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑕𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑕𐑐𐑬𐑑 𐑞𐑱 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑕𐑴 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑩𐑜𐑴 𐑚𐑦𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑥𐑵𐑯𐑤𐑦𐑑 ·𐑩𐑑𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑯 ·𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑾𐑯 ·𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟.

“𐑯 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑯𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑘𐑰 𐑕𐑰 𐑦𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹?” 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚, 𐑣𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑐𐑻𐑗𐑑 𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑼𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥.

“𐑲 𐑕𐑷 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑, 𐑕𐑻, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑛𐑦𐑛, 𐑯 𐑲 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 𐑬𐑑,” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 ·𐑑𐑨𐑖𐑑𐑱𐑜𐑴.

“𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑; 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥—𐑯𐑴, 𐑞 𐑛𐑳𐑚𐑤𐑵𐑯 𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑲𐑯, ·𐑓𐑱𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑻𐑝𐑛 𐑞 𐑛𐑳𐑚𐑤𐑵𐑯 𐑓 𐑥𐑰. 𐑲 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦; 𐑯𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑘𐑰 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑮𐑱𐑟𐑛 𐑞 ·𐑢𐑲𐑑 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑. 𐑞𐑺 𐑖𐑰 𐑚𐑤𐑴𐑟!—𐑞𐑺 𐑖𐑰 𐑚𐑤𐑴𐑟!—𐑞𐑺 𐑖𐑰 𐑚𐑤𐑴𐑟! 𐑞𐑺 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯!—𐑞𐑺 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯!” 𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛, 𐑦𐑯 𐑤𐑪𐑙-𐑛𐑮𐑷𐑯, 𐑤𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑼𐑦𐑙, 𐑥𐑦𐑔𐑪𐑛𐑦𐑒 𐑑𐑴𐑯𐑟, 𐑩𐑑𐑿𐑯𐑛 𐑑 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑨𐑡𐑵𐑩𐑤 𐑐𐑮𐑴𐑤𐑪𐑙𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤'𐑟 𐑝𐑦𐑟𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑡𐑧𐑑𐑕. “𐑣𐑰'𐑟 𐑜𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑕𐑬𐑯𐑛! 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑯𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑟! 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑑𐑪𐑐-𐑜𐑨𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑑-𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑟! 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕. ·𐑥𐑼 ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒, 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑧𐑥𐑚𐑼, 𐑕𐑑𐑱 𐑪𐑯 𐑚𐑹𐑛, 𐑯 𐑒𐑰𐑐 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐. 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑥 𐑞𐑺! 𐑤𐑳𐑓, 𐑤𐑳𐑓 𐑩 𐑐𐑶𐑯𐑑! 𐑕𐑴; 𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑛𐑦, 𐑥𐑨𐑯, 𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑛𐑦! 𐑞𐑺 𐑜𐑴 𐑓𐑤𐑵𐑒𐑕! 𐑯𐑴, 𐑯𐑴; 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑒 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼! 𐑷𐑤 𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑦 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕 𐑞𐑺? 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑚𐑲, 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑚𐑲! 𐑤𐑴𐑼 𐑥𐑰, ·𐑥𐑼 ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒; 𐑤𐑴𐑼, 𐑤𐑴𐑼,—𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑒, 𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑒𐑼!” 𐑯 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑤𐑦𐑛 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑞 𐑺 𐑑 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑒.

“𐑣𐑰 𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑑 𐑤𐑰𐑢𐑼𐑛, 𐑕𐑻,” 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚, “𐑮𐑲𐑑 𐑩𐑢𐑱 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑳𐑕; 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑕𐑰𐑯 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑘𐑧𐑑.”

“𐑚𐑰 𐑛𐑳𐑥, 𐑥𐑨𐑯! 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑕𐑩𐑟! 𐑣𐑸𐑛 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑞 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑥!—𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑕 𐑳𐑐! 𐑖𐑦𐑝𐑼 𐑣𐑻!—𐑖𐑦𐑝𐑼 𐑣𐑻!—𐑕𐑴; 𐑢𐑧𐑤 𐑞𐑨𐑑! 𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕, 𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕!”

𐑕𐑵𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕 𐑚𐑳𐑑 ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒'𐑕 𐑢𐑻 𐑛𐑮𐑪𐑐𐑑; 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑-𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑕𐑧𐑑—𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑐𐑨𐑛𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑐𐑤𐑲𐑦𐑙; 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑢𐑦𐑓𐑑𐑯𐑩𐑕, 𐑖𐑵𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑤𐑰𐑢𐑼𐑛; 𐑯 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑧𐑑. 𐑩 𐑐𐑱𐑤, 𐑛𐑧𐑔-𐑜𐑤𐑦𐑥𐑼 𐑤𐑦𐑑 𐑳𐑐 ·𐑓𐑧𐑛𐑩𐑤𐑩'𐑟 𐑕𐑳𐑙𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑲𐑟; 𐑩 𐑣𐑦𐑛𐑾𐑕 𐑥𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑯𐑷𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑬𐑔.

𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑯𐑶𐑟𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑯𐑷𐑑𐑦𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑖𐑧𐑤𐑟, 𐑞𐑺 𐑤𐑲𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑬𐑟 𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑛 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑞 𐑕𐑰; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑤𐑴𐑤𐑦 𐑞𐑱 𐑯𐑽𐑛 𐑞 𐑓𐑴. 𐑨𐑟 𐑞𐑱 𐑯𐑽𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑞 𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑜𐑮𐑵 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑥𐑹 𐑕𐑥𐑵𐑞; 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑛𐑮𐑷𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑒𐑸𐑐𐑩𐑑 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑢𐑱𐑝𐑟; 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑩 𐑯𐑵𐑯-𐑥𐑧𐑛𐑴, 𐑕𐑴 𐑕𐑼𐑰𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑛. 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑧𐑙𐑔 𐑞 𐑚𐑮𐑧𐑔𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑑𐑼 𐑒𐑱𐑥 𐑕𐑴 𐑯𐑲 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑳𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑐𐑮𐑱, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑲𐑼 𐑛𐑨𐑟𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑳𐑥𐑐 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑝𐑦𐑟𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤, 𐑕𐑤𐑲𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑞 𐑕𐑰 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑓 𐑩𐑯 𐑲𐑕𐑩𐑤𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑔𐑦𐑙, 𐑯 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑿𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑧𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑮𐑦𐑝𐑪𐑤𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑮𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑓𐑲𐑯𐑩𐑕𐑑, 𐑓𐑤𐑰𐑕𐑦, 𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑯𐑦𐑖 𐑓𐑴𐑥. 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑷 𐑞 𐑝𐑭𐑕𐑑, 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑪𐑤𐑝𐑛 𐑮𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑤𐑲𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑡𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑚𐑦𐑘𐑪𐑯𐑛. 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑦𐑑, 𐑓𐑸 𐑬𐑑 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑪𐑓𐑑 ·𐑑𐑻𐑒𐑦𐑖-𐑮𐑳𐑜𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼𐑟, 𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑞 𐑜𐑤𐑦𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑖𐑨𐑛𐑴 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑮𐑷𐑛, 𐑥𐑦𐑤𐑒𐑦 𐑓𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑛, 𐑩 𐑥𐑿𐑟𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑓𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑩𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑖𐑱𐑛; 𐑯 𐑚𐑦𐑣𐑲𐑯𐑛, 𐑞 𐑚𐑤𐑵 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑗𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑓𐑤𐑴𐑛 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑥𐑵𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑝𐑨𐑤𐑦 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑛𐑦 𐑢𐑱𐑒; 𐑯 𐑪𐑯 𐑲𐑞𐑼 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑚𐑮𐑲𐑑 𐑚𐑳𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑼𐑴𐑟 𐑯 𐑛𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑲𐑛. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑚𐑮𐑴𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑤𐑲𐑑 𐑑𐑴𐑟 𐑝 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑛𐑟 𐑝 𐑜𐑱 𐑓𐑬𐑤 𐑕𐑪𐑓𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑓𐑧𐑞𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑕𐑰, 𐑷𐑤𐑑𐑼𐑯𐑩𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞𐑺 𐑓𐑦𐑑𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑓𐑤𐑲𐑑; 𐑯 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑓𐑤𐑨𐑜-𐑕𐑑𐑭𐑓 𐑮𐑲𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑐𐑱𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑣𐑳𐑤 𐑝 𐑩𐑯 𐑸𐑜𐑩𐑕𐑦, 𐑞 𐑑𐑷𐑤 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑖𐑨𐑑𐑼𐑛 𐑐𐑴𐑤 𐑝 𐑩 𐑮𐑰𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑕 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑡𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑤'𐑟 𐑚𐑨𐑒; 𐑯 𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑒𐑤𐑬𐑛 𐑝 𐑕𐑪𐑓𐑑-𐑑𐑴𐑛 𐑓𐑬𐑤𐑟 𐑣𐑪𐑝𐑼𐑦𐑙, 𐑯 𐑑 𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑴 𐑕𐑒𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑩𐑐𐑦 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑞 𐑓𐑦𐑖, 𐑕𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑻𐑗𐑑 𐑯 𐑮𐑪𐑒𐑑 𐑪𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑐𐑴𐑤, 𐑞 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑑𐑱𐑤 𐑓𐑧𐑞𐑼𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑰𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑩𐑯𐑟.

𐑩 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑡𐑶𐑩𐑕𐑯𐑩𐑕—𐑩 𐑥𐑲𐑑𐑦 𐑥𐑲𐑤𐑛𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑴𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑢𐑦𐑓𐑑𐑯𐑩𐑕, 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑞 𐑜𐑤𐑲𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑱𐑤. 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑞 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑚𐑫𐑤 ·𐑡𐑵𐑐𐑦𐑑𐑼 𐑕𐑢𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑢𐑱 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑮𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑖𐑑 ·𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑴𐑐𐑩 𐑒𐑤𐑦𐑙𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑕𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑣𐑹𐑯𐑟; 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑤𐑳𐑝𐑤𐑦, 𐑤𐑽𐑦𐑙 𐑲𐑟 𐑕𐑲𐑛𐑢𐑱𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑥𐑱𐑛; 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑕𐑥𐑵𐑞 𐑚𐑦𐑢𐑦𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑤𐑰𐑑𐑯𐑩𐑕, 𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑓 𐑞 𐑯𐑳𐑐𐑖𐑩𐑤 𐑚𐑬𐑼 𐑦𐑯 ·𐑒𐑮𐑰𐑑; 𐑯𐑪𐑑 ·𐑡𐑴𐑝, 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑥𐑨𐑡𐑩𐑕𐑑𐑦 ·𐑕𐑵𐑐𐑮𐑰𐑥! 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑕𐑼𐑐𐑭𐑕 𐑞 𐑜𐑤𐑹𐑦𐑓𐑲𐑛 ·𐑢𐑲𐑑 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑨𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑴 𐑛𐑦𐑝𐑲𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑢𐑨𐑥.

𐑪𐑯 𐑰𐑗 𐑕𐑪𐑓𐑑 𐑕𐑲𐑛—𐑒𐑴𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑐𐑸𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑕𐑢𐑧𐑤, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑕 𐑤𐑰𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑓𐑤𐑴𐑛 𐑕𐑴 𐑢𐑲𐑛 𐑩𐑢𐑱—𐑪𐑯 𐑰𐑗 𐑚𐑮𐑲𐑑 𐑕𐑲𐑛, 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑖𐑧𐑛 𐑪𐑓 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑲𐑕𐑦𐑙𐑟. 𐑯𐑴 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑞𐑺 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑞 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑟 𐑣𐑵 𐑯𐑱𐑥𐑤𐑩𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑕𐑐𐑹𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑯 𐑩𐑤𐑫𐑼𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑕𐑼𐑧𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑦, 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑝𐑧𐑯𐑗𐑼𐑛 𐑑 𐑩𐑕𐑱𐑤 𐑦𐑑; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑓𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑒𐑢𐑲𐑩𐑑𐑵𐑛 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞 𐑝𐑧𐑕𐑗𐑼 𐑝 𐑑𐑹𐑯𐑱𐑛𐑴𐑟. 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑒𐑭𐑥, 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑲𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑒𐑭𐑥, 𐑴, 𐑢𐑱𐑤! 𐑞𐑬 𐑜𐑤𐑲𐑛𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑪𐑯, 𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑣𐑵 𐑓 𐑞 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑲 𐑞𐑰, 𐑯𐑴 𐑥𐑨𐑑𐑼 𐑣𐑬 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑢𐑱 𐑞𐑬 𐑥𐑳'𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑚𐑦𐑡𐑳𐑜𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑯 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑶𐑛 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹.

𐑯 𐑞𐑳𐑕, 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑞 𐑕𐑼𐑰𐑯 𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑑𐑮𐑪𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑰, 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑢𐑱𐑝𐑟 𐑣𐑵𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛-𐑒𐑤𐑨𐑐𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑕𐑩𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑰𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑮𐑨𐑐𐑗𐑼, ·𐑥𐑪𐑚𐑦 ·𐑛𐑦𐑒 𐑥𐑵𐑝𐑛 𐑪𐑯, 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑕𐑲𐑑 𐑞 𐑓𐑫𐑤 𐑑𐑧𐑮𐑼𐑟 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑥𐑻𐑡𐑛 𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑙𐑒, 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑲𐑼𐑤𐑦 𐑣𐑲𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑮𐑧𐑯𐑗𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑛𐑾𐑕𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑡𐑷. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑕𐑵𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑹 𐑐𐑸𐑑 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑕𐑤𐑴𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑴𐑟 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼; 𐑓 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑴𐑤 𐑥𐑸𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑲𐑟𐑛 𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦 𐑓𐑹𐑥𐑛 𐑩 𐑣𐑲 𐑸𐑗, 𐑤𐑲𐑒 ·𐑝𐑼𐑡𐑦𐑯𐑾'𐑟 ·𐑯𐑨𐑗𐑼𐑩𐑤 ·𐑚𐑮𐑦𐑡, 𐑯 𐑢𐑹𐑯𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑢𐑱𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑨𐑯𐑼𐑛 𐑓𐑤𐑵𐑒𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑺, 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑜𐑪𐑛 𐑮𐑦𐑝𐑰𐑤𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓, 𐑕𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛, 𐑯 𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑕𐑲𐑑. 𐑣𐑪𐑝𐑼𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑣𐑷𐑤𐑑𐑦𐑙, 𐑯 𐑛𐑦𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑦𐑙, 𐑞 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑕𐑰-𐑓𐑬𐑤𐑟 𐑤𐑪𐑙𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑤𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑼𐑛 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑞 𐑨𐑡𐑦𐑑𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑐𐑵𐑤 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑤𐑧𐑓𐑑.

𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑹𐑟 𐑱𐑐𐑰𐑒, 𐑯 𐑐𐑨𐑛𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑛𐑬𐑯, 𐑞 𐑖𐑰𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑞𐑺 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑩𐑛𐑮𐑦𐑓𐑑, 𐑞 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕 𐑯𐑬 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤𐑦 𐑓𐑤𐑴𐑑𐑩𐑛, 𐑩𐑢𐑱𐑑𐑦𐑙 ·𐑥𐑪𐑚𐑦 ·𐑛𐑦𐑒'𐑕 𐑮𐑰𐑩𐑐𐑽𐑩𐑯𐑕.

“𐑩𐑯 𐑬𐑼,” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚, 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑮𐑵𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑴𐑑'𐑕 𐑕𐑑𐑻𐑯; 𐑯 𐑣𐑰 𐑜𐑱𐑟𐑛 𐑚𐑦𐑘𐑪𐑯𐑛 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤'𐑟 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕, 𐑑𐑩𐑢𐑹𐑛𐑟 𐑞 𐑛𐑦𐑥 𐑚𐑤𐑵 𐑕𐑐𐑱𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑯 𐑢𐑲𐑛 𐑢𐑵𐑦𐑙 𐑝𐑱𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑟 𐑑 𐑤𐑰𐑢𐑼𐑛. 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑; 𐑓 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑲𐑟 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑨𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑢𐑧𐑐𐑑 𐑞 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼𐑦 𐑕𐑻𐑒𐑩𐑤. 𐑞 𐑚𐑮𐑰𐑟 𐑯𐑬 𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑛; 𐑞 𐑕𐑰 𐑚𐑦𐑜𐑨𐑯 𐑑 𐑕𐑢𐑧𐑤.

“𐑞 𐑚𐑻𐑛𐑟!—𐑞 𐑚𐑻𐑛𐑟!” 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 ·𐑑𐑨𐑖𐑑𐑱𐑜𐑴.

𐑦𐑯 𐑤𐑪𐑙 ·𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑾𐑯 𐑓𐑲𐑤, 𐑨𐑟 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑣𐑧𐑮𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑢𐑦𐑙, 𐑞 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑚𐑻𐑛𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑯𐑬 𐑷𐑤 𐑓𐑤𐑲𐑦𐑙 𐑑𐑩𐑢𐑹𐑛𐑟 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚'𐑟 𐑚𐑴𐑑; 𐑯 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑓𐑿 𐑘𐑸𐑛𐑟 𐑚𐑦𐑜𐑨𐑯 𐑓𐑤𐑳𐑑𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑞 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼 𐑞𐑺, 𐑢𐑰𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑯 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑡𐑶𐑩𐑕, 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑟. 𐑞𐑺 𐑝𐑦𐑠𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑒𐑰𐑯𐑼 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑥𐑨𐑯'𐑟; ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑳𐑝𐑼 𐑯𐑴 𐑕𐑲𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑰. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑨𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑐𐑽𐑛 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑯 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑛𐑧𐑐𐑔𐑕, 𐑣𐑰 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑷 𐑩 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑤𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑐𐑪𐑑 𐑯𐑴 𐑚𐑦𐑜𐑼 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑩 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑢𐑰𐑟𐑩𐑤, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑩𐑤𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑳𐑐𐑮𐑲𐑟𐑦𐑙, 𐑯 𐑥𐑨𐑜𐑯𐑦𐑓𐑲𐑦𐑙 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑮𐑴𐑟, 𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑦𐑑 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑛, 𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑢𐑻 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑦𐑝𐑰𐑤𐑛 𐑑𐑵 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑒𐑮𐑫𐑒𐑑 𐑮𐑴𐑟 𐑝 𐑢𐑲𐑑, 𐑜𐑤𐑦𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑑𐑰𐑔, 𐑓𐑤𐑴𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑳𐑐 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑳𐑝𐑼𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑚𐑪𐑑𐑩𐑥. 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 ·𐑥𐑪𐑚𐑦 ·𐑛𐑦𐑒'𐑕 𐑴𐑐𐑩𐑯 𐑥𐑬𐑔 𐑯 𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑡𐑷; 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑝𐑭𐑕𐑑, 𐑖𐑨𐑛𐑴𐑛 𐑚𐑳𐑤𐑒 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑣𐑭𐑓 𐑚𐑤𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑚𐑤𐑵 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑰. 𐑞 𐑜𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑬𐑔 𐑘𐑷𐑯𐑛 𐑚𐑦𐑯𐑰𐑔 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩𐑯 𐑴𐑐𐑩𐑯-𐑛𐑹𐑛 𐑥𐑸𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑑𐑵𐑥; 𐑯 𐑜𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑕𐑲𐑛𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑕𐑢𐑰𐑐 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑽𐑦𐑙 𐑹, ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛 𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑭𐑓𐑑 𐑩𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑕 𐑨𐑐𐑼𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯. 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 ·𐑓𐑧𐑛𐑩𐑤𐑩 𐑑 𐑗𐑱𐑯𐑡 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑓𐑹𐑢𐑼𐑛 𐑑 𐑞 𐑚𐑬𐑟, 𐑯 𐑕𐑰𐑟𐑦𐑙 ·𐑐𐑻𐑔'𐑕 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯, 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑭𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑮𐑵 𐑑 𐑜𐑮𐑭𐑕𐑐 𐑞𐑺 𐑹𐑟 𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑻𐑯.

𐑯𐑬, 𐑚𐑲 𐑮𐑰𐑟𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑐𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑨𐑒𐑕𐑦𐑕, 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑚𐑬, 𐑚𐑲 𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑕𐑦𐑐𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯, 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑑 𐑓𐑱𐑕 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤'𐑟 𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑓 𐑐𐑼𐑕𐑰𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑑𐑩𐑡𐑩𐑥, ·𐑥𐑪𐑚𐑦 ·𐑛𐑦𐑒, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑕 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑡𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑩𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑚𐑛 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑕𐑲𐑛𐑤𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑕𐑐𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓, 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑻, 𐑦𐑯 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑, 𐑖𐑵𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑤𐑰𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑤𐑧𐑙𐑔𐑢𐑲𐑟 𐑚𐑦𐑯𐑰𐑔 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑.

𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑯 𐑔𐑮𐑵; 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑐𐑤𐑨𐑙𐑒 𐑯 𐑰𐑗 𐑮𐑦𐑚, 𐑦𐑑 𐑔𐑮𐑦𐑤𐑛 𐑓 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑, 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑴𐑚𐑤𐑰𐑒𐑤𐑦 𐑤𐑲𐑦𐑙 𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑨𐑒, 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑥𐑨𐑯𐑼 𐑝 𐑩 𐑚𐑲𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑖𐑸𐑒, 𐑕𐑤𐑴𐑤𐑦 𐑯 𐑓𐑰𐑤𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑚𐑬𐑟 𐑓𐑫𐑤 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑬𐑔, 𐑕𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑤𐑪𐑙, 𐑯𐑼𐑴, 𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑤𐑴𐑼 𐑡𐑷 𐑒𐑻𐑤𐑛 𐑣𐑲 𐑳𐑐 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑴𐑐𐑩𐑯 𐑺, 𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑑𐑰𐑔 𐑒𐑷𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑮𐑴-𐑤𐑪𐑒. 𐑞 𐑚𐑤𐑵𐑦𐑖 𐑐𐑻𐑤-𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑝 𐑞 𐑡𐑷 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑕 𐑦𐑯𐑗𐑩𐑟 𐑝 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚'𐑟 𐑣𐑧𐑛, 𐑯 𐑮𐑰𐑗𐑑 𐑣𐑲𐑼 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑. 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑨𐑑𐑦𐑑𐑿𐑛 𐑞 ·𐑢𐑲𐑑 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑯𐑬 𐑖𐑫𐑒 𐑞 𐑕𐑤𐑲𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑛𐑼 𐑨𐑟 𐑩 𐑥𐑲𐑤𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑮𐑵𐑩𐑤 𐑒𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑻 𐑥𐑬𐑕. 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑳𐑯𐑩𐑕𐑑𐑪𐑯𐑦𐑖𐑑 𐑲𐑟 ·𐑓𐑧𐑛𐑩𐑤𐑩 𐑜𐑱𐑟𐑛, 𐑯 𐑒𐑮𐑪𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑸𐑥𐑟; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞 𐑑𐑲𐑜𐑼-𐑘𐑧𐑤𐑴 𐑒𐑮𐑵 𐑢𐑻 𐑑𐑳𐑥𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑰𐑗 𐑳𐑞𐑼'𐑟 𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑟 𐑑 𐑜𐑱𐑯 𐑞 𐑳𐑑𐑼𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑻𐑯.

𐑯 𐑯𐑬, 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑚𐑴𐑔 𐑦𐑤𐑨𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑜𐑳𐑯𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑙𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑯 𐑬𐑑, 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑛𐑨𐑤𐑦𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑛𐑵𐑥𐑛 𐑒𐑮𐑭𐑓𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑛𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑖 𐑢𐑱; 𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑥𐑻𐑡𐑛 𐑚𐑦𐑯𐑰𐑔 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑, 𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑛𐑸𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑨𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑚𐑬𐑟, 𐑓 𐑞 𐑚𐑬𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑻; 𐑯 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑞 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑪𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑺𐑦𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑷𐑟𐑛, 𐑨𐑟 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑩 𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑒 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑕𐑦𐑕 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑪𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛, 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑪𐑯𐑩𐑥𐑱𐑯𐑦𐑨𐑒 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚, 𐑓𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑾𐑕 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑲𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑝𐑦𐑕𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑴, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑷𐑤 𐑩𐑤𐑲𐑝 𐑯 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑐𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑡𐑷𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛; 𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑯𐑟𐑦𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑦𐑕, 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑰𐑟𐑛 𐑞 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑚𐑴𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑱𐑒𐑩𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟, 𐑯 𐑢𐑲𐑤𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑴𐑝 𐑑 𐑮𐑧𐑯𐑗 𐑦𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑜𐑮𐑲𐑐. 𐑨𐑟 𐑯𐑬 𐑣𐑰 𐑞𐑳𐑕 𐑝𐑱𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑴𐑝, 𐑞 𐑡𐑷 𐑕𐑤𐑦𐑐𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑣𐑦𐑥; 𐑞 𐑓𐑮𐑱𐑤 𐑜𐑳𐑯𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑚𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑦𐑯, 𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑨𐑐𐑕𐑑, 𐑯 𐑕𐑯𐑨𐑐𐑑, 𐑨𐑟 𐑚𐑴𐑔 𐑡𐑷𐑟, 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑹𐑥𐑩𐑕 𐑖𐑽𐑟, 𐑕𐑤𐑲𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑻𐑞𐑼 𐑭𐑓𐑑, 𐑚𐑦𐑑 𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑭𐑓𐑑 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑰𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑯 𐑑𐑢𐑱𐑯, 𐑯 𐑤𐑪𐑒𐑑 𐑞𐑧𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑝𐑟 𐑓𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑰, 𐑥𐑦𐑛𐑢𐑱 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑢𐑰𐑯 𐑞 𐑑𐑵 𐑓𐑤𐑴𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑕. 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑓𐑤𐑴𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑩𐑕𐑲𐑛, 𐑞 𐑚𐑮𐑴𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑛𐑮𐑵𐑐𐑦𐑙, 𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑵 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑻𐑯-𐑮𐑧𐑒 𐑒𐑤𐑦𐑙𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑞 𐑜𐑳𐑯𐑩𐑤𐑟, 𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑓𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑑 𐑞 𐑹𐑟 𐑑 𐑤𐑨𐑖 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑩𐑒𐑮𐑪𐑕.

𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑤𐑿𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑴𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑, 𐑺 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑕𐑯𐑨𐑐𐑑, ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚, 𐑞 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑑 𐑐𐑼𐑕𐑰𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤'𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑑, 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑦 𐑳𐑐𐑮𐑱𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑧𐑛, 𐑩 𐑥𐑵𐑝𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑵𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑓 𐑞 𐑑𐑲𐑥; 𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑴𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑓𐑲𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑧𐑓𐑼𐑑 𐑑 𐑐𐑫𐑖 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑚𐑲𐑑. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑤𐑦𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑻𐑞𐑼 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤'𐑟 𐑥𐑬𐑔, 𐑯 𐑑𐑦𐑤𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑕𐑲𐑛𐑢𐑱𐑟 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑤𐑦𐑐𐑑, 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑖𐑱𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑪𐑓 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑡𐑷; 𐑕𐑐𐑦𐑤𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑦𐑑, 𐑨𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑤𐑰𐑯𐑛 𐑑 𐑞 𐑐𐑫𐑖; 𐑯 𐑕𐑴 𐑣𐑰 𐑓𐑧𐑤 𐑓𐑤𐑨𐑑-𐑓𐑱𐑕𐑑 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑰.

𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑛𐑮𐑷𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑮𐑱, ·𐑥𐑪𐑚𐑦 ·𐑛𐑦𐑒 𐑯𐑬 𐑤𐑱 𐑨𐑑 𐑩 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕, 𐑝𐑻𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑦 𐑔𐑮𐑳𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑪𐑚𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑳𐑐 𐑯 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑴𐑟; 𐑯 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑕𐑤𐑴𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑦𐑝𐑪𐑤𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑴𐑤 𐑕𐑐𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦; 𐑕𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑝𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑓𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑛 𐑮𐑴𐑟—𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑑𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑦 𐑹 𐑥𐑹 𐑓𐑰𐑑 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼—𐑞 𐑯𐑬 𐑮𐑲𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑢𐑧𐑤𐑟, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑺 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑓𐑤𐑵𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑝𐑟, 𐑛𐑨𐑟𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑮𐑴𐑒 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑑; 𐑝𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑝𐑤𐑦 𐑑𐑪𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑺 𐑖𐑦𐑝𐑼𐑛 𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑱 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑣𐑲𐑼 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑺.* 𐑕𐑴, 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑜𐑱𐑤, 𐑞 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑣𐑭𐑓 𐑚𐑨𐑓𐑩𐑤𐑛 ·𐑗𐑨𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑴𐑟 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑶𐑤 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑚𐑱𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑧𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑴𐑯, 𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑳𐑥𐑓𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑑 𐑴𐑝𐑼𐑤𐑰𐑐 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞𐑺 𐑕𐑒𐑳𐑛.

*𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑥𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑽 𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 𐑢𐑱𐑤. 𐑦𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑰𐑝𐑟 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑛𐑧𐑟𐑦𐑜𐑯𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 (𐑐𐑦𐑗𐑐𐑴𐑤𐑦𐑙) 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑤𐑲𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑼𐑦 𐑳𐑐-𐑯-𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑐𐑶𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤-𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑕, 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑼𐑕𐑲𐑟 𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑛 𐑐𐑦𐑗𐑐𐑴𐑤𐑦𐑙, 𐑐𐑮𐑰𐑝𐑾𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑚𐑛. 𐑚𐑲 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑥𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑯 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑣𐑧𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑝𐑤𐑦 𐑝𐑿 𐑢𐑪𐑑𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑪𐑚𐑡𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑕 𐑥𐑱 𐑚𐑰 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑻𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑥.

𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑕𐑵𐑯 𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑿𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑨𐑑𐑦𐑑𐑿𐑛, ·𐑥𐑪𐑚𐑦 ·𐑛𐑦𐑒 𐑕𐑢𐑨𐑥 𐑕𐑢𐑦𐑓𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑯 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑞 𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑑 𐑒𐑮𐑵; 𐑕𐑲𐑛𐑢𐑱𐑟 𐑗𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑝𐑧𐑯𐑡𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑱𐑒, 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑓 𐑤𐑨𐑖𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑳𐑐 𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑩𐑯𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑯 𐑥𐑹 𐑛𐑧𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑩𐑕𐑷𐑤𐑑. 𐑞 𐑕𐑲𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑤𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑛 𐑚𐑴𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑑 𐑥𐑨𐑛𐑩𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑚𐑤𐑳𐑛 𐑝 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑐𐑕 𐑯 𐑥𐑳𐑤𐑚𐑼𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 ·𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑪𐑒𐑩𐑕'𐑩𐑟 𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑓𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑫𐑒 𐑝 ·𐑥𐑨𐑒𐑩𐑚𐑰𐑟. 𐑥𐑰𐑯𐑢𐑲𐑤 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑣𐑭𐑓 𐑕𐑥𐑳𐑞𐑼𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑴𐑥 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤'𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑑𐑱𐑤, 𐑯 𐑑𐑵 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑝 𐑩 𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑩𐑤 𐑑 𐑕𐑢𐑦𐑥,—𐑞𐑴 𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑒𐑰𐑐 𐑩𐑓𐑤𐑴𐑑, 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑣𐑸𐑑 𐑝 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑐𐑵𐑤 𐑨𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑; 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑐𐑤𐑩𐑕 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚'𐑟 𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑰𐑯, 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑑𐑪𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑳𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑞 𐑤𐑰𐑕𐑑 𐑗𐑭𐑯𐑕 𐑖𐑪𐑒 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑚𐑻𐑕𐑑. 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑'𐑕 𐑓𐑮𐑨𐑜𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑦 𐑕𐑑𐑻𐑯, ·𐑓𐑧𐑛𐑩𐑤𐑩 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑾𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑯 𐑥𐑲𐑤𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑲𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥; 𐑞 𐑒𐑤𐑦𐑙𐑦𐑙 𐑒𐑮𐑵, 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑛𐑮𐑦𐑓𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑧𐑯𐑛, 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑒𐑼 𐑣𐑦𐑥; 𐑥𐑹 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑳𐑓 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑓 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑑 𐑤𐑫𐑒 𐑑 𐑞𐑧𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑝𐑟. 𐑓 𐑕𐑴 𐑮𐑦𐑝𐑪𐑤𐑝𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑩𐑐𐑷𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞 ·𐑢𐑲𐑑 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤'𐑟 𐑨𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑, 𐑯 𐑕𐑴 𐑐𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑩𐑑𐑺𐑦𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑢𐑦𐑓𐑑 𐑞 𐑧𐑝𐑼-𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑻𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑥𐑱𐑛, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑣𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑢𐑵𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑥. 𐑯 𐑞𐑴 𐑞 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕, 𐑳𐑯𐑣𐑸𐑥𐑛, 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑣𐑪𐑝𐑼𐑛 𐑣𐑸𐑛 𐑚𐑲; 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑞𐑱 𐑛𐑺𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑐𐑫𐑤 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑧𐑛𐑦 𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑒, 𐑤𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑚𐑰 𐑞 𐑕𐑦𐑜𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑓 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑡𐑧𐑐𐑼𐑛𐑲𐑟𐑛 𐑒𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑢𐑱𐑟, ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑯 𐑷𐑤; 𐑯𐑹 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑒𐑱𐑕 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑞𐑱 𐑞𐑧𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑝𐑟 𐑣𐑴𐑐 𐑑 𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑱𐑐. 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑲𐑟, 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑞𐑱 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑱𐑯𐑛 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑬𐑑𐑼 𐑧𐑡 𐑝 𐑞 𐑛𐑲𐑼𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑟𐑴𐑯, 𐑣𐑵𐑟 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑼 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑯𐑬 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑞 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑥𐑨𐑯'𐑟 𐑣𐑧𐑛.

𐑥𐑰𐑯𐑑𐑲𐑥, 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑚𐑦𐑜𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐'𐑕 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑟; 𐑯 𐑕𐑒𐑢𐑺𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑻 𐑘𐑸𐑛𐑟, 𐑖𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑹𐑯 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑰𐑯; 𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑬 𐑕𐑴 𐑯𐑲, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼 𐑣𐑱𐑤𐑛 𐑣𐑻!—“𐑕𐑱𐑤 𐑪𐑯 𐑞”—𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑴𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑩 𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑰 𐑛𐑨𐑖𐑑 𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 ·𐑥𐑪𐑚𐑦 ·𐑛𐑦𐑒, 𐑯 𐑢𐑧𐑤𐑥𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑓 𐑞 𐑑𐑲𐑥. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑜𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑦𐑑 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯, 𐑯 𐑗𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑮𐑲𐑟 𐑪𐑯 𐑩 𐑑𐑬𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑒𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑑, 𐑣𐑰 𐑖𐑬𐑑𐑩𐑛,—“𐑕𐑱𐑤 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤!—𐑛𐑮𐑲𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑪𐑓!”

𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛'𐑟 𐑐𐑮𐑬𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑐𐑶𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛; 𐑯 𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑳𐑐 𐑞 𐑗𐑸𐑥𐑛 𐑕𐑻𐑒𐑩𐑤, 𐑖𐑰 𐑦𐑓𐑧𐑒𐑗𐑵𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑸𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑞 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑝𐑦𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑥. 𐑨𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑳𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑢𐑨𐑥 𐑪𐑓, 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕 𐑓𐑤𐑵 𐑑 𐑞 𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑒𐑿.

𐑛𐑮𐑨𐑜𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚'𐑟 𐑚𐑴𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑚𐑤𐑳𐑛-𐑖𐑪𐑑, 𐑚𐑤𐑲𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑲𐑟, 𐑞 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑚𐑮𐑲𐑯 𐑒𐑱𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑮𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑟; 𐑞 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚'𐑟 𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑧𐑙𐑔 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑒𐑮𐑨𐑒, 𐑯 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑐𐑤𐑩𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑣𐑰 𐑘𐑰𐑤𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦'𐑟 𐑛𐑵𐑥: 𐑓 𐑩 𐑑𐑲𐑥, 𐑤𐑲𐑦𐑙 𐑷𐑤 𐑒𐑮𐑳𐑖𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑪𐑑𐑩𐑥 𐑝 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚'𐑟 𐑚𐑴𐑑, 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑑𐑮𐑪𐑛𐑩𐑯 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑓𐑫𐑑 𐑝 𐑣𐑻𐑛𐑟 𐑝 𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑓𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕. 𐑓𐑸 𐑦𐑯𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛, 𐑯𐑱𐑥𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑒𐑱𐑥 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑨𐑟 𐑛𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑤𐑩𐑑 𐑕𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑬𐑑 𐑮𐑩𐑝𐑰𐑯𐑟.

𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑦𐑟𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑕𐑴 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑞 𐑥𐑹 𐑩𐑚𐑮𐑰𐑝𐑦𐑱𐑑 𐑦𐑑. 𐑦𐑯 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑'𐑕 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑕, 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑣𐑸𐑑𐑕 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑛𐑧𐑯𐑕 𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑛𐑰𐑐 𐑐𐑨𐑙, 𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑑𐑴𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑖𐑨𐑤𐑴 𐑐𐑱𐑯𐑟 𐑒𐑲𐑯𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑦𐑓𐑿𐑟𐑛 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑓𐑰𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑼 𐑥𐑧𐑯'𐑟 𐑣𐑴𐑤 𐑤𐑲𐑝𐑟. 𐑯 𐑕𐑴, 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑣𐑸𐑑𐑕, 𐑞𐑴 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑼𐑦 𐑦𐑯 𐑰𐑗 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑓𐑼𐑦𐑙; 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤, 𐑦𐑓 𐑞 𐑜𐑪𐑛𐑟 𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑮𐑰 𐑦𐑑, 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑤𐑲𐑓-𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑨𐑜𐑮𐑦𐑜𐑱𐑑 𐑩 𐑣𐑴𐑤 𐑱𐑡 𐑝 𐑢𐑴, 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑦 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑳𐑐 𐑝 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑱𐑯𐑾𐑕 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑟; 𐑓 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑐𐑶𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑟, 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑯𐑴𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑯𐑱𐑗𐑼𐑟 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑱𐑯 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑲𐑼 𐑕𐑼𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑓𐑼𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑝 𐑦𐑯𐑓𐑽𐑽 𐑕𐑴𐑤𐑟.

“𐑞 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯,” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚, 𐑣𐑭𐑓 𐑢𐑱 𐑮𐑲𐑟𐑦𐑙, 𐑯 𐑛𐑮𐑨𐑜𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑤𐑰𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑪𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑚𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑸𐑥—“𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑱𐑓?”

“𐑲, 𐑕𐑻, 𐑓 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑛𐑸𐑑𐑩𐑛; 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑑,” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚, 𐑖𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑑.

“𐑤𐑱 𐑦𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑥𐑰;—𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑧𐑯?”

“𐑢𐑳𐑯, 𐑑𐑵, 𐑔𐑮𐑰, 𐑓𐑹, 𐑓𐑲𐑝;—𐑞𐑺 𐑢𐑻 𐑓𐑲𐑝 𐑹𐑟, 𐑕𐑻, 𐑯 𐑣𐑽 𐑸 𐑓𐑲𐑝 𐑥𐑧𐑯.”

“𐑞𐑨𐑑'𐑕 𐑜𐑫𐑛.—𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑐 𐑥𐑰, 𐑥𐑨𐑯; 𐑲 𐑢𐑦𐑖 𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛. 𐑕𐑴, 𐑕𐑴, 𐑲 𐑕𐑰 𐑣𐑦𐑥! 𐑞𐑺! 𐑞𐑺! 𐑜𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑤𐑰𐑢𐑼𐑛 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤; 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑩 𐑤𐑰𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑐𐑬𐑑!—𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑪𐑓 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑥𐑰! 𐑞 𐑦𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑨𐑐 𐑮𐑳𐑯𐑟 𐑳𐑐 𐑦𐑯 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚'𐑟 𐑚𐑴𐑯𐑟 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯! 𐑕𐑧𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑤; 𐑬𐑑 𐑹𐑟; 𐑞 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑥!”

𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑪𐑓𐑩𐑯 𐑞 𐑒𐑱𐑕 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑩 𐑚𐑴𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑴𐑝, 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑒𐑮𐑵, 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑑 𐑳𐑐 𐑚𐑲 𐑩𐑯𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑚𐑴𐑑, 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑐 𐑑 𐑢𐑻𐑒 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑧𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑚𐑴𐑑; 𐑯 𐑞 𐑗𐑱𐑕 𐑦𐑟 𐑞𐑳𐑕 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑿𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑛 𐑛𐑳𐑚𐑩𐑤-𐑚𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑑 𐑹𐑟. 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞𐑳𐑕 𐑯𐑬. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞 𐑨𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑐𐑬𐑼 𐑝 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑩𐑤 𐑞 𐑨𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑐𐑬𐑼 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑓 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑑𐑮𐑧𐑚𐑩𐑤-𐑚𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑓𐑦𐑯; 𐑕𐑢𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑝𐑦𐑤𐑪𐑕𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑖𐑴𐑛, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑓 𐑯𐑬, 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑕𐑻𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟, 𐑐𐑫𐑖𐑑 𐑪𐑯, 𐑞 𐑗𐑱𐑕 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑐𐑮𐑵𐑝 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑧𐑓𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑮𐑴𐑤𐑪𐑙𐑛, 𐑦𐑓 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑩 𐑣𐑴𐑐𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑢𐑳𐑯; 𐑯𐑹 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑒𐑮𐑵 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑻 𐑓 𐑕𐑴 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑩 𐑐𐑽𐑾𐑛, 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩𐑯 𐑳𐑯𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑥𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑛, 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑕 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑹; 𐑩 𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑺𐑤𐑦 𐑑𐑪𐑤𐑼𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑚𐑮𐑰𐑓 𐑝𐑦𐑕𐑦𐑕𐑦𐑑𐑿𐑛. 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑦𐑑𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓, 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑟, 𐑪𐑓𐑼𐑛 𐑞 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑥𐑰𐑛𐑾𐑑 𐑥𐑰𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑴𐑝𐑼𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑗𐑱𐑕. 𐑩𐑒𐑹𐑛𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦, 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕 𐑯𐑬 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑓 𐑣𐑻, 𐑯 𐑢𐑻 𐑕𐑵𐑯 𐑕𐑢𐑱𐑛 𐑳𐑐 𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑒𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑟—𐑞 𐑑𐑵 𐑐𐑸𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑑 𐑚𐑴𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑐𐑮𐑰𐑝𐑾𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑣𐑻—𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑣𐑶𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑣𐑻 𐑕𐑲𐑛, 𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑻 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑝𐑩𐑕 𐑣𐑲 𐑳𐑐, 𐑯 𐑕𐑲𐑛𐑢𐑱𐑟 𐑬𐑑𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑧𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑯-𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑟, 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑞 𐑛𐑳𐑚𐑩𐑤-𐑡𐑶𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑝 𐑩𐑯 𐑨𐑤𐑚𐑩𐑑𐑮𐑪𐑕; 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛 𐑚𐑹 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑤𐑰𐑢𐑼𐑛 𐑢𐑱𐑒 𐑝 ·𐑥𐑪𐑚𐑦-·𐑛𐑦𐑒. 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑢𐑧𐑤 𐑯𐑴𐑯, 𐑥𐑦𐑔𐑪𐑛𐑦𐑒 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑟, 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤'𐑟 𐑜𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑐𐑬𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑮𐑧𐑜𐑿𐑤𐑼𐑤𐑦 𐑩𐑯𐑬𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑥𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑-𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑟; 𐑯 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑚𐑰 𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑹𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑨𐑟 𐑡𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑜𐑪𐑯 𐑛𐑬𐑯, ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑞 𐑑𐑲𐑥, 𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑐𐑱𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑒, 𐑚𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑒𐑩𐑤-𐑢𐑪𐑗 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛, 𐑕𐑴 𐑕𐑵𐑯 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑧𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑝 𐑞 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑬𐑼 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑲𐑼𐑛, 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑝𐑶𐑕 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑣𐑻𐑛.—“𐑣𐑵𐑟 𐑦𐑟 𐑞 𐑛𐑳𐑚𐑤𐑵𐑯 𐑯𐑬? ·𐑛'𐑘𐑰 𐑕𐑰 𐑣𐑦𐑥?” 𐑯 𐑦𐑓 𐑞 𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑤𐑲 𐑢𐑪𐑟, 𐑯𐑴, 𐑕𐑻! 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑑𐑢𐑱 𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑭𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑑 𐑤𐑦𐑓𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑻𐑗. 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑱 𐑞 𐑛𐑱 𐑢𐑹 𐑪𐑯; ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚, 𐑯𐑬 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑓𐑑 𐑯 𐑥𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑩𐑕; 𐑩𐑯𐑪𐑯, 𐑳𐑯𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑱𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑐𐑤𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑕.

𐑨𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞𐑳𐑕 𐑢𐑷𐑒𐑦𐑙, 𐑳𐑑𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑯𐑴 𐑕𐑬𐑯𐑛, 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑧𐑐𐑑 𐑑 𐑣𐑱𐑤 𐑞 𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑓𐑑, 𐑹 𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑛 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑣𐑶𐑕𐑑 𐑩 𐑕𐑱𐑤 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑣𐑲𐑼, 𐑹 𐑑 𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑛 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑑 𐑩 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑𐑼 𐑚𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑔—𐑞𐑳𐑕 𐑑 𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑴 𐑐𐑱𐑕𐑦𐑙, 𐑚𐑦𐑯𐑰𐑔 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑤𐑬𐑗𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑑, 𐑨𐑑 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑑𐑻𐑯 𐑣𐑰 𐑐𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑴𐑯 𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑑 𐑚𐑴𐑑, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑛𐑮𐑪𐑐𐑑 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑒𐑢𐑹𐑑𐑼-𐑛𐑧𐑒, 𐑯 𐑤𐑱 𐑞𐑺 𐑮𐑦𐑝𐑻𐑕𐑑; 𐑚𐑮𐑴𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑚𐑬 𐑑 𐑖𐑨𐑑𐑼𐑛 𐑕𐑑𐑻𐑯. 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑐𐑷𐑟𐑛 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑦𐑑; 𐑯 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑩𐑯 𐑷𐑤𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑦 𐑴𐑝𐑼-𐑒𐑤𐑬𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑕𐑒𐑲 𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑖 𐑑𐑮𐑵𐑐𐑕 𐑝 𐑒𐑤𐑬𐑛𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑕𐑱𐑤 𐑩𐑒𐑮𐑪𐑕, 𐑕𐑴 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑞 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑥𐑨𐑯'𐑟 𐑓𐑱𐑕 𐑞𐑺 𐑯𐑬 𐑕𐑑𐑴𐑤 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑨𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑜𐑤𐑵𐑥 𐑨𐑟 𐑞𐑦𐑕.

𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚 𐑕𐑷 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑐𐑷𐑟; 𐑯 𐑐𐑼𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑕 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙, 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑝𐑱𐑯𐑤𐑦, 𐑞𐑴, 𐑑 𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑯𐑕 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑴𐑯 𐑳𐑯𐑩𐑚𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑓𐑹𐑑𐑦𐑑𐑿𐑛, 𐑯 𐑞𐑳𐑕 𐑒𐑰𐑐 𐑳𐑐 𐑩 𐑝𐑨𐑤𐑾𐑯𐑑 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯'𐑟 𐑥𐑲𐑯𐑛, 𐑣𐑰 𐑩𐑛𐑝𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑑, 𐑯 𐑲𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑮𐑧𐑒 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑒𐑤𐑱𐑥𐑛—“𐑞 𐑔𐑦𐑕𐑩𐑤 𐑞 𐑨𐑕 𐑮𐑦𐑓𐑿𐑟𐑛; 𐑦𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑬𐑔 𐑑𐑵 𐑒𐑰𐑯𐑤𐑦, 𐑕𐑻; 𐑣𐑭! 𐑣𐑭!”

“𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑴𐑤𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑟 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑓𐑕 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑩 𐑮𐑧𐑒? 𐑥𐑨𐑯, 𐑥𐑨𐑯! 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑲 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑯𐑴 𐑞𐑰 𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑝 𐑨𐑟 𐑓𐑽𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑓𐑲𐑼 (𐑯 𐑨𐑟 𐑥𐑦𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤) 𐑲 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑕𐑢𐑺 𐑞𐑬 ·𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑑 𐑩 𐑐𐑪𐑤𐑑𐑮𐑵𐑯. 𐑜𐑮𐑴𐑯 𐑯𐑹 𐑤𐑭𐑓 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑚𐑰 𐑣𐑻𐑛 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑩 𐑮𐑧𐑒.”

“𐑲, 𐑕𐑻,” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒 𐑛𐑮𐑷𐑦𐑙 𐑯𐑽, “'𐑑𐑦𐑟 𐑩 𐑕𐑪𐑤𐑩𐑥 𐑕𐑲𐑑; 𐑩𐑯 𐑴𐑥𐑩𐑯, 𐑯 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑤 𐑢𐑳𐑯.”

“𐑴𐑥𐑩𐑯? 𐑴𐑥𐑩𐑯?—𐑞 𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑼𐑦! 𐑦𐑓 𐑞 𐑜𐑪𐑛𐑟 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒 𐑑 𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑒 𐑬𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑑 𐑑 𐑥𐑨𐑯, 𐑞𐑱 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑪𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑒 𐑬𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑑; 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑖𐑱𐑒 𐑞𐑺 𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑟, 𐑯 𐑜𐑦𐑝 𐑩𐑯 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑢𐑲𐑝𐑟' 𐑛𐑸𐑒𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑯𐑑.—𐑚𐑦𐑜𐑪𐑯! 𐑘𐑰 𐑑𐑵 𐑸 𐑞 𐑪𐑐𐑩𐑟𐑦𐑑 𐑐𐑴𐑤𐑟 𐑝 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑔𐑦𐑙; ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒 𐑦𐑟 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚 𐑮𐑦𐑝𐑻𐑕𐑑, 𐑯 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚 𐑦𐑟 ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒; 𐑯 𐑘𐑰 𐑑𐑵 𐑸 𐑷𐑤 𐑥𐑨𐑯𐑒𐑲𐑯𐑛; 𐑯 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑩𐑤𐑴𐑯 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑞 𐑥𐑦𐑤𐑾𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑐𐑰𐑐𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑻𐑔, 𐑯𐑹 𐑜𐑪𐑛𐑟 𐑯𐑹 𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑱𐑚𐑼𐑟! 𐑒𐑴𐑤𐑛, 𐑒𐑴𐑤𐑛—𐑲 𐑖𐑦𐑝𐑼!—𐑣𐑬 𐑯𐑬? 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑓𐑑 𐑞𐑺! ·𐑛'𐑘𐑰 𐑕𐑰 𐑣𐑦𐑥? 𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑬𐑑 𐑓 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑕𐑐𐑬𐑑, 𐑞𐑴 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑐𐑬𐑑 𐑑𐑧𐑯 𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑩 𐑕𐑧𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑛!”

𐑞 𐑛𐑱 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑽𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑳𐑯; 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑞 𐑣𐑧𐑥 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑜𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑩𐑯 𐑮𐑴𐑚 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑮𐑳𐑕𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙. 𐑕𐑵𐑯, 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑛𐑸𐑒, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞 𐑤𐑫𐑒-𐑬𐑑 𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑱𐑯𐑛 𐑳𐑯𐑕𐑧𐑑.

“𐑒𐑭𐑯𐑑 𐑕𐑰 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑬𐑑 𐑯𐑬, 𐑕𐑻;—𐑑𐑵 𐑛𐑸𐑒”—𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 𐑩 𐑝𐑶𐑕 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑺.

“𐑣𐑬 𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑯?”

“𐑨𐑟 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹, 𐑕𐑻,—𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑑 𐑤𐑰𐑢𐑼𐑛.”

“𐑜𐑫𐑛! 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑝𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑤𐑴𐑼 𐑯𐑬 '𐑑𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑲𐑑. 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑮𐑶𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑯 𐑑𐑪𐑐-𐑜𐑨𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑯-𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑟, ·𐑥𐑼 ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒. 𐑢𐑰 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑮𐑳𐑯 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑥𐑹𐑯𐑦𐑙; 𐑣𐑰'𐑟 𐑥𐑱𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑐𐑨𐑕𐑦𐑡 𐑯𐑬, 𐑯 𐑥𐑱 𐑣𐑰𐑝-𐑑 𐑩 𐑢𐑲𐑤. 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑥 𐑞𐑺! 𐑒𐑰𐑐 𐑣𐑻 𐑓𐑫𐑤 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑞 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛!—𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑓𐑑! 𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑛𐑬𐑯!—·𐑥𐑼 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚, 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑩 𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑖 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑑 𐑞 𐑓𐑹-𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑧𐑛, 𐑯 𐑕𐑰 𐑦𐑑 𐑥𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑥𐑹𐑯𐑦𐑙.”—𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑩𐑛𐑝𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑑𐑩𐑢𐑹𐑛𐑟 𐑞 𐑛𐑳𐑚𐑤𐑵𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑥𐑱𐑯-𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑—“𐑥𐑧𐑯, 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑜𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑲𐑯, 𐑓 𐑲 𐑻𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑑; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑲 𐑖𐑨𐑤 𐑤𐑧𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑩𐑚𐑲𐑛 𐑣𐑽 𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑞 ·𐑢𐑲𐑑 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑦𐑟 𐑛𐑧𐑛; 𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑣𐑵𐑕𐑴𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑝 𐑘𐑰 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑮𐑱𐑟𐑩𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑛𐑱 𐑣𐑰 𐑖𐑨𐑤 𐑚𐑰 𐑒𐑦𐑤𐑛, 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑜𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑦𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑨𐑯'𐑟; 𐑯 𐑦𐑓 𐑪𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑛𐑱 𐑲 𐑖𐑨𐑤 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯 𐑮𐑱𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑑𐑧𐑯 𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑖𐑨𐑤 𐑚𐑰 𐑛𐑦𐑝𐑲𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑷𐑤 𐑝 𐑘𐑰! 𐑩𐑢𐑱 𐑯𐑬!—𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑒 𐑦𐑟 𐑞𐑲𐑯, 𐑕𐑻!”

𐑯 𐑕𐑴 𐑕𐑱𐑦𐑙, 𐑣𐑰 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑣𐑭𐑓 𐑢𐑱 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑒𐑳𐑑𐑩𐑤, 𐑯 𐑕𐑤𐑬𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑑, 𐑕𐑑𐑫𐑛 𐑞𐑺 𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑛𐑷𐑯, 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑧𐑐𐑑 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑮𐑬𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑑 𐑕𐑰 𐑣𐑬 𐑞 𐑯𐑲𐑑 𐑢𐑹 𐑪𐑯.

·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 134. 𐑞 ·𐑗𐑱𐑕—·𐑕𐑧𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑛𐑱.

𐑨𐑑 𐑛𐑱-𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑒, 𐑞 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑-𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑐𐑳𐑙𐑒𐑗𐑵𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑥𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑩𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑖.

“·𐑛'𐑘𐑰 𐑕𐑰 𐑣𐑦𐑥?” 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑩𐑤𐑬𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑐𐑱𐑕 𐑓 𐑞 𐑤𐑲𐑑 𐑑 𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑛.

“𐑕𐑰 𐑯𐑳𐑔𐑦𐑙, 𐑕𐑻.”

“𐑑𐑻𐑯 𐑳𐑐 𐑷𐑤 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑯 𐑥𐑱𐑒 𐑕𐑱𐑤! 𐑣𐑰 𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑓𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑼 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑲 𐑔𐑷𐑑 𐑓;—𐑞 𐑑𐑪𐑐-𐑜𐑨𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑟!—𐑲, 𐑞𐑱 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑒𐑧𐑐𐑑 𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑻 𐑷𐑤 𐑯𐑲𐑑. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑯𐑴 𐑥𐑨𐑑𐑼—'𐑑𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑓 𐑞 𐑮𐑳𐑖.”

𐑣𐑽 𐑚𐑰 𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑧𐑛, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑐𐑻𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑕 𐑐𐑼𐑕𐑿𐑑 𐑝 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑐𐑼𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑼 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑿𐑛 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑛𐑱 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑯𐑲𐑑, 𐑯 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑯𐑲𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑛𐑱, 𐑦𐑟 𐑩 𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑲 𐑯𐑴 𐑥𐑰𐑯𐑟 𐑳𐑯𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑬𐑔 𐑕𐑰 𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑼𐑦. 𐑓 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑦𐑟 𐑞 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑒𐑦𐑤, 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑾𐑯𐑕 𐑝 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑽𐑾𐑯𐑕, 𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑓𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑩𐑒𐑢𐑲𐑼𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑯𐑨𐑗𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑡𐑰𐑯𐑾𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑞 ·𐑯𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑑 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑭𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑟; 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑕𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑤 𐑪𐑚𐑟𐑼𐑝𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑩 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛, 𐑞𐑱 𐑢𐑦𐑤, 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑜𐑦𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑕𐑻𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟, 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑨𐑒𐑘𐑼𐑩𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑓𐑹𐑑𐑧𐑤 𐑚𐑴𐑔 𐑞 𐑛𐑦𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑿 𐑑 𐑕𐑢𐑦𐑥 𐑓 𐑩 𐑑𐑲𐑥, 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑕𐑲𐑑, 𐑨𐑟 𐑢𐑧𐑤 𐑨𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑚𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑝 𐑐𐑮𐑴𐑜𐑮𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑛𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑐𐑽𐑾𐑛. 𐑯, 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑒𐑱𐑕𐑩𐑟, 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑩 𐑐𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑑, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑤𐑵𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑲𐑑 𐑝 𐑩 𐑒𐑴𐑕𐑑, 𐑣𐑵𐑟 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑑𐑮𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑧𐑤 𐑯𐑴𐑟, 𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑣𐑰 𐑛𐑦𐑟𐑲𐑼𐑟 𐑖𐑹𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑻𐑯 𐑑 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑓𐑻𐑞𐑼 𐑐𐑶𐑯𐑑; 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑨𐑟 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑐𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑚𐑲 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑕, 𐑯 𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑕 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑲𐑕 𐑚𐑺𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑞 𐑒𐑱𐑐 𐑨𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑝𐑦𐑟𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤, 𐑦𐑯 𐑹𐑛𐑼 𐑞 𐑥𐑹 𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑑 𐑼𐑲𐑑 𐑞 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑴𐑑, 𐑳𐑯𐑕𐑰𐑯 𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛, 𐑦𐑝𐑧𐑯𐑗𐑵𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑝𐑦𐑟𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑛: 𐑕𐑴 𐑛𐑳𐑟 𐑞 𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑼𐑥𐑩𐑯, 𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑕, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤; 𐑓 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑗𐑱𐑕𐑑, 𐑯 𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑡𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑥𐑸𐑒𐑑, 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑕𐑧𐑝𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑬𐑼𐑟 𐑝 𐑛𐑱𐑤𐑲𐑑, 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑯𐑲𐑑 𐑩𐑚𐑕𐑒𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑟 𐑞 𐑓𐑦𐑖, 𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑰𐑗𐑼'𐑟 𐑓𐑿𐑗𐑼 𐑢𐑱𐑒 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑞 𐑛𐑸𐑒𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑦𐑟 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑚𐑤𐑦𐑖𐑑 𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑕 𐑥𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑝 𐑞 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑑𐑼, 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑐𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑑'𐑕 𐑒𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥. 𐑕𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑑𐑼'𐑟 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑕 𐑕𐑒𐑦𐑤, 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑝𐑻𐑚𐑾𐑤 𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑯𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑝 𐑩 𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑮𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼, 𐑩 𐑢𐑱𐑒, 𐑦𐑟 𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑛𐑦𐑟𐑲𐑼𐑛 𐑐𐑻𐑐𐑩𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑢𐑧𐑤 𐑯𐑲 𐑨𐑟 𐑮𐑦𐑤𐑲𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑛𐑓𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛. 𐑯 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑥𐑲𐑑𐑦 𐑲𐑼𐑯 ·𐑤𐑩𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑔𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑥𐑪𐑛𐑼𐑯 𐑮𐑱𐑤𐑢𐑱 𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑴 𐑓𐑩𐑥𐑦𐑤𐑽𐑤𐑦 𐑯𐑴𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑐𐑱𐑕, 𐑞𐑨𐑑, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑢𐑪𐑗𐑩𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟, 𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑛𐑪𐑒𐑑𐑼𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑝 𐑩 𐑚𐑱𐑚𐑦'𐑟 𐑐𐑳𐑤𐑕; 𐑯 𐑤𐑲𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑱 𐑝 𐑦𐑑, 𐑞 𐑳𐑐 𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯 𐑹 𐑞 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑮𐑰𐑗 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑹 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩 𐑕𐑐𐑪𐑑, 𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑹 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩𐑯 𐑬𐑼; 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑕𐑴, 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑, 𐑞𐑺 𐑸 𐑩𐑒𐑱𐑠𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑞𐑰𐑟 ·𐑯𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑑𐑼𐑟 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑳𐑞𐑼 ·𐑤𐑩𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑔𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑛𐑰𐑐, 𐑩𐑒𐑹𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑞 𐑩𐑚𐑟𐑻𐑝𐑛 𐑣𐑿𐑥𐑼 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑛; 𐑯 𐑕𐑱 𐑑 𐑞𐑧𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑝𐑟, 𐑕𐑴 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑬𐑼𐑟 𐑣𐑧𐑯𐑕 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑜𐑪𐑯 𐑑𐑵 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑛 𐑥𐑲𐑤𐑟, 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑮𐑰𐑗𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑹 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑜𐑮𐑰 𐑝 𐑤𐑨𐑑𐑦𐑑𐑿𐑛 𐑹 𐑤𐑪𐑯𐑜𐑦𐑑𐑿𐑛. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑑 𐑮𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑩𐑒𐑿𐑑𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑨𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑕𐑩𐑒𐑕𐑧𐑕𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑧𐑯𐑛, 𐑞 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛 𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑰 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑥𐑩𐑯'𐑟 𐑨𐑤𐑲𐑟; 𐑓 𐑝 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑩𐑝𐑱𐑤 𐑑 𐑞 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑭𐑥𐑛 𐑹 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑚𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑥𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑯𐑼 𐑦𐑟 𐑞 𐑕𐑒𐑦𐑤 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑩𐑖𐑫𐑼𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑣𐑰 𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑜𐑟𐑨𐑒𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑯𐑲𐑯𐑑𐑦-𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑤𐑰𐑜𐑟 𐑯 𐑩 𐑒𐑢𐑹𐑑𐑼 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑹𐑑? 𐑦𐑯𐑓𐑼𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑑𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕, 𐑸 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑨𐑑𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑳𐑚𐑑𐑲𐑤 𐑥𐑨𐑑𐑼𐑟 𐑑𐑳𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑗𐑱𐑕 𐑝 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟.

𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑑𐑹 𐑪𐑯; 𐑤𐑰𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩 𐑓𐑳𐑮𐑴 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑰 𐑨𐑟 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑩 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑩𐑯-𐑚𐑷𐑤, 𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑑, 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑟 𐑩 𐑐𐑤𐑬-𐑖𐑺 𐑯 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑟 𐑳𐑐 𐑞 𐑤𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑤 𐑓𐑰𐑤𐑛.

“𐑚𐑲 𐑕𐑷𐑤𐑑 𐑯 𐑣𐑧𐑥𐑐!” 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚, “𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑕𐑢𐑦𐑓𐑑 𐑥𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑒 𐑒𐑮𐑰𐑐𐑕 𐑳𐑐 𐑢𐑳𐑯'𐑟 𐑤𐑧𐑜𐑟 𐑯 𐑑𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑣𐑸𐑑. 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑯 𐑲 𐑸 𐑑𐑵 𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑝 𐑓𐑧𐑤𐑴𐑟!—𐑣𐑭, 𐑣𐑭! 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑥𐑰 𐑳𐑐, 𐑯 𐑤𐑷𐑯𐑗 𐑥𐑰, 𐑕𐑐𐑲𐑯-𐑢𐑲𐑟, 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑰,—𐑓 𐑚𐑲 𐑤𐑲𐑝-𐑴𐑒𐑕! 𐑥𐑲 𐑕𐑐𐑲𐑯'𐑟 𐑩 𐑒𐑰𐑤. 𐑣𐑭, 𐑣𐑭! 𐑢𐑰 𐑜𐑴 𐑞 𐑜𐑱𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑰𐑝𐑟 𐑯𐑴 𐑛𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑣𐑲𐑯𐑛!”

“𐑞𐑺 𐑖𐑰 𐑚𐑤𐑴𐑟—𐑖𐑰 𐑚𐑤𐑴𐑟!—𐑖𐑰 𐑚𐑤𐑴𐑟!—𐑮𐑲𐑑 𐑩𐑣𐑧𐑛!” 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑬 𐑞 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑-𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑒𐑮𐑲.

“𐑲, 𐑲!” 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚, “𐑲 𐑯𐑿 𐑦𐑑—𐑘𐑰 𐑒𐑭𐑯𐑑 𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑱𐑐—𐑚𐑤𐑴 𐑪𐑯 𐑯 𐑕𐑐𐑤𐑦𐑑 𐑘𐑹 𐑕𐑐𐑬𐑑, 𐑴 𐑢𐑱𐑤! 𐑞 𐑥𐑨𐑛 𐑓𐑰𐑯𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑦𐑟 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑘𐑰! 𐑚𐑤𐑴 𐑘𐑹 𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑥𐑐—𐑚𐑤𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑼 𐑘𐑹 𐑤𐑳𐑙𐑟!—𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑛𐑨𐑥 𐑪𐑓 𐑘𐑹 𐑚𐑤𐑳𐑛, 𐑨𐑟 𐑩 𐑥𐑦𐑤𐑼 𐑖𐑳𐑑𐑕 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼𐑜𐑱𐑑 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑰𐑥!”

𐑯 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑒 𐑬𐑑 𐑓 𐑢𐑧𐑤 𐑯𐑲 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑒𐑮𐑵. 𐑞 𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑯𐑟𐑦𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑗𐑱𐑕 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑢𐑻𐑒𐑑 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑚𐑳𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑳𐑐, 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑢𐑲𐑯 𐑢𐑻𐑒𐑑 𐑩𐑯𐑿. 𐑢𐑪𐑑𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑐𐑱𐑤 𐑓𐑽𐑟 𐑯 𐑓𐑹𐑚𐑴𐑛𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑝 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑓𐑧𐑤𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹; 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑯𐑬 𐑒𐑧𐑐𐑑 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑕𐑲𐑑 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑷 𐑝 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞𐑱 𐑢𐑻 𐑚𐑮𐑴𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑳𐑐, 𐑯 𐑪𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑕𐑲𐑛𐑟 𐑮𐑬𐑑𐑩𐑛, 𐑨𐑟 𐑑𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑛 𐑐𐑮𐑺𐑦 𐑣𐑺𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑒𐑨𐑑𐑼 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑞 𐑚𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑲𐑕𐑩𐑯. 𐑞 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑝 ·𐑓𐑱𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑕𐑯𐑨𐑗𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑺 𐑕𐑴𐑤𐑟; 𐑯 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑻𐑦𐑙 𐑐𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑤𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑰𐑝𐑾𐑕 𐑛𐑱; 𐑞 𐑮𐑨𐑒 𐑝 𐑞 𐑐𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑯𐑲𐑑'𐑕 𐑕𐑩𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑕; 𐑞 𐑓𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑑, 𐑳𐑯𐑓𐑽𐑦𐑙, 𐑚𐑤𐑲𐑯𐑛, 𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑢𐑱 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑞𐑺 𐑢𐑲𐑤𐑛 𐑒𐑮𐑭𐑓𐑑 𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑐𐑤𐑳𐑯𐑡𐑦𐑙 𐑑𐑩𐑢𐑹𐑛𐑟 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑓𐑤𐑲𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑸𐑒; 𐑚𐑲 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑟, 𐑞𐑺 𐑣𐑸𐑑𐑕 𐑢𐑻 𐑚𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑙. 𐑞 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑚𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑟 𐑝 𐑞𐑺 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑟, 𐑯 𐑮𐑳𐑖𐑑 𐑞 𐑝𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑤 𐑪𐑯 𐑚𐑲 𐑸𐑥𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑦𐑟𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤; 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑞 𐑕𐑦𐑥𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑳𐑯𐑕𐑰𐑯 𐑱𐑡𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑕𐑴 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑤𐑱𐑝𐑛 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑑 𐑞 𐑮𐑱𐑕.

𐑞𐑱 𐑢𐑻 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑥𐑨𐑯, 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑔𐑻𐑑𐑦. 𐑓 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑛 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑷𐑤; 𐑞𐑴 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑐𐑫𐑑 𐑑𐑩𐑜𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑝 𐑷𐑤 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑟—𐑴𐑒, 𐑯 𐑥𐑱𐑐𐑩𐑤, 𐑯 𐑐𐑲𐑯 𐑢𐑫𐑛; 𐑲𐑼𐑯, 𐑯 𐑐𐑦𐑗, 𐑯 𐑣𐑧𐑥𐑐—𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑮𐑨𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑰𐑗 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑒𐑮𐑰𐑑 𐑣𐑳𐑤, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑖𐑪𐑑 𐑪𐑯 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑢𐑱, 𐑚𐑴𐑔 𐑚𐑨𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑯 𐑛𐑦𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑩𐑤 𐑒𐑰𐑤; 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑕𐑴, 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑡𐑵𐑨𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑵, 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑥𐑨𐑯'𐑟 𐑝𐑨𐑤𐑼, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑨𐑯'𐑟 𐑓𐑽; 𐑜𐑦𐑤𐑑 𐑯 𐑜𐑦𐑤𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑕, 𐑷𐑤 𐑝𐑼𐑲𐑩𐑑𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑢𐑧𐑤𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑯𐑩𐑕, 𐑯 𐑢𐑻 𐑷𐑤 𐑛𐑦𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑓𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑜𐑴𐑤 𐑢𐑦𐑗 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑞𐑺 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑤𐑹𐑛 𐑯 𐑒𐑰𐑤 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑐𐑶𐑯𐑑 𐑑.

𐑞 𐑮𐑦𐑜𐑦𐑙 𐑤𐑦𐑝𐑛. 𐑞 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑-𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑟, 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑞 𐑑𐑪𐑐𐑕 𐑝 𐑑𐑷𐑤 𐑐𐑭𐑥𐑟, 𐑢𐑻 𐑬𐑑𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑑𐑳𐑓𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑸𐑥𐑟 𐑯 𐑤𐑧𐑜𐑟. 𐑒𐑤𐑦𐑙𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑩 𐑕𐑐𐑸 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛, 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑮𐑰𐑗𐑑 𐑓𐑹𐑔 𐑞 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑝𐑦𐑙𐑟; 𐑳𐑞𐑼𐑟, 𐑖𐑱𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑺 𐑲𐑟 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑝𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑛 𐑕𐑳𐑯𐑤𐑲𐑑, 𐑕𐑨𐑑 𐑓𐑸 𐑬𐑑 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑮𐑪𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑘𐑸𐑛𐑟; 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑸𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑓𐑫𐑤 𐑚𐑺𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑥𐑹𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑟, 𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑦 𐑯 𐑮𐑲𐑐 𐑓 𐑞𐑺 𐑓𐑱𐑑. 𐑭! 𐑣𐑬 𐑞𐑱 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑴𐑝 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑓𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑑 𐑚𐑤𐑵𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑒 𐑬𐑑 𐑞 𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑶 𐑞𐑧𐑥!

“𐑢𐑲 𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑘𐑰 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑬𐑑 𐑓 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑦𐑓 𐑘𐑰 𐑕𐑰 𐑣𐑦𐑥?” 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚, 𐑢𐑧𐑯, 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑞 𐑤𐑨𐑐𐑕 𐑝 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑕𐑦𐑯𐑕 𐑞 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑒𐑮𐑲, 𐑯𐑴 𐑥𐑹 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑣𐑻𐑛. “𐑕𐑢𐑱 𐑥𐑰 𐑳𐑐, 𐑥𐑧𐑯; 𐑘𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑰𐑝𐑛; 𐑯𐑪𐑑 ·𐑥𐑪𐑚𐑦 ·𐑛𐑦𐑒 𐑒𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑕 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑪𐑛 𐑡𐑧𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑱, 𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑩𐑐𐑽𐑟.”

𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑕𐑴; 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑰𐑜𐑼𐑯𐑩𐑕, 𐑞 𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑓 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤-𐑕𐑐𐑬𐑑, 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑦𐑝𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑦𐑑𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑕𐑵𐑯 𐑐𐑮𐑵𐑝𐑛; 𐑓 𐑣𐑸𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑣𐑨𐑛 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑮𐑰𐑗𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑻𐑗; 𐑣𐑸𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞 𐑮𐑴𐑐 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑱𐑛 𐑑 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑐𐑦𐑯 𐑪𐑯 𐑛𐑧𐑒, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑒 𐑞 𐑒𐑰-𐑯𐑴𐑑 𐑑 𐑩𐑯 𐑹𐑒𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑩, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑞 𐑺 𐑝𐑲𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑚𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑗𐑸𐑡𐑩𐑟 𐑝 𐑮𐑲𐑓𐑩𐑤𐑟. 𐑞 𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑳𐑥𐑓𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑣𐑩𐑤𐑵 𐑝 𐑔𐑻𐑑𐑦 𐑚𐑳𐑒𐑕𐑒𐑦𐑯 𐑤𐑳𐑙𐑟 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑣𐑻𐑛, 𐑨𐑟—𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑯𐑽𐑼 𐑑 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑞 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑦𐑥𐑨𐑡𐑦𐑯𐑼𐑦 𐑡𐑧𐑑, 𐑤𐑧𐑕 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑩 𐑥𐑲𐑤 𐑩𐑣𐑧𐑛—·𐑥𐑪𐑚𐑦 ·𐑛𐑦𐑒 𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑝𐑿! 𐑓 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑒𐑭𐑥 𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑕𐑐𐑬𐑑𐑦𐑙𐑟; 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑐𐑰𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑜𐑳𐑖 𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑧𐑛, 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑞 ·𐑢𐑲𐑑 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑯𐑬 𐑮𐑦𐑝𐑰𐑤 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑝𐑦𐑕𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑦; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑓𐑸 𐑥𐑹 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑕 𐑓𐑦𐑯𐑪𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑪𐑯 𐑝 𐑚𐑮𐑰𐑗𐑦𐑙. 𐑮𐑲𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑳𐑑𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑝𐑦𐑤𐑪𐑕𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑓𐑻𐑞𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑛𐑧𐑐𐑔𐑕, 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑞𐑳𐑕 𐑚𐑵𐑥𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑲𐑼 𐑚𐑳𐑤𐑒 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑐𐑘𐑫𐑼 𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑺, 𐑯 𐑐𐑲𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑳𐑐 𐑩 𐑥𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑛𐑨𐑟𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑴𐑥, 𐑖𐑴𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕 𐑑 𐑞 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑝 𐑕𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑥𐑲𐑤𐑟 𐑯 𐑥𐑹. 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑥𐑴𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑕, 𐑞 𐑑𐑹𐑯, 𐑦𐑯𐑮𐑱𐑡𐑛 𐑢𐑱𐑝𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑖𐑱𐑒𐑕 𐑪𐑓, 𐑕𐑰𐑥 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑱𐑯; 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑒𐑱𐑕𐑩𐑟, 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑚𐑮𐑰𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑨𐑒𐑑 𐑝 𐑛𐑦𐑓𐑲𐑩𐑯𐑕.

“𐑞𐑺 𐑖𐑰 𐑚𐑮𐑰𐑗𐑩𐑟! 𐑞𐑺 𐑖𐑰 𐑚𐑮𐑰𐑗𐑩𐑟!” 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑲, 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑥𐑧𐑠𐑼𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑚𐑮𐑩𐑝𐑭𐑛𐑴𐑟 𐑞 ·𐑢𐑲𐑑 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑑𐑪𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑕𐑨𐑥𐑩𐑯-𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑑 ·𐑣𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑯. 𐑕𐑴 𐑕𐑳𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑰𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑤𐑵 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑰, 𐑯 𐑮𐑦𐑤𐑰𐑝𐑛 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑚𐑤𐑵𐑼 𐑥𐑸𐑡𐑦𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑒𐑲, 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑱 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑮𐑱𐑟𐑛, 𐑓 𐑞 𐑥𐑴𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑, 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑪𐑤𐑼𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑜𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑼𐑛 𐑯 𐑜𐑤𐑺𐑛 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑜𐑤𐑱𐑕𐑽; 𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑫𐑛 𐑞𐑺 𐑜𐑮𐑨𐑡𐑵𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑓𐑱𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑯 𐑓𐑱𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑢𐑱 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑐𐑸𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑑𐑦, 𐑑 𐑞 𐑛𐑦𐑥 𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑩𐑯 𐑩𐑛𐑝𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑖𐑬𐑼 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑝𐑱𐑤.

“𐑲, 𐑚𐑮𐑰𐑗 𐑘𐑹 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑯, ·𐑥𐑪𐑚𐑦 ·𐑛𐑦𐑒!” 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚, “𐑞𐑲 𐑬𐑼 𐑯 𐑞𐑲 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯 𐑸 𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛!—𐑛𐑬𐑯! 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑝 𐑘𐑰, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑓𐑹. 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕!—𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑚𐑲!”

𐑳𐑯𐑥𐑲𐑯𐑛𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑞 𐑑𐑰𐑛𐑾𐑕 𐑮𐑴𐑐-𐑤𐑨𐑛𐑼𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑖𐑮𐑬𐑛𐑟, 𐑞 𐑥𐑧𐑯, 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑖𐑵𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑟, 𐑕𐑤𐑦𐑛 𐑑 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑒, 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑲𐑕𐑩𐑤𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑨𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑟 𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑤𐑘𐑼𐑛𐑟; 𐑢𐑲𐑤 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚, 𐑤𐑧𐑕 𐑛𐑸𐑑𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑮𐑨𐑐𐑦𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑛𐑮𐑪𐑐𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑻𐑗.

“𐑤𐑴𐑼 𐑩𐑢𐑱,” 𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛, 𐑕𐑴 𐑕𐑵𐑯 𐑨𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑮𐑰𐑗𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑴𐑑—𐑩 𐑕𐑐𐑺 𐑢𐑳𐑯, 𐑮𐑦𐑜𐑛 𐑞 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼𐑯𐑵𐑯 𐑐𐑮𐑰𐑝𐑾𐑕. “·𐑥𐑼 ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒, 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑦𐑟 𐑞𐑲𐑯—𐑒𐑰𐑐 𐑩𐑢𐑱 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑒𐑰𐑐 𐑯𐑽 𐑞𐑧𐑥. 𐑤𐑴𐑼, 𐑷𐑤!”

𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑓 𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑒 𐑑𐑧𐑮𐑼 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞𐑧𐑥, 𐑚𐑲 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑩𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓, ·𐑥𐑪𐑚𐑦 ·𐑛𐑦𐑒 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑛, 𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑬 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑓 𐑞 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑒𐑮𐑵𐑟. 𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚'𐑟 𐑚𐑴𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑩𐑤; 𐑯 𐑗𐑽𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑧𐑯, 𐑣𐑰 𐑑𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑣𐑧𐑛-𐑯-𐑣𐑧𐑛,—𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑟, 𐑐𐑫𐑤 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑳𐑐 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑛,—𐑩 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑳𐑯𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑔𐑦𐑙; 𐑓 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑤𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑑, 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩 𐑒𐑹𐑕 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑒𐑤𐑵𐑛𐑟 𐑞 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑧𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤'𐑟 𐑕𐑲𐑛𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑝𐑦𐑠𐑩𐑯. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑺 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑒𐑤𐑴𐑕 𐑤𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑛, 𐑯 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕 𐑢𐑻 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑯 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐'𐑕 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑕 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑲; 𐑞 ·𐑢𐑲𐑑 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑗𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑓𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑾𐑕 𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑛, 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑻, 𐑮𐑳𐑖𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑴𐑐𐑩𐑯 𐑡𐑷𐑟, 𐑯 𐑩 𐑤𐑨𐑖𐑦𐑙 𐑑𐑱𐑤, 𐑪𐑓𐑼𐑛 𐑩𐑐𐑷𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑨𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑪𐑯 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑕𐑲𐑛; 𐑯 𐑣𐑰𐑛𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑲𐑼𐑯𐑟 𐑛𐑸𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑚𐑴𐑑, 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑪𐑯 𐑩𐑯𐑲𐑩𐑤𐑱𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑰𐑗 𐑕𐑧𐑐𐑼𐑩𐑑 𐑐𐑤𐑨𐑙𐑒 𐑝 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕 𐑢𐑻 𐑥𐑱𐑛. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑕𐑒𐑦𐑤𐑓𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑵𐑝𐑼𐑛, 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑢𐑰𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑛 𐑗𐑸𐑡𐑼𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑰𐑤𐑛; 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕 𐑓 𐑩 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑦𐑤𐑵𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥; 𐑞𐑴, 𐑨𐑑 𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑩 𐑐𐑤𐑨𐑙𐑒'𐑕 𐑚𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑔; 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑑𐑲𐑥, ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚'𐑟 𐑳𐑯𐑻𐑔𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑤𐑴𐑜𐑩𐑯 𐑑𐑹 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑒𐑮𐑲 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑑 𐑖𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑟.

𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑳𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑵𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟, 𐑞 ·𐑢𐑲𐑑 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑕𐑴 𐑒𐑮𐑪𐑕𐑑 𐑯 𐑮𐑰𐑒𐑮𐑪𐑕𐑑, 𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑔𐑬𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑢𐑱𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑨𐑙𐑜𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑞 𐑕𐑤𐑨𐑒 𐑝 𐑞 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑤𐑲𐑯𐑟 𐑯𐑬 𐑓𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑱 𐑓𐑹𐑖𐑹𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑛, 𐑯, 𐑝 𐑞𐑧𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑝𐑟, 𐑢𐑹𐑐𐑑 𐑞 𐑛𐑦𐑝𐑴𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕 𐑑𐑩𐑢𐑹𐑛𐑟 𐑞 𐑐𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑲𐑼𐑯𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥; 𐑞𐑴 𐑯𐑬 𐑓 𐑩 𐑥𐑴𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑛𐑮𐑵 𐑩𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑩 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤, 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑓 𐑑 𐑮𐑨𐑤𐑦 𐑓 𐑩 𐑥𐑹 𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑕 𐑗𐑸𐑡. 𐑕𐑰𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑪𐑐𐑼𐑑𐑿𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑦, ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑐𐑱𐑛 𐑬𐑑 𐑥𐑹 𐑤𐑲𐑯: 𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑮𐑨𐑐𐑦𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑣𐑷𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑯 𐑡𐑻𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑦𐑑 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯—𐑣𐑴𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑱 𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑚𐑼 𐑦𐑑 𐑝 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑕𐑯𐑸𐑤𐑟—𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑤𐑴!—𐑩 𐑕𐑲𐑑 𐑥𐑹 𐑕𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑡 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑞 𐑦𐑥𐑚𐑨𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑑𐑰𐑔 𐑝 𐑖𐑸𐑒𐑕!

𐑒𐑷𐑑 𐑯 𐑑𐑢𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛—𐑒𐑹𐑒𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑵𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑥𐑱𐑟𐑩𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑤𐑲𐑯, 𐑤𐑵𐑕 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑟 𐑯 𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑺 𐑚𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑸𐑚𐑟 𐑯 𐑐𐑶𐑯𐑑𐑕, 𐑒𐑱𐑥 𐑓𐑤𐑨𐑖𐑦𐑙 𐑯 𐑛𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑳𐑐 𐑑 𐑞 𐑗𐑪𐑒𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑬𐑟 𐑝 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚'𐑟 𐑚𐑴𐑑. 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑚𐑰 𐑛𐑳𐑯. 𐑕𐑰𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑-𐑯𐑲𐑓, 𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑰𐑗𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑦𐑯—𐑔𐑮𐑵—𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑—𐑞 𐑮𐑱𐑟 𐑝 𐑕𐑑𐑰𐑤; 𐑛𐑮𐑨𐑜𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑤𐑲𐑯 𐑚𐑦𐑘𐑪𐑯𐑛, 𐑐𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑑, 𐑦𐑯𐑚𐑹𐑛, 𐑑 𐑞 𐑚𐑬𐑟𐑥𐑩𐑯, 𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑑𐑢𐑲𐑕 𐑕𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑮𐑴𐑐 𐑯𐑽 𐑞 𐑗𐑪𐑒𐑕—𐑛𐑮𐑪𐑐𐑑 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑕𐑧𐑐𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑓𐑨𐑜𐑴 𐑝 𐑕𐑑𐑰𐑤 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑕𐑰; 𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑷𐑤 𐑓𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯. 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑, 𐑞 ·𐑢𐑲𐑑 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑩 𐑕𐑳𐑛𐑩𐑯 𐑮𐑳𐑖 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑞 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑱𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑑𐑨𐑙𐑜𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑤𐑲𐑯𐑟; 𐑚𐑲 𐑕𐑴 𐑛𐑵𐑦𐑙, 𐑦𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑮𐑨𐑜𐑛 𐑞 𐑥𐑹 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑪𐑤𐑝𐑛 𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕 𐑝 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚 𐑯 ·𐑓𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑒 𐑑𐑩𐑢𐑹𐑛𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑤𐑵𐑒𐑕; 𐑛𐑨𐑖𐑑 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑑𐑩𐑜𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑑𐑵 𐑮𐑴𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑳𐑕𐑒𐑕 𐑪𐑯 𐑩 𐑕𐑻𐑓-𐑚𐑰𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑚𐑰𐑗, 𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑛𐑲𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑕𐑰, 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑩𐑐𐑽𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑚𐑶𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑱𐑤𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑩𐑥, 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑗, 𐑓 𐑩 𐑕𐑐𐑱𐑕, 𐑞 𐑴𐑛𐑼𐑩𐑕 𐑕𐑰𐑛𐑼 𐑗𐑦𐑐𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑕 𐑛𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑯 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛, 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑯𐑳𐑑𐑥𐑧𐑜 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑕𐑢𐑦𐑓𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑑𐑻𐑛 𐑚𐑴𐑤 𐑝 𐑐𐑳𐑯𐑗.

𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑞 𐑑𐑵 𐑒𐑮𐑵𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑕𐑻𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼𐑟, 𐑮𐑰𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑬𐑑 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑞 𐑮𐑦𐑝𐑪𐑤𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑤𐑲𐑯-𐑑𐑳𐑚𐑟, 𐑹𐑟, 𐑯 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑓𐑤𐑴𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑗𐑼, 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑱𐑕𐑤𐑴𐑐 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 ·𐑓𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑒 𐑚𐑪𐑚𐑛 𐑳𐑐 𐑯 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩𐑯 𐑧𐑥𐑐𐑑𐑦 𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑤, 𐑑𐑢𐑦𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑤𐑧𐑜𐑟 𐑳𐑐𐑢𐑼𐑛𐑟 𐑑 𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑱𐑐 𐑞 𐑛𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑡𐑷𐑟 𐑝 𐑖𐑸𐑒𐑕; 𐑯 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑤𐑳𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑦𐑙𐑦𐑙 𐑬𐑑 𐑓 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑑 𐑤𐑱𐑛𐑩𐑤 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑳𐑐; 𐑯 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑞 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑥𐑨𐑯'𐑟 𐑤𐑲𐑯—𐑯𐑬 𐑐𐑸𐑑𐑦𐑙—𐑩𐑛𐑥𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑫𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑰𐑥𐑦 𐑐𐑵𐑤 𐑑 𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑒𐑿 𐑣𐑵𐑥 𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑫𐑛;—𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑲𐑤𐑛 𐑕𐑦𐑥𐑩𐑤𐑑𐑱𐑯𐑾𐑕𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑩 𐑔𐑬𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑒𐑮𐑰𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑐𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑤𐑟,—·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚'𐑟 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑳𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑚𐑴𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑛𐑮𐑷𐑯 𐑳𐑐 𐑑𐑩𐑢𐑹𐑛𐑟 ·𐑣𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑚𐑲 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑦𐑟𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑲𐑼𐑟,—𐑨𐑟, 𐑨𐑮𐑴-𐑤𐑲𐑒, 𐑖𐑵𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑐𐑻𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑼𐑤𐑦 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑕𐑰, 𐑞 ·𐑢𐑲𐑑 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑛𐑨𐑖𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑮𐑷𐑛 𐑓𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑛 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑚𐑪𐑑𐑩𐑥, 𐑯 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑦𐑑, 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑯 𐑴𐑝𐑼, 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑺; 𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑦𐑑 𐑓𐑧𐑤 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯—𐑜𐑳𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑛𐑬𐑯𐑢𐑼𐑛𐑟—𐑯 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑜𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑬𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑦𐑑, 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑕𐑰𐑤𐑟 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑩 𐑕𐑰-𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑒𐑱𐑝.

𐑞 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑳𐑐𐑮𐑲𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑴𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑥 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤—𐑥𐑪𐑛𐑦𐑓𐑲𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑛𐑦𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑨𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑒 𐑞 𐑕𐑻𐑓𐑦𐑕—𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑪𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑺𐑦𐑤𐑦 𐑤𐑷𐑯𐑗𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑦𐑑, 𐑑 𐑩 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑼 𐑝 𐑞 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑥𐑱𐑛; 𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑨𐑒 𐑑 𐑦𐑑, 𐑣𐑰 𐑯𐑬 𐑤𐑱 𐑓 𐑩 𐑥𐑴𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑕𐑤𐑴𐑤𐑦 𐑓𐑰𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑤𐑵𐑒𐑕 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑑 𐑕𐑲𐑛; 𐑯 𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑩 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱 𐑹, 𐑚𐑦𐑑 𐑝 𐑐𐑤𐑨𐑙𐑒, 𐑞 𐑤𐑰𐑕𐑑 𐑗𐑦𐑐 𐑹 𐑒𐑮𐑳𐑥 𐑝 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕 𐑑𐑳𐑗𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑒𐑦𐑯, 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑑𐑱𐑤 𐑕𐑢𐑦𐑓𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑮𐑵 𐑚𐑨𐑒, 𐑯 𐑒𐑱𐑥 𐑕𐑲𐑛𐑢𐑱𐑟 𐑕𐑥𐑲𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑕𐑰. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑕𐑵𐑯, 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑓 𐑕𐑨𐑑𐑦𐑕𐑓𐑲𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑻𐑒 𐑓 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑛𐑳𐑯, 𐑣𐑰 𐑐𐑫𐑖𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑤𐑰𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑓𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑛 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑞 𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯, 𐑯 𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑑𐑨𐑙𐑜𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑤𐑲𐑯𐑟, 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑿𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑤𐑰𐑢𐑼𐑛 𐑢𐑱 𐑨𐑑 𐑩 𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑼'𐑟 𐑥𐑦𐑔𐑪𐑛𐑦𐑒 𐑐𐑱𐑕.

𐑨𐑟 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹, 𐑞 𐑩𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑝 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑣𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 𐑞 𐑣𐑴𐑤 𐑓𐑲𐑑, 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯 𐑒𐑱𐑥 𐑚𐑺𐑦𐑙 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑑 𐑞 𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑒𐑿, 𐑯 𐑛𐑮𐑪𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑚𐑴𐑑, 𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑑 𐑳𐑐 𐑞 𐑓𐑤𐑴𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑯𐑼𐑟, 𐑑𐑳𐑚𐑟, 𐑹𐑟, 𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑑𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑧𐑤𐑕 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑚𐑰 𐑒𐑷𐑑 𐑨𐑑, 𐑯 𐑕𐑱𐑓𐑤𐑦 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑻 𐑛𐑧𐑒𐑕. 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑛 𐑖𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑼𐑟, 𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑕, 𐑯 𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑟; 𐑤𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑛 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑿𐑠𐑩𐑯𐑟; 𐑮𐑧𐑯𐑗𐑑 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑟 𐑯 𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟; 𐑦𐑯𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑕𐑦𐑟 𐑝 𐑮𐑴𐑐; 𐑖𐑨𐑑𐑼𐑛 𐑹𐑟 𐑯 𐑐𐑤𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑕; 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑞𐑺; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑯𐑴 𐑓𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑹 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑕𐑽𐑾𐑕 𐑦𐑤 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑷𐑤𐑩𐑯 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑢𐑳𐑯. 𐑨𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑞 ·𐑓𐑧𐑛𐑩𐑤𐑩 𐑞 𐑛𐑱 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹, 𐑕𐑴 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑬 𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑜𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑤𐑦𐑙𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑴𐑑'𐑕 𐑚𐑮𐑴𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑣𐑭𐑓, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑩𐑓𐑹𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑩 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑨𐑮𐑩𐑑𐑦𐑝𐑤𐑦 𐑰𐑟𐑦 𐑓𐑤𐑴𐑑; 𐑯𐑹 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑴 𐑦𐑜𐑟𐑷𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑰𐑝𐑾𐑕 𐑛𐑱'𐑟 𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑣𐑨𐑐.

𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑐𐑑 𐑑 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑒, 𐑷𐑤 𐑲𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑓𐑭𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥; 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑛 𐑝 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑲 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑣𐑭𐑓-𐑣𐑳𐑙 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑖𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑼 𐑝 ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒, 𐑣𐑵 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑞𐑳𐑕 𐑓𐑸 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑹𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑑 𐑩𐑕𐑦𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥. 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑲𐑝𐑼𐑦 𐑤𐑧𐑜 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑕𐑯𐑨𐑐𐑑 𐑪𐑓, 𐑤𐑰𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑖𐑹𐑑 𐑖𐑸𐑐 𐑕𐑐𐑤𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼.

“𐑲, 𐑲, ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒, '𐑑𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑢𐑰𐑑 𐑑 𐑤𐑰𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟, 𐑚𐑰 𐑞 𐑤𐑰𐑯𐑼 𐑣𐑵 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑦𐑤; 𐑯 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑴𐑤𐑛 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑤𐑰𐑯𐑛 𐑪𐑓𐑩𐑯𐑼 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑟.”

“𐑞 𐑓𐑧𐑮𐑵𐑤 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑫𐑛, 𐑕𐑻,” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑞 𐑒𐑸𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑼, 𐑯𐑬 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑳𐑐; “𐑲 𐑐𐑫𐑑 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑢𐑻𐑒 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑧𐑜.”

“𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑯𐑴 𐑚𐑴𐑯𐑟 𐑚𐑮𐑴𐑒𐑩𐑯, 𐑕𐑻, 𐑲 𐑣𐑴𐑐,” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑑𐑮𐑵 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑻𐑯.

“𐑲! 𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑕𐑐𐑤𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑛 𐑑 𐑐𐑰𐑕𐑩𐑟, ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚!—𐑛'𐑘𐑰 𐑕𐑰 𐑦𐑑.—𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑚𐑮𐑴𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑚𐑴𐑯, 𐑴𐑤𐑛 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑦𐑟 𐑳𐑯𐑑𐑳𐑗𐑑; 𐑯 𐑲 𐑩𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑 𐑯𐑴 𐑤𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑴𐑯 𐑝 𐑥𐑲𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑡𐑪𐑑 𐑥𐑹 𐑥𐑰, 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑛𐑧𐑛 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑'𐑕 𐑤𐑪𐑕𐑑. 𐑯𐑹 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑯𐑹 𐑥𐑨𐑯, 𐑯𐑹 𐑓𐑰𐑯𐑛, 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑕𐑴 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑨𐑟 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑟 𐑴𐑤𐑛 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑴𐑯 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑐𐑼 𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑒𐑕𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙. 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑤𐑰𐑛 𐑑𐑳𐑗 𐑘𐑪𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑓𐑤𐑹, 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑱𐑐 𐑘𐑪𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑮𐑵𐑓?—𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑓𐑑 𐑞𐑺! 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑢𐑱?”

“𐑛𐑧𐑛 𐑑 𐑤𐑰𐑢𐑼𐑛, 𐑕𐑻.”

“𐑳𐑐 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑥, 𐑞𐑧𐑯; 𐑐𐑲𐑤 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑤 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯, 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑒𐑰𐑐𐑼𐑟! 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑞 𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑺 𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕 𐑯 𐑮𐑦𐑜 𐑞𐑧𐑥—·𐑥𐑼 ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒 𐑩𐑢𐑱, 𐑯 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑𐑼 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑'𐑕 𐑒𐑮𐑵𐑟.”

“𐑤𐑧𐑑 𐑥𐑰 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑐 𐑞𐑰 𐑑𐑩𐑢𐑹𐑛𐑟 𐑞 𐑚𐑫𐑤𐑢𐑼𐑒𐑕, 𐑕𐑻.”

“𐑴, 𐑴, 𐑴! 𐑣𐑬 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑕𐑐𐑤𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼 𐑜𐑹𐑟 𐑥𐑰 𐑯𐑬! 𐑩𐑒𐑻𐑕𐑩𐑛 𐑓𐑱𐑑! 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑳𐑯𐑒𐑪𐑙𐑒𐑼𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑴𐑤 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩 𐑒𐑮𐑱𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑥𐑱𐑑!”

“𐑕𐑻?”

“𐑥𐑲 𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦, 𐑥𐑨𐑯, 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑞𐑰. 𐑜𐑦𐑝 𐑥𐑰 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑓 𐑩 𐑒𐑱𐑯—𐑞𐑺, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑖𐑦𐑝𐑼𐑛 𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑕 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑛𐑵. 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑𐑼 𐑞 𐑥𐑧𐑯. 𐑖𐑫𐑼𐑤𐑦 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑘𐑧𐑑. 𐑚𐑲 𐑣𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑑 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑚𐑰!—𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑦𐑙?—𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑒! 𐑒𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑷𐑤.”

𐑞 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑥𐑨𐑯'𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑔𐑷𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑑𐑮𐑵. 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑦, 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑸𐑟𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑞𐑺.

“𐑞 ·𐑐𐑸𐑟𐑰!” 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚—“𐑣𐑰 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑒𐑷𐑑 𐑦𐑯——”

“𐑞 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑒 𐑝𐑪𐑥𐑦𐑑 𐑮𐑧𐑯𐑗 𐑞𐑰!—𐑮𐑳𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑝 𐑘𐑰 𐑩𐑚𐑳𐑝, 𐑱𐑤𐑴, 𐑒𐑨𐑚𐑦𐑯, 𐑓𐑴𐑒𐑕𐑩𐑤—𐑓𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥—𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑜𐑪𐑯—𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑜𐑪𐑯!”

𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑦 𐑞𐑱 𐑮𐑩𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑛 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑑𐑲𐑛𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑸𐑟𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑴𐑢𐑺 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛.

“𐑲, 𐑕𐑻,” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚—“𐑒𐑷𐑑 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑞 𐑑𐑨𐑙𐑜𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑝 𐑘𐑹 𐑤𐑲𐑯—𐑲 𐑔𐑷𐑑 𐑲 𐑕𐑷 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑛𐑮𐑨𐑜𐑦𐑙 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼.”

“𐑥𐑲 𐑤𐑲𐑯! 𐑥𐑲 𐑤𐑲𐑯? 𐑜𐑪𐑯?—𐑜𐑪𐑯? 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑥𐑰𐑯𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑻𐑛?—𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑛𐑧𐑔-𐑯𐑧𐑤 𐑮𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑦𐑑, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑴𐑤𐑛 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑖𐑱𐑒𐑕 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑓 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑻 𐑞 𐑚𐑧𐑤𐑓𐑮𐑦. 𐑞 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯, 𐑑𐑵!—𐑑𐑪𐑕 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑞 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑼 𐑞𐑺,—𐑛'𐑘𐑰 𐑕𐑰 𐑦𐑑?—𐑞 𐑓𐑹𐑡𐑛 𐑲𐑼𐑯, 𐑥𐑧𐑯, 𐑞 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑤'𐑟—𐑯𐑴, 𐑯𐑴, 𐑯𐑴,—𐑚𐑤𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑛 𐑓𐑵𐑤! 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑛𐑸𐑑 𐑦𐑑!—'𐑑𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑦𐑖!—𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑓𐑑 𐑞𐑺! 𐑒𐑰𐑐 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑯𐑱𐑤𐑛—·𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑒!—𐑷𐑤 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑑 𐑞 𐑮𐑦𐑜𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕—𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑧𐑒𐑑 𐑞 𐑹𐑟—𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑽𐑟! 𐑞 𐑲𐑼𐑯𐑟, 𐑞 𐑲𐑼𐑯𐑟!—𐑣𐑶𐑕𐑑 𐑞 𐑮𐑶𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑣𐑲𐑼—𐑩 𐑐𐑫𐑤 𐑪𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑖𐑰𐑑𐑕!—𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑥 𐑞𐑺! 𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑛𐑦, 𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑛𐑦 𐑓 𐑘𐑹 𐑤𐑲𐑓! 𐑲'𐑤 𐑑𐑧𐑯 𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑜𐑻𐑛𐑩𐑤 𐑞 𐑳𐑯𐑥𐑧𐑠𐑼𐑛 𐑜𐑤𐑴𐑚; 𐑘𐑱 𐑯 𐑛𐑲𐑝 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑦𐑑, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑲'𐑤 𐑕𐑤𐑱 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑘𐑧𐑑!”

“𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 ·𐑜𐑪𐑛! 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑓 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑕𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑖𐑴 𐑞𐑲𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓,” 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒; “𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼, 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑢𐑦𐑤𐑑 𐑞𐑬 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑗𐑼 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑥𐑨𐑯—𐑦𐑯 ·𐑡𐑰𐑟𐑩𐑕' 𐑯𐑱𐑥 𐑯𐑴 𐑥𐑹 𐑝 𐑞𐑦𐑕, 𐑞𐑨𐑑'𐑕 𐑢𐑻𐑕 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑛𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑤'𐑟 𐑥𐑨𐑛𐑯𐑩𐑕. 𐑑𐑵 𐑛𐑱𐑟 𐑗𐑱𐑕𐑑; 𐑑𐑢𐑲𐑕 𐑕𐑑𐑴𐑝 𐑑 𐑕𐑐𐑤𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑟; 𐑞𐑲 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑤𐑧𐑜 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑕 𐑥𐑹 𐑕𐑯𐑨𐑗𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑞𐑰; 𐑞𐑲 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑤 𐑖𐑨𐑛𐑴 𐑜𐑪𐑯—𐑷𐑤 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑥𐑪𐑚𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑰 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑢𐑹𐑯𐑦𐑙𐑟:—𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑥𐑹 𐑢𐑫𐑛𐑕𐑑 𐑞𐑬 𐑣𐑨𐑝?—𐑖𐑨𐑤 𐑢𐑰 𐑒𐑰𐑐 𐑗𐑱𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑥𐑻𐑛𐑼𐑩𐑕 𐑓𐑦𐑖 𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑢𐑪𐑥𐑐𐑕 𐑞 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑥𐑨𐑯? 𐑖𐑨𐑤 𐑢𐑰 𐑚𐑰 𐑛𐑮𐑨𐑜𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑑 𐑞 𐑚𐑪𐑑𐑩𐑥 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑰? 𐑖𐑨𐑤 𐑢𐑰 𐑚𐑰 𐑑𐑴𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑑 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑓𐑻𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛? 𐑴, 𐑴,—·𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑲𐑩𐑑𐑦 𐑯 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑕𐑓𐑩𐑥𐑦 𐑑 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑥𐑹!”

“𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒, 𐑝 𐑤𐑱𐑑 𐑲'𐑝 𐑓𐑧𐑤𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑤𐑦 𐑥𐑵𐑝𐑛 𐑑 𐑞𐑰; 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑕𐑦𐑯𐑕 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑬𐑼 𐑢𐑰 𐑚𐑴𐑔 𐑕𐑷—𐑞𐑬 𐑯𐑴'𐑕𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑑, 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑩𐑯𐑳𐑞𐑼'𐑟 𐑲𐑟. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑥𐑨𐑑𐑼 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑚𐑰 𐑞 𐑓𐑮𐑳𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑞𐑲 𐑓𐑱𐑕 𐑑 𐑥𐑰 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑐𐑭𐑥 𐑝 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛—𐑩 𐑤𐑦𐑐𐑤𐑩𐑕, 𐑳𐑯𐑓𐑰𐑗𐑼𐑛 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑙𐑒. 𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑦𐑟 𐑓 𐑧𐑝𐑼 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚, 𐑥𐑨𐑯. 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑣𐑴𐑤 𐑨𐑒𐑑'𐑕 𐑦𐑥𐑿𐑑𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑮𐑰𐑛. '𐑑𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑮𐑦𐑣𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑞𐑰 𐑯 𐑥𐑰 𐑩 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑾𐑯 𐑘𐑽𐑟 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑮𐑴𐑤𐑛. 𐑓𐑵𐑤! 𐑲 𐑨𐑥 𐑞 ·𐑓𐑱𐑑𐑕' 𐑤𐑧𐑓𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑩𐑯𐑑; 𐑲 𐑨𐑒𐑑 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑹𐑛𐑼𐑟. 𐑤𐑫𐑒 𐑞𐑬, 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑤𐑦𐑙! 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑬 𐑴𐑚𐑱𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑥𐑲𐑯.—𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑥𐑰, 𐑥𐑧𐑯. 𐑘𐑰 𐑕𐑰 𐑩𐑯 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑒𐑳𐑑 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑥𐑐; 𐑤𐑰𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑪𐑯 𐑩 𐑖𐑦𐑝𐑼𐑛 𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑕; 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑐𐑑 𐑳𐑐 𐑪𐑯 𐑩 𐑤𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑓𐑫𐑑. '𐑑𐑦𐑟 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚—𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦'𐑟 𐑐𐑸𐑑; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚'𐑟 𐑕𐑴𐑤'𐑟 𐑩 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑐𐑰𐑛, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑵𐑝𐑟 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑩 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑛 𐑤𐑧𐑜𐑟. 𐑲 𐑓𐑰𐑤 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑛, 𐑣𐑭𐑓 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛, 𐑨𐑟 𐑮𐑴𐑐𐑕 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑑𐑴 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑦𐑜𐑩𐑑𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑜𐑱𐑤; 𐑯 𐑲 𐑥𐑱 𐑤𐑫𐑒 𐑕𐑴. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑺 𐑲 𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑒, 𐑘𐑰'𐑤 𐑣𐑽 𐑥𐑰 𐑒𐑮𐑨𐑒; 𐑯 𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑘𐑰 𐑣𐑽 𐑞𐑨𐑑, 𐑯𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚'𐑟 𐑣𐑷𐑟𐑼 𐑑𐑴𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑻𐑐𐑩𐑕 𐑘𐑧𐑑. 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑰𐑝 𐑘𐑰, 𐑥𐑧𐑯, 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑛 𐑴𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑟? 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑤𐑭𐑓 𐑩𐑤𐑬𐑛, 𐑯 𐑒𐑮𐑲 𐑪𐑙𐑒𐑹! 𐑓 𐑺 𐑞𐑱 𐑛𐑮𐑬𐑯, 𐑛𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑑𐑢𐑲𐑕 𐑮𐑲𐑟 𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑻𐑓𐑦𐑕; 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑮𐑲𐑟 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯, 𐑑 𐑕𐑦𐑙𐑒 𐑓 𐑧𐑝𐑼𐑥𐑹. 𐑕𐑴 𐑢𐑦𐑞 ·𐑥𐑪𐑚𐑦 ·𐑛𐑦𐑒—𐑑𐑵 𐑛𐑱𐑟 𐑣𐑰'𐑟 𐑓𐑤𐑴𐑑𐑩𐑛—𐑑𐑩𐑥𐑪𐑮𐑴 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑚𐑰 𐑞 𐑔𐑻𐑛. 𐑲, 𐑥𐑧𐑯, 𐑣𐑰'𐑤 𐑮𐑲𐑟 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑕 𐑥𐑹,—𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑑 𐑕𐑐𐑬𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑! ·𐑛'𐑘𐑰 𐑓𐑰𐑤 𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑝 𐑥𐑧𐑯, 𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑝?”

“𐑨𐑟 𐑓𐑽𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑓𐑲𐑼,” 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚.

“𐑯 𐑨𐑟 𐑥𐑦𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤,” 𐑥𐑳𐑑𐑼𐑛 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚. 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑓𐑹𐑢𐑼𐑛, 𐑣𐑰 𐑥𐑳𐑑𐑼𐑛 𐑪𐑯: “𐑞 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑛 𐑴𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑟! 𐑯 𐑘𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑛𐑱 𐑲 𐑑𐑷𐑒𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑑 ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒 𐑞𐑺, 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑲 𐑚𐑮𐑴𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑚𐑴𐑑. 𐑴! 𐑣𐑬 𐑝𐑨𐑤𐑾𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑲 𐑕𐑰𐑒 𐑑 𐑛𐑮𐑲𐑝 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑳𐑞𐑼𐑟' 𐑣𐑸𐑑𐑕 𐑢𐑪𐑑'𐑕 𐑒𐑤𐑦𐑯𐑗𐑑 𐑕𐑴 𐑓𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑲𐑯!—𐑞 ·𐑐𐑸𐑟𐑰—𐑞 ·𐑐𐑸𐑟𐑰!—𐑜𐑪𐑯, 𐑜𐑪𐑯? 𐑯 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑑 𐑜𐑴 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹:—𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑕𐑰𐑯 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯 𐑺 𐑲 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑐𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑖—𐑣𐑬'𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑?—𐑞𐑺'𐑟 𐑩 𐑮𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑤 𐑯𐑬 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑚𐑨𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑤𐑷𐑘𐑼𐑟 𐑚𐑨𐑒𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑜𐑴𐑕𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑣𐑴𐑤 𐑤𐑲𐑯 𐑝 𐑡𐑳𐑡𐑩𐑟:—𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑣𐑷𐑒'𐑕 𐑚𐑰𐑒 𐑦𐑑 𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑕 𐑥𐑲 𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑯. 𐑲'𐑤, 𐑲'𐑤 𐑕𐑪𐑤𐑝 𐑦𐑑, 𐑞𐑴!”

𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑛𐑳𐑕𐑒 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛, 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑲𐑑 𐑑 𐑤𐑰𐑢𐑼𐑛.

𐑕𐑴 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑕 𐑥𐑹 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑤 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑖𐑹𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑛, 𐑯 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑐𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑯𐑽𐑤𐑦 𐑨𐑟 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑰𐑝𐑾𐑕 𐑯𐑲𐑑; 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦, 𐑞 𐑕𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑝 𐑣𐑨𐑥𐑼𐑟, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑣𐑳𐑥 𐑝 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑲𐑯𐑛𐑕𐑑𐑴𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑣𐑻𐑛 𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑯𐑽𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑱𐑤𐑲𐑑, 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑑𐑶𐑤𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑯𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑰𐑑 𐑯 𐑒𐑺𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑮𐑦𐑜𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑺 𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕 𐑯 𐑖𐑸𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑺 𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑖 𐑢𐑧𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑓 𐑞 𐑥𐑪𐑮𐑴. 𐑥𐑰𐑯𐑑𐑲𐑥, 𐑝 𐑞 𐑚𐑮𐑴𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑒𐑰𐑤 𐑝 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚'𐑟 𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑑 𐑒𐑮𐑭𐑓𐑑 𐑞 𐑒𐑸𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑼 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑩𐑯𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑤𐑧𐑜; 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑨𐑟 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑯𐑲𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹, 𐑕𐑤𐑬𐑗𐑑 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑕𐑑𐑫𐑛 𐑓𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑒𐑳𐑑𐑩𐑤; 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑛, 𐑣𐑰𐑤𐑾𐑑𐑮𐑴𐑐 𐑜𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑕 𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑕𐑦𐑐𐑱𐑑𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑜𐑪𐑯 𐑚𐑨𐑒𐑢𐑼𐑛 𐑪𐑯 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑛𐑲𐑩𐑤; 𐑕𐑨𐑑 𐑛𐑿 𐑰𐑕𐑑𐑢𐑼𐑛 𐑓 𐑞 𐑻𐑤𐑾𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑯.

·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 135. 𐑞 ·𐑗𐑱𐑕.—𐑔𐑻𐑛 𐑛𐑱.

𐑞 𐑥𐑹𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑞 𐑔𐑻𐑛 𐑛𐑱 𐑛𐑷𐑯𐑛 𐑓𐑺 𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑖, 𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑕 𐑥𐑹 𐑞 𐑕𐑪𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑼𐑦 𐑯𐑲𐑑-𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑓𐑹-𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑-𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑮𐑦𐑤𐑰𐑝𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑒𐑮𐑬𐑛𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑛𐑱𐑤𐑲𐑑 𐑤𐑫𐑒-𐑬𐑑𐑕, 𐑣𐑵 𐑛𐑪𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑯 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑕𐑐𐑸.

“·𐑛'𐑘𐑰 𐑕𐑰 𐑣𐑦𐑥?” 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑲𐑑.

“𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑓𐑨𐑤𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑱𐑒, 𐑞𐑴; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑓𐑪𐑤𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑒, 𐑞𐑨𐑑'𐑕 𐑷𐑤. 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑥 𐑞𐑺; 𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑛𐑦, 𐑨𐑟 𐑞𐑬 𐑜𐑴𐑩𐑕𐑑, 𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑜𐑴𐑦𐑙. 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑩 𐑤𐑳𐑝𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑱 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯! 𐑢𐑻 𐑦𐑑 𐑩 𐑯𐑿-𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛, 𐑯 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑓 𐑩 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑼-𐑣𐑬𐑕 𐑑 𐑞 𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑩𐑤𐑟, 𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑥𐑹𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑝 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑔𐑮𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑴𐑐𐑩𐑯 𐑑 𐑞𐑧𐑥, 𐑩 𐑓𐑺𐑼 𐑛𐑱 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑛𐑷𐑯 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛. 𐑣𐑽'𐑟 𐑓𐑵𐑛 𐑓 𐑔𐑷𐑑, 𐑣𐑨𐑛 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑑 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑕; 𐑣𐑰 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑓𐑰𐑤𐑟, 𐑓𐑰𐑤𐑟, 𐑓𐑰𐑤𐑟; 𐑞𐑨𐑑'𐑕 𐑑𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯𐑳𐑓 𐑓 𐑥𐑹𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑥𐑨𐑯! 𐑑 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒'𐑕 𐑷𐑛𐑨𐑕𐑦𐑑𐑦. 𐑜𐑪𐑛 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑮𐑲𐑑 𐑯 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑡. 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑟, 𐑹 𐑷𐑑 𐑑 𐑚𐑰, 𐑩 𐑒𐑵𐑤𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑯 𐑩 𐑒𐑭𐑥𐑯𐑩𐑕; 𐑯 𐑬𐑼 𐑐𐑫𐑼 𐑣𐑸𐑑𐑕 𐑔𐑮𐑪𐑚, 𐑯 𐑬𐑼 𐑐𐑫𐑼 𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑟 𐑚𐑰𐑑 𐑑𐑵 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑓 𐑞𐑨𐑑. 𐑯 𐑘𐑧𐑑, 𐑲'𐑝 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑔𐑷𐑑 𐑥𐑲 𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑒𐑭𐑥—𐑓𐑮𐑴𐑟𐑩𐑯 𐑒𐑭𐑥, 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑕𐑒𐑳𐑤 𐑒𐑮𐑨𐑒𐑕 𐑕𐑴, 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑜𐑤𐑭𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑞 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑛 𐑑 𐑲𐑕, 𐑯 𐑖𐑦𐑝𐑼 𐑦𐑑. 𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑣𐑺 𐑦𐑟 𐑜𐑮𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑯𐑬; 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑥𐑴𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑜𐑮𐑴𐑦𐑙, 𐑯 𐑣𐑰𐑑 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑮𐑰𐑛 𐑦𐑑; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑯𐑴, 𐑦𐑑'𐑕 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑹𐑑 𐑝 𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑜𐑮𐑭𐑕 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑜𐑮𐑴 𐑧𐑯𐑦𐑢𐑺, 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑢𐑰𐑯 𐑞 𐑻𐑔𐑦 𐑒𐑤𐑧𐑓𐑑𐑕 𐑝 ·𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑯𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑲𐑕 𐑹 𐑦𐑯 ·𐑝𐑧𐑕𐑵𐑝𐑾𐑕 𐑤𐑭𐑝𐑩. 𐑣𐑬 𐑞 𐑢𐑲𐑤𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑚𐑤𐑴 𐑦𐑑; 𐑞𐑱 𐑢𐑦𐑐 𐑦𐑑 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑥𐑰 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑑𐑹𐑯 𐑖𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑟 𐑝 𐑕𐑐𐑤𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑤𐑨𐑖 𐑞 𐑑𐑪𐑕𐑑 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑞𐑱 𐑒𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑑. 𐑩 𐑝𐑲𐑤 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑯𐑴 𐑛𐑬𐑑 𐑚𐑤𐑴𐑯 𐑺 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑩𐑯 𐑒𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑛𐑹𐑟 𐑯 𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑟, 𐑯 𐑢𐑹𐑛𐑟 𐑝 𐑣𐑪𐑕𐑐𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑟, 𐑯 𐑝𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑤𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑞𐑧𐑥, 𐑯 𐑯𐑬 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑟 𐑚𐑤𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑞𐑼 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑓𐑤𐑰𐑕𐑩𐑟. 𐑬𐑑 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑦𐑑!—𐑦𐑑'𐑕 𐑑𐑱𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛. 𐑢𐑻 𐑲 𐑞 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛, 𐑲'𐑛 𐑚𐑤𐑴 𐑯𐑴 𐑥𐑹 𐑪𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩 𐑢𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑛, 𐑥𐑦𐑟𐑼𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛. 𐑲'𐑛 𐑒𐑮𐑷𐑤 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑢𐑺 𐑑 𐑩 𐑒𐑱𐑝, 𐑯 𐑕𐑤𐑦𐑙𐑒 𐑞𐑺. 𐑯 𐑘𐑧𐑑, '𐑑𐑦𐑟 𐑩 𐑯𐑴𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑮𐑴𐑦𐑒 𐑔𐑦𐑙, 𐑞 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛! 𐑣𐑵 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑒𐑪𐑙𐑒𐑼𐑛 𐑦𐑑? 𐑦𐑯 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑓𐑲𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑯 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑼𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑤𐑴. 𐑮𐑳𐑯 𐑑𐑦𐑤𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑑, 𐑯 𐑿 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑮𐑳𐑯 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑦𐑑. 𐑣𐑭! 𐑩 𐑒𐑬𐑼𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑒𐑕 𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑒 𐑯𐑱𐑒𐑩𐑛 𐑥𐑧𐑯, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑰𐑝 𐑩 𐑕𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑩𐑤 𐑚𐑤𐑴. 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑦𐑟 𐑩 𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑝𐑼 𐑔𐑦𐑙—𐑩 𐑯𐑴𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑼 𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑. 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑯𐑬 𐑞 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑩 𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑜𐑟𐑨𐑕𐑐𐑼𐑱𐑑 𐑯 𐑬𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑡 𐑥𐑹𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑥𐑨𐑯, 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑸 𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑩𐑕, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑨𐑟 𐑪𐑚𐑡𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑕, 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑱𐑡𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕. 𐑞𐑺'𐑟 𐑩 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑤, 𐑩 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑒𐑳𐑯𐑦𐑙, 𐑴, 𐑩 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑥𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑕 𐑛𐑦𐑓𐑼𐑩𐑯𐑕! 𐑯 𐑘𐑧𐑑, 𐑲 𐑕𐑱 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯, 𐑯 𐑕𐑢𐑺 𐑦𐑑 𐑯𐑬, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑺'𐑟 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑷𐑤 𐑜𐑤𐑹𐑾𐑕 𐑯 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛. 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑢𐑹𐑥 ·𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑛 ·𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑟, 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑰𐑕𐑑, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑒𐑤𐑽 𐑣𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑚𐑤𐑴 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑪𐑯, 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑪𐑙 𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑛𐑓𐑭𐑕𐑑, 𐑝𐑦𐑜𐑼𐑩𐑕 𐑥𐑲𐑤𐑛𐑯𐑩𐑕; 𐑯 𐑝𐑽 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞𐑺 𐑥𐑸𐑒, 𐑣𐑬𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑞 𐑚𐑱𐑕𐑼 𐑒𐑳𐑮𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑰 𐑥𐑱 𐑑𐑻𐑯 𐑯 𐑑𐑨𐑒, 𐑯 𐑥𐑲𐑑𐑾𐑕𐑑 ·𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑦𐑕𐑦𐑐𐑦𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑕𐑢𐑦𐑓𐑑 𐑯 𐑕𐑢𐑻𐑝 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑, 𐑳𐑯𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑺 𐑑 𐑜𐑴 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑. 𐑯 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑦𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑩𐑤 ·𐑐𐑴𐑤𐑟! 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑕𐑱𐑥 ·𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑛𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑴 𐑛𐑦𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑤𐑴 𐑥𐑲 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑪𐑯; 𐑞𐑰𐑟 ·𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑛𐑟, 𐑹 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑞𐑧𐑥—𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑴 𐑳𐑯𐑗𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤, 𐑯 𐑓𐑫𐑤 𐑨𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑪𐑙, 𐑚𐑤𐑴 𐑥𐑲 𐑒𐑰𐑤𐑛 𐑕𐑴𐑤 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑙! 𐑑 𐑦𐑑! 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑓𐑑 𐑞𐑺! 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑛'𐑘𐑰 𐑕𐑰?”

“𐑯𐑳𐑔𐑦𐑙, 𐑕𐑻.”

“𐑯𐑳𐑔𐑦𐑙! 𐑯 𐑯𐑵𐑯 𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛! 𐑞 𐑛𐑳𐑚𐑤𐑵𐑯 𐑜𐑴𐑟 𐑩-𐑚𐑧𐑜𐑦𐑙! 𐑕𐑰 𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑯! 𐑲, 𐑲, 𐑦𐑑 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑕𐑴. 𐑲'𐑝 𐑴𐑝𐑼𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥. 𐑣𐑬, 𐑜𐑪𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑑? 𐑲, 𐑣𐑰'𐑟 𐑗𐑱𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑰 𐑯𐑬; 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑲, 𐑣𐑦𐑥—𐑞𐑨𐑑'𐑕 𐑚𐑨𐑛; 𐑲 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑯𐑴𐑯 𐑦𐑑, 𐑑𐑵. 𐑓𐑵𐑤! 𐑞 𐑤𐑲𐑯𐑟—𐑞 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑟 𐑣𐑰'𐑟 𐑑𐑴𐑦𐑙. 𐑲, 𐑲, 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑮𐑳𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑚𐑲 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑯𐑲𐑑. 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑! 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑! 𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑛𐑬𐑯, 𐑷𐑤 𐑝 𐑘𐑰, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞 𐑮𐑧𐑜𐑿𐑤𐑼 𐑤𐑫𐑒 𐑬𐑑𐑕! 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑕𐑩𐑟!”

𐑕𐑑𐑽𐑦𐑙 𐑨𐑟 𐑖𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑛𐑳𐑯, 𐑞 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛'𐑟 𐑒𐑢𐑹𐑑𐑼, 𐑕𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑯𐑬 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑐𐑶𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑮𐑦𐑝𐑻𐑕 𐑛𐑦𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯, 𐑞 𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑕𐑑 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑛 𐑣𐑸𐑛 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑮𐑰𐑟 𐑨𐑟 𐑖𐑰 𐑮𐑰𐑗𐑻𐑯𐑛 𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑰𐑥 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑻 𐑴𐑯 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑒.

“𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑞 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛 𐑣𐑰 𐑯𐑬 𐑕𐑑𐑽𐑟 𐑓 𐑞 𐑴𐑐𐑩𐑯 𐑡𐑷,” 𐑥𐑻𐑥𐑼𐑛 ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓, 𐑨𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑶𐑤𐑛 𐑞 𐑯𐑿-𐑣𐑷𐑤𐑛 𐑥𐑱𐑯-𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑕 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑮𐑱𐑤. “𐑜𐑪𐑛 𐑒𐑰𐑐 𐑳𐑕, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑷𐑤𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑦 𐑥𐑲 𐑚𐑴𐑯𐑟 𐑓𐑰𐑤 𐑛𐑨𐑥𐑐 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑰, 𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑢𐑧𐑑 𐑥𐑲 𐑓𐑤𐑧𐑖. 𐑲 𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑛𐑬𐑑 𐑥𐑰 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑲 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑴𐑚𐑱 𐑥𐑲 ·𐑜𐑪𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑴𐑚𐑱𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑥!”

“𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑑 𐑕𐑢𐑱 𐑥𐑰 𐑳𐑐!” 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚, 𐑩𐑛𐑝𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑞 𐑣𐑧𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑯 𐑚𐑭𐑕𐑒𐑩𐑑. “𐑢𐑰 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑥𐑰𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑕𐑵𐑯.”

“𐑲, 𐑲, 𐑕𐑻,” 𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑑𐑢𐑱 ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒 𐑛𐑦𐑛 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚'𐑟 𐑚𐑦𐑛𐑦𐑙, 𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑕 𐑥𐑹 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑕𐑢𐑳𐑙 𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑲.

𐑩 𐑣𐑴𐑤 𐑬𐑼 𐑯𐑬 𐑐𐑭𐑕𐑑; 𐑜𐑴𐑤𐑛-𐑚𐑰𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑬𐑑 𐑑 𐑱𐑡𐑩𐑟. 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑦𐑑𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑯𐑬 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑛 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑚𐑮𐑧𐑔𐑕 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑒𐑰𐑯 𐑕𐑩𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑕. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑, 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑐𐑶𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑪𐑓 𐑞 𐑢𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑚𐑬, ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑬𐑑 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯, 𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑-𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑟 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑖𐑮𐑰𐑒𐑕 𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑳𐑐 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑓 𐑞 𐑑𐑳𐑙𐑟 𐑝 𐑓𐑲𐑼 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑝𐑶𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑑.

“𐑓𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑛 𐑑 𐑓𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑛 𐑲 𐑥𐑰𐑑 𐑞𐑰, 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑔𐑻𐑛 𐑑𐑲𐑥, ·𐑥𐑪𐑚𐑦 ·𐑛𐑦𐑒! 𐑪𐑯 𐑛𐑧𐑒 𐑞𐑺!—𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑕 𐑖𐑸𐑐𐑼 𐑳𐑐; 𐑒𐑮𐑬𐑛 𐑣𐑻 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛'𐑟 𐑲. 𐑣𐑰'𐑟 𐑑𐑵 𐑓𐑸 𐑪𐑓 𐑑 𐑤𐑴𐑼 𐑘𐑧𐑑, ·𐑥𐑼 ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒. 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑖𐑱𐑒! 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑥𐑟𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑑𐑪𐑐-𐑥𐑷𐑤! 𐑕𐑴, 𐑕𐑴; 𐑣𐑰 𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑓𐑭𐑕𐑑, 𐑯 𐑲 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑛𐑬𐑯. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑤𐑧𐑑 𐑥𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑥𐑹 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑤𐑫𐑒 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑓𐑑 𐑣𐑽 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑰; 𐑞𐑺'𐑟 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑓 𐑞𐑨𐑑. 𐑩𐑯 𐑴𐑤𐑛, 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑕𐑲𐑑, 𐑯 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑣𐑬 𐑕𐑴 𐑘𐑳𐑙; 𐑲, 𐑯 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑗𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑛 𐑩 𐑢𐑦𐑙𐑒 𐑕𐑦𐑯𐑕 𐑲 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑷 𐑦𐑑, 𐑩 𐑚𐑶, 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑕𐑨𐑯𐑛-𐑣𐑦𐑤𐑟 𐑝 ·𐑯𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑑! 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥!—𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥!—𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑑 ·𐑯𐑴𐑩 𐑨𐑟 𐑑 𐑥𐑰. 𐑞𐑺'𐑟 𐑩 𐑕𐑪𐑓𐑑 𐑖𐑬𐑼 𐑑 𐑤𐑰𐑢𐑼𐑛. 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑤𐑳𐑝𐑤𐑦 𐑤𐑰𐑢𐑼𐑛𐑦𐑙𐑟! 𐑞𐑱 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑤𐑰𐑛 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑢𐑺—𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑧𐑤𐑕 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛, 𐑥𐑹 𐑐𐑭𐑥𐑦 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑞 𐑐𐑭𐑥𐑟. 𐑤𐑰𐑢𐑼𐑛! 𐑞 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑜𐑴𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑱; 𐑤𐑫𐑒 𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑢𐑼𐑛, 𐑞𐑧𐑯; 𐑞 𐑚𐑧𐑑𐑼 𐑦𐑓 𐑞 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑼𐑼 𐑒𐑢𐑹𐑑𐑼. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑚𐑲, 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑚𐑲, 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑-𐑣𐑧𐑛! 𐑢𐑪𐑑'𐑕 𐑞𐑦𐑕?—𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑯? 𐑲, 𐑑𐑲𐑯𐑦 𐑥𐑪𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑢𐑹𐑐𐑑 𐑒𐑮𐑨𐑒𐑕. 𐑯𐑴 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑯 𐑢𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑯𐑟 𐑪𐑯 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚'𐑟 𐑣𐑧𐑛! 𐑞𐑺'𐑟 𐑞 𐑛𐑦𐑓𐑼𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑯𐑬 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑢𐑰𐑯 𐑥𐑨𐑯'𐑟 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑱𐑡 𐑯 𐑥𐑨𐑑𐑼'𐑟. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑲, 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑, 𐑢𐑰 𐑚𐑴𐑔 𐑜𐑮𐑴 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑑𐑩𐑜𐑧𐑞𐑼; 𐑕𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑬𐑼 𐑣𐑳𐑤𐑟, 𐑞𐑴, 𐑸 𐑢𐑰 𐑯𐑪𐑑, 𐑥𐑲 𐑖𐑦𐑐? 𐑲, 𐑥𐑲𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑩 𐑤𐑧𐑜, 𐑞𐑨𐑑'𐑕 𐑷𐑤. 𐑚𐑲 𐑣𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑛𐑧𐑛 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑚𐑧𐑑𐑼 𐑝 𐑥𐑲 𐑤𐑲𐑝 𐑓𐑤𐑧𐑖 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑢𐑱. 𐑲 𐑒𐑭𐑯𐑑 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑺 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑦𐑑; 𐑯 𐑲'𐑝 𐑯𐑴𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑕 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑝 𐑛𐑧𐑛 𐑑𐑮𐑰𐑟 𐑬𐑑𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑞 𐑤𐑲𐑝𐑟 𐑝 𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑝 𐑞 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑝𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑓 𐑝 𐑝𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑓𐑭𐑞𐑼𐑟. 𐑢𐑪𐑑'𐑕 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑧𐑛? 𐑣𐑰 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑜𐑴 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑥𐑰, 𐑥𐑲 𐑐𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑑; 𐑯 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑕𐑰𐑯 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯? 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑺? 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑲𐑟 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑚𐑪𐑑𐑩𐑥 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑰, 𐑕𐑩𐑐𐑴𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑲 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑕𐑑𐑺𐑟? 𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑯𐑲𐑑 𐑲'𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑢𐑺𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑣𐑰 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑕𐑦𐑙𐑒 𐑑. 𐑲, 𐑲, 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑥𐑹 𐑞𐑬 𐑑𐑴𐑤𐑛'𐑕𐑑 𐑛𐑲𐑼𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑑𐑮𐑵𐑔 𐑨𐑟 𐑑𐑳𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑲𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓, 𐑴 ·𐑐𐑸𐑟𐑰; 𐑚𐑳𐑑, ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚, 𐑞𐑺 𐑞𐑲 𐑖𐑪𐑑 𐑓𐑧𐑤 𐑖𐑹𐑑. 𐑜𐑫𐑛-𐑚𐑲, 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑-𐑣𐑧𐑛—𐑒𐑰𐑐 𐑩 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑲 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑞 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑲'𐑥 𐑜𐑪𐑯. 𐑢𐑰'𐑤 𐑑𐑷𐑒 𐑑-𐑥𐑪𐑮𐑴, 𐑯𐑱, 𐑑-𐑯𐑲𐑑, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑤𐑲𐑟 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑞𐑺, 𐑑𐑲𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑯 𐑑𐑱𐑤.”

𐑣𐑰 𐑜𐑱𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑻𐑛; 𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑜𐑱𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑦 𐑤𐑴𐑼𐑛 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑞 𐑒𐑤𐑴𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑚𐑤𐑵 𐑺 𐑑 𐑞 𐑛𐑧𐑒.

𐑦𐑯 𐑛𐑿 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕 𐑢𐑻 𐑤𐑴𐑼𐑛; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑖𐑨𐑤𐑪𐑐'𐑕 𐑕𐑑𐑻𐑯, ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑡𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑪𐑝𐑼𐑛 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑐𐑶𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑑, 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑱𐑝𐑛 𐑑 𐑞 𐑥𐑱𐑑,—𐑣𐑵 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑛 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑑𐑨𐑒𐑩𐑤-𐑮𐑴𐑐𐑕 𐑪𐑯 𐑛𐑧𐑒—𐑯 𐑚𐑨𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑐𐑷𐑟.

“𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒!”

“𐑕𐑻?”

“𐑓 𐑞 𐑔𐑻𐑛 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑥𐑲 𐑕𐑴𐑤'𐑟 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑑𐑕 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑝𐑶𐑦𐑡, ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒.”

“𐑲, 𐑕𐑻, 𐑞𐑬 𐑢𐑦𐑤𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑴.”

“𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑕 𐑕𐑱𐑤 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞𐑺 𐑐𐑹𐑑𐑕, 𐑯 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼𐑢𐑼𐑛𐑟 𐑸 𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑦𐑙, ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒!”

“𐑑𐑮𐑵𐑔, 𐑕𐑻: 𐑕𐑨𐑛𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑑𐑮𐑵𐑔.”

“𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑛𐑲 𐑨𐑑 𐑧𐑚 𐑑𐑲𐑛; 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑴 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼; 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑓𐑫𐑤 𐑝 𐑞 𐑓𐑤𐑳𐑛;—𐑯 𐑲 𐑓𐑰𐑤 𐑯𐑬 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑'𐑕 𐑷𐑤 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑒𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑒𐑴𐑥, ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒. 𐑲 𐑨𐑥 𐑴𐑤𐑛;—𐑖𐑱𐑒 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑥𐑰, 𐑥𐑨𐑯.”

𐑞𐑺 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑥𐑧𐑑; 𐑞𐑺 𐑲𐑟 𐑓𐑭𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑛; ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒'𐑕 𐑑𐑺𐑟 𐑞 𐑜𐑤𐑵.

“𐑴, 𐑥𐑲 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯, 𐑥𐑲 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯!—𐑯𐑴𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑣𐑸𐑑—𐑜𐑴 𐑯𐑪𐑑—𐑜𐑴 𐑯𐑪𐑑!—𐑕𐑰, 𐑦𐑑'𐑕 𐑩 𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑝 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑰𐑐𐑕; 𐑣𐑬 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑞 𐑨𐑜𐑩𐑯𐑦 𐑝 𐑞 𐑐𐑼𐑕𐑢𐑱𐑠𐑩𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯!”

“𐑤𐑴𐑼 𐑩𐑢𐑱!”—𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚, 𐑑𐑪𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑥𐑱𐑑'𐑕 𐑸𐑥 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑣𐑦𐑥. “𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑵!”

𐑦𐑯 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑐𐑫𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑒𐑤𐑴𐑕 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑻𐑯.

“𐑞 𐑖𐑸𐑒𐑕! 𐑞 𐑖𐑸𐑒𐑕!” 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 𐑩 𐑝𐑶𐑕 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑤𐑴 𐑒𐑨𐑚𐑦𐑯-𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑴 𐑞𐑺; “𐑴 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑼, 𐑥𐑲 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑼, 𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑚𐑨𐑒!”

𐑚𐑳𐑑 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑣𐑻𐑛 𐑯𐑳𐑔𐑦𐑙; 𐑓 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑴𐑯 𐑝𐑶𐑕 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑣𐑲-𐑤𐑦𐑓𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑞𐑧𐑯; 𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑 𐑤𐑰𐑐𐑑 𐑪𐑯.

𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑞 𐑝𐑶𐑕 𐑕𐑐𐑱𐑒 𐑑𐑮𐑵; 𐑓 𐑕𐑒𐑺𐑕 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑣𐑰 𐑐𐑫𐑖𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑯𐑳𐑥𐑚𐑼𐑟 𐑝 𐑖𐑸𐑒𐑕, 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑲𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑬𐑑 𐑞 𐑛𐑸𐑒 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼𐑟 𐑚𐑦𐑯𐑰𐑔 𐑞 𐑣𐑳𐑤, 𐑥𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑯𐑨𐑐𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑚𐑤𐑱𐑛𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑹𐑟, 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑞𐑱 𐑛𐑦𐑐𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼; 𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑱 𐑩𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑛 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞𐑺 𐑚𐑲𐑑𐑕. 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑩 𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑳𐑯𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤-𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑕𐑢𐑹𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑰𐑟; 𐑞 𐑖𐑸𐑒𐑕 𐑨𐑑 𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑩𐑐𐑨𐑮𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑓𐑪𐑤𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑾𐑯𐑑 𐑢𐑱 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑝𐑳𐑤𐑗𐑼𐑟 𐑣𐑪𐑝𐑼 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑞 𐑚𐑨𐑯𐑼𐑟 𐑝 𐑥𐑸𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑮𐑧𐑡𐑦𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑰𐑕𐑑. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑞 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑖𐑸𐑒𐑕 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑩𐑚𐑟𐑻𐑝𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛 𐑕𐑦𐑯𐑕 𐑞 ·𐑢𐑲𐑑 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛; 𐑯 𐑢𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚'𐑟 𐑒𐑮𐑵 𐑢𐑻 𐑷𐑤 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑑𐑲𐑜𐑼-𐑘𐑧𐑤𐑴 𐑚𐑸𐑚𐑼𐑾𐑯𐑟, 𐑯 𐑞𐑺𐑓𐑹 𐑞𐑺 𐑓𐑤𐑧𐑖 𐑥𐑹 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑒𐑦 𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑖𐑸𐑒𐑕—𐑩 𐑥𐑨𐑑𐑼 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑢𐑧𐑤 𐑯𐑴𐑯 𐑑 𐑩𐑓𐑧𐑒𐑑 𐑞𐑧𐑥,—𐑣𐑬𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟, 𐑞𐑱 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑑 𐑓𐑪𐑤𐑴 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑚𐑴𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑 𐑥𐑩𐑤𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑳𐑞𐑼𐑟.

“𐑣𐑸𐑑 𐑝 𐑮𐑷𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑰𐑤!” 𐑥𐑻𐑥𐑼𐑛 ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒 𐑜𐑱𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑞 𐑕𐑲𐑛, 𐑯 𐑓𐑪𐑤𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑲𐑟 𐑞 𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑰𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑴𐑑—“𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑞𐑬 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑲𐑑?—𐑤𐑴𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑲 𐑒𐑰𐑤 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑮𐑨𐑝𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑖𐑸𐑒𐑕, 𐑯 𐑓𐑪𐑤𐑴𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑞𐑧𐑥, 𐑴𐑐𐑩𐑯-𐑥𐑬𐑞𐑛 𐑑 𐑞 𐑗𐑱𐑕; 𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑔𐑻𐑛 𐑛𐑱?—𐑓 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑛𐑱𐑟 𐑓𐑤𐑴 𐑑𐑩𐑜𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑿𐑩𐑕 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑕 𐑐𐑼𐑕𐑿𐑑; 𐑚𐑰 𐑖𐑫𐑼 𐑞 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑞 𐑥𐑹𐑯𐑦𐑙, 𐑞 𐑕𐑧𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑞 𐑯𐑵𐑯, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑔𐑻𐑛 𐑞 𐑰𐑝𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑯 𐑞 𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑔𐑦𐑙—𐑚𐑰 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑥𐑱. 𐑴! 𐑥𐑲 ·𐑜𐑪𐑛! 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑖𐑵𐑑𐑕 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑥𐑰, 𐑯 𐑤𐑰𐑝𐑟 𐑥𐑰 𐑕𐑴 𐑛𐑧𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑭𐑥, 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑,—𐑓𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑑𐑪𐑐 𐑝 𐑩 𐑖𐑳𐑛𐑼! 𐑓𐑿𐑗𐑼 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑕𐑢𐑦𐑥 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑥𐑰, 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑧𐑥𐑐𐑑𐑦 𐑬𐑑𐑤𐑲𐑯𐑟 𐑯 𐑕𐑒𐑧𐑤𐑩𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑟; 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑐𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑣𐑬 𐑜𐑮𐑴𐑯 𐑛𐑦𐑥. 𐑥𐑺𐑦, 𐑜𐑻𐑤! 𐑞𐑬 𐑓𐑱𐑛𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑐𐑱𐑤 𐑜𐑤𐑹𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑦𐑣𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑥𐑰; 𐑚𐑶! 𐑲 𐑕𐑰𐑥 𐑑 𐑕𐑰 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞𐑲 𐑲𐑟 𐑜𐑮𐑴𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑕 𐑚𐑤𐑵. 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑚𐑤𐑩𐑥𐑟 𐑝 𐑤𐑲𐑓 𐑕𐑰𐑥 𐑒𐑤𐑽𐑦𐑙; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑒𐑤𐑬𐑛𐑟 𐑕𐑢𐑰𐑐 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑢𐑰𐑯—𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑲 𐑡𐑻𐑯𐑦'𐑟 𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑦𐑙? 𐑥𐑲 𐑤𐑧𐑜𐑟 𐑓𐑰𐑤 𐑓𐑱𐑯𐑑; 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑵 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑓𐑫𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑛𐑱. 𐑓𐑰𐑤 𐑞𐑲 𐑣𐑸𐑑,—𐑚𐑰𐑑𐑕 𐑦𐑑 𐑘𐑧𐑑? 𐑕𐑑𐑻 𐑞𐑲𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓, ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒!—𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑝 𐑦𐑑 𐑪𐑓—𐑥𐑵𐑝, 𐑥𐑵𐑝! 𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑒 𐑩𐑤𐑬𐑛!—𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑-𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑞𐑺! 𐑕𐑰 𐑘𐑰 𐑥𐑲 𐑚𐑶'𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑤?—𐑒𐑮𐑱𐑟𐑛;—𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑓𐑑 𐑞𐑺!—𐑒𐑰𐑐 𐑞𐑲 𐑒𐑰𐑯𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑲 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕:—𐑥𐑸𐑒 𐑢𐑧𐑤 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤!—𐑣𐑴! 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯!—𐑛𐑮𐑲𐑝 𐑪𐑓 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑷𐑒! 𐑕𐑰! 𐑣𐑰 𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑕—𐑣𐑰 𐑑𐑺𐑟 𐑞 𐑝𐑱𐑯”—𐑐𐑶𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑞 𐑮𐑧𐑛 𐑓𐑤𐑨𐑜 𐑓𐑤𐑲𐑦𐑙 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑥𐑱𐑯-𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑒—“𐑣𐑭! 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑹𐑟 𐑩𐑢𐑱 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑦𐑑!—𐑢𐑺'𐑟 𐑞 𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑯𐑬? 𐑕𐑰'𐑕𐑑 𐑞𐑬 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑲𐑑, 𐑴 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚!—𐑖𐑳𐑛𐑼, 𐑖𐑳𐑛𐑼!”

𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑜𐑪𐑯 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑓𐑸, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑚𐑲 𐑩 𐑕𐑦𐑜𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑-𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑟—𐑩 𐑛𐑬𐑯𐑢𐑼𐑛 𐑐𐑶𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑸𐑥, ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑯𐑿 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑕𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑯𐑽 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑯𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑 𐑮𐑲𐑟𐑦𐑙, 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑛 𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑱 𐑩 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑲𐑛𐑢𐑱𐑟 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑝𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑤; 𐑞 𐑚𐑦𐑗𐑸𐑥𐑛 𐑒𐑮𐑵 𐑥𐑱𐑯𐑑𐑱𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑕, 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑣𐑧𐑛-𐑚𐑰𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑝𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑥𐑼𐑛 𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑥𐑼𐑛 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑞 𐑩𐑐𐑴𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑬.

“𐑛𐑮𐑲𐑝, 𐑛𐑮𐑲𐑝 𐑦𐑯 𐑘𐑹 𐑯𐑱𐑤𐑟, 𐑴 𐑘𐑰 𐑢𐑱𐑝𐑟! 𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑳𐑑𐑼𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑟 𐑛𐑮𐑲𐑝 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑦𐑯! 𐑘𐑰 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑 𐑩 𐑤𐑦𐑛; 𐑯 𐑯𐑴 𐑒𐑪𐑓𐑦𐑯 𐑯 𐑯𐑴 𐑣𐑻𐑕 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑚𐑰 𐑥𐑲𐑯:—𐑯 𐑣𐑧𐑥𐑐 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑒𐑦𐑤 𐑥𐑰! 𐑣𐑭! 𐑣𐑭!”

𐑕𐑳𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑞 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼𐑟 𐑼𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑕𐑤𐑴𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑢𐑧𐑤𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑚𐑮𐑷𐑛 𐑕𐑻𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑟; 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑦 𐑳𐑐𐑣𐑰𐑝𐑛, 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑓 𐑕𐑲𐑛𐑢𐑱𐑟 𐑕𐑤𐑲𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑩 𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑥𐑻𐑡𐑛 𐑚𐑻𐑜 𐑝 𐑲𐑕, 𐑕𐑢𐑦𐑓𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑲𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑻𐑓𐑦𐑕. 𐑩 𐑤𐑴 𐑮𐑳𐑥𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑣𐑻𐑛; 𐑩 𐑕𐑳𐑚𐑑𐑼𐑱𐑯𐑾𐑕 𐑣𐑳𐑥; 𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑛 𐑞𐑺 𐑚𐑮𐑧𐑔𐑕; 𐑨𐑟 𐑚𐑦𐑛𐑮𐑨𐑜𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑮𐑴𐑐𐑕, 𐑯 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑟, 𐑯 𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟, 𐑩 𐑝𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑓𐑹𐑥 𐑖𐑪𐑑 𐑤𐑧𐑙𐑔𐑢𐑲𐑟, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑴𐑚𐑤𐑰𐑒𐑤𐑦 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑕𐑰. 𐑖𐑮𐑬𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑔𐑦𐑯 𐑛𐑮𐑵𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑝𐑱𐑤 𐑝 𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑑, 𐑦𐑑 𐑣𐑪𐑝𐑼𐑛 𐑓 𐑩 𐑥𐑴𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑚𐑴𐑛 𐑺; 𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑓𐑧𐑤 𐑕𐑢𐑪𐑥𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑨𐑒 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑛𐑰𐑐. 𐑒𐑮𐑳𐑖𐑑 𐑔𐑻𐑑𐑦 𐑓𐑰𐑑 𐑳𐑐𐑢𐑼𐑛𐑟, 𐑞 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼𐑟 𐑓𐑤𐑨𐑖𐑑 𐑓 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑣𐑰𐑐𐑕 𐑝 𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑟, 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑚𐑮𐑴𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑨𐑙𐑒 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑖𐑬𐑼 𐑝 𐑓𐑤𐑱𐑒𐑕, 𐑤𐑰𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑕𐑻𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑻𐑓𐑦𐑕 𐑒𐑮𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑯𐑿 𐑥𐑦𐑤𐑒 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑞 𐑥𐑸𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑙𐑒 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤.

“𐑜𐑦𐑝 𐑢𐑱!” 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑑 𐑞 𐑹𐑟𐑥𐑧𐑯, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕 𐑛𐑸𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑓𐑹𐑢𐑼𐑛 𐑑 𐑞 𐑩𐑑𐑨𐑒; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑥𐑨𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑘𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑛𐑱'𐑟 𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑖 𐑲𐑼𐑯𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑒𐑼𐑴𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥, ·𐑥𐑪𐑚𐑦 ·𐑛𐑦𐑒 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑚𐑲𐑯𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑩𐑟𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑓𐑧𐑤 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑣𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑯. 𐑞 𐑢𐑲𐑛 𐑑𐑽𐑟 𐑝 𐑢𐑧𐑤𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑴𐑝𐑼𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑮𐑷𐑛 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑓𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑛, 𐑚𐑦𐑯𐑰𐑔 𐑞 𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑕𐑐𐑨𐑮𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑕𐑒𐑦𐑯, 𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑑 𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑑𐑩𐑜𐑧𐑞𐑼; 𐑨𐑟 𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑪𐑯, 𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑱𐑥 𐑗𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑑𐑱𐑤 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕; 𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑕 𐑥𐑹 𐑓𐑤𐑱𐑤𐑛 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑩𐑐𐑸𐑑; 𐑕𐑐𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑬𐑑 𐑞 𐑲𐑼𐑯𐑟 𐑯 𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑑𐑵 𐑥𐑱𐑑𐑕' 𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕, 𐑯 𐑛𐑨𐑖𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑝 𐑞 𐑳𐑐𐑼 𐑐𐑸𐑑 𐑝 𐑞𐑺 𐑚𐑬𐑟, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑤𐑰𐑝𐑦𐑙 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚'𐑟 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑 𐑩 𐑕𐑒𐑸.

𐑢𐑲𐑤 ·𐑛𐑨𐑜𐑵 𐑯 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜 𐑢𐑻 𐑕𐑑𐑪𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑛 𐑐𐑤𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑕; 𐑯 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑕𐑢𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑬𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞𐑧𐑥, 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑛, 𐑯 𐑖𐑴𐑛 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑲𐑼 𐑓𐑤𐑨𐑙𐑒 𐑨𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑖𐑪𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯; 𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑴𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑩 𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑒 𐑒𐑮𐑲 𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑳𐑐. 𐑤𐑨𐑖𐑑 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑯 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑑 𐑞 𐑓𐑦𐑖'𐑩𐑟 𐑚𐑨𐑒; 𐑐𐑦𐑯𐑘𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑟 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑗, 𐑛𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑐𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑯𐑲𐑑, 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑮𐑰𐑤𐑛 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑵𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑤𐑲𐑯𐑟 𐑼𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑞 𐑣𐑭𐑓 𐑑𐑹𐑯 𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑸𐑟𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑰𐑯; 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑱𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑮𐑱𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑱𐑛 𐑑 𐑖𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑟; 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑲𐑟 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑛 𐑓𐑫𐑤 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑴𐑤𐑛 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚.

𐑞 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯 𐑛𐑮𐑪𐑐𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛.

“𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑵𐑤𐑛, 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑵𐑤𐑛!”—𐑛𐑮𐑷𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑤𐑰𐑯 𐑚𐑮𐑧𐑔—“𐑲, ·𐑐𐑸𐑟𐑰! 𐑲 𐑕𐑰 𐑞𐑰 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯.—𐑲, 𐑯 𐑞𐑬 𐑜𐑴𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹; 𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕, 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑦𐑟 𐑞 𐑣𐑻𐑕 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑬 𐑛𐑦𐑛𐑕𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑥𐑦𐑕. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑲 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑞𐑰 𐑑 𐑞 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑤𐑧𐑑𐑼 𐑝 𐑞𐑲 𐑢𐑻𐑛. 𐑢𐑺 𐑦𐑟 𐑞 𐑕𐑧𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑣𐑻𐑕? 𐑩𐑢𐑱, 𐑥𐑱𐑑𐑕, 𐑑 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐! 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕 𐑸 𐑿𐑕𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑯𐑬; 𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑺 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑦𐑓 𐑘𐑰 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑑𐑲𐑥, 𐑯 𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑻𐑯 𐑑 𐑥𐑰; 𐑦𐑓 𐑯𐑪𐑑, ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑳𐑓 𐑑 𐑛𐑲—·𐑛𐑬𐑯, 𐑥𐑧𐑯! 𐑞 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑪𐑓𐑼𐑟 𐑑 𐑡𐑳𐑥𐑐 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑚𐑴𐑑 𐑲 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑯, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑲 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯. 𐑘𐑰 𐑸 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑥𐑧𐑯, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑥𐑲 𐑸𐑥𐑟 𐑯 𐑥𐑲 𐑤𐑧𐑜𐑟; 𐑯 𐑕𐑴 𐑴𐑚𐑱 𐑥𐑰.—𐑢𐑺'𐑟 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤? 𐑜𐑪𐑯 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯?”

𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑑 𐑑𐑵 𐑯𐑲 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑; 𐑓 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑓 𐑚𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑱𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑒𐑹𐑐𐑕 𐑣𐑰 𐑚𐑹, 𐑯 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑓 𐑞 𐑐𐑼𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑼 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑼 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑩 𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑡 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑤𐑰𐑢𐑼𐑛 𐑝𐑶𐑦𐑡, ·𐑥𐑪𐑚𐑦 ·𐑛𐑦𐑒 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑬 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑢𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑹𐑢𐑼𐑛; 𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑐𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐,—𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑞𐑳𐑕 𐑓𐑸 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑺𐑦 𐑛𐑦𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑞𐑴 𐑓 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑣𐑻 𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑢𐑱 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑪𐑐𐑑. 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑕𐑢𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑳𐑑𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑝𐑦𐑤𐑪𐑕𐑦𐑑𐑦, 𐑯 𐑯𐑬 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑐𐑼𐑕𐑿𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑴𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑐𐑭𐑔 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑰.

“𐑴! 𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚,” 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒, “𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑑𐑵 𐑤𐑱𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑑, 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑯𐑬, 𐑞 𐑔𐑻𐑛 𐑛𐑱, 𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑟𐑦𐑕𐑑. 𐑕𐑰! 𐑥𐑪𐑚𐑦 ·𐑛𐑦𐑒 𐑕𐑰𐑒𐑕 𐑞𐑰 𐑯𐑪𐑑. 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑞𐑬, 𐑞𐑬, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑨𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑰𐑒𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥!”

𐑕𐑧𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑱𐑤 𐑑 𐑞 𐑮𐑲𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛, 𐑞 𐑤𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑴𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑢𐑦𐑓𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑧𐑤𐑛 𐑑 𐑤𐑰𐑢𐑼𐑛, 𐑚𐑲 𐑚𐑴𐑔 𐑹𐑟 𐑯 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑝𐑩𐑕. 𐑯 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑢𐑧𐑯 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑤𐑲𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑝𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑤, 𐑕𐑴 𐑯𐑽 𐑨𐑟 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑢𐑦𐑖 ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒'𐑕 𐑓𐑱𐑕 𐑨𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑤𐑰𐑯𐑛 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑞 𐑮𐑱𐑤, 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑱𐑤𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑑 𐑑𐑻𐑯 𐑞 𐑝𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑤 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑, 𐑯 𐑓𐑪𐑤𐑴 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑑𐑵 𐑕𐑢𐑦𐑓𐑑𐑤𐑦, 𐑨𐑑 𐑩 𐑡𐑵𐑛𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑕 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑝𐑩𐑤. 𐑜𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑳𐑐𐑢𐑼𐑛𐑟, 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑷 ·𐑑𐑨𐑖𐑑𐑱𐑜𐑴, ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑧𐑜, 𐑯 ·𐑛𐑨𐑜𐑵, 𐑰𐑜𐑼𐑤𐑦 𐑥𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑞 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑-𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑟; 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑞 𐑹𐑟𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑢𐑻 𐑮𐑪𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑑𐑵 𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑝𐑛 𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑡𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑣𐑶𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑲𐑛, 𐑯 𐑢𐑻 𐑚𐑦𐑟𐑦𐑤𐑦 𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑻𐑒 𐑦𐑯 𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑺𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑧𐑥. 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑞 𐑳𐑞𐑼, 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑞 𐑐𐑹𐑑-𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑟, 𐑨𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑛, 𐑣𐑰 𐑷𐑤𐑕𐑴 𐑒𐑷𐑑 𐑓𐑤𐑲𐑦𐑙 𐑜𐑤𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑝 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚 𐑯 ·𐑓𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑒, 𐑚𐑦𐑟𐑦𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑧𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑝𐑟 𐑪𐑯 𐑛𐑧𐑒 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑚𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑝 𐑯𐑿 𐑲𐑼𐑯𐑟 𐑯 𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟. 𐑨𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑷 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑦𐑕; 𐑨𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑻𐑛 𐑞 𐑣𐑨𐑥𐑼𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑮𐑴𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕; 𐑓𐑸 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑣𐑨𐑥𐑼𐑟 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑛𐑮𐑲𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑯𐑱𐑤 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑸𐑑. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑮𐑨𐑤𐑦𐑛. 𐑯 𐑯𐑬 𐑥𐑸𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑝𐑱𐑯 𐑹 𐑓𐑤𐑨𐑜 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑜𐑪𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑥𐑱𐑯-𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑-𐑣𐑧𐑛, 𐑣𐑰 𐑖𐑬𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑑 ·𐑑𐑨𐑖𐑑𐑱𐑜𐑴, 𐑣𐑵 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑡𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑐𐑻𐑗, 𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯 𐑓 𐑩𐑯𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑓𐑤𐑨𐑜, 𐑯 𐑩 𐑣𐑨𐑥𐑼 𐑯 𐑯𐑱𐑤𐑟, 𐑯 𐑕𐑴 𐑯𐑱𐑤 𐑦𐑑 𐑑 𐑞 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑.

𐑢𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑓𐑨𐑜𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑛𐑱𐑟' 𐑮𐑳𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑗𐑱𐑕, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑢𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑯𐑪𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑥𐑐𐑼 𐑣𐑰 𐑚𐑹; 𐑹 𐑢𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑤𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑰𐑑𐑓𐑩𐑤𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑯 𐑥𐑨𐑤𐑦𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥: 𐑢𐑦𐑗𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑑𐑮𐑵, 𐑞 ·𐑢𐑲𐑑 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤'𐑟 𐑢𐑱 𐑯𐑬 𐑚𐑦𐑜𐑨𐑯 𐑑 𐑩𐑚𐑱𐑑, 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛, 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑 𐑕𐑴 𐑮𐑨𐑐𐑦𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑯𐑽𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑕 𐑥𐑹; 𐑞𐑴 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑰𐑛 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤'𐑟 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑕𐑴 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑩 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑨𐑟 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹. 𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑨𐑟 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑜𐑤𐑲𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑝𐑟 𐑞 𐑳𐑯𐑐𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑦𐑙 𐑖𐑸𐑒𐑕 𐑩𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥; 𐑯 𐑕𐑴 𐑐𐑻𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑒 𐑑 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑; 𐑯 𐑕𐑴 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑿𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑦𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑐𐑤𐑲𐑦𐑙 𐑹𐑟, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑚𐑤𐑱𐑛𐑟 𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑱𐑥 𐑡𐑨𐑜𐑩𐑛 𐑯 𐑒𐑮𐑳𐑯𐑗𐑑, 𐑯 𐑤𐑧𐑓𐑑 𐑕𐑥𐑷𐑤 𐑕𐑐𐑤𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑰, 𐑨𐑑 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑛𐑦𐑐.

“𐑣𐑰𐑛 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑯𐑪𐑑! 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑑𐑰𐑔 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑜𐑦𐑝 𐑯𐑿 𐑮𐑪𐑤𐑩𐑒𐑕 𐑑 𐑘𐑹 𐑹𐑟. 𐑐𐑫𐑤 𐑪𐑯! '𐑑𐑦𐑟 𐑞 𐑚𐑧𐑑𐑼 𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑑, 𐑞 𐑖𐑸𐑒'𐑕 𐑡𐑷 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑞 𐑘𐑰𐑤𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼.”

“𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑚𐑲𐑑, 𐑕𐑻, 𐑞 𐑔𐑦𐑯 𐑚𐑤𐑱𐑛𐑟 𐑜𐑮𐑴 𐑕𐑥𐑷𐑤𐑼 𐑯 𐑕𐑥𐑷𐑤𐑼!”

“𐑞𐑱 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑦𐑯𐑳𐑓! 𐑐𐑫𐑤 𐑪𐑯!—𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑣𐑵 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑑𐑧𐑤”—𐑣𐑰 𐑥𐑳𐑑𐑼𐑛—“𐑢𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑖𐑸𐑒𐑕 𐑕𐑢𐑦𐑥 𐑑 𐑓𐑰𐑕𐑑 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑹 𐑪𐑯 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚?—𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑐𐑫𐑤 𐑪𐑯! 𐑲, 𐑷𐑤 𐑩𐑤𐑲𐑝, 𐑯𐑬—𐑢𐑰 𐑯𐑽 𐑣𐑦𐑥. 𐑞 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑥! 𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑞 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑥! 𐑤𐑧𐑑 𐑥𐑰 𐑐𐑭𐑕,”—𐑯 𐑕𐑴 𐑕𐑱𐑦𐑙 𐑑𐑵 𐑝 𐑞 𐑹𐑟𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑐𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑓𐑹𐑢𐑼𐑛 𐑑 𐑞 𐑚𐑬𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑓𐑤𐑲𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑴𐑑.

𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑧𐑙𐑔 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑭𐑓𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑒𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑕𐑲𐑛, 𐑯 𐑮𐑨𐑯 𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 ·𐑢𐑲𐑑 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤'𐑟 𐑓𐑤𐑨𐑙𐑒, 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑤𐑦 𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑦𐑝𐑾𐑕 𐑝 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑩𐑛𐑝𐑭𐑯𐑕—𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑤—𐑯 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑓𐑺𐑤𐑦 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑥𐑴𐑒𐑦 𐑥𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑑, 𐑢𐑦𐑗, 𐑔𐑮𐑴𐑯 𐑪𐑓 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤'𐑟 𐑕𐑐𐑬𐑑, 𐑒𐑻𐑤𐑛 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑, ·𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑨𐑛𐑯𐑪𐑒 𐑣𐑳𐑥𐑐; 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑞𐑳𐑕 𐑒𐑤𐑴𐑕 𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥; 𐑢𐑧𐑯, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦 𐑸𐑗𐑑 𐑚𐑨𐑒, 𐑯 𐑚𐑴𐑔 𐑸𐑥𐑟 𐑤𐑧𐑙𐑔𐑢𐑲𐑟 𐑣𐑲-𐑤𐑦𐑓𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑑 𐑞 𐑐𐑶𐑟, 𐑣𐑰 𐑛𐑸𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑽𐑕 𐑲𐑼𐑯, 𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑸 𐑓𐑽𐑕𐑼 𐑒𐑻𐑕 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑣𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑱𐑤. 𐑨𐑟 𐑚𐑴𐑔 𐑕𐑑𐑰𐑤 𐑯 𐑒𐑻𐑕 𐑕𐑨𐑙𐑒 𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑪𐑒𐑩𐑑, 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑓 𐑕𐑳𐑒𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑩 𐑥𐑼𐑨𐑕, ·𐑥𐑪𐑚𐑦 ·𐑛𐑦𐑒 𐑕𐑲𐑛𐑢𐑱𐑟 𐑮𐑲𐑞𐑛; 𐑕𐑐𐑨𐑟𐑥𐑪𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑲 𐑓𐑤𐑨𐑙𐑒 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑞 𐑚𐑬, 𐑯, 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑣𐑴𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑦𐑑, 𐑕𐑴 𐑕𐑳𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑 𐑴𐑝𐑼, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑦𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑓 𐑞 𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑝𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑐𐑸𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑜𐑳𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑣𐑰 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑒𐑤𐑳𐑙, ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑕 𐑥𐑹 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑑𐑪𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑕𐑰. 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟, 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑝 𐑞 𐑹𐑟𐑥𐑧𐑯—𐑣𐑵 𐑓𐑹𐑯𐑿 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑲𐑕 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑛𐑸𐑑, 𐑯 𐑢𐑻 𐑞𐑺𐑓𐑹 𐑳𐑯𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑺𐑛 𐑓 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑦𐑓𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑕—𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑓𐑤𐑳𐑙 𐑬𐑑; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑕𐑴 𐑓𐑧𐑤, 𐑞𐑨𐑑, 𐑦𐑯 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑑𐑵 𐑝 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑒𐑤𐑳𐑗𐑑 𐑞 𐑜𐑳𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯, 𐑯 𐑮𐑲𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑤𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑤 𐑪𐑯 𐑩 𐑒𐑴𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑱𐑝, 𐑣𐑻𐑤𐑛 𐑞𐑧𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑝𐑟 𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑯𐑚𐑹𐑛 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯; 𐑞 𐑔𐑻𐑛 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑐𐑤𐑩𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑮𐑪𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑕𐑑𐑻𐑯, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑩𐑓𐑤𐑴𐑑 𐑯 𐑕𐑢𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑙.

𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑦𐑥𐑩𐑤𐑑𐑱𐑯𐑾𐑕𐑤𐑦, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑥𐑲𐑑𐑦 𐑝𐑴𐑤𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑳𐑯𐑜𐑮𐑨𐑡𐑵𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛, 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑱𐑯𐑾𐑕 𐑕𐑢𐑦𐑓𐑑𐑯𐑩𐑕, 𐑞 ·𐑢𐑲𐑑 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑛𐑸𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑞 𐑢𐑧𐑤𐑑𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑰. 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑧𐑯 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 𐑬𐑑 𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑽𐑟𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑑 𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑯𐑿 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑤𐑲𐑯, 𐑯 𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑴; 𐑯 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑭𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑵 𐑑 𐑑𐑻𐑯 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑪𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑕𐑰𐑑𐑕, 𐑯 𐑑𐑴 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑 𐑳𐑐 𐑑 𐑞 𐑥𐑸𐑒; 𐑞 𐑥𐑴𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑞 𐑑𐑮𐑧𐑗𐑼𐑩𐑕 𐑤𐑲𐑯 𐑓𐑧𐑤𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑛𐑳𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯 𐑯 𐑑𐑳𐑜, 𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑯𐑨𐑐𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑧𐑥𐑐𐑑𐑦 𐑺!

“𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑒𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑰? 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑕𐑦𐑯𐑿 𐑒𐑮𐑨𐑒𐑕!—'𐑑𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑴𐑤 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯; 𐑹𐑟! 𐑹𐑟! 𐑚𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑥!”

𐑣𐑽𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑕 𐑮𐑳𐑖 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑰-𐑒𐑮𐑨𐑖𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑴𐑑, 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑢𐑰𐑤𐑛 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑙𐑒 𐑓𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑛 𐑨𐑑 𐑚𐑱; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑵𐑖𐑩𐑯, 𐑒𐑨𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑲𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑯𐑽𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑒 𐑣𐑳𐑤 𐑝 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐; 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑦𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑹𐑕 𐑝 𐑷𐑤 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑻𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟; 𐑚𐑦𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑑—𐑦𐑑 𐑥𐑱 𐑚𐑰—𐑩 𐑤𐑸𐑡𐑼 𐑯 𐑯𐑴𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑼 𐑓𐑴; 𐑝 𐑩 𐑕𐑳𐑛𐑩𐑯, 𐑣𐑰 𐑚𐑹 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑩𐑛𐑝𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑐𐑮𐑬, 𐑕𐑥𐑲𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑡𐑷𐑟 𐑩𐑥𐑦𐑛 𐑓𐑲𐑼𐑦 𐑖𐑬𐑼𐑟 𐑝 𐑓𐑴𐑥.

𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑜𐑼𐑛; 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑕𐑥𐑴𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑛. “𐑲 𐑜𐑮𐑴 𐑚𐑤𐑲𐑯𐑛; 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟! 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑧𐑗 𐑬𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑥𐑰 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑲 𐑥𐑱 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑜𐑮𐑴𐑐 𐑥𐑲 𐑢𐑱. ·𐑦𐑕'𐑑 𐑯𐑲𐑑?”

“𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤! 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐!” 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑯𐑡𐑦𐑙 𐑹𐑟𐑥𐑧𐑯.

“𐑹𐑟! 𐑹𐑟! 𐑕𐑤𐑴𐑐 𐑛𐑬𐑯𐑢𐑼𐑛𐑟 𐑑 𐑞𐑲 𐑛𐑧𐑐𐑔𐑕, 𐑴 𐑕𐑰, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑺 𐑦𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑓 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑑𐑵 𐑤𐑱𐑑, ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑥𐑱 𐑕𐑤𐑲𐑛 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑, 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑸𐑒! 𐑲 𐑕𐑰: 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐! 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐! 𐑛𐑨𐑖 𐑪𐑯, 𐑥𐑲 𐑥𐑧𐑯! 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑘𐑰 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑱𐑝 𐑥𐑲 𐑖𐑦𐑐?”

𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑹𐑟𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑓𐑹𐑕𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑚𐑴𐑑 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑞 𐑕𐑤𐑧𐑡-𐑣𐑨𐑥𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑰𐑟, 𐑞 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑢𐑱𐑤-𐑕𐑥𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑚𐑬-𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑝 𐑑𐑵 𐑐𐑤𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑕 𐑚𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑔𐑮𐑵, 𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑, 𐑞 𐑑𐑧𐑥𐑐𐑼𐑺𐑦𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑱𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑛 𐑚𐑴𐑑 𐑤𐑱 𐑯𐑽𐑤𐑦 𐑤𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑝𐑟; 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑣𐑭𐑓-𐑢𐑱𐑛𐑦𐑙, 𐑕𐑐𐑤𐑨𐑖𐑦𐑙 𐑒𐑮𐑵, 𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑸𐑛 𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑪𐑐 𐑞 𐑜𐑨𐑐 𐑯 𐑚𐑱𐑤 𐑬𐑑 𐑞 𐑐𐑹𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼.

𐑥𐑰𐑯𐑑𐑲𐑥, 𐑓 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑚𐑦𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑, ·𐑑𐑨𐑖𐑑𐑱𐑜𐑴'𐑟 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑-𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑥𐑼 𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑱𐑯𐑛 𐑕𐑩𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛; 𐑯 𐑞 𐑮𐑧𐑛 𐑓𐑤𐑨𐑜, 𐑣𐑭𐑓-𐑮𐑨𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑨𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑐𐑤𐑨𐑛, 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑦𐑑𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑬𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑨𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑴𐑯 𐑓𐑹𐑢𐑼𐑛-𐑓𐑤𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑸𐑑; 𐑢𐑲𐑤 ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒 𐑯 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚, 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑯𐑰𐑔, 𐑒𐑷𐑑 𐑕𐑲𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑛𐑬𐑯-𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑼 𐑡𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑕𐑵𐑯 𐑨𐑟 𐑣𐑰.

“𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤! 𐑳𐑐 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑥, 𐑳𐑐 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑥! 𐑴, 𐑷𐑤 𐑘𐑰 𐑕𐑢𐑰𐑑 𐑐𐑬𐑼𐑟 𐑝 𐑺, 𐑯𐑬 𐑣𐑳𐑜 𐑥𐑰 𐑒𐑤𐑴𐑕! 𐑤𐑧𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑑 ·𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑳𐑒 𐑛𐑲, 𐑦𐑓 𐑛𐑲 𐑣𐑰 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑, 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑢𐑫𐑥𐑩𐑯'𐑟 𐑓𐑱𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑦𐑑. 𐑳𐑐 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑥, 𐑲 𐑕𐑱—𐑘𐑰 𐑓𐑵𐑤𐑟, 𐑞 𐑡𐑷! 𐑞 𐑡𐑷! 𐑦𐑟 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑞 𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑝 𐑷𐑤 𐑥𐑲 𐑚𐑻𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑐𐑮𐑱𐑼𐑟? 𐑷𐑤 𐑥𐑲 𐑤𐑲𐑓-𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑓𐑦𐑛𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑟? 𐑴, ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚, ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚, 𐑤𐑴, 𐑞𐑲 𐑢𐑻𐑒. 𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑛𐑦! 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑥𐑟𐑥𐑩𐑯, 𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑛𐑦. 𐑯𐑱, 𐑯𐑱! 𐑳𐑐 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑥 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯! 𐑣𐑰 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑟 𐑑 𐑥𐑰𐑑 𐑳𐑕! 𐑴, 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑳𐑯𐑩𐑐𐑰𐑟𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑚𐑮𐑬 𐑛𐑮𐑲𐑝𐑟 𐑪𐑯 𐑑𐑩𐑢𐑹𐑛𐑟 𐑢𐑳𐑯, 𐑣𐑵𐑟 𐑛𐑿𐑑𐑦 𐑑𐑧𐑤𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑐𐑸𐑑. 𐑥𐑲 ·𐑜𐑪𐑛, 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑥𐑰 𐑯𐑬!”

“𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑥𐑰, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑥𐑰, 𐑣𐑵𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑿 𐑸 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑯𐑬 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑐 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚; 𐑓 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚, 𐑑𐑵, 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑕 𐑣𐑽. 𐑲 𐑜𐑮𐑦𐑯 𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑰, 𐑞𐑬 𐑜𐑮𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑱𐑤! 𐑣𐑵 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑐𐑑 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚, 𐑹 𐑒𐑧𐑐𐑑 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚 𐑩𐑢𐑱𐑒, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚'𐑟 𐑴𐑯 𐑳𐑯𐑢𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑲? 𐑯 𐑯𐑬 𐑐𐑫𐑼 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚 𐑜𐑴𐑟 𐑑 𐑚𐑧𐑛 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑩 𐑥𐑨𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑕 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑷𐑤 𐑑𐑵 𐑕𐑪𐑓𐑑; 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑻 𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑓𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑚𐑮𐑳𐑖𐑢𐑫𐑛! 𐑲 𐑜𐑮𐑦𐑯 𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑰, 𐑞𐑬 𐑜𐑮𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑱𐑤! 𐑤𐑫𐑒 𐑘𐑰, 𐑕𐑳𐑯, 𐑥𐑵𐑯, 𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑟! 𐑲 𐑒𐑷𐑤 𐑘𐑰 𐑩𐑕𐑨𐑕𐑦𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑨𐑟 𐑜𐑫𐑛 𐑩 𐑓𐑧𐑤𐑴 𐑨𐑟 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑕𐑐𐑬𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑳𐑐 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑜𐑴𐑕𐑑. 𐑓 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑨𐑑, 𐑲 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑙 𐑜𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑘𐑰, 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑘𐑰 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑞 𐑒𐑳𐑐! 𐑴, 𐑴! 𐑴, 𐑴! 𐑞𐑬 𐑜𐑮𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞𐑺'𐑤 𐑚𐑰 𐑐𐑤𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑦 𐑝 𐑜𐑳𐑤𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑵𐑯! 𐑢𐑲 𐑓𐑤𐑲 𐑘𐑰 𐑯𐑪𐑑, 𐑴 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚! 𐑓 𐑥𐑰, 𐑪𐑓 𐑖𐑵𐑟 𐑯 𐑡𐑨𐑒𐑩𐑑 𐑑 𐑦𐑑; 𐑤𐑧𐑑 ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚 𐑛𐑲 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑛𐑮𐑷𐑼𐑟! 𐑩 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑥𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑦 𐑯 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑕𐑷𐑤𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑛𐑧𐑔, 𐑞𐑴;—𐑗𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑟! 𐑗𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑟! 𐑗𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑟! 𐑴, ·𐑓𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑒, 𐑓 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑮𐑧𐑛 𐑗𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑺 𐑢𐑰 𐑛𐑲!”

“𐑗𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑟? 𐑲 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑢𐑦𐑖 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑰 𐑢𐑻 𐑢𐑺 𐑞𐑱 𐑜𐑮𐑴. 𐑴, ·𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑚, 𐑲 𐑣𐑴𐑐 𐑥𐑲 𐑐𐑫𐑼 𐑥𐑳𐑞𐑼'𐑟 𐑛𐑮𐑷𐑯 𐑥𐑲 𐑐𐑸𐑑-𐑐𐑱 𐑺 𐑞𐑦𐑕; 𐑦𐑓 𐑯𐑪𐑑, 𐑓𐑿 𐑒𐑪𐑐𐑼𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑯𐑬 𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑑 𐑣𐑻, 𐑓 𐑞 𐑝𐑶𐑦𐑡 𐑦𐑟 𐑳𐑐.”

𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐'𐑕 𐑚𐑬𐑟, 𐑯𐑽𐑤𐑦 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑯𐑬 𐑣𐑳𐑙 𐑦𐑯𐑨𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑝; 𐑣𐑨𐑥𐑼𐑟, 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑐𐑤𐑨𐑙𐑒, 𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟, 𐑯 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑟, 𐑥𐑦𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑒𐑤𐑦 𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑱𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟, 𐑡𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑞𐑱 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑛𐑸𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞𐑺 𐑝𐑺𐑾𐑕 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑶𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕; 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑺 𐑦𐑯𐑗𐑭𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑲𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑑 𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑤𐑦 𐑝𐑲𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑮𐑰𐑛𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑱𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑧𐑛, 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑩 𐑚𐑮𐑷𐑛 𐑚𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑝 𐑴𐑝𐑼𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑧𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑻𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑼 𐑓𐑴𐑥 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑨𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑮𐑳𐑖𐑑. 𐑮𐑧𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑚𐑿𐑖𐑩𐑯, 𐑕𐑢𐑦𐑓𐑑 𐑝𐑧𐑯𐑡𐑩𐑯𐑕, 𐑦𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑥𐑨𐑤𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑻 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑴𐑤 𐑨𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑, 𐑯 𐑕𐑐𐑲𐑑 𐑝 𐑷𐑤 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑹𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑥𐑨𐑯 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑛𐑵, 𐑞 𐑕𐑪𐑤𐑦𐑛 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑚𐑳𐑑𐑮𐑩𐑕 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑛 𐑕𐑥𐑴𐑑 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐'𐑕 𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑚𐑼𐑛 𐑚𐑬, 𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑯 𐑑𐑦𐑥𐑚𐑼𐑟 𐑮𐑰𐑤𐑛. 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑓𐑧𐑤 𐑓𐑤𐑨𐑑 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑓𐑱𐑕𐑩𐑟. 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑤𐑪𐑡𐑛 𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑒𐑕, 𐑞 𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑽𐑟 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑓𐑑 𐑖𐑫𐑒 𐑪𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑚𐑫𐑤-𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑯𐑧𐑒𐑕. 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑞 𐑚𐑮𐑰𐑗, 𐑞𐑱 𐑣𐑻𐑛 𐑞 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼𐑟 𐑐𐑹, 𐑨𐑟 𐑥𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑑𐑪𐑮𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑩 𐑓𐑤𐑵𐑥.

“𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐! 𐑞 𐑣𐑻𐑕!—𐑞 𐑕𐑧𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑣𐑻𐑕!” 𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑛 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑; “𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑰 ·𐑩𐑥𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑯!”

𐑛𐑲𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑦𐑯𐑰𐑔 𐑞 𐑕𐑧𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑖𐑦𐑐, 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑮𐑨𐑯 𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑝𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑒𐑰𐑤; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼, 𐑕𐑢𐑦𐑓𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑖𐑪𐑑 𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑻𐑓𐑦𐑕 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯, 𐑓𐑸 𐑪𐑓 𐑞 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑚𐑬, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑓𐑿 𐑘𐑸𐑛𐑟 𐑝 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚'𐑟 𐑚𐑴𐑑, 𐑢𐑺, 𐑓 𐑩 𐑑𐑲𐑥, 𐑣𐑰 𐑤𐑱 𐑒𐑢𐑲𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑑.

“𐑲 𐑑𐑻𐑯 𐑥𐑲 𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑯. 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑣𐑴, ·𐑑𐑨𐑖𐑑𐑱𐑜𐑴! 𐑤𐑧𐑑 𐑥𐑰 𐑣𐑽 𐑞𐑲 𐑣𐑨𐑥𐑼. 𐑴! 𐑘𐑰 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑳𐑯𐑕𐑼𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑛 𐑕𐑐𐑲𐑼𐑟 𐑝 𐑥𐑲𐑯; 𐑞𐑬 𐑳𐑯𐑒𐑮𐑨𐑒𐑑 𐑒𐑰𐑤; 𐑯 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑜𐑪𐑛-𐑚𐑫𐑤𐑦𐑛 𐑣𐑳𐑤; 𐑞𐑬 𐑓𐑻𐑥 𐑛𐑧𐑒, 𐑯 𐑣𐑷𐑑𐑦 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑥, 𐑯 ·𐑐𐑴𐑤-𐑐𐑶𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑐𐑮𐑬,—𐑛𐑧𐑔-𐑜𐑤𐑹𐑾𐑕 𐑖𐑦𐑐! 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑘𐑰 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑐𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑖, 𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑 𐑥𐑰? 𐑨𐑥 𐑲 𐑒𐑳𐑑 𐑪𐑓 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑓𐑪𐑯𐑛 𐑐𐑮𐑲𐑛 𐑝 𐑥𐑰𐑯𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑑 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑟? 𐑴, 𐑤𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑧𐑔 𐑪𐑯 𐑤𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑤𐑲𐑓! 𐑴, 𐑯𐑬 𐑲 𐑓𐑰𐑤 𐑥𐑲 𐑑𐑪𐑐𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑤𐑲𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑲 𐑑𐑪𐑐𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑓. 𐑣𐑴, 𐑣𐑴! 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑷𐑤 𐑘𐑹 𐑓𐑻𐑞𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑟, 𐑐𐑹 𐑘𐑰 𐑯𐑬 𐑦𐑯, 𐑘𐑰 𐑚𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑴𐑟 𐑝 𐑥𐑲 𐑣𐑴𐑤 𐑓𐑹𐑜𐑪𐑯 𐑤𐑲𐑓, 𐑯 𐑑𐑪𐑐 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑐𐑲𐑤𐑛 ·𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑚𐑼 𐑝 𐑥𐑲 𐑛𐑧𐑔! 𐑑𐑩𐑢𐑹𐑛𐑟 𐑞𐑰 𐑲 𐑮𐑴𐑤, 𐑞𐑬 𐑷𐑤-𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑶𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑳𐑯𐑒𐑪𐑙𐑒𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑱𐑤; 𐑑 𐑞 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑲 𐑜𐑮𐑨𐑐𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞𐑰; 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑣𐑧𐑤'𐑟 𐑣𐑸𐑑 𐑲 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑚 𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑰; 𐑓 𐑣𐑱𐑑'𐑕 𐑕𐑱𐑒 𐑲 𐑕𐑐𐑦𐑑 𐑥𐑲 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑮𐑧𐑔 𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑰. 𐑕𐑦𐑙𐑒 𐑷𐑤 𐑒𐑪𐑓𐑦𐑯𐑟 𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑣𐑻𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑐𐑵𐑤! 𐑯 𐑕𐑦𐑯𐑕 𐑯𐑲𐑞𐑼 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑚𐑰 𐑥𐑲𐑯, 𐑤𐑧𐑑 𐑥𐑰 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑑𐑴 𐑑 𐑐𐑰𐑕𐑩𐑟, 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑗𐑱𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑰, 𐑞𐑴 𐑑𐑲𐑛 𐑑 𐑞𐑰, 𐑞𐑬 𐑛𐑨𐑥𐑛 𐑢𐑱𐑤! 𐑞𐑳𐑕, 𐑲 𐑜𐑦𐑝 𐑳𐑐 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑽!”

𐑞 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑛𐑸𐑑𐑩𐑛; 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑓𐑤𐑵 𐑓𐑹𐑢𐑼𐑛; 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑦𐑜𐑯𐑲𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑝𐑦𐑤𐑪𐑕𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑞 𐑤𐑲𐑯 𐑮𐑨𐑯 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑵𐑝𐑟;—𐑮𐑨𐑯 𐑓𐑬𐑤. 𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚 𐑕𐑑𐑵𐑐𐑑 𐑑 𐑒𐑤𐑽 𐑦𐑑; 𐑣𐑰 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑒𐑤𐑽 𐑦𐑑; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞 𐑓𐑤𐑲𐑦𐑙 𐑑𐑻𐑯 𐑒𐑷𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑞 𐑯𐑧𐑒, 𐑯 𐑝𐑶𐑕𐑤𐑩𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑨𐑟 ·𐑑𐑻𐑒𐑦𐑖 𐑥𐑿𐑑𐑕 𐑚𐑴𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑺 𐑝𐑦𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑥, 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑖𐑪𐑑 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑, 𐑺 𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑵 𐑯𐑿 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑜𐑪𐑯. 𐑯𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑, 𐑞 𐑣𐑧𐑝𐑦 𐑲-𐑕𐑐𐑤𐑲𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑮𐑴𐑐'𐑕 𐑓𐑲𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑓𐑤𐑵 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑒-𐑧𐑥𐑐𐑑𐑦 𐑑𐑳𐑚, 𐑯𐑪𐑒𐑑 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑩𐑯 𐑹𐑟𐑥𐑩𐑯, 𐑯 𐑕𐑥𐑲𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑕𐑰, 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑩𐑐𐑽𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑛𐑧𐑐𐑔𐑕.

𐑓 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑, 𐑞 𐑑𐑮𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑴𐑑'𐑕 𐑒𐑮𐑵 𐑕𐑑𐑫𐑛 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤; 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑛. “𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐? 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 ·𐑜𐑪𐑛, 𐑢𐑺 𐑦𐑟 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐?” 𐑕𐑵𐑯 𐑞𐑱 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑛𐑦𐑥, 𐑚𐑦𐑢𐑦𐑤𐑛𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑰𐑛𐑾𐑥𐑟 𐑕𐑷 𐑣𐑻 𐑕𐑲𐑛𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑓𐑱𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑥, 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑜𐑨𐑖𐑩𐑕 ·𐑓𐑱𐑑𐑩 ·𐑥𐑹𐑜𐑩𐑯𐑩; 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑞 𐑳𐑐𐑼𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑕 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼; 𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑓𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑲 𐑦𐑯𐑓𐑨𐑗𐑵𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯, 𐑹 𐑓𐑦𐑛𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑦, 𐑹 𐑓𐑱𐑑, 𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑕 𐑤𐑪𐑓𐑑𐑦 𐑐𐑻𐑗𐑩𐑟, 𐑞 𐑐𐑱𐑜𐑩𐑯 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑽𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑥𐑱𐑯𐑑𐑱𐑯𐑛 𐑞𐑺 𐑕𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑤𐑫𐑒𐑬𐑑𐑕 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑰. 𐑯 𐑯𐑬, 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑒 𐑕𐑻𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑕𐑰𐑟𐑛 𐑞 𐑤𐑴𐑯 𐑚𐑴𐑑 𐑦𐑑𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓, 𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑒𐑮𐑵, 𐑯 𐑰𐑗 𐑓𐑤𐑴𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑹, 𐑯 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑕-𐑐𐑴𐑤, 𐑯 𐑕𐑐𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑙, 𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑥𐑩𐑑 𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑥𐑩𐑑, 𐑷𐑤 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑯 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝𐑹𐑑𐑧𐑒𐑕, 𐑒𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑛 𐑞 𐑕𐑥𐑷𐑤𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑗𐑦𐑐 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑛 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑕𐑲𐑑.

𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑢𐑧𐑤𐑥𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑥𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑐𐑹𐑛 𐑞𐑧𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑝𐑟 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑙𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑾𐑯 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑥𐑱𐑯𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑, 𐑤𐑰𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑓𐑿 𐑦𐑯𐑗𐑩𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑦𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑑 𐑕𐑐𐑸 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑝𐑦𐑟𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤, 𐑑𐑩𐑜𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑰𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑘𐑸𐑛𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑓𐑤𐑨𐑜, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑒𐑭𐑥𐑤𐑦 𐑳𐑯𐑡𐑩𐑤𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑲𐑮𐑪𐑯𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤 𐑒𐑴𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑲𐑛𐑦𐑙𐑟, 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑞 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑶𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑴𐑟 𐑞𐑱 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑑𐑳𐑗𐑑;—𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑, 𐑩 𐑮𐑧𐑛 𐑸𐑥 𐑯 𐑩 𐑣𐑨𐑥𐑼 𐑣𐑪𐑝𐑼𐑛 𐑚𐑨𐑒𐑢𐑼𐑛𐑤𐑦 𐑳𐑐𐑤𐑦𐑓𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑴𐑐𐑩𐑯 𐑺, 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑨𐑒𐑑 𐑝 𐑯𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑓𐑤𐑨𐑜 𐑓𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑼 𐑯 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑓𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑼 𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑕𐑲𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑐𐑸. 𐑩 𐑕𐑒𐑲-𐑣𐑷𐑒 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑑𐑷𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑙𐑤𐑦 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑓𐑪𐑤𐑴𐑛 𐑞 𐑥𐑱𐑯-𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑒 𐑛𐑬𐑯𐑢𐑼𐑛𐑟 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑯𐑨𐑗𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑣𐑴𐑥 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑸𐑟, 𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑓𐑤𐑨𐑜, 𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑴𐑛𐑦𐑙 ·𐑑𐑨𐑖𐑑𐑱𐑜𐑴 𐑞𐑺; 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑚𐑻𐑛 𐑯𐑬 𐑗𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑕𐑧𐑐𐑑 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑚𐑮𐑷𐑛 𐑓𐑤𐑳𐑑𐑼𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑢𐑰𐑯 𐑞 𐑣𐑨𐑥𐑼 𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑫𐑛; 𐑯 𐑕𐑦𐑥𐑩𐑤𐑑𐑱𐑯𐑾𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑓𐑰𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑨𐑑 ·𐑧𐑔𐑽𐑾𐑤 𐑔𐑮𐑦𐑤, 𐑞 𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑥𐑻𐑡𐑛 𐑕𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑡 𐑚𐑦𐑯𐑰𐑔, 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑛𐑧𐑔-𐑜𐑭𐑕𐑐, 𐑒𐑧𐑐𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑥𐑼 𐑓𐑮𐑴𐑟𐑩𐑯 𐑞𐑺; 𐑯 𐑕𐑴 𐑞 𐑚𐑻𐑛 𐑝 𐑣𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑯, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑸𐑒𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑒 𐑖𐑮𐑰𐑒𐑕, 𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑽𐑾𐑤 𐑚𐑰𐑒 𐑔𐑮𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑳𐑐𐑢𐑼𐑛𐑟, 𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑴𐑤 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑝 𐑓𐑹𐑥 𐑓𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑤𐑨𐑜 𐑝 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚, 𐑢𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑖𐑦𐑐, 𐑢𐑦𐑗, 𐑤𐑲𐑒 ·𐑕𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑯, 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑦𐑙𐑒 𐑑 𐑣𐑧𐑤 𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑖𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑛𐑮𐑨𐑜𐑛 𐑩 𐑤𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑐𐑸𐑑 𐑝 𐑣𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑙 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑻, 𐑯 𐑣𐑧𐑤𐑥𐑩𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑣𐑻𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑦𐑑.

𐑯𐑬 𐑕𐑥𐑷𐑤 𐑓𐑬𐑤𐑟 𐑓𐑤𐑵 𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑰𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑞 𐑘𐑧𐑑 𐑘𐑷𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑜𐑳𐑤𐑓; 𐑩 𐑕𐑳𐑤𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑕𐑻𐑓 𐑚𐑰𐑑 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑕𐑑𐑰𐑐 𐑕𐑲𐑛𐑟; 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑨𐑐𐑕𐑑, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑖𐑮𐑬𐑛 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑰 𐑮𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑪𐑯 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑮𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑓𐑲𐑝 𐑔𐑬𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑘𐑽𐑟 𐑩𐑜𐑴.

·𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑒𐑑𐑕. (𐑕𐑩𐑐𐑤𐑲𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑩 ·𐑕𐑳𐑚-·𐑕𐑳𐑚-·𐑤𐑲𐑚𐑮𐑺𐑾𐑯).

𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑚𐑰 𐑕𐑰𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑥𐑽 𐑐𐑱𐑯𐑟𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑳𐑮𐑴𐑼 𐑯 𐑜𐑮𐑳𐑚-𐑢𐑻𐑥 𐑝 𐑩 𐑐𐑫𐑼 𐑛𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑩 ·𐑕𐑳𐑚-·𐑕𐑳𐑚 𐑩𐑐𐑽𐑟 𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑜𐑪𐑯 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑞 𐑤𐑪𐑙 ·𐑝𐑨𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑰𐑑-𐑕𐑑𐑷𐑤𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑻𐑔, 𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑳𐑐 𐑢𐑪𐑑𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑥 𐑩𐑤𐑵𐑠𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑧𐑯𐑦𐑢𐑱𐑟 𐑓𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑚𐑫𐑒 𐑢𐑪𐑑𐑕𐑴𐑧𐑝𐑼, 𐑕𐑱𐑒𐑮𐑩𐑛 𐑹 𐑐𐑮𐑴𐑓𐑱𐑯. 𐑞𐑺𐑓𐑹 𐑿 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑯𐑪𐑑, 𐑦𐑯 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑒𐑱𐑕 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑰𐑕𐑑, 𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑜𐑩𐑤𐑛𐑦-𐑐𐑦𐑜𐑩𐑤𐑛𐑦 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑑𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕, 𐑣𐑬𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑷𐑔𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑒, 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑒𐑑𐑕, 𐑓 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑜𐑪𐑕𐑐𐑩𐑤 ·𐑕𐑧𐑑𐑪𐑤𐑩𐑡𐑦. 𐑓𐑸 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑦𐑑. 𐑨𐑟 𐑑𐑳𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑱𐑯𐑗𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑷𐑔𐑼𐑟 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑤𐑦, 𐑨𐑟 𐑢𐑧𐑤 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑐𐑴𐑩𐑑𐑕 𐑣𐑽 𐑩𐑐𐑽𐑦𐑙, 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑒𐑑𐑕 𐑸 𐑕𐑴𐑤𐑦 𐑝𐑨𐑤𐑿𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑹 𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑑𐑱𐑯𐑦𐑙, 𐑨𐑟 𐑩𐑓𐑹𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑜𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑻𐑛𐑟 𐑲 𐑝𐑿 𐑝 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑿𐑩𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑧𐑛, 𐑔𐑷𐑑, 𐑓𐑨𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑛, 𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑙 𐑝 ·𐑤𐑩𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑔𐑩𐑯, 𐑚𐑲 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑯𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑯 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑼𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟, 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑤𐑵𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑬𐑼 𐑴𐑯.

𐑕𐑴 𐑓𐑺 𐑞𐑰 𐑢𐑧𐑤, 𐑐𐑫𐑼 𐑛𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑩 ·𐑕𐑳𐑚-·𐑕𐑳𐑚, 𐑣𐑵𐑟 𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑱𐑑𐑼 𐑲 𐑨𐑥. 𐑞𐑬 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑪𐑙𐑜𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑴𐑐𐑤𐑩𐑕, 𐑕𐑨𐑤𐑴 𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑚 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑯𐑴 𐑢𐑲𐑯 𐑝 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑢𐑹𐑥; 𐑯 𐑓 𐑣𐑵𐑥 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 ·𐑐𐑱𐑤 ·𐑖𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑚𐑰 𐑑𐑵 𐑮𐑴𐑟𐑦-𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑪𐑙; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑵𐑥 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑤𐑳𐑝𐑟 𐑑 𐑕𐑦𐑑, 𐑯 𐑓𐑰𐑤 𐑐𐑫𐑼-𐑛𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑖, 𐑑𐑵; 𐑯 𐑜𐑮𐑴 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑝𐑦𐑝𐑾𐑤 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑑𐑽𐑟; 𐑯 𐑕𐑱 𐑑 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑚𐑤𐑳𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑓𐑫𐑤 𐑲𐑟 𐑯 𐑧𐑥𐑐𐑑𐑦 𐑜𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑩𐑟, 𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑷𐑤𐑑𐑩𐑜𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑳𐑯𐑐𐑤𐑧𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑕𐑨𐑛𐑯𐑩𐑕—𐑜𐑦𐑝 𐑦𐑑 𐑳𐑐, ·𐑕𐑳𐑚-·𐑕𐑳𐑚𐑟! 𐑓 𐑚𐑲 𐑣𐑬 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑞 𐑥𐑹 𐑐𐑱𐑯𐑟 𐑘𐑰 𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑑 𐑐𐑤𐑰𐑟 𐑞 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛, 𐑚𐑲 𐑕𐑴 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑞 𐑥𐑹 𐑖𐑨𐑤 𐑘𐑰 𐑓 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑜𐑴 𐑔𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑤𐑩𐑕! 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑲 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑒𐑤𐑽 𐑬𐑑 ·𐑣𐑨𐑥𐑐𐑑𐑩𐑯 ·𐑒𐑹𐑑 𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑑𐑵𐑦𐑤𐑼𐑦𐑟 𐑓 𐑘𐑰! 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑜𐑳𐑤𐑐 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑘𐑹 𐑑𐑽𐑟 𐑯 𐑣𐑲 𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑓𐑑 𐑑 𐑞 𐑮𐑶𐑩𐑤-𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑘𐑹 𐑣𐑸𐑑𐑕; 𐑓 𐑘𐑹 𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑣𐑵 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑜𐑪𐑯 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑸 𐑒𐑤𐑽𐑦𐑙 𐑬𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑯-𐑕𐑑𐑹𐑦𐑛 𐑣𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑯𐑟, 𐑯 𐑥𐑱𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑮𐑧𐑓𐑿𐑡𐑰𐑟 𐑝 𐑤𐑪𐑙-𐑐𐑨𐑥𐑐𐑼𐑛 ·𐑜𐑱𐑚𐑮𐑦𐑩𐑤, ·𐑥𐑦𐑒𐑲𐑧𐑤, 𐑯 ·𐑮𐑨𐑓𐑲𐑧𐑤, 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑕𐑑 𐑘𐑹 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑦𐑙. 𐑣𐑽 𐑘𐑰 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑒 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑕𐑐𐑤𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑛 𐑣𐑸𐑑𐑕 𐑑𐑩𐑜𐑧𐑞𐑼—𐑞𐑺, 𐑘𐑰 𐑖𐑨𐑤 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑒 𐑳𐑯𐑕𐑐𐑤𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑜𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑩𐑟!

———————

“𐑯 ·𐑜𐑪𐑛 𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟.”

—·𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑩𐑕𐑦𐑕.

“·𐑤𐑩𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑔𐑩𐑯 𐑥𐑱𐑒𐑩𐑔 𐑩 𐑐𐑭𐑔 𐑑 𐑖𐑲𐑯 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑣𐑦𐑥; 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒 𐑞 𐑛𐑰𐑐 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑣𐑹𐑦.”

—·𐑡𐑪𐑚.

“𐑯𐑬 𐑞 ·𐑤𐑹𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑺𐑛 𐑩 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑓𐑦𐑖 𐑑 𐑕𐑢𐑪𐑤𐑴 𐑳𐑐 ·𐑡𐑴𐑯𐑩.”

—·𐑡𐑴𐑯𐑩.

“𐑞𐑺 𐑜𐑴 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑕; 𐑞𐑺 𐑦𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 ·𐑤𐑩𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑔𐑩𐑯 𐑣𐑵𐑥 𐑞𐑬 𐑣𐑨𐑕𐑑 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑑 𐑐𐑤𐑱 𐑞𐑺𐑦𐑯.”

—·𐑕𐑭𐑥𐑟.

“𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑛𐑱, 𐑞 ·𐑤𐑹𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑹, 𐑯 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑, 𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑪𐑙 𐑕𐑹𐑛, 𐑖𐑨𐑤 𐑐𐑳𐑯𐑦𐑖 ·𐑤𐑩𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑔𐑩𐑯 𐑞 𐑐𐑽𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑻𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑑, 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 ·𐑤𐑩𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑔𐑩𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑒𐑮𐑫𐑒𐑧𐑛 𐑕𐑻𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑑; 𐑯 𐑣𐑰 𐑖𐑨𐑤 𐑕𐑤𐑱 𐑞 𐑛𐑮𐑨𐑜𐑩𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑰.”

—·𐑲𐑟𐑱𐑩.

“𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑴𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑚𐑦𐑕𐑲𐑛𐑟 𐑒𐑳𐑥𐑩𐑔 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑒𐑱𐑪𐑕 𐑝 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑥𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑟 𐑥𐑬𐑔, 𐑚𐑰 𐑦𐑑 𐑚𐑰𐑕𐑑, 𐑚𐑴𐑑, 𐑹 𐑕𐑑𐑴𐑯, 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑦𐑑 𐑜𐑴𐑟 𐑷𐑤 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑓𐑬𐑤 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑕𐑢𐑪𐑤𐑴 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟, 𐑯 𐑐𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑔 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑪𐑑𐑩𐑥𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑜𐑳𐑤𐑓 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑷𐑯𐑗.”

—·𐑣𐑪𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛𐑟 ·𐑐𐑤𐑵𐑑𐑸𐑒𐑕 ·𐑥𐑪𐑮𐑩𐑤𐑟.

“𐑞 ·𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑾𐑯 ·𐑕𐑰 𐑚𐑮𐑰𐑛𐑩𐑔 𐑞 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑦𐑜𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑸: 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑞 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑯 ·𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑐𐑵𐑤𐑕 𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑛 ·𐑚𐑱𐑤𐑰𐑯, 𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑳𐑐 𐑨𐑟 𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑦𐑯 𐑤𐑧𐑙𐑔 𐑨𐑟 𐑓𐑹 𐑱𐑒𐑼𐑟 𐑹 𐑸𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛.”

—·𐑣𐑪𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛𐑟 ·𐑐𐑤𐑦𐑯𐑦.

“𐑕𐑒𐑺𐑕𐑤𐑦 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑢𐑰 𐑐𐑮𐑴𐑕𐑰𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑑𐑵 𐑛𐑱𐑟 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑰, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑯𐑮𐑲𐑟 𐑩 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑯 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑥𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑰, 𐑩𐑐𐑽𐑛. 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑞 𐑓𐑹𐑥𐑼, 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑝 𐑩 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑥𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑩𐑕 𐑕𐑲𐑟.... 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑒𐑱𐑥 𐑑𐑩𐑢𐑹𐑛𐑟 𐑳𐑕, 𐑴𐑐𐑩𐑯-𐑥𐑬𐑞𐑛, 𐑮𐑱𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑝𐑟 𐑪𐑯 𐑷𐑤 𐑕𐑲𐑛𐑟, 𐑯 𐑚𐑰𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑕𐑰 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑩 𐑓𐑴𐑥.”

—·𐑑𐑫𐑒𐑕 ·𐑤𐑵𐑕𐑾𐑯. “𐑞 ·𐑑𐑮𐑵 ·𐑣𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑦.”

“𐑣𐑰 𐑝𐑦𐑟𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑒𐑳𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑦 𐑷𐑤𐑕𐑴 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑝𐑿 𐑝 𐑒𐑨𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑹𐑕-𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑴𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑝𐑨𐑤𐑿 𐑓 𐑞𐑺 𐑑𐑰𐑔, 𐑝 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑣𐑰 𐑚𐑮𐑷𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑑 𐑞 𐑒𐑦𐑙.... 𐑞 𐑚𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑒𐑨𐑗𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑴𐑯 𐑒𐑳𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑦, 𐑝 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑢𐑻 𐑓𐑹𐑑𐑦-𐑱𐑑, 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑓𐑦𐑓𐑑𐑦 𐑘𐑸𐑛𐑟 𐑤𐑪𐑙. 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑕 𐑣𐑵 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑒𐑦𐑤𐑛 𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑦 𐑦𐑯 𐑑𐑵 𐑛𐑱𐑟.”

—·𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑹 ·𐑪𐑒𐑞𐑼𐑟 𐑝𐑻𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑯𐑨𐑩𐑑𐑦𐑝 𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑛𐑬𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑬𐑔 𐑚𐑲 ·𐑒𐑦𐑙 ·𐑨𐑤𐑓𐑮𐑩𐑛, ⸰𐑱𐑛 890.

“𐑯 𐑢𐑺𐑨𐑟 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑟; 𐑢𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑚𐑰𐑕𐑑 𐑹 𐑝𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑤; 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑼 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑛𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑜𐑳𐑤𐑓 𐑝 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑥𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑟 (𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟) 𐑥𐑬𐑔, 𐑸 𐑦𐑥𐑰𐑛𐑾𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑤𐑪𐑕𐑑 𐑯 𐑕𐑢𐑪𐑤𐑴𐑛 𐑳𐑐, 𐑞 𐑕𐑰-𐑜𐑳𐑡𐑩𐑯 𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑲𐑼𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑕𐑩𐑒𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑦𐑑𐑦, 𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑕𐑤𐑰𐑐𐑕.”

—·𐑥𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑱𐑯. —𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑤𐑩𐑡𐑦 𐑓 ·𐑮𐑲𐑥𐑪𐑯𐑛 ·𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑪𐑯𐑛.

“𐑤𐑧𐑑 𐑳𐑕 𐑓𐑤𐑲, 𐑤𐑧𐑑 𐑳𐑕 𐑓𐑤𐑲! ·𐑴𐑤𐑛 ·𐑯𐑦𐑒 𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑥𐑰 𐑦𐑓 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 ·𐑤𐑩𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑔𐑩𐑯 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑮𐑲𐑚𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑯𐑴𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑓𐑩𐑑 ·𐑥𐑴𐑟𐑩𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑤𐑲𐑓 𐑝 𐑩 𐑐𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑑 ·𐑡𐑴𐑚.”

—·𐑮𐑨𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑱.

“𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑤𐑦𐑝𐑼 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑑𐑵 𐑒𐑸𐑑𐑤𐑴𐑛𐑟.”

—·𐑕𐑑𐑴𐑟 ·𐑨𐑯𐑩𐑤𐑟.

“𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 ·𐑤𐑩𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑔𐑩𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑱𐑒𐑩𐑔 𐑞 𐑕𐑰𐑟 𐑑 𐑕𐑰𐑞 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑚𐑶𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑐𐑨𐑯.”

—𐑤𐑹𐑛 ·𐑚𐑱𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑟 ·𐑝𐑻𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑭𐑥𐑟.

“𐑑𐑳𐑗𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑥𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑩𐑕 𐑚𐑳𐑤𐑒 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑹 ·𐑹𐑒 𐑢𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑰𐑝𐑛 𐑯𐑳𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑻𐑑𐑩𐑯. 𐑞𐑱 𐑜𐑮𐑴 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑰𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑨𐑑, 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑴𐑥𐑳𐑗 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑒𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑝 𐑶𐑤 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑚𐑰 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑢𐑱𐑤.”

—𐑦𐑚𐑦𐑛. “𐑣𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑦 𐑝 ·𐑤𐑲𐑓 𐑯 ·𐑛𐑧𐑔.”

“𐑞 𐑕𐑪𐑝𐑮𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑪𐑯 𐑻𐑔 𐑦𐑟 ·𐑐𐑸𐑥𐑩𐑕𐑧𐑑𐑦 𐑓 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑢𐑼𐑛 𐑚𐑮𐑵𐑟.”

—𐑒𐑦𐑙 ·𐑣𐑧𐑯𐑮𐑦.

“𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑢𐑱𐑤.”

—·𐑣𐑨𐑥𐑤𐑩𐑑.

“𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑑 𐑕𐑩𐑒𐑘𐑫𐑼, 𐑯𐑴 𐑕𐑒𐑦𐑤 𐑝 𐑤𐑰𐑗𐑩𐑟 𐑸𐑑

𐑥𐑴𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑩𐑝𐑱𐑤, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑑 𐑮𐑩𐑑𐑻𐑯 𐑱𐑜𐑱𐑯

𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑵𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑢𐑻𐑒𐑼, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑤𐑴𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑸𐑑,

𐑛𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑑, 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑮𐑧𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑮𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑐𐑱𐑯,

𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑢𐑵𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑑 𐑖𐑹 𐑓𐑤𐑲𐑟 𐑔𐑮𐑿 𐑞 𐑥𐑱𐑯.”

—𐑞 ·𐑓𐑺𐑦 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑯

“𐑦𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑕 𐑨𐑟 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟, 𐑞 𐑥𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑣𐑵𐑟 𐑝𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑐𐑰𐑕𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑒𐑭𐑥 𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑞 𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑦𐑑 𐑚𐑶𐑤.”

—𐑕𐑻 ·𐑢𐑦𐑤𐑾𐑥 ·𐑛𐑨𐑝𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑯𐑑. 𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑓𐑦𐑕 𐑑 ·𐑜𐑪𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑚𐑺.

“𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥𐑩𐑕𐑧𐑑𐑦 𐑦𐑟, 𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑡𐑳𐑕𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑬𐑑, 𐑕𐑦𐑯𐑕 𐑞 𐑤𐑻𐑯𐑧𐑛 ·𐑣𐑪𐑟𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑻𐑒 𐑝 𐑔𐑻𐑑𐑦 𐑘𐑽𐑟, 𐑕𐑱𐑧𐑔 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑯𐑤𐑦, ·𐑯𐑧𐑕𐑒𐑦𐑴 𐑒𐑢𐑦𐑛 𐑕𐑦𐑑.”

—𐑕𐑻 ⸰𐑑 𐑚𐑮𐑬𐑯. 𐑝 ·𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥𐑩 ·𐑕𐑧𐑑𐑦 𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥𐑩 ·𐑕𐑧𐑑𐑦 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤. 𐑝𐑰𐑛𐑱 𐑣𐑦𐑟 ⸰𐑝𐑰.

“𐑤𐑲𐑒 ·𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑕𐑼𐑟 ·𐑑𐑱𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑪𐑛𐑼𐑯 𐑓𐑤𐑱𐑤

𐑣𐑰 𐑔𐑮𐑧𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑮𐑵𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑪𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑩𐑕 𐑑𐑱𐑤.

* * * *

𐑞𐑺 𐑓𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑑 𐑡𐑨𐑝𐑤𐑦𐑯𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑲𐑛 𐑣𐑰 𐑢𐑺𐑟,

𐑯 𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑨𐑒 𐑩 𐑜𐑮𐑴𐑝 𐑝 𐑐𐑲𐑒𐑕 𐑩𐑐𐑽𐑟.”

—·𐑢𐑷𐑤𐑼𐑟 ·𐑚𐑨𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑼 ·𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛𐑟

“𐑚𐑲 𐑸𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 ·𐑤𐑩𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑔𐑩𐑯, 𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑛 𐑩 ·𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑢𐑧𐑤𐑔 𐑹 ·𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑑—(𐑦𐑯 ·𐑤𐑨𐑑𐑦𐑯, ·𐑕𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑟) 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑩𐑯 𐑸𐑑𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑤 𐑥𐑨𐑯.”

—𐑴𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑝 ·𐑣𐑪𐑚𐑟𐑩𐑟 ·𐑤𐑩𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑔𐑩𐑯.

“𐑕𐑦𐑤𐑦 ·𐑥𐑨𐑯𐑕𐑴𐑤 𐑕𐑢𐑪𐑤𐑴𐑛 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑 𐑗𐑵𐑦𐑙, 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑓 𐑦𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑩 𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑥𐑬𐑔 𐑝 𐑩 𐑢𐑱𐑤.”

—𐑐𐑦𐑤𐑜𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑟 ·𐑐𐑮𐑴𐑜𐑮𐑧𐑕.

“𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑰 𐑚𐑰𐑕𐑑

·𐑤𐑩𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑔𐑩𐑯, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 ·𐑜𐑪𐑛 𐑝 𐑷𐑤 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑢𐑻𐑒𐑕

·𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑣𐑿𐑡𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑢𐑦𐑥 𐑞 𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑰𐑥.”

—𐑐𐑨𐑮𐑩𐑛𐑲𐑕 ·𐑤𐑪𐑕𐑑.

“𐑞𐑺 ·𐑤𐑩𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑔𐑩𐑯,

·𐑣𐑿𐑡𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑝 𐑤𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑒𐑮𐑰𐑗𐑼𐑟, 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑛𐑰𐑐

·𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑧𐑗𐑑 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑦 𐑕𐑤𐑰𐑐𐑕 𐑹 𐑕𐑢𐑦𐑥𐑟,

𐑯 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑟 𐑩 𐑥𐑵𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛; 𐑯 𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑜𐑦𐑤𐑟

·𐑛𐑮𐑷𐑟 𐑦𐑯, 𐑯 𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑮𐑧𐑔 𐑕𐑐𐑬𐑑𐑕 𐑬𐑑 𐑩 𐑕𐑰.”

—𐑦𐑚𐑦𐑛.

“𐑞 𐑥𐑲𐑑𐑦 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑕𐑢𐑦𐑥 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑕𐑰 𐑝 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼, 𐑯 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑩 𐑕𐑰 𐑝 𐑶𐑤 𐑕𐑢𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑥.”

—𐑓𐑫𐑤𐑼𐑟 ·𐑐𐑮𐑴𐑓𐑱𐑯 𐑯 ·𐑣𐑴𐑤𐑦 ·𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑑.

“𐑕𐑴 𐑒𐑤𐑴𐑕 𐑚𐑦𐑣𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑦 𐑤𐑲

𐑞 𐑣𐑿𐑡 ·𐑤𐑩𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑔𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑑 𐑩𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑞𐑺 𐑐𐑮𐑱,

𐑯 𐑜𐑦𐑝 𐑯𐑴 𐑗𐑱𐑕, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑕𐑢𐑪𐑤𐑴 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑮𐑲,

𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑞𐑺 𐑜𐑱𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑡𐑷𐑟 𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑞 𐑢𐑱.”

—·𐑛𐑮𐑲𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑟 ·𐑨𐑯𐑩𐑕 ·𐑥𐑼𐑨𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑕

“𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑤𐑴𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑻𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐, 𐑞𐑱 𐑒𐑳𐑑 𐑪𐑓 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑧𐑛, 𐑯 𐑑𐑴 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑚𐑴𐑑 𐑨𐑟 𐑯𐑽 𐑞 𐑖𐑹 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑒𐑳𐑥; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑚𐑰 𐑩𐑜𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑑𐑢𐑧𐑤𐑝 𐑹 𐑔𐑻𐑑𐑰𐑯 𐑓𐑰𐑑 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼.”

—·𐑑𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑕 ·𐑧𐑡𐑩𐑟 ·𐑑𐑧𐑯 ·𐑝𐑶𐑦𐑡𐑩𐑟 𐑑 ·𐑕𐑐𐑦𐑑𐑕𐑚𐑼𐑜𐑩𐑯, 𐑦𐑯 ·𐑐𐑻𐑗𐑩𐑟.

“𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑢𐑱 𐑞𐑱 𐑕𐑷 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑕𐑐𐑹𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯, 𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑢𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑓𐑳𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑳𐑐 𐑞 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑞𐑺 𐑐𐑲𐑐𐑕 𐑯 𐑝𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑕, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑯𐑱𐑗𐑼 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕𐑑 𐑪𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑖𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑼𐑟.”

—𐑕𐑻 T. 𐑣𐑻𐑚𐑼𐑑𐑕 ·𐑝𐑶𐑦𐑡𐑩𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 ·𐑱𐑖𐑩 𐑯 ·𐑨𐑓𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑩. ·𐑣𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑕 ·𐑒𐑪𐑤.

“𐑣𐑽 𐑞𐑱 𐑕𐑷 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑣𐑿𐑡 𐑑𐑮𐑵𐑐𐑕 𐑝 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑱 𐑢𐑻 𐑓𐑹𐑕𐑑 𐑑 𐑐𐑮𐑴𐑕𐑰𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑛𐑰𐑤 𐑝 𐑒𐑷𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑓 𐑓𐑽 𐑞𐑱 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑮𐑳𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞𐑧𐑥.”

—·𐑖𐑬𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑟 ·𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑔 ·𐑕𐑻𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑯𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑜𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯.

“𐑢𐑰 𐑕𐑧𐑑 𐑕𐑱𐑤 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 ·𐑧𐑤𐑚𐑩, 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛 N.E. 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑒𐑷𐑤𐑛 𐑞 ·𐑡𐑴𐑯𐑩𐑕-𐑦𐑯-𐑞-·𐑢𐑱𐑤.... 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑕𐑱 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑒𐑭𐑯𐑑 𐑴𐑐𐑩𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑥𐑬𐑔, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑩 𐑓𐑱𐑚𐑩𐑤.... 𐑞𐑱 𐑓𐑮𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑤𐑲𐑥 𐑳𐑐 𐑞 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑕 𐑑 𐑕𐑰 𐑢𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑞𐑱 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑕𐑰 𐑩 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑓 𐑞 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑳𐑝𐑼𐑼 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑩 𐑛𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑑 𐑓 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑐𐑱𐑯𐑟.... 𐑲 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑑𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑝 𐑩 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑯𐑽 ·𐑖𐑧𐑑𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑩𐑚𐑳𐑝 𐑩 𐑚𐑨𐑮𐑩𐑤 𐑝 𐑣𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑧𐑤𐑦.... 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑝 𐑬𐑼 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑽𐑟 𐑑𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑥𐑰 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑰 𐑒𐑷𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑕 𐑩 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑦𐑯 ·𐑕𐑐𐑦𐑑𐑕𐑚𐑼𐑜𐑩𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑢𐑲𐑑 𐑷𐑤 𐑴𐑝𐑼.”

—𐑩 ·𐑝𐑶𐑦𐑡 𐑑 ·𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑯𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛, ⸰𐑱𐑛 1671.·𐑣𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑕 ·𐑒𐑪𐑤.

“𐑕𐑧𐑝𐑼𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑒𐑳𐑥 𐑦𐑯 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑒𐑴𐑕𐑑 (·𐑓𐑲𐑓) ·𐑭𐑯𐑴 1652, 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑱𐑑𐑦 𐑓𐑰𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑤𐑧𐑙𐑔 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤-𐑚𐑴𐑯 𐑒𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑒𐑱𐑥 𐑦𐑯, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 (𐑨𐑟 𐑲 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑓𐑹𐑥𐑛), 𐑚𐑦𐑕𐑲𐑛𐑟 𐑩 𐑝𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑝 𐑶𐑤, 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑩𐑓𐑹𐑛 500 𐑢𐑱𐑑 𐑝 𐑚𐑩𐑤𐑰𐑯. 𐑞 𐑡𐑷𐑟 𐑝 𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑓 𐑩 𐑜𐑱𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑜𐑸𐑛𐑩𐑯 𐑝 ·𐑐𐑦𐑑𐑓𐑧𐑮𐑩𐑯.”

—·𐑕𐑦𐑚𐑨𐑤𐑑𐑕 ·𐑓𐑲𐑓 𐑯 ·𐑒𐑦𐑯𐑮𐑪𐑕.

“𐑥𐑲𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑩𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑛 𐑑 𐑑𐑮𐑲 𐑢𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑲 𐑒𐑨𐑯 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑𐑼 𐑯 𐑒𐑦𐑤 𐑞𐑦𐑕 ·𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥𐑩-·𐑕𐑰𐑑𐑲 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑓 𐑲 𐑒𐑫𐑛 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑣𐑽 𐑝 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑹𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑒𐑦𐑤𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑥𐑨𐑯, 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑽𐑕𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑯 𐑕𐑢𐑦𐑓𐑑𐑯𐑩𐑕.”

—·𐑮𐑦𐑗𐑼𐑛 ·𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑓𐑼𐑛𐑟 ·𐑤𐑧𐑑𐑼 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 ·𐑚𐑼𐑥𐑿𐑛𐑩𐑟. 𐑓𐑦𐑤. 𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑟. ⸰𐑱𐑛 1668.

“𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑰 ·𐑜𐑪𐑛𐑟 𐑝𐑶𐑕 𐑴𐑚𐑱.”

—N. 𐑰. 𐑐𐑮𐑲𐑥𐑼.

“𐑢𐑰 𐑕𐑷 𐑷𐑤𐑕𐑴 𐑩𐑚𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑝 𐑤𐑸𐑡 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟, 𐑞𐑺 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑥𐑹 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑕𐑳𐑞𐑼𐑯 𐑕𐑰𐑟, 𐑨𐑟 𐑲 𐑥𐑱 𐑕𐑱, 𐑚𐑲 𐑩 𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑛 𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯; 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑢𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑓 𐑑 𐑞 𐑯𐑹𐑔𐑢𐑼𐑛 𐑝 𐑳𐑕.”

—𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯 ·𐑒𐑬𐑤𐑰𐑟 ·𐑝𐑶𐑦𐑡 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑞 ·𐑜𐑤𐑴𐑚, ⸰𐑱𐑛 1729.

“... 𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑮𐑧𐑔 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑦𐑟 𐑓𐑮𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑩𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑗 𐑩𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑐𐑹𐑑𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑥𐑧𐑤, 𐑨𐑟 𐑑 𐑚𐑮𐑦𐑙 𐑪𐑯 𐑩 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑹𐑛𐑼 𐑝 𐑞 𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑯.”

—·𐑵𐑘𐑴𐑟 ·𐑕𐑬𐑔 ·𐑩𐑥𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑩.

“𐑑 𐑓𐑦𐑓𐑑𐑦 𐑗𐑴𐑟𐑩𐑯 𐑕𐑦𐑤𐑓𐑕 𐑝 𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑤 𐑯𐑴𐑑,

𐑢𐑰 𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑞 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑹𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑗𐑸𐑡, 𐑞 𐑐𐑧𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑴𐑑.

𐑪𐑓𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑢𐑰 𐑯𐑴𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑯-𐑓𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑓𐑧𐑯𐑕 𐑑 𐑓𐑱𐑤,

·𐑞𐑴 𐑕𐑑𐑳𐑓𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑵𐑐𐑕 𐑯 𐑸𐑥𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑮𐑦𐑚𐑟 𐑝 𐑢𐑱𐑤.”

—𐑮𐑱𐑐 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑤𐑪𐑒

“𐑦𐑓 𐑢𐑰 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑺 𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑥𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑒𐑑 𐑑 𐑥𐑨𐑜𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑿𐑛, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑳𐑐 𐑞𐑺 𐑩𐑚𐑴𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑛𐑰𐑐, 𐑢𐑰 𐑖𐑨𐑤 𐑓𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑞𐑱 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑩𐑐𐑽 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑧𐑥𐑐𐑑𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑩𐑯. 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑦𐑟 𐑛𐑬𐑑𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑞 𐑤𐑸𐑡𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑥𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯.”

—𐑜𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑕𐑥𐑦𐑔, ·𐑯𐑨𐑑. 𐑣𐑦𐑕𐑑.

“𐑦𐑓 𐑿 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑮𐑲𐑑 𐑩 𐑓𐑱𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑓 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑟, 𐑿 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑥𐑱𐑒 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑒 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟.”

—𐑜𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑕𐑥𐑦𐑔 𐑑 ·𐑡𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑯.

“𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼𐑯𐑵𐑯 𐑢𐑰 𐑕𐑷 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑩𐑐𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑩 𐑮𐑪𐑒, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑩 𐑛𐑧𐑛 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑕𐑳𐑥 ·𐑱𐑠𐑦𐑨𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑕 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑒𐑦𐑤𐑛, 𐑯 𐑢𐑻 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑑𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑩𐑖𐑹. 𐑞𐑱 𐑕𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑑 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑰𐑤 𐑞𐑧𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑝𐑟 𐑚𐑦𐑣𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑦𐑯 𐑹𐑛𐑼 𐑑 𐑩𐑝𐑶𐑛 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑰𐑯 𐑚𐑲 𐑳𐑕.”

—𐑒𐑫𐑒𐑕 ·𐑝𐑶𐑦𐑡𐑩𐑟.

“𐑞 𐑤𐑸𐑡𐑼 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟, 𐑞𐑱 𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑛𐑩𐑥 𐑝𐑧𐑯𐑗𐑼 𐑑 𐑩𐑑𐑨𐑒. 𐑞𐑱 𐑕𐑑𐑨𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑕𐑴 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑛𐑮𐑧𐑛 𐑝 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑝 𐑞𐑧𐑥, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑬𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑰 𐑞𐑱 𐑸 𐑩𐑓𐑮𐑱𐑛 𐑑 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑰𐑝𐑩𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑯𐑱𐑥𐑟, 𐑯 𐑒𐑨𐑮𐑦 𐑛𐑳𐑙, 𐑤𐑲𐑥-𐑕𐑑𐑴𐑯, 𐑡𐑵𐑯𐑦𐑐𐑼-𐑢𐑫𐑛, 𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑸𐑑𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑯𐑱𐑗𐑼 𐑦𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕, 𐑦𐑯 𐑹𐑛𐑼 𐑑 𐑑𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑓𐑲 𐑯 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑝𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑞𐑺 𐑑𐑵 𐑯𐑽 𐑩𐑐𐑮𐑴𐑗.”

—𐑵𐑯𐑴 ·𐑝𐑪𐑯 ·𐑑𐑮𐑶𐑤𐑟 ·𐑤𐑧𐑑𐑼𐑟 𐑪𐑯 ·𐑚𐑨𐑙𐑒𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑯 ·𐑕𐑴𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑟 ·𐑝𐑶𐑦𐑡 𐑑 ·𐑲𐑕𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑦𐑯 1772.

“𐑞 ·𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥𐑩𐑕𐑧𐑑𐑦 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 ·𐑯𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑳𐑒𐑴𐑦𐑕, 𐑦𐑟 𐑩𐑯 𐑨𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑝, 𐑓𐑽𐑕 𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑥𐑩𐑤, 𐑯 𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑢𐑲𐑼𐑟 𐑝𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑩𐑛𐑮𐑧𐑕 𐑯 𐑚𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑯𐑩𐑕 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑼𐑥𐑧𐑯.”

—·𐑑𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑕 ·𐑡𐑧𐑓𐑼𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑟 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤 ·𐑥𐑩𐑥𐑹𐑾𐑤 𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑯𐑗 𐑥𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑼 𐑦𐑯 1778.

“𐑯 𐑐𐑮𐑱, 𐑕𐑻, 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛 𐑦𐑟 𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑩𐑤 𐑑 𐑦𐑑?”

—·𐑧𐑛𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑛 ·𐑚𐑻𐑒𐑕 𐑮𐑧𐑓𐑼𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑦𐑯 ·𐑐𐑸𐑤𐑩𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑯𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑑 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤-·𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑼𐑦.

“𐑕𐑐𐑱𐑯—𐑩 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑖𐑹𐑟 𐑝 ·𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑩𐑐.”

—·𐑧𐑛𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑛 ·𐑚𐑻𐑒. (𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑢𐑺.)

“𐑩 𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑔 𐑚𐑮𐑭𐑯𐑗 𐑝 𐑞 𐑒𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑹𐑛𐑦𐑯𐑼𐑦 𐑮𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑯𐑿, 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑜𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑼𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑜𐑸𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑯 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑑𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑕𐑰𐑟 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑐𐑲𐑮𐑩𐑑𐑕 𐑯 𐑮𐑪𐑚𐑼𐑟, 𐑦𐑟 𐑞 𐑮𐑲𐑑 𐑑 𐑮𐑶𐑩𐑤 𐑓𐑦𐑖, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑸 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑻𐑡𐑩𐑯. 𐑯 𐑞𐑰𐑟, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑲𐑞𐑼 𐑔𐑮𐑴𐑯 𐑩𐑖𐑹 𐑹 𐑒𐑷𐑑 𐑯𐑽 𐑞 𐑒𐑴𐑕𐑑, 𐑸 𐑞 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑐𐑼𐑑𐑦 𐑝 𐑞 𐑒𐑦𐑙.”

—𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑴𐑯.

“𐑕𐑵𐑯 𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑹𐑑 𐑝 𐑛𐑧𐑔 𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑵𐑟 𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑺:

·𐑮𐑪𐑛𐑥𐑪𐑯𐑛 𐑳𐑯𐑻𐑦𐑙 𐑴𐑼 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑕𐑩𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑟

𐑞 𐑚𐑸𐑚𐑛 𐑕𐑑𐑰𐑤, 𐑯 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑑𐑻𐑯 𐑩𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑟.”

—𐑓𐑷𐑤𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑼𐑟 ·𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑒.

“𐑚𐑮𐑲𐑑 𐑖𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑮𐑵𐑓𐑕, 𐑞 𐑛𐑴𐑥𐑟, 𐑞 𐑕𐑐𐑲𐑼𐑟,

𐑯 𐑮𐑪𐑒𐑩𐑑𐑕 𐑚𐑤𐑵 𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑛𐑮𐑦𐑝𐑩𐑯,

𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑙 𐑞𐑺 𐑥𐑴𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑦 𐑓𐑲𐑼

·𐑼𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑞 𐑝𐑷𐑤𐑑 𐑝 𐑣𐑧𐑝𐑩𐑯.

“𐑕𐑴 𐑓𐑲𐑼 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼 𐑑 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑐𐑺,

𐑞 𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑕𐑻𐑝𐑟 𐑪𐑯 𐑣𐑲,

𐑳𐑐-𐑕𐑐𐑬𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑩 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑺,

𐑑 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑕 𐑳𐑯𐑢𐑰𐑤𐑛𐑦 𐑡𐑶.”

—·𐑒𐑵𐑐𐑼, 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑒𐑢𐑰𐑯𐑟 ·𐑝𐑦𐑟𐑦𐑑 𐑑 ·𐑤𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑯.

“𐑑𐑧𐑯 𐑹 𐑓𐑦𐑓𐑑𐑰𐑯 𐑜𐑨𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑝 𐑚𐑤𐑳𐑛 𐑸 𐑔𐑮𐑴𐑯 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑣𐑸𐑑 𐑨𐑑 𐑩 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑴𐑒, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑦𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑕 𐑝𐑦𐑤𐑪𐑕𐑦𐑑𐑦.”

—𐑡𐑪𐑯 ·𐑣𐑳𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑟 𐑩𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑧𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑩 𐑢𐑱𐑤. (𐑩 𐑕𐑥𐑷𐑤 𐑕𐑲𐑟𐑛 𐑢𐑳𐑯.)

“𐑞 𐑱𐑹𐑑𐑩 𐑝 𐑩 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑦𐑟 𐑤𐑸𐑡𐑼 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑹 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑞 𐑥𐑱𐑯 𐑐𐑲𐑐 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼-𐑢𐑻𐑒𐑕 𐑨𐑑 ·𐑤𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑯 ·𐑚𐑮𐑦𐑡, 𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼 𐑮𐑹𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑐𐑨𐑕𐑦𐑡 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑐𐑲𐑐 𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑓𐑽𐑽 𐑦𐑯 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑕 𐑯 𐑝𐑦𐑤𐑪𐑕𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑑 𐑞 𐑚𐑤𐑳𐑛 𐑜𐑳𐑖𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑣𐑸𐑑.”

—𐑐𐑱𐑤𐑰𐑟 ·𐑔𐑦𐑪𐑤𐑩𐑡𐑦.

“𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑦𐑟 𐑩 𐑥𐑨𐑥𐑦𐑓𐑼𐑩𐑕 𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑥𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑 𐑣𐑲𐑯𐑛 𐑓𐑰𐑑.”

—𐑚𐑨𐑮𐑩𐑯 ·𐑒𐑿𐑝𐑽.

“𐑦𐑯 40 𐑛𐑦𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑟 𐑕𐑬𐑔, 𐑢𐑰 𐑕𐑷 ·𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥𐑩𐑕𐑧𐑑𐑦 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑞 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑝 𐑥𐑱, 𐑞 𐑕𐑰 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑒𐑳𐑝𐑼𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞𐑧𐑥.”

—·𐑒𐑴𐑯𐑧𐑑𐑕 ·𐑝𐑶𐑦𐑡 𐑓 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑻𐑐𐑩𐑕 𐑝 ·𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥𐑩𐑕𐑧𐑑𐑦 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤 ·𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑼𐑦.

“𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑮𐑰 𐑧𐑤𐑦𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑯𐑰𐑔 𐑥𐑰 𐑕𐑢𐑨𐑥,

·𐑓𐑤𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑛 𐑯 𐑛𐑲𐑝𐑛, 𐑦𐑯 𐑐𐑤𐑱, 𐑦𐑯 ·𐑗𐑱𐑕, 𐑦𐑯 𐑚𐑨𐑑𐑩𐑤,

·𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑟 𐑝 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑒𐑳𐑤𐑼, 𐑓𐑹𐑥, 𐑯 𐑒𐑲𐑯𐑛;

𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑤𐑨𐑙𐑜𐑢𐑦𐑡 𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑐𐑱𐑯𐑑, 𐑯 𐑥𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑯𐑼

·𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑕𐑰𐑯; 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑛𐑮𐑧𐑛 ·𐑤𐑩𐑝𐑲𐑩𐑔𐑩𐑯

𐑑 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑧𐑒𐑑 𐑥𐑦𐑤𐑾𐑯𐑟 𐑐𐑰𐑐𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑢𐑱𐑝:

𐑜𐑨𐑞𐑼𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑖𐑴𐑤𐑟 𐑦𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑕, 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑓𐑤𐑴𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛𐑟,

·𐑤𐑧𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑽𐑾𐑕 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙𐑒𐑑𐑕 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑕𐑑

𐑯 𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑒𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑮𐑰𐑡𐑩𐑯, 𐑞𐑴 𐑪𐑯 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑕𐑲𐑛

·𐑩𐑕𐑷𐑤𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑝𐑼𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑕 𐑧𐑯𐑩𐑥𐑦𐑟,

·𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟, 𐑖𐑸𐑒𐑕, 𐑯 𐑥𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑟, 𐑸𐑥𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑳𐑯𐑑 𐑹 𐑡𐑷,

𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑕𐑹𐑛𐑟, 𐑕𐑷𐑟, 𐑕𐑐𐑲𐑮𐑩𐑤 𐑣𐑹𐑯𐑟, 𐑹 𐑣𐑫𐑒𐑑 𐑓𐑨𐑙𐑟.”

—𐑥𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑜𐑪𐑥𐑼𐑰𐑟 ·𐑢𐑻𐑤𐑛 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑞 ·𐑓𐑤𐑳𐑛.

“·𐑲𐑴!  𐑐𐑾𐑯!  ·𐑲𐑴! 𐑕𐑦𐑙.

𐑑 𐑞 𐑓𐑦𐑯𐑦 𐑐𐑰𐑐𐑩𐑤𐑟 𐑒𐑦𐑙.

𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑩 𐑥𐑲𐑑𐑽 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑞𐑦𐑕

𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑝𐑭𐑕𐑑 ·𐑩𐑑𐑤𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑒 𐑦𐑟;

𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑩 𐑓𐑨𐑑𐑼 𐑓𐑦𐑖 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑣𐑰,

·𐑓𐑤𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑟 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑴𐑤𐑼 ·𐑕𐑰.”

—·𐑗𐑸𐑤𐑟 ·𐑤𐑨𐑥𐑟 ·𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑳𐑥𐑓 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤.

“𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑘𐑽 1690 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑐𐑻𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑪𐑯 𐑩 𐑣𐑲 𐑣𐑦𐑤 𐑩𐑚𐑟𐑻𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑕𐑐𐑬𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑯 𐑕𐑐𐑹𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑰𐑗 𐑳𐑞𐑼, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑩𐑚𐑟𐑻𐑝𐑛: 𐑞𐑺—𐑐𐑶𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑞 𐑕𐑰—𐑦𐑟 𐑩 𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑯 𐑐𐑭𐑕𐑗𐑼 𐑢𐑺 𐑬𐑼 𐑗𐑦𐑤𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑜𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑛-𐑗𐑦𐑤𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑜𐑴 𐑓 𐑚𐑮𐑧𐑛.”

—·𐑴𐑚𐑩𐑛 ·𐑥𐑱𐑕𐑰𐑟 ·𐑣𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑦 𐑝 ·𐑯𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑑.

“𐑲 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑑 𐑩 𐑒𐑪𐑑𐑦𐑡 𐑓 ·𐑕𐑵𐑟𐑩𐑯 𐑯 𐑥𐑲𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑯 𐑥𐑱𐑛 𐑩 𐑜𐑱𐑑𐑢𐑱 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑹𐑥 𐑝 𐑩 ·𐑜𐑪𐑔𐑦𐑒 ·𐑸𐑗, 𐑚𐑲 𐑕𐑧𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑳𐑐 𐑩 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑡𐑷 𐑚𐑴𐑯𐑟.”

—𐑣𐑷𐑔𐑹𐑯𐑟 ·𐑑𐑢𐑲𐑕 ·𐑑𐑴𐑤𐑛 ·𐑑𐑱𐑤𐑟.

“𐑖𐑰 𐑒𐑱𐑥 𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑒 𐑩 𐑥𐑪𐑯𐑿𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑓 𐑣𐑻 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑤𐑳𐑝, 𐑣𐑵 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑒𐑦𐑤𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑩 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑩𐑕𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑒 𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯, 𐑯𐑴 𐑤𐑧𐑕 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑓𐑹𐑑𐑦 𐑘𐑽𐑟 𐑩𐑜𐑴.”

—𐑦𐑚𐑦𐑛.

“𐑯𐑴, ·𐑕𐑻, 𐑑𐑦𐑟 𐑩 ·𐑮𐑲𐑑 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤,” 𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑼𐑛 ·𐑑𐑪𐑥; “𐑲 𐑕𐑷 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑬𐑑; 𐑣𐑰 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑳𐑐 𐑩 𐑐𐑺 𐑝 𐑨𐑟 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑮𐑱𐑯𐑚𐑴𐑟 𐑨𐑟 𐑩 ·𐑒𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑗𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑖 𐑑 𐑤𐑫𐑒 𐑨𐑑 𐑣𐑰𐑟 𐑩 ·𐑮𐑭𐑤 𐑶𐑤-𐑚𐑳𐑑, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑓𐑧𐑤𐑴!”

—𐑒𐑵𐑐𐑼𐑟 ·𐑐𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑑.

“𐑞 𐑐𐑱𐑐𐑼𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑚𐑮𐑷𐑑 𐑦𐑯, 𐑯 𐑢𐑰 𐑕𐑷 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑚𐑼𐑤𐑦𐑯 ·𐑜𐑩𐑟𐑧𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑩𐑛𐑿𐑕𐑑 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑑𐑱𐑡 𐑞𐑺.”

—·𐑧𐑒𐑼𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑟 ·𐑒𐑪𐑯𐑝𐑼𐑕𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑢𐑦𐑞 ·𐑜𐑻𐑑𐑩.

“𐑥𐑲 ·𐑜𐑪𐑛! ·𐑥𐑼 ·𐑗𐑱𐑕, 𐑢𐑪𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑞 𐑥𐑨𐑑𐑼?” 𐑲 𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑼𐑛, “𐑢𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑴𐑝 𐑚𐑲 𐑩 𐑢𐑱𐑤.”

—“𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑑𐑦𐑝 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑒 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤 ·𐑖𐑦𐑐 ·𐑧𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑕 𐑝 ·𐑯𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑑, 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑩𐑑𐑨𐑒𐑑 𐑯 𐑓𐑲𐑯𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑶𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑩 𐑤𐑸𐑡 ·𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑩𐑕𐑦𐑓𐑦𐑒 ·𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯.” 𐑚𐑲 ·𐑴𐑢𐑧𐑯 ·𐑗𐑱𐑕 𐑝 ·𐑯𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑑, 𐑓𐑻𐑕𐑑 𐑥𐑱𐑑 𐑝 𐑕𐑧𐑛 𐑝𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑤. 𐑯𐑿 ·𐑘𐑹𐑒, 1821.

“𐑩 𐑥𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑯𐑼 𐑕𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑖𐑮𐑬𐑛𐑟 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑯𐑲𐑑,

𐑞 𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑛 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑐𐑲𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑓𐑮𐑰;

𐑯𐑬 𐑚𐑮𐑲𐑑, 𐑯𐑬 𐑛𐑦𐑥𐑛, 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞 𐑥𐑵𐑯𐑤𐑲𐑑 𐑐𐑱𐑤,

𐑯 𐑞 𐑓𐑪𐑕𐑓𐑼 𐑜𐑤𐑰𐑥𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑒 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤,

𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑑 𐑓𐑤𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑼𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑰.”

—·𐑦𐑤𐑦𐑟𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑔 ·𐑴𐑒𐑕 ·𐑕𐑥𐑦𐑔.

“𐑞 𐑒𐑢𐑪𐑯𐑑𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑝 𐑤𐑲𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑛𐑮𐑷𐑯 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕 𐑦𐑯𐑜𐑱𐑡𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑗𐑼 𐑝 𐑞𐑦𐑕 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑩𐑥𐑬𐑯𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑷𐑤𐑑𐑩𐑜𐑧𐑞𐑼 𐑑 10,440 𐑘𐑸𐑛𐑟 𐑹 𐑯𐑽𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑦𐑒𐑕 ·𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑤𐑦𐑖 𐑥𐑲𐑤𐑟....

“𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑖𐑱𐑒𐑕 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑑𐑮𐑦𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑕 𐑑𐑱𐑤 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑺, 𐑢𐑦𐑗, 𐑒𐑮𐑨𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩 𐑢𐑦𐑐, 𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑟 𐑑 𐑞 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑝 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑹 𐑓𐑹 𐑥𐑲𐑤𐑟.”

—𐑕𐑒𐑹𐑟𐑚𐑦.

“𐑥𐑨𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑨𐑜𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑻𐑟 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑖 𐑩𐑑𐑨𐑒𐑕, 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑓𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑦𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 ·𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑮𐑴𐑤𐑟 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑯 𐑴𐑝𐑼; 𐑣𐑰 𐑮𐑽𐑟 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑹𐑥𐑩𐑕 𐑣𐑧𐑛, 𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑢𐑲𐑛 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑡𐑷𐑟 𐑕𐑯𐑨𐑐𐑕 𐑨𐑑 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦𐑔𐑦𐑙 𐑼𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥; 𐑣𐑰 𐑮𐑳𐑖𐑩𐑟 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑧𐑛; 𐑞𐑱 𐑸 𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑐𐑧𐑤𐑛 𐑚𐑦𐑓𐑹 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑝𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑕𐑢𐑦𐑓𐑑𐑯𐑩𐑕, 𐑯 𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑑𐑲𐑥𐑟 𐑳𐑑𐑼𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑶𐑛.... 𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑩 𐑥𐑨𐑑𐑼 𐑝 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑩𐑕𐑑𐑪𐑯𐑦𐑖𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑛𐑼𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑣𐑨𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑕𐑴 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑩𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑙, 𐑯, 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑻𐑖𐑩𐑤 𐑐𐑶𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑝𐑿, 𐑕𐑴 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑹𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑩𐑯 𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑥𐑩𐑤 (𐑨𐑟 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤) 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑕𐑴 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑲𐑼𐑤𐑦 𐑯𐑦𐑜𐑤𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑩𐑛, 𐑹 𐑖𐑵𐑛 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑕𐑴 𐑤𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑒𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑦𐑪𐑕𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑞 𐑯𐑿𐑥𐑼𐑩𐑕, 𐑯 𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑝 𐑞𐑧𐑥 𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑐𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑩𐑚𐑟𐑻𐑝𐑼𐑟, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑝 𐑤𐑱𐑑 𐑘𐑽𐑟, 𐑥𐑳𐑕𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑐𐑩𐑟𐑧𐑕𐑑 𐑞 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑩𐑚𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑯 𐑞 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑝𐑰𐑯𐑾𐑯𐑑 𐑪𐑐𐑼𐑑𐑿𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑦𐑟 𐑝 𐑢𐑦𐑑𐑯𐑩𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑺 𐑣𐑨𐑚𐑦𐑑𐑿𐑛𐑟.”

—·𐑑𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑕 ·𐑚𐑦𐑱𐑤𐑟 ·𐑣𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑦 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤, 1839.

“𐑞 ·𐑒𐑨𐑖𐑩𐑤𐑪𐑑” (𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤) “𐑦𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑧𐑑𐑼 𐑸𐑥𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑑𐑮𐑵 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤” (𐑜𐑮𐑰𐑯𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑹 ·𐑮𐑲𐑑 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤) “𐑦𐑯 𐑐𐑩𐑟𐑧𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑩 𐑓𐑹𐑥𐑦𐑛𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑧𐑐𐑩𐑯 𐑨𐑑 𐑲𐑞𐑼 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑧𐑥𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑝 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑚𐑪𐑛𐑦, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑷𐑤𐑕𐑴 𐑥𐑹 𐑓𐑮𐑰𐑒𐑢𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑟 𐑩 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑐𐑩𐑟𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑑 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑤𐑶 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑢𐑧𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑩𐑓𐑧𐑯𐑕𐑦𐑝𐑤𐑦 𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑨𐑯𐑼 𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑕 𐑕𐑴 𐑸𐑑𐑓𐑩𐑤, 𐑚𐑴𐑤𐑛, 𐑯 𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑗𐑦𐑝𐑩𐑕, 𐑨𐑟 𐑑 𐑤𐑰𐑛 𐑑 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑮𐑦𐑜𐑸𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑨𐑟 𐑞 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑛𐑱𐑯𐑡𐑼𐑩𐑕 𐑑 𐑩𐑑𐑨𐑒 𐑝 𐑷𐑤 𐑞 𐑯𐑴𐑯 𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑖𐑰𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑚.”

—·𐑓𐑮𐑧𐑛𐑼𐑦𐑒 ·𐑛𐑧𐑚𐑧𐑤 ·𐑚𐑧𐑯𐑩𐑑𐑕 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙 ·𐑝𐑶𐑦𐑡 ·𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑞 ·𐑜𐑤𐑴𐑚, 1840.

𐑪𐑒𐑑𐑴𐑚𐑼 13.  “𐑞𐑺 𐑖𐑰 𐑚𐑤𐑴𐑟,” 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑕𐑳𐑙 𐑬𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑-𐑣𐑧𐑛.

“𐑢𐑺 𐑩𐑢𐑱?” 𐑛𐑦𐑥𐑭𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑞 𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑦𐑯.

“𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑐𐑶𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑪𐑓 𐑞 𐑤𐑰 𐑚𐑬, 𐑕𐑻.”

“𐑮𐑱𐑟 𐑳𐑐 𐑘𐑹 𐑢𐑰𐑤.  𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑛𐑦!”  “𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑛𐑦, 𐑕𐑻.”

“𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑-𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑩𐑣𐑶!  𐑛𐑵 𐑿 𐑕𐑰 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑯𐑬?”

“𐑲 𐑲, 𐑕𐑻!  𐑩 𐑖𐑴𐑤 𐑝 ·𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟!  𐑞𐑺 𐑖𐑰 𐑚𐑤𐑴𐑟!  𐑞𐑺 𐑖𐑰

𐑚𐑮𐑰𐑗𐑩𐑟!”

“𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑬𐑑! 𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑬𐑑 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑑𐑲𐑥!”

“𐑲 ·𐑲, 𐑕𐑻!  𐑞𐑺 𐑖𐑰 𐑚𐑤𐑴𐑟! 𐑞𐑺—𐑞𐑺—𐑞𐑸 𐑖𐑰

𐑚𐑤𐑴𐑟—·𐑚𐑴𐑟—𐑚𐑴-𐑴-·𐑴𐑕!”

“𐑣𐑬 𐑓𐑸 𐑪𐑓?”

“𐑑𐑵 𐑥𐑲𐑤𐑟 𐑯 𐑩 𐑣𐑭𐑓.”

“𐑔𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑯 𐑤𐑲𐑑𐑯𐑦𐑙! 𐑕𐑴 𐑯𐑽!  𐑒𐑷𐑤 𐑷𐑤 𐑣𐑨𐑯𐑛𐑟.”

—J. ·𐑮𐑪𐑕 ·𐑚𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑟 ·𐑧𐑗𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑝 𐑩 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙 ·𐑒𐑮𐑵𐑟. 1846.

“𐑞 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤-𐑖𐑦𐑐 ·𐑜𐑤𐑴𐑚, 𐑪𐑯 𐑚𐑹𐑛 𐑝 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑝𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑤 𐑩𐑒𐑻𐑛 𐑞 𐑣𐑪𐑮𐑦𐑛 𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑯𐑟𐑨𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑢𐑰 𐑸 𐑩𐑚𐑬𐑑 𐑑 𐑮𐑦𐑤𐑱𐑑, 𐑚𐑦𐑤𐑪𐑙𐑛 𐑑 𐑞 𐑲𐑤𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑝 ·𐑯𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑑.”

—“𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑑𐑦𐑝 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑜𐑤𐑴𐑚 ·𐑥𐑿𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑦,” 𐑚𐑲 ·𐑤𐑱 𐑯 ·𐑣𐑳𐑕𐑦 𐑕𐑼𐑝𐑲𐑝𐑼𐑟. ⸰𐑱𐑛 1828.

𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑳𐑯𐑕 𐑐𐑼𐑕𐑿𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑩 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑢𐑵𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛, 𐑣𐑰 𐑐𐑨𐑮𐑦𐑛 𐑞 𐑩𐑕𐑷𐑤𐑑 𐑓 𐑕𐑳𐑥 𐑑𐑲𐑥 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑩 𐑤𐑭𐑯𐑕; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑞 𐑓𐑘𐑫𐑼𐑾𐑕 𐑥𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑼 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑧𐑙𐑔 𐑮𐑳𐑖𐑑 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑; 𐑣𐑦𐑥𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓 𐑯 𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑮𐑱𐑛𐑟 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑟𐑻𐑝𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑤𐑰𐑐𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑞𐑱 𐑕𐑷 𐑞 𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑧𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑦𐑑𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤.”

—𐑥𐑦𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑼𐑦 ·𐑡𐑻𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑝 ·𐑑𐑲𐑼𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑯 ·𐑚𐑧𐑯𐑩𐑑.

“·𐑯𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑑 𐑦𐑑𐑕𐑧𐑤𐑓,” 𐑕𐑧𐑛 ·𐑥𐑼 ·𐑢𐑧𐑚𐑕𐑑𐑼, “𐑦𐑟 𐑩 𐑝𐑧𐑮𐑦 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑯 𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑽 𐑐𐑹𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑯𐑨𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑼𐑩𐑕𐑑. 𐑞𐑺 𐑦𐑟 𐑩 𐑐𐑪𐑐𐑿𐑤𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑱𐑑 𐑹 𐑯𐑲𐑯 𐑔𐑬𐑟𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑐𐑻𐑕𐑩𐑯𐑟 𐑤𐑦𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑽 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑰, 𐑨𐑛𐑦𐑙 𐑤𐑸𐑡𐑤𐑦 𐑧𐑝𐑮𐑦 𐑘𐑽 𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑯𐑨𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑩𐑤 𐑢𐑧𐑤𐑔 𐑚𐑲 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑤𐑛𐑩𐑕𐑑 𐑯 𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑐𐑻𐑕𐑩𐑝𐑽𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑳𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑦.”

—𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑹𐑑 𐑝 ·𐑛𐑨𐑯𐑾𐑤 ·𐑢𐑧𐑚𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑟 ·𐑕𐑐𐑰𐑗 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 U. 𐑟. 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑩𐑑, 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑨𐑐𐑤𐑦𐑒𐑱𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑓 𐑞 ·𐑦𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑩 ·𐑚𐑮𐑱𐑒𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼 𐑨𐑑 ·𐑯𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑑. 1828.

“𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑓𐑧𐑤 𐑛𐑦𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑣𐑦𐑥, 𐑯 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑚𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑒𐑦𐑤𐑛 𐑣𐑦𐑥 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 𐑥𐑴𐑥𐑧𐑯𐑑.”

—“𐑞 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 ·𐑒𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼𐑟, 𐑹 𐑞 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑥𐑩𐑯𐑟 ·𐑩𐑛𐑝𐑧𐑯𐑗𐑼𐑟 𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟 ·𐑚𐑲𐑪𐑜𐑮𐑩𐑓𐑦, 𐑜𐑨𐑞𐑼𐑛 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑣𐑴𐑥𐑢𐑼𐑛 ·𐑒𐑮𐑵𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑩𐑛𐑹 ·𐑐𐑮𐑧𐑚𐑩𐑤.” 𐑚𐑲 ·𐑮𐑧𐑝 ·𐑣𐑧𐑯𐑮𐑦 T. ·𐑗𐑰𐑝𐑼.

“𐑦𐑓 𐑿 𐑥𐑱𐑒 𐑞 𐑤𐑰𐑕𐑑 𐑛𐑨𐑥 𐑚𐑦𐑑 𐑝 𐑯𐑶𐑟,” 𐑮𐑦𐑐𐑤𐑲𐑛 ·𐑕𐑨𐑥𐑿𐑩𐑤, “𐑲 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑛 𐑿 𐑑 𐑣𐑧𐑤.”

—𐑤𐑲𐑓 𐑝 ·𐑕𐑨𐑥𐑿𐑩𐑤 ·𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑕𐑑𐑪𐑒 (𐑞 𐑥𐑿𐑑𐑦𐑯𐑽), 𐑚𐑲 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑚𐑮𐑳𐑞𐑼, ·𐑢𐑦𐑤𐑾𐑥 ·𐑒𐑪𐑥𐑕𐑑𐑪𐑒. 𐑩𐑯𐑳𐑞𐑼 ·𐑝𐑻𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤-𐑖𐑦𐑐 ·𐑜𐑤𐑴𐑚 𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑑𐑦𐑝.

“𐑞 𐑝𐑶𐑦𐑡𐑩𐑟 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑛𐑳𐑗 𐑯 ·𐑦𐑙𐑜𐑤𐑦𐑖 𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑯𐑹𐑞𐑼𐑯 ·𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯, 𐑦𐑯 𐑹𐑛𐑼, 𐑦𐑓 𐑐𐑪𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤, 𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑳𐑝𐑼 𐑩 𐑐𐑨𐑕𐑦𐑡 𐑔𐑮𐑵 𐑦𐑑 𐑑 ·𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑾, 𐑞𐑴 𐑞𐑱 𐑓𐑱𐑤𐑛 𐑝 𐑞𐑺 𐑥𐑱𐑯 𐑪𐑚𐑡𐑧𐑒𐑑, 𐑤𐑱𐑛-𐑴𐑐𐑩𐑯 𐑞 𐑣𐑷𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤.”

—·𐑥𐑩𐑒𐑳𐑤𐑩𐑒𐑕 ·𐑒𐑩𐑥𐑻𐑖𐑩𐑤 ·𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯𐑼𐑦.

“𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑟 𐑸 𐑮𐑦𐑕𐑦𐑐𐑮𐑩𐑒𐑩𐑤; 𐑞 𐑚𐑷𐑤 𐑮𐑰𐑚𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑟, 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑑 𐑚𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑓𐑹𐑢𐑼𐑛 𐑩𐑜𐑱𐑯; 𐑓 𐑯𐑬 𐑦𐑯 𐑤𐑱𐑦𐑙 𐑴𐑐𐑩𐑯 𐑞 𐑣𐑷𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑝 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑕𐑰𐑥 𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑦𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑑𐑤𐑦 𐑣𐑦𐑑 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑯𐑿 𐑒𐑤𐑵𐑟 𐑑 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑱𐑥 𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑦𐑒 ·𐑯𐑹𐑔-·𐑢𐑧𐑕𐑑 ·𐑐𐑨𐑕𐑦𐑡.”

—𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 “𐑕𐑳𐑥𐑔𐑦𐑙” 𐑳𐑯𐑐𐑳𐑚𐑤𐑦𐑖𐑑.

“𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑦𐑥𐑐𐑪𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑑 𐑥𐑰𐑑 𐑩 𐑢𐑱𐑤-𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑬𐑑 𐑚𐑰𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑒 𐑚𐑲 𐑣𐑻 𐑯𐑽 𐑩𐑐𐑽𐑩𐑯𐑕. 𐑞 𐑝𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑤 𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑼 𐑖𐑹𐑑 𐑕𐑱𐑤, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑤𐑫𐑒-𐑬𐑑𐑕 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑥𐑭𐑕𐑑-𐑣𐑧𐑛𐑟, 𐑰𐑜𐑼𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑒𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑢𐑲𐑛 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑐𐑨𐑯𐑕 𐑼𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑞𐑧𐑥, 𐑣𐑨𐑟 𐑩 𐑑𐑴𐑑𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑛𐑦𐑓𐑼𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑺 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞𐑴𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑜𐑱𐑡𐑛 𐑦𐑯 𐑮𐑧𐑜𐑿𐑤𐑼 𐑝𐑶𐑦𐑡.”

—𐑒𐑳𐑮𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑕 𐑯 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙. U.S. ·𐑧𐑒𐑕. 𐑧𐑒𐑕.

“𐑐𐑦𐑛𐑧𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑾𐑯𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑝𐑦𐑕𐑦𐑯𐑦𐑑𐑦 𐑝 ·𐑤𐑳𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑯 𐑯 𐑧𐑤𐑕𐑢𐑺 𐑥𐑱 𐑮𐑧𐑒𐑩𐑤𐑧𐑒𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑰𐑯 𐑤𐑸𐑡 𐑒𐑻𐑝𐑛 𐑚𐑴𐑯𐑟 𐑕𐑧𐑑 𐑳𐑐𐑮𐑲𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑻𐑔, 𐑲𐑞𐑼 𐑑 𐑓𐑹𐑥 𐑸𐑗𐑩𐑟 𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑜𐑱𐑑𐑢𐑱𐑟, 𐑹 𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑩𐑟 𐑑 𐑨𐑤𐑒𐑴𐑝𐑟, 𐑯 𐑞𐑱 𐑥𐑱 𐑐𐑼𐑣𐑨𐑐𐑕 𐑣𐑨𐑝 𐑚𐑰𐑯 𐑑𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑢𐑻 𐑞 𐑮𐑦𐑚𐑟 𐑝 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟.”

—𐑑𐑱𐑤𐑟 𐑝 𐑩 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤 ·𐑝𐑶𐑦𐑡𐑼 𐑑 𐑞 ·𐑸𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑒 ·𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯.

“𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑯𐑪𐑑 𐑑𐑦𐑤 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑𐑕 𐑮𐑩𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑐𐑼𐑕𐑿𐑑 𐑝 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑢𐑲𐑑𐑕 𐑕𐑷 𐑞𐑺 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑦𐑯 𐑚𐑤𐑳𐑛𐑦 𐑐𐑩𐑟𐑧𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑡𐑩𐑟 𐑦𐑯𐑮𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑩𐑥𐑳𐑙 𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑵.”

—𐑯𐑿𐑟𐑐𐑱𐑐𐑼 ·𐑩𐑒𐑬𐑯𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑯 ·𐑮𐑰𐑑𐑱𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑞 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤-·𐑖𐑦𐑐 ·𐑣𐑴𐑚𐑩𐑥𐑨𐑒.

“𐑦𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑡𐑧𐑯𐑼𐑩𐑤𐑦 𐑢𐑧𐑤 𐑯𐑴𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑒𐑮𐑵𐑟 𐑝 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑝𐑧𐑕𐑩𐑤𐑟 (·𐑩𐑥𐑧𐑮𐑦𐑒𐑩𐑯) 𐑓𐑿 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑮𐑦𐑑𐑻𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑞 𐑖𐑦𐑐𐑕 𐑪𐑯 𐑚𐑹𐑛 𐑝 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑞𐑱 𐑛𐑦𐑐𐑸𐑑𐑩𐑛.”

—𐑒𐑮𐑵𐑟 𐑦𐑯 𐑩 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤 ·𐑚𐑴𐑑.

“𐑕𐑳𐑛𐑩𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑩 𐑥𐑲𐑑𐑦 𐑥𐑨𐑕 𐑦𐑥𐑻𐑡𐑛 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑢𐑷𐑑𐑼, 𐑯 𐑖𐑪𐑑 𐑳𐑐 𐑐𐑻𐑐𐑩𐑯𐑛𐑦𐑒𐑿𐑤𐑼𐑤𐑦 𐑦𐑯𐑑𐑵 𐑞 𐑺. 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤.”

—·𐑥𐑦𐑮𐑾𐑥 ·𐑒𐑪𐑓𐑦𐑯 𐑹 𐑞 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤 ·𐑓𐑦𐑖𐑼𐑥𐑩𐑯.

“𐑞 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑛 𐑑 𐑚𐑰 𐑖𐑫𐑼; 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑚𐑦𐑔𐑦𐑙𐑒 𐑿, 𐑣𐑬 𐑿 𐑢𐑫𐑛 𐑥𐑨𐑯𐑦𐑡 𐑩 𐑐𐑬𐑼𐑓𐑩𐑤 𐑳𐑯𐑚𐑮𐑴𐑒𐑩𐑯 𐑒𐑴𐑤𐑑, 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑞 𐑥𐑽 𐑩𐑐𐑤𐑲𐑩𐑯𐑕 𐑝 𐑩 𐑮𐑴𐑐 𐑑𐑲𐑛 𐑑 𐑞 𐑮𐑵𐑑 𐑝 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑑𐑱𐑤.”

—𐑩 ·𐑗𐑨𐑐𐑑𐑼 𐑪𐑯 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑯 ·𐑮𐑦𐑚𐑟 𐑯 ·𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑒𐑕.

“𐑪𐑯 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑩𐑒𐑱𐑠𐑩𐑯 𐑲 𐑕𐑷 𐑑𐑵 𐑝 𐑞𐑰𐑟 𐑥𐑪𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑼𐑟 (𐑢𐑱𐑤𐑟) 𐑐𐑮𐑪𐑚𐑩𐑚𐑤𐑦 𐑥𐑱𐑤 𐑯 𐑓𐑰𐑥𐑱𐑤, 𐑕𐑤𐑴𐑤𐑦 𐑕𐑢𐑦𐑥𐑦𐑙, 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑞 𐑳𐑞𐑼, 𐑢𐑦𐑞𐑦𐑯 𐑤𐑧𐑕 𐑞𐑨𐑯 𐑩 𐑕𐑑𐑴𐑯𐑟 𐑔𐑮𐑴 𐑝 𐑞 𐑖𐑹” (𐑑𐑧𐑮𐑩 ·𐑛𐑧𐑤 ·𐑓𐑢𐑱𐑜𐑴), “𐑴𐑝𐑼 𐑢𐑦𐑗 𐑞 𐑚𐑰𐑗 𐑑𐑮𐑰 𐑧𐑒𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑚𐑮𐑭𐑯𐑗𐑩𐑟.”

—·𐑛𐑸𐑢𐑦𐑯𐑟 ·𐑝𐑶𐑦𐑡 𐑝 𐑩 ·𐑯𐑨𐑗𐑼𐑩𐑤𐑦𐑕𐑑.

“'𐑕𐑑𐑻𐑯 𐑷𐑤!' 𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑒𐑤𐑱𐑥𐑛 𐑞 𐑥𐑱𐑑, 𐑨𐑟 𐑩𐑐𐑪𐑯 𐑑𐑻𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑣𐑧𐑛, 𐑣𐑰 𐑕𐑷 𐑞 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑯𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑡𐑷𐑟 𐑝 𐑩 𐑤𐑸𐑡 ·𐑕𐑐𐑻𐑥 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤 𐑒𐑤𐑴𐑟 𐑑 𐑞 𐑣𐑧𐑛 𐑝 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑑, 𐑔𐑮𐑧𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑑𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑳𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯;—'·𐑕𐑑𐑻𐑯 𐑷𐑤, 𐑓 𐑘𐑹 𐑤𐑲𐑝𐑟!'”

—·𐑢𐑹𐑑𐑩𐑯 𐑞 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤 ·𐑒𐑦𐑤𐑼.

“𐑕𐑴 𐑚𐑰 𐑗𐑽𐑦, 𐑥𐑲 𐑤𐑨𐑛𐑟, 𐑤𐑧𐑑 𐑘𐑹 𐑣𐑸𐑑𐑕 𐑯𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑓𐑱𐑤, ·𐑢𐑲𐑤 𐑞 𐑚𐑴𐑤𐑛 𐑣𐑸𐑐𐑵𐑯𐑽 𐑦𐑟 𐑕𐑑𐑮𐑲𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑞 𐑢𐑱𐑤!”

—·𐑯𐑨𐑯𐑑𐑳𐑒𐑩𐑑 ·𐑕𐑪𐑙.

“𐑴, 𐑞 𐑮𐑺 𐑴𐑤𐑛 ·𐑢𐑱𐑤, 𐑥𐑦𐑛 𐑕𐑑𐑹𐑥 𐑯 𐑜𐑱𐑤

𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑦𐑟 𐑴𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑣𐑴𐑥 𐑢𐑦𐑤 𐑚𐑰

𐑩 𐑡𐑲𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑥𐑲𐑑, 𐑢𐑺 𐑥𐑲𐑑 𐑦𐑟 𐑮𐑲𐑑,

𐑯 ·𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑝 𐑞 𐑚𐑬𐑯𐑛𐑤𐑩𐑕 𐑕𐑰.”

—𐑢𐑱𐑤 ·𐑕𐑪𐑙.

𐑧𐑐𐑦𐑤𐑪𐑜

“𐑯 𐑲 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑱𐑧𐑥 ·𐑦𐑕𐑒𐑱𐑐𐑑 ·𐑩𐑤𐑴𐑯 𐑑 ·𐑑𐑧𐑤 ·𐑞𐑰” 𐑡𐑪𐑚.

𐑞 𐑛𐑮𐑭𐑥𐑩'𐑟 𐑛𐑳𐑯. 𐑢𐑲 𐑞𐑧𐑯 𐑣𐑽 𐑛𐑳𐑟 𐑧𐑯𐑦 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑕𐑑𐑧𐑐 𐑓𐑹𐑔?—𐑚𐑦𐑒𐑪𐑟 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑕𐑼𐑝𐑲𐑝 𐑞 𐑮𐑧𐑒.

𐑦𐑑 𐑕𐑴 𐑗𐑭𐑯𐑕𐑑, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑞 ·𐑐𐑸𐑟𐑰'𐑟 𐑛𐑦𐑕𐑩𐑐𐑽𐑩𐑯𐑕, 𐑲 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑣𐑰 𐑣𐑵𐑥 𐑞 ·𐑓𐑱𐑑𐑕 𐑹𐑛𐑱𐑯𐑛 𐑑 𐑑𐑱𐑒 𐑞 𐑐𐑤𐑱𐑕 𐑝 ·𐑱𐑣𐑨𐑚'𐑟 𐑚𐑬𐑟𐑥𐑩𐑯, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑚𐑬𐑟𐑥𐑩𐑯 𐑩𐑕𐑿𐑥𐑛 𐑞 𐑝𐑱𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑 𐑐𐑴𐑕𐑑; 𐑞 𐑕𐑱𐑥, 𐑣𐑵, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑 𐑛𐑱 𐑞 𐑔𐑮𐑰 𐑥𐑧𐑯 𐑢𐑻 𐑑𐑪𐑕𐑑 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑬𐑑 𐑝 𐑞 𐑮𐑪𐑒𐑦𐑙 𐑚𐑴𐑑, 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑛𐑮𐑪𐑐𐑑 𐑩𐑕𐑑𐑻𐑯. 𐑕𐑴, 𐑓𐑤𐑴𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑥𐑸𐑡𐑦𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑦𐑯𐑕𐑿𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑰𐑯, 𐑯 𐑦𐑯 𐑓𐑫𐑤 𐑕𐑲𐑑 𐑝 𐑦𐑑, 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑞 𐑣𐑭𐑓𐑕𐑐𐑧𐑯𐑑 𐑕𐑳𐑒𐑖𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑞 𐑕𐑳𐑙𐑒 𐑖𐑦𐑐 𐑮𐑰𐑗𐑑 𐑥𐑰, 𐑲 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑚𐑳𐑑 𐑕𐑤𐑴𐑤𐑦, 𐑛𐑮𐑷𐑯 𐑑𐑩𐑢𐑹𐑛𐑟 𐑞 𐑒𐑤𐑴𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑝𐑹𐑑𐑧𐑒𐑕. 𐑢𐑧𐑯 𐑲 𐑮𐑰𐑗𐑑 𐑦𐑑, 𐑦𐑑 𐑣𐑨𐑛 𐑕𐑩𐑚𐑕𐑲𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑑 𐑩 𐑒𐑮𐑰𐑥𐑦 𐑐𐑵𐑤. 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑯 𐑮𐑬𐑯𐑛, 𐑞𐑧𐑯, 𐑯 𐑧𐑝𐑼 𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑑𐑮𐑨𐑒𐑑𐑦𐑙 𐑑𐑩𐑢𐑹𐑛𐑟 𐑞 𐑚𐑳𐑑𐑩𐑯-𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑒 𐑚𐑳𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑨𐑑 𐑞 𐑨𐑒𐑕𐑦𐑕 𐑝 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑕𐑤𐑴𐑤𐑦 𐑢𐑰𐑤𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑻𐑒𐑩𐑤, 𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑩𐑯𐑳𐑞𐑼 ·𐑦𐑒𐑕𐑦𐑩𐑯 𐑲 𐑛𐑦𐑛 𐑮𐑦𐑝𐑪𐑤𐑝. 𐑑𐑦𐑤, 𐑜𐑱𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑝𐑲𐑑𐑩𐑤 𐑕𐑧𐑯𐑑𐑼, 𐑞 𐑚𐑤𐑨𐑒 𐑚𐑳𐑚𐑩𐑤 𐑳𐑐𐑢𐑼𐑛 𐑚𐑻𐑕𐑑; 𐑯 𐑯𐑬, 𐑤𐑦𐑚𐑼𐑱𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑮𐑰𐑟𐑩𐑯 𐑝 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑒𐑳𐑯𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑐𐑮𐑦𐑙, 𐑯, 𐑴𐑦𐑙 𐑑 𐑦𐑑𐑕 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑚𐑶𐑩𐑯𐑕𐑦, 𐑮𐑲𐑟𐑦𐑙 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑜𐑮𐑱𐑑 𐑓𐑹𐑕, 𐑞 𐑒𐑪𐑓𐑦𐑯 𐑤𐑲𐑓-𐑚𐑶 𐑖𐑪𐑑 𐑤𐑧𐑙𐑔𐑢𐑲𐑟 𐑓𐑮𐑪𐑥 𐑞 𐑕𐑰, 𐑓𐑧𐑤 𐑴𐑝𐑼, 𐑯 𐑓𐑤𐑴𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑥𐑲 𐑕𐑲𐑛. 𐑚𐑶𐑛 𐑳𐑐 𐑚𐑲 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑒𐑪𐑓𐑦𐑯, 𐑓 𐑷𐑤𐑥𐑴𐑕𐑑 𐑢𐑳𐑯 𐑣𐑴𐑤 𐑛𐑱 𐑯 𐑯𐑲𐑑, 𐑲 𐑓𐑤𐑴𐑑𐑩𐑛 𐑪𐑯 𐑩 𐑕𐑪𐑓𐑑 𐑯 𐑛𐑻𐑡𐑤𐑲𐑒 𐑥𐑱𐑯. 𐑞 𐑳𐑯𐑣𐑸𐑥𐑦𐑙 𐑖𐑸𐑒𐑕, 𐑞𐑱 𐑜𐑤𐑲𐑛𐑩𐑛 𐑚𐑲 𐑨𐑟 𐑦𐑓 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑐𐑨𐑛𐑤𐑪𐑒𐑕 𐑪𐑯 𐑞𐑺 𐑥𐑬𐑞𐑟; 𐑞 𐑕𐑨𐑝𐑦𐑡 𐑕𐑰-𐑣𐑷𐑒𐑕 𐑕𐑱𐑤𐑛 𐑢𐑦𐑞 𐑖𐑰𐑞𐑛 𐑚𐑰𐑒𐑕. 𐑪𐑯 𐑞 𐑕𐑧𐑒𐑩𐑯𐑛 𐑛𐑱, 𐑩 𐑕𐑱𐑤 𐑛𐑮𐑵 𐑯𐑽, 𐑯𐑽𐑼, 𐑯 𐑐𐑦𐑒𐑑 𐑥𐑰 𐑳𐑐 𐑨𐑑 𐑤𐑭𐑕𐑑. 𐑦𐑑 𐑢𐑪𐑟 𐑞 𐑛𐑰𐑝𐑾𐑕-𐑒𐑮𐑵𐑟𐑦𐑙 ·𐑮𐑱𐑗𐑩𐑤, 𐑞𐑨𐑑 𐑦𐑯 𐑣𐑻 𐑮𐑰𐑑𐑮𐑱𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑕𐑻𐑗 𐑭𐑓𐑑𐑼 𐑣𐑻 𐑥𐑦𐑕𐑦𐑙 𐑗𐑦𐑤𐑛𐑮𐑩𐑯, 𐑴𐑯𐑤𐑦 𐑓𐑬𐑯𐑛 𐑩𐑯𐑳𐑞𐑼 𐑹𐑓𐑩𐑯.